All right good afternoon everybody
Welcome!good to see you
Hope you all have started your attack labs
Everybody started? be a good time to start I think
Anyway I hope you're enjoying it, that's a that's a new one this semester that's
I think really interesting and modern and current
Okay today we're going to...
Today we're going to talk about something called the memory hierarchy
Now so far in the class we've thought of memory
When we're looking at our assembly language programs
We've thought of memory as an array of bytes
It's the big array of bytes that we can access with that an index called an address
But in actuality the memory system is a very complex hierarchy of devices
That provides this abstraction of this this large linear array
And so today we're going to look at how memory hierarchies are built
And why they're built the way they are
And what we'll see is that this sort of beautiful confluence of the properties of storage devices
And the properties of programs come together to create this...
This beautiful design called a memory hierarchy
So we're going to quickly kind of do a high-level tour of storage technologies and trends
We're not going to go into a whole lot of detail
The point in looking at these at these the properties of these technologies is that
There are some fundamental properties that determine their performance and their speed
And determine limits on their performance and speed
And so I want you to have a,you know, just some high-level idea of what those what those properties are
And then we'll look at a property of programs called locality of reference
And we'll see how that locality and the properties of storage devices
Come together to suggest this design of memory systems as a hierarchy
Okay so we'll look at memories first
Now the the workhorse memory is called a random access memory or RAM
I'm sure it's traditionally packaged up as a chip
And then you put multiple chips together to form your main memory
And there's a basic storage unit called a cell which where each cell stores one bit
Okay now there's a RAM comes in two varieties
There's a DRAM and DRAM and they're distinguished by the way that those cells are implemented
So in
and SRAM requires it's more complex than DRAM it requires like 4,6 transistors per bit whereas DRAM only requires a one transistor
Okay so you'll see that SRAM are going to be more expensive lots more expensive
Because they're more complex each cell is more complex
But they're also much faster like ten order magnitude faster than DRAMs
And they have there's some other properties too like
SRAM constantly,a DRAM constantly needs to be refreshed
If you don't hit it with a voltage
It loses the charge whereas DRAM while it needs to be plugged in
And and have an electric charge it doesn't need to be refreshed
SRAM is a lot more reliable than DRAM so it
There's less need for error detection and correction
And there and so because of this difference right the SRAMs are costlier smaller and faster than DRAMs
We find SRAMs being used in these small fast memories on chip called cache memories
And we're going to learn all about those on Thursday
And then DRAM is the workhorse used in main memories and the frame buffers associated with graphics cards
Now DRAM and SRAM are volatile in the sense that if they're powered off they lose all the information right so this is why
When you turn your computer off you have to you lose everything in your memory
And you have to when you turn it back on you have to sort of reload everything from your disk
There's a different another kind of memory called a nonvolatile memory which retains its information when it's powered off
And there's a whole bunch of these things that so called up read-only memory
So the generic name for these nonvolatile memories is read only memories ROM
And there's a whole bunch of different kinds sort of going back in time the original read only memories were ROMs
And they can only be programmed once when the chip was produced
And then over time gradually over period of like 20 or 30 years
There were improvements in the way that ROMs could be programmed and in how they were erased
So they could be reprogrammed
The what we have today the the modern form of read only memories is called flash memory
Which provides the capability of erasing you can erase just chunks of the the flash memory called blocks
And then the downside is that these things wear out after about a hundred thousand erasers
Okay so you can erase and reprogram a hundred thousand times and then it's your bricked
Now that these nonvolatile memories are show up in with
So called firmware which is software
That's that's programmed into a ROM
And you see those in the BIOS of computers so when you power on your computer
The very first instructions that execute are stored in a ROM right
If you're wondered like where do those things come from so they're stored in ROM
And then there's a boot process where gradually more and more information is
And instructions are loaded into memory
You know IO.IO devices have little computers in them call controllers
These controllers consist of instructions and data that are that are stored in ROMs
And you see them all over the place in these solid state disks
That to the system look like a rotating disk
But they're built of flash memories
Okay and these are you see these in thumb drives smartphones tablets and laptops
And they're even starting to show up in servers now
So the memories are connected to the CPU using sort of wires that are collectively called buses
Okay so data flows across the wires back and forth from the,we have the CPU chip
And it consists of register file these are the general-purpose registers %rax, %rdi and so on
And there's an arithmetic logic unit that reads and writes data from the register files
And then manipulates that data in some way by doing some kind of arithmetic operation or some logical operation
And if instructions need to access memory
So if there's you're doing a move,a move instruction that reads or writes to memory
Then that's handled by a bus interface which is connected to a what we'll call a system bus
And then that's connected to an I/O bridge and this
This is another collection of chips,Intel calls this what I'm calling the I/O bridge,they call the chipset
Okay but it's it's a collection of chips separate from the process the CPU chip
And then the I/O bridge is connected to another bus called the memory bus which connects the main memory
Okay now this is kind of an abstraction I don't want you to take this too literally
But it gives you the idea of how information flows in the system
Okay modern modern systems use proprietary bus designs and they're very arcane and increasingly complex
So we're just going to use a fairly simple abstraction for these bus architectures
Now when is,now suppose you do a load operation like movq
The eight bytes at address a into %rax
Okay so we call that a load because we're loading from the point of view of the CPU
We're loading data into the CPU
But we're loading and we're loading data from memory into the CPU
So when the CPU executes movq instruction like this
It first places the address of A on the memory bus
And then the main memory census that address and it reads the contents the eight bytes at address A
So it retrieves the word 8 byte word from address a and places it back on the bus
The those bits travel through the I/O bridge to the bus interface
And then the CPU reads the the word x from the data word x from the bus and in composition to register %rax
Okay so it's now writing is is similar again
So here we're doing a move instruction movq from %rax into address A main memory
Okay so the the CPU starts as before by placing the address a on the bus
Main memory reads that address and then it waits for the data to arrive on the bus
So the CPU then places the contents of %rax on the bus
Those contents travel across to main memory
Which then reads the reads that word from the bus and stores it at address A
Ok so that the point of all this is that operations that occur
You know reads and writes of registers
Because the register file is very close to the ALU, these happen in on the order of a few cycles
Ok register,the register very close to the ALU
So those operations are very happened very quickly
Whereas memories actually this is a set of chips that are very far away relatively speaking from the CPU
And there's a lot going on in when if you have to read or write memory there's
It you have to do multiple operations on the bus,data has to travel propagate across that bus all this stuff takes time
So memory operations reads and writes are typically
You know maybe 50 nanoseconds 100 nanoseconds whereas operations that occur between registers are sub nanosecond
On the order of so you're talking about a one to two orders of magnitude difference
If you have to go off chip to to retrieve something from memory
Ok so that's the first sort of big takeaway item about memory systems
Now in other popular storage technology is rotating disks
And I don't know if you've ever torn one apart they're kind of interesting there's a series of platters
Each platter is coated with a magnetic material
And then and then bits ones and zeros are encoded in that magnetic material
And then there's this arm that can it's it's hinged right here
And then it can it floats over the platter so it floats on a thin layer of air over the platter
And there's a read/write head at the very end that can sense the changes in the magnetic field that encode the bits
Okay so these platters are spinning around like counterclockwise like this, this arm can go back and forth
So there's a lot of mechanical gear so this is all mechanical
So the mechanical nature of a rotating disc
Means it's going to be slower right then DRAMs and SRAMs
And there's also electronics like it's like a little computer in firmware
That that actually controls the operation of this drive that controls how this arm goes back and forth
And and and controls how the data is read off of the the read/write head
So just in a little more detail we can think of these disks consists of platters
Each platter has two surfaces the top and a bottom
And then each surface consists of these trees are concentric rings  called tracks
And then each track consists of us it consists of sectors which contain the data
So typically 512,512 bits, oh I'm sorry bytes
And then except these tracks are separated by gaps
That goat that these gaps like right here that don't contain data
Now platters are aligned on top of each other on the spindle
And so tracks that are aligned on the different surfaces
Such as this track here on those the collection of those
Tracks form what we call a cylinder okay because it has a cylindrical shape
Now the capacity of disks is that the number of bits that can be stored
And vendors kind of they all dis vendors use they quote the capacity in gigabytes
But where a gigabyte is 10^9 bytes right instead of 2^20,okay like like you would expect
So what...I'm not sure why they do this
But it allows by by quoting their capacity and gigabytes in 10^9 bytes
It's a bigger number right
So it looks better it looks like there's more information
It's a little I don't really know why they do it but I think that's why it is
And it's one of those little bit annoying things that we just have to just  know about and get used to
Now the capacity is determined by 2 independent technology factors
One is the recording density so that's how many bits can you pack into a single sector
Or porous or at least a portion of a track
And then the track density which is sort of how close can you put those tracks together
And then the product of those two is what's called the areal density and that determines the overall capacity of the disc
So the higher the areal capacity the more bits you can squeeze on to that onto that surface
Now in the old days when aerial densities were fairly low
Each each track on the surface would have the same number of sectors
Okay so there was a constant number of sectors per track
So now what happens as you as your tracks go from the
You know near the whole by the spindle as they go as they move outward
Right if you have the same number of sectors with the same bit density
That the gaps between sectors are going to get bigger and bigger as you go out
And you're going to be wasting more and more of your space
So at when aerial densities were fairly low this was okay
But after a while it just became not okay to waste that much room
So what modern systems do is they partition the tracks into these
So called rook recording zones
Where each recording zone such as this right here
Each recording zone has a consonant number of sectors
So each track in a recording zone has the same number of sectors
And of course as you move outward if you move outward in the recording zone
You're going to have bigger and bigger gaps
But then you start a new recording zone
That will have more sectors per track and then within that
So you can see in this outer in this outer zone you have more you have more sectors
Than you do on this inner zone
Okay so that's a way to kind of deal with that sort of that growth in the gaps to keep it from getting too large
And so because we don't really have the number of sectors per track isn't constant
We'll use an Average the average sectors per track across
All recording zones when we do serve our capacity estimates
Okay so you can imagine the formula for computing the disk capacity is fairly straightforward
It's the number of bytes per sector
Times the average number of sectors per track
Times the average number of tracks per surface times the number of surfaces per platter
Times the number of platters per disk okay
Now let's look at how just work
So these these surfaces are spinning at a fixed rotational rate
Now a typical rate may be 7200 rpm s is a fairly common rotational rate
So the disc is spinning around you can see this pretty proud of that
So it's spinning around counter clockwise and then the arm
Moves radially here we go
The arm moves radially and it can go over any of the tracks
Okay all right that's enough
Okay now when you have multiple platters
Each one of these each one of these there's actually multiple arms and there's a read/write head on each surface
So if the platters has to - if - if each side of the platter
Is coated with this magnetic material then
You'll have you have a read/write head on each side
And then these are all connected they kind of move together
Now originally these these read/write heads would be they were rigid
Right because the densities tracked densities weren't that high
So they could they could just sort of licks and even though the tracks didn't align perfectly
They could just sort of they could they could still cover
The read/write heads could still cover the tracks with these fixed  with these fixed arms
But nowadays that the densities are so high
That they actually the controller can actually move the read/write heads a little bit
So that it matches up with that all of the tracks on all of the surfaces
Okay so let's look at how this works how we read data
So we have our
This is our this is our arm and the tip of the arrow is the read/write head
And it's positioned and the platter is rotating counterclockwise
And it's positioned just ready to read the blue sector
So it as the blue sector spins underneath the read/write head
It senses those bits and sends them up to the controller which passes them back up to the  the CPU
And now the CPU is requested that the disk
It's requested the red data from the red sector
So we have to take the controller takes that read/write head
Moves it back to reds track
And then waits for it to spin around and
And to the to the read/write head
And then it reads that that red that red sector
Okay so when we first so there's really three components going on here that determine
How long it takes to read one of these sectors
The when we move the head that's called a seek
When we waited for the red track to sort of rotate around
That's called the rotational latency so however long it takes
On average it will be half of the half of the time
It takes for the entire to circle all the way around
And then there's the data transfer which is
Sort of how long it takes for that
For that track to pass under the read/write head
Now the reason the reason it's important to know this is that
These three components you add them together and that's the that's what your average
X time it takes to access data
That time is dominated by the seek time
So seek times are measured in milliseconds right so we're moving this head there's
This there's a servo that has to fire up and there's actual mechanical motion
And that that takes time
And it's on the order of three to nine milliseconds and this has been true for decades
Right so this this value is not changing right
There's just sort of fundamental mechanical limits
That make it very difficult to to decrease this this value
Now the rotational latency
The time that it takes to spin around will we'll call that the t average rotation
And then the time it takes to read the the bits will call t average transfer
Okay so we have t average seek which is this seek time rotational latency and transfer time
And now if we just take some typical numbers   and plug those in
You see that our seek time is on the order of milliseconds
The rotational rate is also on the order of milliseconds right
So there's there's also mechanical limits and how fast you can you can spin these around
The access time and the transfer time  is very small
So it's orders of magnitude smaller because you just have to read a few that the bits that are in one sector
Okay so if you look you can see that the total access time is dominated by seek  and rotational latency
So you know a good rule of thumb just for sort of estimating how long it takes to read from a disk
It is just take twice the seek the seek time and you'll be pretty close
And basically the transfer time is you get that for free
Now here's the here's the important thing to know about disks
We SRAM access times about four nanoseconds to get a double word
Dram is about 60 nanoseconds
So DRAM is about an order of magnitude slower than SRAM
But disk is 40,000 times slower than SRAM
So that's 4,000 orders of magnitude difference
That's huge and it's it's 250 times orders of magnitude slower than DRAMs
So the there's a big gap between DRAM and SRAM
And there's an even bigger gap between disk and other memory types
Now modern disks present a much simpler view
Than so we then this track cylinder sector geometry
So modern modern disk controllers actually present
To the CPU they present the disk as a sequence of logical blocks
Where each block is is a multiple of a sector size
So this in simplest case a block is just a logical block is one sector
And then blocks are numbered starting at zero
And they just go all the way up to some to some large number
And then the the disk controller keeps the mapping maintains the mapping between logical blocks
And the actual physical sectors
So as in the old saying is you know most interesting ideas in computer science are involve some form of indirection
So this is a level of indirection
That provides you know this mapping between logical blocks and physical blocks
So it allows disk controllers to take some cylinders and reserve them as spare cylinders
That aren't mapped in illogical blocks
And then if there's if one of the sectors goes bad in a cylinder
That the disk controller can just copy the data over to a spare cylinder and then just keep going right
So this is why your 4matic capacity is less than sort of the if you know if you counted the number of actual cylinders on the disk
Your 4matic capacity is less than the maximum capacity
Because some of those cylinders are being reserved for failures
Now devices like disks are connected to the to the CPU and the memory
Via the I/O bridge over another kind of bus called an I/O bus
This what I'm showing you now is actually not representative of modern systems
It's representative of what was called the pci bus about five years ago
Modern buses now are the pci bus is a broadcast bus meaning it's just a single set of wires
So if any device us changes the values on those wires
Every device on that bus can see those values
Okay that's called a broadcast bus and it's a simplest kind of way to hook things together
Modern systems use a bus structure called pci express
Which although it has the word pci and it's completely different it's point-to-point
So devices are connected by a set of point-to-point connections
Arbitrated by a-- by some kind of a switch
And we won't go into it it's the same idea it it's a much more efficient design
It's much faster and but it provides the same capability mainly it just attaches up
It allows you to attach all of your devices to your to your CPU
So just think of this bus as this sort of a single set of wires
Where each wire carries a bit
And every device attached to it can see all the values of all the wires
And so it there's some devices that are just built it directly into the motherboard and they attach to the bus like
You know disks have just plugged directly into sockets on a motherboard
And you know your graphics adapter and the USB controller
And then the system presents an interface
So you can plug mouse things like mice and keyboards into the USB controller
And then there's expansion slots that allow you that are
Connect to the wires in the in the bus that allow you to add other devices right
Maybe network you know if you want to put a network adapter there
Now what happens when we want to read a disk sector
Well the CPU initiates this read by writing a triple
So it writes three different values it writes a command like say read
It writes a logical block number
So I want to read a logical block number
And I want to place the contents of that logical block at a certain address in memory
Okay so it's a command logical block number in a memory address
The disk controller reads the whatever sector corresponds to that logical block
So we'll assume that logical blocks are consists of one sector
And then it does this interesting thing it copies it takes control of the bus
And it copies the data this is the disk controller now
Copies the data across the I/O bus through the I/O bridge and directly to main memory without ever notifying the CPU
So the CPU is completely oblivious to the fact that this transfer is going on
And then once it's once its transfer the data to main memory
Then it notifies the CPU using this mechanism called an interrupt
So it actually asserts a pin on the the actual CPU chip itself
So it it changes the value of that pin from 0 to 1
And that trigger is an interrupt and which notifies the CPU that sector has been copy
Ok so then the CPU if there's some program somewhere waiting for that data to be read into memory
So now now the CPU can can execute that program and deal with that memory
So what this what this mechanism allows
And the reason they do this is because disks are just so god-awful slow
The within 10 milliseconds a system could be executing millions and millions of instructions
The CPU could be executing millions and millions of instructions
It will be a terrible waste if the CPU waited for that data to come off the disk
So what it does is it it issues this request to the disk controller
And then while that well that really slow laborious process is going on
The CPU can be executing other instructions and doing other useful work
So this is really essential to just sort of getting reasonable performance
And from keeping this really slow disk system from slowing the system down
Now there's another interesting hype kind of disk called a solid-state disk
Which is kind of halfway between rotating and rotating discs  and DRAM memories
In a solid-state disk to the to the CPU
It looks exactly like a rotating disk it has the same socket plug
It has the same physical interface that has the same packaging
It looks like a rotating disc
But instead of having all these mechanical parts it's actually built entirely out of flash memory
And firmware that acts as the the controller
So inside of a solid-state disk there's a firmware a set of firmware called the flash translation layer
Which serves the purpose as the same purpose as the disk controller does in a rotating disk d
And then the memory itself the read
Data can be read read and written from the flash memory in units of pages
Which depending on the technology can be 512 kbytes to 4 k bytes
And then a sequence of pages forms a block
Now these these these blocks are different from the logical blocks that the CPU does
So it's kind of an unfortunate overlap of terms
But the the trick is or the I guess the limitation is that data is written in units of pages
But a page can only be written after the entire block has been erased
Okay so that's that seems kind of weird but that's that's the way it works
So what that means is if you want to write
If you want to write to a page you have to find a block somewhere that's been erased
You have to copy all of the other pages in your target block over to that new block and then you can do the right
Okay so you can see that rights now become fairly complex operation reads you can read anything
And then like all flash a so it's kind of an efficient right because you're writing one page
But to do that you have to sort of copy all the other pages in it block and you have to erase the whole
And then when you finish then you erase this block so it can be used for for other writes yes
So eventually after a hundred thousand repeated writes these we're out
Now the flash translation layer xin modern systems
Do all kinds of fancy proprietary algorithms to sort of extend the life they use caching
And and various tricks to extend the life of these SSD
So in practice it's not really a problem which I'll show you in a second
So the performance characteristics of SSDs
Now you can think of a typical hard drive you might be able to get
You know I mean what if when I measure them when I measure my drives
I maybe forty fifty megabytes per second that would be a typical rate
Okay these SSDs are 10 times faster than that
So for sequential reads you can get about 500 50 megabytes
Sequential writes are a little bit slower
Random access whether you're reading or writing is a little bit slower than sequential access
And as we'll see this is that this is fairly common
It's it's in memory systems it's almost always better to do things sequentially  than to jump around
And erasing random writes are slower because erase erasing takes about a millisecond right
So now we're back up to that that millisecond range which is which is slow
And as I mentioned yet if you modify one one one page after all the other pages in that block have to be copy
Now earlier SSDs had a huge gap between random writes and sequential reads
But they because of sort of improvements in the flash translation layer
These aren't really that that difference right reading and writing it's it's writing is slower
But they're doing all kinds of interesting amazing things to get these numbers fairly close
Ok so art when we have a model of SSDs we really don't need to distinguish anymore that between reads and writes
You okay so SSDs because they have no moving parts
They're faster they take less power they're more rugged
You know which is why they're good for thumb drives
And you know ipods and things like that
But they have this potential to wear out
Which could be a problem but in practice it's not for example
Intel guarantees that you can do 128 petabytes of writes
Before your SSD is no longer good
So that's a lot of data to write I mean think about how many years it would take to write that much data
And as of 2015 as of now
They're a lot more expensive per byte than rotating disks
So rotating disks are much bigger but they're slower
SSDs are smaller and faster
Now if you take
If you look at the performance characteristics of these different storage devices relative to CPU
Over time you get this really interesting graph
Now this graph shows on the y-axis access time in nanoseconds  or in a log scale
Okay so each one of these each change in units from 1,000 to 10,000 represents a order of magnitude difference in access time
On the x-axis I've plotted time going from 1985 to 2015
And then I've plotted the sort of the the access time or the cycle time of
The access time of the these devices disk SSD DRAM and SRAM
And the cycle time of processors
So let's look at on the bottom we have the the cycle time of processors over time
And what you see is it's going down at is this sort of exponential rate  from 1985 to 2003
There's the doubling basically every 18 months or two years in clock frequency and a resulting
Halving of the cycle time over this 18-month two to two year period
So this so what what manufacturers did until 2003
To make their processors faster was a but they would just double the clock frequency
They decrease the feature size of the chips that they were making
And that would allow them to put things closer together
And then have that and then increase the clock frequency by a proportional amount
Now this all ended 2003 was an interesting year in computer history
Because of this there's a sort of unfortunate property that the power that you consume
Is proportional to your frequency
Okay so the more power I mean the higher the frequency the more power you consume
By 2003 the processor that Intel was getting ready to ship was going to burn about 800 watts of power
Think about 800 watt light bulbs inside your laptop and
I actually saw an early prototype of one of these devices
And the the heatsink to absorb the power from the chip was about this big it was about four square inches
It's a giant thing just sitting on the motherboard
So that's what we what we say is that processor design hit the power wall in 2003
They could no longer just continue to increase clock frequencies
To to get faster to make faster computers
And what so what they had to do after 2003
Instead of increasing the clock frequency and try and set up doubling the clock frequency
They put more processor cores onto the chips
So now they subdivided a CPU chip into individual processor cores
Each one could execute its own instructions
And then so and by running in parallel
You could do more effective work so the effective cycle time could continue to go down
So what I've what I plotted here on the bottom is the effective cycle time
So basically the the cycle time divided by the number of cores
So here in 2005 that the first systems use two cores
So now you can run two independent threads or two independent programs
And currently it's about four cores server class systems you can get eight cores
And there's even some 12 core chips
So in the future what's going to happen is that the the clock frequencies are going to stay fairly constant
So you can see the site you can see the the cycle times are
They actually increased a little bit here and then they're slowly going down but it's generally flat
And so the only way to really get more performance
Go forward is to increase the number of independent course
And that's just that's just the way it's got to be
Now here in the the black circle the second line I've plotted the access time for SRAM over time
And you can see that SRAM is tracking CPU pretty good
And it and there's it's it's an order of magnitude slower but
It's tracking the CPU performance pretty well
Dram you can see there's a huge gap between the CPU and the DRAM several orders of magnitude
And in the last few years DRAMs have gotten a little better
But they've proven surprisingly difficult to to make faster
SSDs are kind of in between disks and DRAM
And then disks up here you can see at a million nanoseconds that's the that's a millisecond
So you can see disks are sort of in this in this sort of millisecond range with access times
And those those that they've gone down a little bit but not really too much
So the point I want to make is that there's this huge gap between DRAM  SSD disk in and CPUs
And in some cases it's even getting worse as time goes by so that's a problem right how
Our programs all need data our data is stored in memory and disk
So if if our if our computers are getting faster
And our storage devices are are staying relatively the same or relatively slower
Then we've got a problem right increases in in our in computer performance won't
It'll be hard to make our programs run faster
Because we'll be limited by the time it takes to to access the data
Ok so that's that that's sort of the fundamental problem that we have to deal with
And it turns out that the key to bridging this this gap between the CPU and and memory
Is this is this very basic fundamental property of programs called locality
Okay and so this is an essential sort of fundamental enduring property of programs
So we say that so programs have this property called locality
And what this means is that
I'm sorry I'll just I have to read it because it's it's really accurate definition
So programs tend to use data and instructions whose addresses are near or equal to those that they have used recently
Okay so if a program access is a data item the chances are very high
That it's going to access that data item or a nearby data item sometime in the near future
Okay that likelihood that the program is going to access that data item or a nearby a data item
In the near future is that is this property called locality
So well does we just typically distinguish two two different kinds of locality
Temporal locality is the property that recently referenced items are likely to be referenced again in the near future
Kaycee 50 so if you read a variable
Chances are you're going to read that variable again
For example suppose you're summing into a variable inside of a loop
Each loop iteration you're going to access that that variable okay
Spatial locality is that the tendency for items with nearby addresses up that
That items if we access if we access one item chances are high we're going to access a nearby item
Okay so let's look at this little snippet of code and see if we can identify all the different kinds of locality in this code
So we have two different kinds of of references there's data references
And then there's instructions right so we're reading instructions out of memory
And those instructions are referencing data okay
So first of all notice that we're we're referencing the elements of an array in succession
So we're increasing I by one each time and then we're
So we're incrementing I through the loop and we're reading a[i]
Okay so this is called a stride one reference pattern the
The stride is how much we're incrementing this this index
So we're since we're incrementing it by one we call that a stride one pattern
So what kind of what kind of locality is the these repeated references to a[i] spatial or temporal
That spatial right because we're accessing nearby items
Okay what about the referencing this this variable some inside the loop
That's temporal
Now what about instructions
So we're referencing where each loop iteration where reference we're executing a sequence of instructions
So what kind of locality is that
Within each loop iteration? no that's spatial right
Because we're just executing a sequence of instructions within each loop iteration
But then we cycle through the loop repeatedly
So we'll chances so each loop iteration we're going to access each of those instructions
That we access the previous loop iteration right
So we go up we just keep at we're just going to keep executing the sum
Assembly language instructions that implement this loop body
Now in this simple example it's probably this one instruction
But in general your loop can have multiple instructions
Now when I claim to you I'm one of the one of the main sort of points of this just this whole course
Is that as a professional programmer
It's an essential skill that that you be able to look at code and so get a qualitative sense of its locality
Because as we'll see good locality turns into good performance
The way that systems are built these days
So as a programmer it's very important for you to be able to kind of look at code and get some qualitative sense
Like yeah that's pretty good locality that's terrible locality right that that's
And what you want to do is avoid the terrible locality in your code
So let's look at a simple example here
To see what I mean by this
So what I'm doing is I'm taking an array a two-dimensional array a
With m m rows and n columns
And within it a doubly nested loop iterating on I and j
I'm summing the elements of that array
Okay seems this a very simple operation what could go wrong right
So it turns out if you write this code to have bad locality  it will run order magnitude slower
Okay so if just look at this if you look at this do you think this has good locality or bad locality
Let's look at the with respect to the accesses of a
Good or bad ?
Well so how is how is a laid out in memory right
It's row wise all right so see uses used lays out a raised row wise
So the first all the elements of the first row followed by all the elements
Of the second row followed by all the elements of the third row
Okay so how are we accessing this array
Look at we're accessing a[i][j] and we're varying j the fastest
So we hold I constant and then we vary j
And then we access all so we hold the I constant to access row i
And then we vary j to access all the columns in that row
Okay so each each hitter and then we increase and then we go back and increase i
So now we're accessing the next row
Okay so if we were to look at the addresses of a[i][j] the sequence of addresses  that are being read
Those would correspond to a stride one access and so we'd be accessing all the elements of a sequentially in order
Okay so that's really good spatial locality right that's the best you can do
Now what about what about and then we have temporal locality on some so that's good
Right so everything about this is pretty good so this is the good case
Now what about this what I've done I've taken the same program
And I've just inverted the loops so it's a loop on j first and then on i
And then I just have the same inner loop body
Now what does that do to this what does that do to the spatial locality of our accesses okay
Yes
Terrible because it's going you should be offended what do you see this isn't lawful
But it's terrible right because look it
So we're now we're holding j
We're holding j constant and then we're iterating through the jt element of each row so that's skipping
We have n we have n elements in each row so we're doing a stride n access through memory
So we're going like this
And then we're incrementing then we're looking then we're incrementing the column by one and then we're doing this again
So it's terrible spatial locality this is the worst spatial locality we could get
Now let's look at a three dimensional array
And let me ask you that let me post the following question
Can you based on this sort of qualitative idea that
This idea that you want you want to try to get a stride one reference pattern
Okay so how would you permute these given this given this inner body
A[k][i][j] how would you promote that permute these these loop indices to give stride one reference pattern
Okay that's right kij is right
So what in general we want to do is we want to go going from right to left
We want we want those indices to be changing the fastest
So we want j we want k and I to be held constant and then we want to change j
Then we want to increment I and then for that value that those values of k and i
We want to want to sequence through all the the values of j again
Okay
Okay so we've looked at properties of technology of storage technologies
And well we and there's this sort of basic sort of fundamental principle that cheaper storage
You bigger storage higher capacity storage is cheaper
More expensive storage is smaller
Because we just don't have that we don't we can't spend enough money
There's this gap there's this gap between our storage devices and the CPU
That is in at least in the case of disks are getting bigger
And we have programs that exhibit locality
Okay so these three things these properties of storage technologies
And properties of our programs
Complement each other in this beautiful way to suggest and inform the design of our storage systems
And this design is something called a memory hierarchy
Okay here's the idea of a memory hierarchy
You layer instead of a flat memory system you now
You create your memory system as a hierarchy of devices
And at the top of the at the top of this hierarchy
You have your smaller faster and more expensive storage devices
So at the very top you have registers
Which are which can be accessed and within one cycle right one instruction
While that instructions executing can access read and write into a register
Okay so registers are at the top of the hierarchy
But because those are in custom silicon they're very expensive right
The fabrication plants to make processors cost billions of dollars
Okay so this is the most expensive and
Because of that it's also the smallest we've only got 16 registers at the top of the hierarchy
Now below that we put one or more SRAM memories remember SRAM is faster
It's the fastest kind of memory
So we put one or more so-called caches cache memories built out of SRAM
In the processor chip itself
And then and these caches because they're made out of SRAM they're on the order of megabytes in size
Okay they're much bigger than registers but they're they're megabytes
Okay which if we look and then beneath that is our
Main memory which is built out of DRAMs and those can be gigabytes  tens of gigabytes on modern systems
And then below that is our local disks
And we can even have lower layers like web servers that are storing you know for storing stuff on google
That you can think of that as just part of our our hierarchy
Now here's the here's the key idea and a higher in a in a memory hierarchy
Each level in this hierarchy holds data that's retrieved from the next lower level
Okay so caches hold registers hold data that's that's stored in the l1 cache
The l1 cache holds data that's retrieved from the l2 cache the l3 cache holds data  that's restored
That's that's retrieved from main memory main memory holds data that's retrieved from secondary disk and so on
Now as we'll see the that the reason memory systems are designed like this
Is that they when you have this kind of system
This you can access in general you can access your data at the speed of the fastest item in the day
And at the top of the hierarchy
So that's the fastest
But with the cost of the storage at the lower part of the hierarchy
Okay so this this works all because of an idea called caching
So a cache and compete to took to a computer scientist is a
It's a smaller faster storage device that acts as a staging area for the data and a larger slower device
So just like like here you can think of your main memory is a cache for data
That's stored on disk right you read memory from disk and then you store it in main memory
Okay you can think of the main memory as a staging area
So once you get the data from the disk you don't access it again on the disk you access it in memory which is much faster
Ok so this idea propagates all the way up the hierarchy
Okay so we you can think of a cache on
One way to think of a cache is imagine your backpack when you're getting ready to come to school in the morning
So you're in your apartment which is kind of far away from school
So before you come into school you take items from from your house
And you put them in your backpack right
Then you come to school if you need those items you get there in your backpack
You know if you didn't do that
Every time you needed something you'd have to walk back home and get it  and then walk back to school
All right so it's so the idea of caching is very you know it's a very familiar kind of simple notion
But it turns out to be quite powerful and it shows up in all parts of computer systems
Okay so so what we say is that for each level k in the hierarchy
The the faster smaller device at level k serves as a cache
For the larger slower device at level k+1
And remember our our levels go from so l0 is the highest
So this the smallest lowest level is actually the highest
The further step in the cat in the hierarchy and as we increase the levels
We're going down the hierarchy
Now why do they work so this is this is a really fundamental idea
They work because of locality
So because of locality programs tend to access data that's stored at level k
More often than they access data at level k+1 o
Okay so if we access an item at level +1
We can move it up to level k chances are because of locality we're going to access it again
Okay so now we're accessing the data at level k multiple times at the rate at the speed of love
Okay not at the speed of level k plus one okay so that's
That's the fun the fundal fundamental idea
And because we're not accessing data at level +1 as often
We can afford to use slower storage devices which are cheaper
In this and thus we can make them bigger and cheaper per gig
So what this does is the hierarchy creates a a large pool of storage
That's roughly about the size of the lowest level
That can be accessed at the speed at the highest level
All right let's let's look at how caching works in a general way
And then we'll see on thursday how these hardware cache memories work
Okay but like I said caching is a very general idea that can be applied at all levels in the hierarchy
So here we have a cache - so the in all kinds of most caches there's some kind of transfer unit
To go from one level to the next
So here we have at this at this upper level
We have a what we'll call the cache that can hold four blocks
So our our memory and then at the lower level we have memory
And this memory is partitioned into blocks of some fixed size that's this
That's the way cache is at nearly near the upper part of the hierarchy work
Now at the lower levels like if you're accessing data say from a web server
Then the the data is partitioned into files typically
Okay but it upper levels the data is partitioned into blocks so just suppose this is main memory
And then above that we have a that consists of a bunch of these blocks
So we just take the memory and partition into blocks where each block is the same number of bytes
And then data will be transferred between memory and the cache in block size transfer units
Okay so if you need data from the memory if the cache needs data from the memory it'll grab a whole block
And then at any point in time the cache holds a subset of the the blocks in main memory
Okay so this this cache is much faster but it's also much slower
And because of that and it's much smaller
I'm sorry it's much faster but it's it's much more expensive because it's faster it's more expensive
And because it's more expensive it's smaller
Now suppose the cash once de-reference say that the CPU asks for data that's contained in block four
So it looks it looks to see if the data is in the cache it's not
So the cache asks the memory to give it block four
So that block is copied from memory into the cache
Overwriting the one of the existing in this case block eight it will overwrite blockade
So now now block four is is in our cache
Now suppose now now suppose the CPU s for a some data that's in block ten
That gets copied up and and we overwrite that that block
Now the whole idea of storing it in the cache is that we're hoping that the seek the program that's executing on the CPU
Will reuse one of those blocks we just spent all the time
We went to all this trouble to copy it from memory to to this cache  and we know that's slow
So now suppose that the CPU needs some data in block  b in this case fourteen
Okay so it needs it needs a we're a memory word that's stored that was originally stored in memory it in block fourteen
Well now this cache can just return that's what we call a hit right so the
Block that we access is in the cache so that's good hits are good
Because now we can return that block directly to CPU
And this this memory is much faster than if we had to go all the way to main memory to the DRAM
Okay so the SRAM much faster than the DRAM
So the CPU gets that block fourteen much faster than it would have
If it had just gone all the way to memory
Okay the sort of other the the opposite of a hit is a miss
So suppose the CPU s for block twelve
The cache looks for that block can't find it
That's a miss so the the cash has to ask that the main memory the DRAM for block 12
Where it gets copied into the cache and then it can return that
So that takes longer right so the CPU has to wait for that block to be ex to be fetched from memory
And so misses are slow so hits are good because they're fast
Misses are bad because they're they're slow
Now we typically distinguish between several different kinds of caches
So the first kind of miss is a cold miss or a compulsory miss
Which is caused because there's just nothing in the cache
Initially caches they're empty they have no blocks and as we fetch
As we fetch blocks from the lower level from the next the next level and put them in the cache
The cache will slowly fill up with blocks
And we'll get and that will increase the likelihood of hits
But when the cache is empty we're going to miss every time right
So there's just no way to avoid cold misses right you got
Oh so this is called warming up your cache so as you load data items into the cache
Initially it's cold and as you add more items you're warming it up meaning that you're increasing the likelihood of a hit
Now there's a there's another sort of symmetric kind of miss which is called a capacity miss
And these misses are due to the fact that the cache is just a certain size right you just can't
In the example we looked at we only had four blocks
So if we're if we're trying if our if our if our temporal locality involves eight blocks
You know say if the loop that we're accessing is  is accessing elements in array
That that consists of eight blocks there's just not enough room to store eight blocks and that four block cache
So we're going to get misses right we would need a bigger cache to be able to satisfy and store those eight blocks
And if we had a big enough cache then we get good hit rate right if we could store all the blocks
In our cache then we then then the cache could take advantage of the spatial and temporal locality within that program
So in general what we call this set of blocks at any point in time when a program is running
We call the set of blocks that are sort of being accessed over and over again the working set
And so your working set and the working set will change you know as you go from loop to loop  from function to function
But at a point in time in your program when
It you have this idea of a working set which is sort of the blocks that you need to have stored in your cache
Ok and well so when you're working set size exceeds your cache size then you get capacity misses
There's this other kind of weird miss called the conflict miss
Which has to do with the way that caches are often implemented
So the idea is that most caches especially hardware caches because they're they have to be simple
They have they limit where a block can be placed to some
Small set of positions in the cache
So like one of the the simplest models is to just take
Block I can only be placed in block I mod the cache size
So in our that that little cache we saw that had four blocks
We would take we would take block I from memory and we would stick it at block I mod 4
So block 0 would go at block 0 in our cache
As would block 4 and as would block 8 block 9 would go into block 1 in the cache
And that's when that happens suppose suppose we use that model so we're going to take
Block I and we're going to put it we can only place it in the cache
At block I mod 4
Now suppose our suppose our reference pattern involves from memory block zero block four and block eight
It's only three blocks so we have we have enough room in the cache to store
Those three blocks but because of the way we've decided to place blocks each block will be will evict
When we access block four it'll go into block zero in the cache
When we access blocked four in the cache
It'll overwrite that block and it'll go into block zero in the cache
And so because of this it's really the access pattern conspiring with the  algorithm
That we're using for placing blocks
Okay so because of this we have plenty of room in the cache
But because of this sort of the access pattern conspiring with the placement algorithm
We get misses every time
We'll see how we'll see how conflict marisa's work in detail when we study your caches tomorrow
So
So this is these these caches exist everywhere in the memory hierarchy and
So all of them are caches of one form or another right
So you can think of the registers as a type of cache
What are they cache for eight byte words
Okay where's it cached it's cached right on the CPU itself
What's the latency it's instant and happens within an instruction
And then who manages the cache somebody has to manage the cache when
When when there's a request to load an item from the lower level in the hierarchy
Something has to decide what to do with that where to put it in the cache that's called managing the cache
Well in this case the compiler manages the cache
When you when you compile your C code the compiler figures out which register
Data items from memory are going to go into okay
So tlb this is something this is a cache that's used in virtual memory
Then there's these hardware caches called l1 and l2 caches
So they store 64 byte blocks on modern Intel systems
And they're cached on the CPU chip itself in in s ramps that are built right into the CPU chip
And depending on whether l1 caches to on core i7s have a latency of 4 cycles
And l2 has a latency of 10 cycles
And both of these are managed by hardware
So when you when the CPU fetches an item from the l1 cache hardware figure finds it
And if there's a miss and a block is loaded from l2 hardware in the l1 cache figures out where to put it
Ok so all this is done without any intervention by hardware
Disks contain buffer operating systems maintain buffer caches
So in this case what's cached is portions of files
Ok and they're cached in main memory
And latency to 2 main memories about a hundred cycles or so
And these are managed by the operating system
So the operating system reserves a portion of memory to store files that you've loaded so
So the operating system exploits locality if you if you read a file
And then start reading referencing bytes from that file it will actually be served from the
File cache and it won't go out to disk
Network networks maintain caches like things like nfs and afs maintain local caches on disk
Your browser has a cache so when it fetches files from from servers
It stores those files locally on disk so if you reference those web pages again
They're served from from your local disk rather than going all the way across the network
Ok so the point is that these caches exist everywhere in the memory hierarchy
And they're all based on the same principles they're just implemented in different ways
Ok so just to summarize what we've what we've done today
We've seen that there's there's a gap between the CPU and our storage devices that continues to increase
We've seen that well-written programs have this property called locality
And we've seen that caching by taking by using caching
We can build a memory hierarchy that takes advantage of locality and programs
And allows us to build storage systems that where we can access data at the rate of the fastest device
But at the cost and capacity of the devices at the the lowest level
Ok so thursday we're going to look at a very specific part of the hierarchy called cache memories