Welcome good to see you
欢迎，很高兴见到大家
Today we're going to begin a transitioning from
今天我们要转变一下研究内容
How a programs interact with hardware to how they interact with software in particular system software
从程序如何与硬件交互，以及它们如何与特定系统软件中的软件交互开始
And we're going to start that investigation by studying and learning about a process called linking
我们将通过研究和弄懂一个叫做链接的过程开始
Which is how the system builds your programs ok
这能帮助你好好弄清楚系统是如何构建你的程序
So we're going to study the process of linking
所以我们要学习链接的过程
And then I'm going to show you a really cool technique called library interpositioning
然后我将向你展示一项非常酷的技术，称为库打桩技术
Which allows you to use linking to actually intercept on function calls in libraries like the standard C library
这允许你使用链接实际拦截像标准 C 库这样的库中的函数调用
So it's a very powerful and interesting technique and it's all enabled by by linking
所以它是一种非常强大而且有趣的技术，它通过链接实现
So let's start with a simple program
让我们从一个非常简单的程序开始吧
This program consists of two modules a main.c and sum.c
这个程序里包含两个模块 main.c 和 sum.c
sum.c takes as an array as an argument and a length n
sum.c 将一个数组和一个长度 n 作为参数
And then it sums up the elements of that array and returns the sum  back to the caller
然后它计算了该数组中元素的总和并将总和返回给调用者
main.c calls the sum function
main.c 调用了 sum 函数
Using and passes it a two element array of ints
使用并传递一个两元素的 int 类型数组
And then returns the value received from some
然后返回了从其中收到的值
Yeah we that that's kind of an odd thing to do to return your exit status like that
是的，我们认为像这样返回退出状态是件奇怪的事情
But we just did it so that the compiler wouldn't optimize away all of a code
但我们这样做，以便编译器不会优化掉所有代码
I know let's look at what happens if when we want to compile those those two modules
让我们来看看如果我们想要编译那两个模块会发生什么
For each of main.c and sum.c
对于每个 main.c 和 sum.c
The GCC calls a series of translators on that,on those modules,on those .c files
GCC 会在这些模块上调用 .c 文件上的一系列翻译器
First calls the C preprocessor cpp
首先调用 C 预处理器 cpp(将 main.c 翻译成 ASCII 中间文件 main.i)
Then it calls the compiler,the actual compiler which is cc1
然后它调用编译器，实际上使用的编译器是叫 cc1(将 main.i 翻译成 ASCII 汇编语言文件 main.s)
The compiler generates assembly which is then translated by the assembler as
编译器生成汇编程序，然后汇编器将其翻译
And resulting in a .o file called main.o
结果生成了一个 .o 文件,称为 main.o
Similar things happens for sum.c
sum.c 也发生了类似的事情
So after these three translators work on the code
在这三个翻译器处理完代码之后
We have two object files two .o files
生成了两个 .o 格式目标文件
The linker takes those those .o files
链接器取到这些 .o 格式目标文件
And put some,links them together sort of smashes them together to form a single executable called that we can then run
然后放一些（必要的系统目标文件），将它们链接在一起，将它们拼凑在一起，创建一个单个的可执行文件然后运行
Then we can then load and run on the system
然后我们就可以加载并运行到系统上
So the main.c and sum.c they are called source files
所以 main.c 和 sum.c 被称为源文件
These .o files are object files that
这些 .o 文件
We are separately compiled
虽然是我们分开编译的目标文件
But we call them relocatable object files
但我们还是要叫他们可重定位目标文件
Because they can be combined together to form the fully linked executable object file
因为它们可以组合在一起形成完全链接的可执行目标文件
So why do we do it like this, you know why do we allow this so-called separate compilation
那为什么我们这样做呢，你知道为什么我们允许这种所谓的分开编译
You know why don't we just have like one big you know one big file that with all of code in it
你知道为什么我们不喜欢一个包含所有代码的大文件
Well there's a couple reasons the first is is modularity so by allowing you to break your code into smaller pieces
有一些原因，首先是模块化，所以允许你将代码分解成更小的部分
You can put related functions into separate source files
你可以将相关功能放入单独的源文件中
You can define libraries of functions
你可以定义函数库
So it's just good technique and it allows you to kind of break your code up into nice modular pieces
所以这只是一种很好的技术，它可以让你将代码分解成很好的模块化部分
The other reason is efficiency
另一个理由是效率
So if we've broken up our program into multiple chunks
所以如果我们把我们的程序分为多个块
If we change and if we only need to change one of the chunks
如果我们改变，比如如果我们只需要更改其中一个块
We don't have to recompile the all the other modules
我们就没必要重新编译所有其他模块
Right we can just recompile the one module that we changed and then link them all together again
对，我们可以重新编译我们更改的一个模块，然后再将它们全部链接在一起
Right so it's efficient in time it's also efficient in space
所以这在时间和空间上都是有效的
Because you can take all of the functions in the standard C library you could put them all together
因为你可以使用标准 C 库中的所有功能，所以你可以将它们放在一起
But then the only functions that you actually get compiled and linked into your program are the ones that you actually call
但是，实际编译并链接到程序中的唯一函数是你实际调用的函数
Ok so you can save space
好的，这样你就可以节省空间
You don't you know normally you use only a small subset of the standard C functions
你通常不知道你其实只使用标准 C 函数的一小部分
So there's no point in linking all of those functions into your code if you don't need them
因此，如果你不需要将所有这些功能链接到代码中，那就没有意义了
Alright so what do linkers do
好吧，那么链接器做了什么呢
Well there's two main tasks that a linker performs
链接器执行的主要任务有两个
The first is called simple resolution
第一个被称为简单解析（符号解析）
So programs define and reference symbols
为了程序定义和应用符号
Okay that what the linker refers to as symbols and these are global variables and functions
好的，链接器称为符号，这些是全局变量和函数
Okay in the names and those objects they're referred to as a symbol
在名称和那些对象中，它们被称为符号
So here we're declaring,we're defining a symbol called swap
第一行代码，我们在这里声明，我们正在定义一个名为swap的符号
Here we're referring when we call swap, we're referring to that symbol
中间这行我们称之为 swap ，我们指的是那个符号
Okay that's a reference to the symbol
是的，这是对符号的一种引用
And here we're defining a pointer to an int called xp
最后一行，我们定义了一个指向名为 xp 的 int 类型指针
So we're defining xp and we're initializing it to the address of x
所以我们定义了 xp ，将它初始化为取 x 的地址
So we're referring,that's a reference to x
这指的是，这是对 x 的引用
Okay so the symbol definitions are stored in the object file by the assembler
汇编器将符号定义存储在目标文件中
In a symbol table which is an array of structs
在这个符号表里面，全是一系列结构数组
Where each structs contains information about the symbol
每个结构数组里面包含有关该符号的信息
Like the name of the symbol its size and where it's located
比如符号的名称，它的大小和位置等等信息
Now what we mean by symbol resolution is that during the linker linking process
所以现在我们说符号解析的意思是在链接器链接过程中
The linker associates each symbol reference with exactly one symbol definition
链接器将每个符号引用与一个符号定义相关联
Okay so it's possible in multiple
好的，所以这可能有多个
You know why is this an issue well it's possible like in multiple modules
这中间可能会有些问题，比如在多个模块中
You may declare a global variable with the same name
你可能会声明一个有相同名称的全局变量
The linker has to decide which one of those definitions to use for all subsequent references
链接器必须决定将其中的某个定义用于所有后续引用
Now once the linker is associated a unique object
一旦链接器和一个独一无二的目标建立联系
With each a unique symbol definition with each reference
每个引用都会有一个唯一的符号定义
Then it does the second step which is relocation
然后它执行第二步，即重定位
And during relocation it merges all of the modules together
在重定位期间，它会将所有模块合并在一起
Into a single executable object module that can be directly loaded and executed on the system
进入单个可执行目标模块后，就可以直接在系统上加载和执行
So when it does this merging
所以当它合并时
It has to figure out where each symbol,each function and each variable is going to be stored
它必须弄清楚每个符号，每个函数和每个变量是要准备存储在哪
And this is called relocation
这称为重定位
Because initially functions are just stored at some offset in their object module
因为最初的函数只是存储在其目标模块中的某个偏移处
Right because that the linker doesn't know where those functions are actually going to be eventually a loaded into memory
正确，因为链接器不知道这些函数最终会被真正加载到内存中的哪个地方
So before relocation the address of a function in the object module is just its offset in the module and similarly for data
所以在重定向前目标模块中的函数地址只是它在模块中的偏移量，对于数据也是如此
During the relocation step the linker decides on
在重定位步骤期间，链接器会决定
Where each symbol is going to be ultimately located in memory one at x,when the program executes
当程序执行时，每个符号最终将位于 x 中的存储区中的哪里
And it binds that those absolute memory locations to the symbol
并且它将那些绝对存储器位置绑定到符号
And then it goes and looks at all the references to those symbols
然后它会继续向下执行并查看所有对这些符号的引用
And it updates those references so that they now they point to the correct address
而且它它会更新那些引用，以便它们现在能指向正确的地址
Okay so figure out where stuff is going to go
好的，所以弄清楚原料要去哪里
For each definition figure out where it's going to go and for each reference then update that reference
对于每个定义，找出它要去的位置以及每个引用，然后更新该引用
So it now points to the right spot
所以它现在指向正确的位置
So let's look at what these...how these steps work in more detail
那么让我们来看看这些......这些步骤如何更详细地运作
Before that we need to define a few things
在那之前我们需要定义一些东西
So there's three kinds of object modules that I've alluded to
所以我提到了三种目标模块
There's the .o file which is a relocatable object module this is the output of the assembler
.o 文件是可重定位目标模块，这是汇编器的输出
And it's not a binary file
它不是一个二进制文件
But it's not in any form that can be directly loaded into memory
但它不能以任何形式直接加载到内存中
It needs to be manipulated by the linker before it can be actually used
在实际使用之前，需要由链接器对其进行操作
There's the executable object file which is generated by the linker
由链接器生成的可执行目标文件
These is called a.out files
这被称为 a.out 文件
Sometimes historically the very first Linux systems the executable
在历史上第一个Linux操作系统就是可执行的
This sort of the default name that they the developers of Unix used,the default name for their executables was a.out
这是Unix开发人员使用的默认名称，其可执行文件的默认名称是a.out
So that's just sort of a historical reason that it's called a.out
所以这只是一个历史原因所以它被称为a.out
And then there's another type of object file called a shared object file or .so file
然后是另一种称为共享目标文件或.so文件的目标文件
Which is a modern technique for creating shared libraries
这是一种用于创建共享库的现代技术
And we'll look at those,we'll look at those later today
那个我们之后再了解，将在今天晚些时候再学习了解
Now object modules come in a standard format called ELF format
现在，目标模块采用称为ELF格式的标准格式
And it's a unified format for .o files for executables and for .so files
它是可执行文件，.so文件，.o文件的统一格式
They all use the same format,the same general format
他们都使用一样的格式，一样的通用的格式
So this while these ELF binaries are
这就是这些 ELF 二进制文件
Their binaries they're very structured
他们的二进制文件非常有条理
Ok and they're broken up into sections
他们被分成几个部分
The at the beginning is a header,that defines things like the size of the word the byte ordering
开头是一个头，它定义了（生成该文件系统的）字节顺序和字的大小
Whether it's a .o,a .out or a .so
无论是 .o,.out 还是 .so
So it just provides some sort of general information about this binary
它只是提供了关于这个二进制文件的一般信息
And then there's what's a so called segment header table which is
然后就是所谓的节头部表
It's only defined for the executable object files
它只在可执行目标文件中定义
And indicates where all the different segments of the code are going to go in memory
并指出代码的所有不同段在内存中的位置
So where does your stack go, where do your shared libraries go
那么你的栈在哪里，你的共享库去了哪里
Where does your that you're initialized and uninitialized data
你初始化数据和未初始化数据的位置在哪里
Where does your code go
你的代码去了哪里
Right so all these various sections are defined in the segment header table
正确，因此所有这些不同的部分都在段头表中定义
And then there's the code itself which is called the .text section for sort of arcane historical reasons
然后是代码本身，出于某种神秘的历史原因它被称为.text部分
So .text is always code
.text 一般是代码
And then that's followed by read only data
然后是只读数据
Such as the jump tables in switch statements
比如switch语句中的跳转表
So text and read only the .text and .rodata have the property that they're both read-only you don't write to them
因此，文本.text和只读.rodata具有以下属性：它们都是只读的，你不会写入它们
Then that's followed by the .data section
然后是.data部分
Which is contains space for all of your initialized global variables
它包含了所有初始化全局变量的空间
And then there's a section called .bss
接下来是一个名为.bss的部分
Which defines the uninitialized global variables
它定义了未初始化的全局变量
Now this doesn't actually take up any space because they're uninitialized droids
这个节实际上并没有占用任何实际的空间，因为它们仅仅是未初始化的占位符
Ok but there are entries in the symbol table for them
好的，但符号表中会有条目
And in it at when this program gets loaded these variables are going to need
在这个程序加载时会需要这些变量
They're actually going to have to have space allocated for them
在这个时候就必须为他们分配空间
.bss is another one of those sort of arcane names,that cope goes all the way back to the 60s
.bss 是另一种神秘的名字，应对可以追溯到60年代
For there was IBM instruction called the block started by symbol
那时候IBM指令将其称为块符号
I think a better way to remember what it means is better save space
我认为理解它的意义最好的方式是 better save space (BSS)的缩写
Ok so you can,if you have a separate section for the uninitialized variable since uninitialized
好的，如果在未初始化过程开始时有一个单独的节用于未初始化的变量，你可以这样理解
You don't have to...they don't have to consume any room in the .o file
他们不必占用.o文件中的任何空间
Ok there's also a section for the symbol table
好的接下来还有一个部分是针对符号表的
This contained like I said it's an array of structs for procedures global variables
就像我之前说的那样它包含程序全局变量的结构数组
And anything defined with the static attribute
以及我们使用static属性定义的任何内容
And each one of these symbols gets an entry in the symbol table
并且这些符号中的每一个都在符号表中获得了一个条目
And then there's two sections called them that contain relocation info so this is the notes
然后有两个部分称为包含重定位信息的部分，称为记录
When that linker went and identified all the references to symbols it put a little note to see
当链接器去识别所有对符号的引用时，它就会记下一些记录
I'm going to have to remember to fix this the reference to this symbol up
我不得不记住去安排对这个符号的引用
When I actually create the executable
在我实际创建可执行文件时
So a relocation entry is just like that the linker
所以重定向条目就像链接器一样
That it's a note that the assembler makes to the linker to say hey you're going to have to fix up this this reference
这是一个记录，汇编程序让链接器说“嘿”，你将不得不安排这个引用
Because I don't know I don't know where this symbol is actually going to be stored in memory when it's loaded
因为我不知道这个符号在加载时实际存储在内存中的位置
Okay and then there's a debug section that contains
好的，接下来是调试部分
Information that relates line numbers to in the source code to line numbers in the machine code
它包含了将源代码中的行号与机器代码中的行号相关联的信息
Okay and so this is called .debug and this is what you get when you compile with -g
好的，所以这叫做 .debug，这是你用-g编译时得到的
And then there's a header table that tells you where all these different sections start
然后有一个节头表，告诉你所有这些不同部分的起始位置
Now to a linker there's three different kinds of symbols
现在我们说链接器有三种不同的符号
Global symbols are defined in some module m
全局符号在一些模块 m 中定义
And they can be used by other modules
它们可以被其他模块使用
Right so I mean did you notice when we...if we have a program that consists of multiple modules
是的，所以我的意思是你注意到我们......如果我们有一个由多个模块组成的程序
And we compile each one of those modules into a .o file
然后我们将每个模块编译成一个 .o 文件
Will be calling functions that aren't defined,that are defined by other modules right
将调用由其他模块正确定义的未定义的函数
Okay so those,but there's no error though that the compiler doesn't throw an error
好吧那些，但是虽然编译器没有抛出错误
Because it's assuming that those are defined in other modules and
因为它假设那些是在其他模块中定义的
It assumes the linker will be able to find them in and determine the address
它假定链接器能够找到它们并确定地址
So anything that's defined with that, any global,either global variable or function name
所以用任何全局变量或函数名定义的任何东西
That's defined without the static attribute is a global symbol
没有静态属性的定义是全局符号
Okay now and then external symbols are kind of the flip side of that
External symbols are symbols that are referenced by some module
But defined in some other module
Okay so in a little running example
When main.c code called the function some it was referencing an external symbol
Okay and then there's local symbols and these are symbols that are defined and referenced within a module
Okay and those you create that,this is not this is different from local variables
Okay the linker you know local C variables are managed by the compiler on the stack
Linker has no idea about local C variables
Okay in this context when we talk about a local symbol
We're talking about is either, is a global variable or function declared with the static attribute
Whose that can only be referenced from within that module
So we say that the scope of the a function or global variable defined with the static
Attribute is limited to the module that it was defined in
Okay so this is in C, this is how we do abstraction
And this is how we can create sort of private functions that
And private functions that can't be called from outside that module
Okay so for instance if we want to make a library in C of functions, we want to make a collection of functions that
Other programs can then call it link into their program and call
The functions that we want to make visible to other programs are defined without the static attribute
And the functions that we want to have private and just be internal
We declare what the static attribute okay
And that way we get abstraction and we get hiding information hiding
And we're only exposing data and functions that we want to expose
All right so let's look in detail how the symbol resolution step works
We call a example program
So here we're referencing a global called array
That's defined within main.c
Here we're defining main
A global called main
Here we're referencing a global called sum
That's defined in sum.c
And val is a local C variable on the stack and linker knows nothing about that okay
Now loads i, s which are also local variables
Now let's make sure that we understand the difference between local static C variables versus local non static C variables so
Here we're defining a local static variable called int
Within this function f
Now because it's local, its scope is limited to this function
So this variable x can only be referenced within function f
And similarly for this definition of x in function g
Can only be referenced by function g
Now what's ,but because it's declared with the static attribute it's not stored on the stack
It's actually stored in .data just like a global would be
So it's like a global in the sense that it's actually stored in .data rather than the stack
But it's like a local C variable in the sense that its scope is limited just to the function that it's defined in
Okay so what the compiler will do it'll allocate space for each definition of x
So this and it'll give it some name to disambiguate it
So maybe it will call this one x.1
And maybe this one x.2
So these symbols are allocated in .data because
Because they're initialized and they get symbol table entries just like any other symbol
Okay so I said that during symbol resolution
The linker associates each reference,each symbol reference to exactly one unique symbol definition
Now how does it do that if there's multiple symbol definitions across all the modules
So to understand this will define symbols as being either strong or weak
So strong symbols are either procedures or function names or initialize global variables
Weak symbols or uninitialized global variables
Okay so int foo here is a strong symbol
Because it's initialized,we're initializing it. p1 is strong by definition
foo is weak in p2.c, this definition of foo is weak
Because it's uninitialized and the definition of p2 is strong
Okay so that the rules, the linker uses are the following
Multiple strong symbols not allowed so that's an error
Okay so that means that if across multiple modules we declare a function with the same name
The linker will throw an error that's not allowed
Given a strong symbol and multiple weak symbols if the linker will always choose the the strong symbol
Now remember if we initialize a global variable
And we if we declare an initialized global variable across multiple modules that's an error
Because those are strong symbols okay by rule one
But if we have one strong symbol and multiple weak symbols all with the same name
Then the compiler will choose the strong symbol
Okay and it will associate all references to that symbol will go to that strong symbol
And if there's multiple weak symbols then it just picks an arbitrary one
And this is we'll see can be problematic now you can override with this GCC flag called no common
And if you declare your function with this no common argument
Then multiple weak symbols will throw an error in a linker
All right so why do we care about all this stuff well it turns out
If you're not aware of this stuff you can run into some really serious problems
That are just perplexing and confounding right so
Linker errors are like the worst kind
They're the hardest kind of debug because people aren't usually aware of what's going on inside their linkers
And usually it's only like the very best programmers that really understand
You know how these linkers work and what kind of errors they can throw and how to debug them
So let me show you some examples of these kind of errors
All right so we have a program
We have two modules so each of these rectangles corresponds to a module
And we're defining p1 in each module so
That's too strong symbols that's an error
Okay now here we've defining p1 and p2 so we're okay
But now we've got two week symbols both are integers variables called x
So and if these modules are referencing x the linker will just pick it will just pick one of these to serve as the definition
But is this really what you want
Now in this case it doesn't really hurt anything because x is declared in both modules as an int
All right so it'll just be some integer sized variable
That and it'll be somewhere
And but it doesn't really matter which one the linker chooses
But we start to get into trouble if we declare these weak symbols with different types
So here we've declared an int x in one module and a double x in another module
So if we write to x, if the linker just arbitrarily chooses this,this symbol definition to use
Now this is a symbol that of length 8 of size 8
If we anywhere in this program,if the linker chooses that then, anywhere in the program
Those references to x will be to this double word,this double word
Even in this module if we reference x it'll be an 8-byte right
So it will overwrite y with the
Hi order excuse me
[student speaking]
Oh no it's completely,it's just pick one arbitrarily
And you don't know
I mean it
Now this is here's a problem we've defined a strong symbol x because we've initializes
So the linker will always,will associate all references to x to this integer sized this integer sized symbol
So if we write
Oh yeah right,so rights to x here
This will be a double in this module but it will overwrite y in this module
So that's really nasty
And here we were defining a strong symbol x
So references to x in the second module will always get it will refer to this initialized variable which might not
So it might not be what you want right
You may be assuming that it's uninitialized in your code
Okay and then you get the, the ultimate nightmare scenario is suppose
You know because we're following a standard ABI we can compile our code with multiple compilers
And this actually happens in some oh yes questions
[student speaking]
Oh yeah actually you're right
It will still take preference and and you'll be writing a for by quantity
Which is what you want so that slides not quite right
So oh yeah what is the point of doing the static versus non static
If it's always being referenced just locally in constantly what is the point of declaring  it's time
-is it it stores it in like -no no no it's
If you reference up if you reference a variable
You mean so a variable is defined in your module
And then you...with the static...right
Oh they're both,they're both local
So you do this if you want to value two to retain
From if you want if you want that variable to retain value from invocation to invocation
So suppose you it's usually a bad idea as we'll see when we study threads
Because it makes your code non thread safe
But like early like random number generators
Would it would compute a pseudo-random number
And then it would store it in a static variable
And then use that as the the starting value for the next time you call that function
So whenever you want values to persist across function invocation to reduce static
Yes something really crash
Well wait a minute let me...
Let me get this straight writes to x and p2 will actually correspond to the memory
Look that it will actually go to the memory location I'm sorry I need to amend that
So writes to x in p2 will be 8 bytes
Because the compiler you know the compiler knows that it's a double
But it'll go to a memory location that's only 4 bytes
Because x because the linker chose the strong symbol
Okay so the rights to x and p2 will actually overwrite y
I'm sorry yes question
[student speaking]
That's just usually the way it happens
You know...[student speaking]
No no no global variables go in data they don't go on the stack
But usually if you define local variables in a function
It will put them,it will allocate them one after the other on the stack
Okay all right so all this discussion about
These weird strong weak symbol rules that the linker have
It's another reason to avoid global variables if you can
Now if you need to declare a global see if you can declare it static
Because that'll limited scope to the the module that it's declared in
So that's a good idea if you can do it
And if you define a global variable initialize it
So that you'll find,you'll discover if you have multiple initialize global symbols with the same name in your code
And then if you want to it's always good practice
If you're referencing an external variable to tell the compiler about it by using the x turn attribute
All right
So now at this point the linker has associated every symbol reference  with some simple definition
Now it has to take all those object relocatable object files and smush them together
And create like one big executable
So suppose with our example a little running example
Each main.o and sum.o contain a code and initialize data
sum.o doesn't have any initialize data it just has code
And then there's their system code that actually runs before and after your program so
When your program run it actually starts executing a startup code from  from lib.c
That that sort of initializes things and then the last thing that it does is it calls main and passes it rc and rv
Okay and then when you're, when your program exits
Well that's a cyst call,but if your program if your main function routine does a return
Then it returns back to that startup code which then doesn't exit okay
So this is just...so this this consists of of text and data as well
And so when the linker relocates these object files
It takes all of the code the text sections from each of the modules
And puts them together contiguously init in the .text section for the executable object file
Ok so it just puts them together in some order that it determines
And it creates a combined .text section in the executable
That contains all of the system code and the all of the all of the code defined in the modules
And then it does the same thing with the data takes all the .data
Sections from the various object files and puts them together
In one combined .data section in the executable
And it also emerges the symbol tables and in the debug information as well
Now when it just the act the act of sort of
Relocating these object files requires the linker
To figure out where it's going to actually store these
These different these different symbols when the system gets, when this program gets loaded
So it has to pick an address for main that
That function will start at some absolute address
It's going to have... it's going to do the same for swap,so for all the all the data arrays right
And but the problem is that when this code is compiled,the compiler doesn't know what addresses the linker is going to pick
So the compiler creates these reminders to the linker called relocation entries
Which are then stored in the relocation sections of the the object file
And these relocation entries are instructions to the linker that's something
That there's a reference to a symbol that's going to have to be patched up
When the the code is actually relocated and merged into the executable
So let's look at a couple of these a couple of examples so in
Our in our main.c module there was a reference to this global symbol called array
Okay and then there was also a reference to this global symbol sum which is the function
So the compiler creates two relocation entries
The first one for the reference to the array a
So here we're moving remember %edi is the first argument
So remember a sum function takes the address of the of array
Of the input array as its argument
So this move we're moving the address of the array into %edi for the first argument
But the compiler doesn't know what that address is going to be
Right so it just it just it just
It just moves in an immediate value of 0 into %edi temporarily right so you can see this is all zeros
The bf is the move instruction and then there's all zeros for now
And then it places this relocation entry in the relocation section of main.o
And it says to the linker at offset a
So these let me remind you these are main.o
Module only contains one function
So that function starts that offsets zero in the code section of the module in the .text section of the module
If there were other functions in this module they would follow immediately after
Ok and it so you can see what the compiler it's just generating offsets of these instructions
From the beginning of the .text section
And it includes this relocation entry which says to the linker hey
When you're relocating main.o add offset a in this .text section
You've got a reference,a reference to an array in the form of a 32-bit address
Ok so that,so eventually the linker is going to have to patch up these
So this is address , this is address a
It's going to have to patch up the four bytes starting at address a
With the absolute address of the symbol array
And then similarly the reference to,the reference to,this the reference to this function some
The compiler has no idea where some actually will end up
It doesn't even know what module it's in or even if it's, even if it is defined in a module
So in this case it just it does a call with all zeros
And then it adds this relocation entry that says to the linker
At offset f you've got a four byte pc-relative reference to a function,to assemble called sum
And then it this is sort of a arcane detail that but and it includes
There's an option to include a bias in the in the offset
And since we're using since calls are always resolved using pc-relative addressing
The value that's going to be placed here at these four bytes that offset f
Is going to be an offset from the current %rip value or program or counter value
And since the program counter always points to the nest get next instruction
It includes this which is four bytes away it includes this
This offset of minus four
So I talked about it in detail in the book if you really want to know how this works
But just the point here is that there's enough information for the linker to actually fill in the right address
So now if we look at the relocated text section
So if we compile this code into an executable and then we use object on to disassemble it
Then what you see is this reference here
Where we move the address of the address of a into %edi
Those four bytes which were original zero have now been updated with the actual address of array in memory at runtime
Okay so the linkers decided that the array is going to go at address 0x601018
And then it's actually patched that the four bytes in the cup in the in the move instruction with that absolute address
And the call to sum is...it's also been updated
But this one's interesting right that
So the address it's been updated with the pc relative address of five
Okay so when this program runs
This call instruction
What it will do when it when it determines when it computes the absolute address of the function sum
It will take...
It will take the current value of the program counter which is the next instruction so 0x4004e3
And it will add to it whatever value is in this immediate field
Okay which is a two's comp... interpret it as a two's complement integer so it can go
It can be relative you can go - or +
In this case it's saying that the function that you want to call is at 0x4004e3 + 5
Which is 0x4004e8 which is the address of some
Okay and so the linker does that the compiler has all the smarts
The compiler computed the relocation entry
The linker is just blindly going through each of those relocation entries and just doing what it's told
Okay but the net result is that now all of these these references have been patched up with valid absolute addresses
Now once the linkers created an object file
That object file can be loaded the code and data
And that object file can be loaded directly into memory with no further modification
Ok so the if you look at all of the read-only sections in the executable
So there's this init section which
We're not to worry about that, all the code is in the .text and things like jump tables are in .rodata
All of this data can be loaded directly into memory as is
Okay so these bytes can just be copied directly into memory
And that forms the so called a read-only code segment
The data in the .data and .bss  sections can also be copied directly into memory
And in the case of the variables and .data they'll be initialized to a value that's stored in the symbol table
So we're drawing a memory here
This is the (memory) address space that every Linux program sees
And we're drawing addresses starting from 0 and going up increasing as we grow up
And every program is loaded at this the same address  0x400000
And so the the code comes directly from the object file the data comes directly from the object file
And then that's followed by a runtime heap
Which is created and managed by malloc
So when you need dynamically need to allocate memory
Like using malloc that memory comes out of this heap
Which starts immediately following the data segment and grows upwards
The stack is at the very top of the visible memory that's available to application programs
The memory above that is restricted to the kernel
Okay so if you try to access those memory locations you'll get a seg fault
And then the stack as we know grows down so this is managed and created a run time
And then there's this region somewhere in this huge gap between the stack and the heap
There's a region for shared libraries so the .so files all get loaded into this memory mapped region for shared libraries
Now that the top of the heap is indicated by this global variable
Maintained by the kernel called break brk
And the the top of the stack as we know is maintained by the general purpose register %rsp
Now there's a little bit of a...this is a little bit of a simplification
If you actually look at the addresses returned by malloc
There's actually,a there's actually two heaps
There's a heap up here and in the high memory that grows down
That's used for large objects,very large
You know if you mount like a whole bunch of space
And then the heap that grows up is  is reserved for smaller smaller objects
So I'm not really sure why they do this
I think it allows them to have separate allocation algorithms for large objects and small objects
Okay so one of the real advantages of linking is that allows us to create libraries of things
So it's always something we want to do as programmers we always...
We always want to create abstractions and then present those abstractions to users
Right and we do that by creating libraries defining an api
Yes
[student speaking]
I think it just is...no no it
Actually that's a good question I... the things I've done it just grows until it runs out of memory right there
So I don't think actually that's a really good question I mean I've...
I've done those experiments and it eventually reaches some limit
Yeah I don't know it's a very large number
But I so you know as programmers we always want to abstract define apis
Implement package up those api's and make them available to to other programmers
So how can we actually do that how can we make commonly used functions available to other programmers
Well one thing given what we've learned so far
You could just take all the functions and put them all in a single big C file right
And then programmers would just link that C file into their programs if they want to use them right
Another option would be to take that might get kind of unwieldy if it's a big library right
Lipsi has hundreds and hundreds of functions
So another option would might be to just take each function put it in a separate file
And then compile them all together and compile and link them all together
So this is more space and time efficient than then the first option
But it seems like it would be burdensome on the programmer because
The program would have to know where all the all these functions were and put them in make files
It'd just be a lot of you know this you could end up with a ridiculously large command line to GCC
So that one solution to this problem is that
The first solution that the developers of Unix came up with us
Something called a static library
So the the idea where the static library is that you create this archive  called a .a file
Which is it's just a collection of .o file where each .o file contains a function
Ok so you take all the functions in your library you use option two to create a bunch of .o files
And then you use a program called an archive or AR  to take those .o files
Put them together in a all together in a big file called an archive
With a table of contents at the beginning that tells you the offset of each one of the .o files
Ok so an archive is just this concatenated collection of .o files
And then and then you link you pass that archive to the linker
And it only takes the .o files that are actually referenced  and links them into the code
Right so it's a more efficient way you can have a huge archive
But like lib.c but if you only call printf
The only .o file you get is printf.o
Okay so the way this works is
As before we take
We take all the functions we want to put in our library
We run them through our translators to get .o files
We pass those to the archiver to get a the archive
So in this case libc.a
And which has this code for printf that we might want to use
Right and so we can recreate that archive anytime we want
So if one of these functions changes like say printf changes
You just re archive the dot recompile printf and then re archive all of the .o files
So in libc it's about 1500 object files
And it's archived things like printf,scanf,simple integer math and there's also a math library
Which has you know several hundred common functions for things like
Floating point math sin,cos,tan gent etc
These libraries the convention is that a library always is prefixed with lib with lib and then
And then sort of new some indication of what it what it does
So now let's see how linking with these static libraries would work
So I've created a little example here
I've created a library called libvector.a
And it consists of functions that manipulate vectors
And this is a real simple library it just adds
There's a function to add two vectors x and y together and return the result in z
And then another similar function that will do pairwise multiplication of two vectors so
x[i]*y[i] equals z[i]
Now I compile these two programs and pack I want to package them into an archive called libvector.a
And then in my main program I'm going to call one of those functions addvec
To add these two vectors x and y together
So now what happens when we compile this this program
We've already we've constructed the archive libc.a  from addvec.o and multvec.o
And we pass that archive to the linker along with a main 2.0 relocatable object file
And we also pass it libc.a
Which has the definition of which contains printf.o
And anything else that printf.o my call
So these three the linker detects the reference to addvec the function addvec
And so it just pulls addvec.o out and ignores the rest,similarly for printf.o
And then it compiles all those
Main main.o addvec.o and printf.o all together into this fully linked executable
Called prog2c for compiled time
So we're doing this,we're doing this link,we're doing this this linking at compile time
When we call a GCC
Now what the linker does when it's using static libraries
It scans all the .o files and .a files in order on the command line
So you're just typing GCC and then a list of .o files and .a files in some order
So during the scan it keeps a list of the current unresolved references right
If let's say let's say it looks at main.o first and there's a reference to printf
That's an unresolved reference because print is not defined in main.o
So that goes in a list of undefined references
And at some point or another as each new .o file or .a file is encountered
The linker tries to without but list of references with the symbols that are defined in that .o file or .a file
And then if there's any entries in the list at the end of the scan then there's error
Okay so that the key here is that the linker will try to resolve these references from left to right on the command line
And so this is another sort of important thing for you to know as programmers
Because the order that you put your files on the command line actually makes a difference
Okay so you can get sort of weird baffling linker errors if you use the wrong order
So for instance suppose we've got
A function an object module called libtest
That calls a function that's defined in lmine.a
Okay so these -L, -L period that says to look for,to look for a library files in the current directory
That's what the dot look there first and then look in the normal places that you look
And the the -l that's a it's like an abbreviation
We could replace this with just the fully spelled out lmind.a
Okay but you'll see this this  -l used a lot
So libtest calls a function that's declared in lmind.a
So the linker looks at it looks at the unresolved symbols in libtest.o
And it detects that there's this unresolved function let's say it's called foo
I know it's it's called libfun
So and it puts it on the list and then it goes on to the next command line entry and that's lmine.a
And in there it finds it finds this symbol of libfun
And it resolves the reference to that libfun to the actual address the relocated address
Now if we switch the order and we put lmine.a first followed by libtest.o
Well there's no unresolved references in this library
Right it's just the collection of function definitions
So it there's no unresolved references so the linker looks at that that's all good
And then it looks at libtest.o and now there's an unresolved reference to two libfun
But we're out of we're at the end of the command line
So that's a linker error
So you get this you get this really cryptic error message
And if you didn't know about this ordering rule you wouldn't have any idea how to debug
It okay so the static libraries are kind of the old fashioned solution that
The modern solution is to use dynamic libraries or shared libraries
So the reason the reason there's this sort of newer form of libraries
That static libraries have some disadvantages
So every if you compile with static libraries
Then every every function that uses printf
Which or every program that uses printf has to have a copy of printf
Okay but almost every every program uses printf right
So there's a shared libraries allow provide a mechanism where there can just be one
Wherever there's just one instance of a shared library member like printf
And every program running on the system will share that one copy
So that's sort of the big disadvantage is this potential duplication
So shared libraries are different in the sense that they contain
Code and data that are linked and loaded into the program not when it's
Not when it's compiled and linked and into a executable object file
But actually when the program is loaded into the system
So linking of references to shared library objects is deferred
Until the program is actually loaded into memory
Until the executable object file is actually loaded into memory
And this can either and it can even happen
It can happen when the program is actually loaded into memory but it can also happen at runtime anytime at runtime
So you can be...you can be running a program
And that program can arbitrarily decide to load a function that's declared in a shared library
Okay and I'll show you that it's really cool
Now these things are often called they're called shared libraries
They're called dynamic link libraries like in windows they're called dlls
.iso files they're all referenced the same thing
Okay so that this like I said you can...
The dynamic linking can occur when the program's loaded or after it's loaded and actually running
And there's this sort of big deal that shared library routines can be shared by multiple processes
And we'll look at this this will make sense when we look at virtual memories
So don't worry about that now
But but here's how the process works
So we've,first we have to create instead of creating an archive
We create a shared library,so our libvector routines
Instead of creating an archive a file we create a shared a .so file
Using the shared argument to GCC
So we take our two input functions a addvec and multvec
And share it says to create and we're telling GCC to create a shared library  and place it in libvector.so
Okay and so and there's also that the C developers have created a punctured library called libc.so
That contains printf and on it and other standard library functions
So we take our program main2,this is the same program that calls addvec
And we compile it into main2.o
And we pass main2.0 and  these .so files to the linker
Now the linker doesn't at this point it doesn't actually copy let's say we're using addvec or printf
It doesn't actually copy those functions or do anything with them in the executable
It just makes a note in the symbol table that those functions will need to be the
References to those functions will need to be resolved when the program is loaded
Okay so it,it puts in a relocation entry that says fix this up when you load the program
So it's partially linked but it's not fully linked
You can't take that,you can't take a program,you can't take a executable file
That was dynamically linked and loaded directly
What you do is the loader which is the execve system call
And we'll learn more about that, but just this is just a sys call that loads loads executables into memory and runs them
The loader takes the executable
And then it takes the shared .so files
That this program needs k it also made when the linker also made a note of which .so files it needs
So the loader calls the dynamic linker which takes those .so files
And then actually resolves all the references to any on any unresolved reference
Okay so the the address of addvec,the addvec and printf functions isn't determined until the program is loaded
And by that and it isn't determined by the dynamic linker until the program is loaded
So that the dynamic linker does it goes through a similar process that the static linker did
Sort of fixing up references to add back at references to printf
And then at that point the binary is in a form that can be executed directly
So question-yes-what if you look the part where did like where is that like if you include violence and use anger and greed zero actually
Okay the question is what happens if you include a file
So includes are handled by the C preprocessor
So they're gone, they're long gone, by the time the by the time the linker gets around to it
Okay so the C preprocessor just takes #define,#include
And and interprets those and outputs another C program
So if you include a file the C preprocessor just takes that file and just expands it
And the output C program contains an expanded version of all the files that you include it
Okay now what's really cool is that you can also do this dynamic linking at runtime
So what I showed you before we're doing it at load time
But you can also arbitrarily decide to load link and call a function from a shared from a from any function defined in a .so file
And the way you do it is there's a there's an interface called the dlopen
That's in lib.c that allows you to do this
So let's say we want to this is our main program and just like before we want to call addvec
Okay but addvec now is defined in a .so file
The exact same .so file that we generated before
When we compile,so we'll call this dll.c,when we compile this program ddl.c
We have no idea that it's going to call a function from lib.so
We just compile it as though a standalone C program
Within this program though we declare a pointer a function pointer called addvec
And we give the prototype for this function
It's pointers city so it's a two input arrays the output array on the size
And then first we dynamically load the shared library that contains the function we want
So we call dlopen and we say load up this .so file into memory
So that I can call a function
But don't resolve,you know don't worry about the resolving the references to it functions until I actually tell you too
That's the lazy part
And so what what this deal open returns a handle
That then you use in subsequent calls okay
So if we don't if the handle is null there was some kind of error like maybe this data .so file does exist
So once we've opened that .so file then we use dlsym with the handle so this
And then we give it as we pass as a string the name of the function that we want to invoke
And what we get back from dlsym as a pointer to that function
And then we can use that function just like any other function so we can use that function pointer
And we call it just as though it were a statically defined function
So you can see this is real very powerful technique
Okay so looks let's finish the last little bits of the class
I want to show you it to try to convince you that linking is is actually interesting which is kind of a hard sell sometime
Yes question...yes...no it's that's how you know
No you just it's declared as a function pointer
And you then you just use the name of the function you don't have to dereference it
Or you just you call it you call the function by just using that function pointer name okay
Just like I did
If you dereference it I just get back a pointer value
You get back the address of that function
All right so it's kind of a hard sell to that to convince you that linking is interesting
But I'm going to try
Ok so there's this powerful technique called inner library inter positioning
And the goal is to intercept function calls from libraries
And do something intercept them for some reason
Right so what we typically want to do is intercept a function call
Maybe record some to some statistics or do some error checking
And then call the real function as intended
Right so the idea is we're going to create wrappers
And when the program when a program calls a function what we're going to do is we're going to execute its wrapper instead
Okay and we're going to do it without changing any of the source
Now there's a lot of reasons there's a lot of applications for this
That the neatest one that I know is that these facebook engineers
So we're trying to deal with this year-long bug in the facebook iPhone app
And nobody could figure out what was going on
And they figured it out using library inter positioning
They figured out that there was something in the network stack writing to the wrong location
They figured it out by intercepting all the calls from their facebook app  that did rights
So things like write to the ep right
So they just they intercepted all those calls and then they were able to
To when they looked at the arguments and how those functions were being called
They determine the air
You can also use it for monitoring and profiling like
So if you want to know like how many times different functions get called you can you can interpose
We use it for generating address traces
So you're malloc when you do your malloc lab later in the semester
You're going to be evaluating your malloc using a traces
That we generated from real programs using this inter positioning technique
Right so we enter post on all the malloc and free calls in like netscape
And then we just recorded what addresses and sizes
Malloc was returning and what what blocks free was freeing up
And we just created a trace of those, and then, so let me show you how you would do this
So the idea let's say we have this main program
And the idea is to trace all the malloc and free calls
So there's one malloc call and there's one free call
And we want to know what these addresses are and we want to know what these sizes are
So we can do this at either compile time, link time or run time
To do it at compile time
We first write wrapper functions called mymalloc and myfree
Where mymalloc call most the real malloc function
And then it prints out the the size that it was called and the address that malloc returned
Okay so this when we run our program it will print out these all these addresses
And it does the same thing for free
And then here's the trick in malloc.h
We define malloc to be mymalloc ,okay and free to be myfree
And then we give the prototype for it so the compiler doesn't get confused
And then we can compile mymalloc.c into a .o file
And then we call week then we complete we call our program
Which is our main program int.c for inner positioning
And we call that and here's the trick
We call it with the -I argument
And we say look for any include files in the current directory
Okay so this was similar to that -L argument
But because we tell GCC to look in the current directory first
So this is sort of where the inner positioning happens
This because when it does that it's going to it's going to find a
It's going to find a library called malloc.h
I mean .h file called malloc.h
And so all the calls to malloc will be translated by the C preprocessor to mymalloc
So when we run this it prints out the the trip malloc and free trace
Now we can also do this at link time
So we can tell C,in order to do this we had to get access to the
We had to compile the program,we didn't have to change it but we had to compile it
We can use link time at our positioning if to avoid that compilation
So the way this works we define our wrapper functions with this special name underscore underscore wrap malloc
And this calls the real malloc function and then prints out the information
And then at link time then we do the inter positioning by calling the linker with this special -Wl  argument
And so what this does the -Wl flag to GCC says hey
Take what follows the argument that follows replace all the commas with spaces
And then invoke the linker with this argument
Okay so what we're doing is passing a linker arguments to the linker
And this --wrap argument to the linker
It tells the linker to resolve all references to malloc as underscore underscore wrap malloc
And all references to underscore real malloc - should be resolved as malloc
Okay so anywhere in the program what we call malloc it'll be resolved to underscore underscore wrap malloc
And it will invoke our wrapper and then the wrapper calls real malloc
Which by because of this flag resolves to the the actual malloc routine
Now here you can also in the really the really amazing thing
You can also do this inter positioning it load timer and run time when the program is loaded
So you don't even need access to the .o files all you need is access to the executable
Right and for every program we have access to the executable
So think about that we can take any program
And we can interpose on its library calls at runtime
So the way we do this is we write the wrapper function now uses the dlsym call that we saw before
And we call it with this special function the special argument called next
And we silver and what this is saying is get the address of the real malloc
Okay so and we're going to trick the linker into looking first to implementation of malloc
But here we want the real one,so we're telling it to get to look in the next place,its next place that it would normally look
And fetch the the address of malloc
So the result is a pointer a function pointer called mallocp
And then we can just call that function to get to call the libc malloc
And then print out the the data
Okay we do the same thing for free, we use dlsym in exactly the same way for free
And then the inter positioning now happens when the program is loaded
So notice we built this our main program now in tar for run time inter positioning
We built it I'm sorry we created our .so file mymalloc.so using the shared argument
And then we compiled int.c into this executable called intr
But notice there's no mention of mymalloc.so anywhere
And now the inner positioning happens when we actually run the program
And we do it,we affect the the inner positioning by setting an environment variable called ld-preload to mymalloc.so
And so what this is a environment variable that tells the dynamic linker
To look first in the value, it looked first in the the value of ld preload is a list of locations
Look first in those locations when to resolve references
And only later look in the normal system places
So we're saying to look in mymalloc.so unresolved references first
And then we're invoking,so this is in bash this is how you initialize an environment variable
So we're initializing it to mymalloc.so and then we're loading and running the program
And so the ld so all the references to malloc get turned into the references to the wrapper function
The malloc function that we defined in our program okay
Ok so that's it so that that inter positioning is a really cool technique
And it's only possible because of linkers so
alright so good we'll see you on on Thursday and good luck with your cache labs