all right well good afternoon everybody good to see you welcome
welcome to all those students watching on video as well
before we start we were talking about joinable and detached threads
and you asked the question about why you would ever want to have threads running in non detached mode
you know why you'd ever run in want to have him running joinable
and I didn't give you a very good answer so I want to try to to answer that for you better
turns out there's an important class of sort of parallel programming
there's a there's an important parallel programming model called fork and join
where program consists of a series of phases
in each phase in each phase you have a worker or a master sorry
and it creates a bunch of worker threads
and then each of those worker threads solve some part of the problem for that phase
like some maybe you take your data structure and you break it up into chunks
and then each thread updates the its own chunk of that data structure
but for whatever reason the the master then has to wait for the worker threads to finish before it can go on to the next phase
so it it does adjourn so this is called the fork
and then it waits for all the threads to finish
by doing a join okay so this is called
this is called the fork and this is called the join
and only when all of the threads have finished
can it go and do the next do the next phase
okay so this this model is really important in things like scientific computing where
you might you're simulating some domain you're simulating nature
so you represent that as some domain like maybe you're simulating
how heat flows over a plate you know metal plate
and so you might might have these workers
you might partition the domain amongst a set of those workers
and then each one of these phases is a time step
and then so once once all the workers have finished a time step then they can advance to the next time step
and so sorry I don't know why I didn't think of it
that's a that's an important reason why you'd want this
okay so we saw
we've seen the threaded threaded programs are are nice
because you they you can share all the global variables
but this the sharing can can have unintended consequences
so somehow we need a mechanism where we can control
how the flows of each individual thread are interleaved
so that bad things don't happen when we share data structures
okay so this this process of controlling the the interleaving is called synchronization
so we're going to look at techniques that you can use to write correct threaded programs by properly synchronizing them
now first though we need to have a clear idea
so sharing is the issue right if we have threads that aren't sharing any resources
then there's no problem right
that we saw this when we looked at it processes there's no shared data structures with processes
so we process these just run independently we don't really care how they're interleaved note no worries okay
but as soon as they introduce sharing then then we have to be careful
okay so to understand how to synchronize threads we first need to have a clear idea
of of what we mean by sharing in in threaded C programs
so the the answer is not as simple as global variables are shared and stack variables are not shared
okay so with instead what we X is shared
if and only if multiple threads reference some instance so that that variable X  all right
so if only one thread is accessing a particular variable
then it's it's not shared
okay so
in order to know exactly what we mean by shared we need to answer three questions
okay first what is the memory model for threads
okay second how are instances of variables mapped to memory
and then and then third how many threads might be referencing those the instances of those variables
okay so we'll look at each of those now in turn each of those three questions
okay so first is that the memory model
the conceptual model is a little bit different from the the operational model the way it really works
okay so conceptually
we have multiple threads that run in the context of a single process
okay and some of that context is shared and some of its not shared
so each thread has its own separate thread ID,stack,stack pointer,program counter,condition codes,general-purpose registers
and then they all share the remaining process context which is data structures that the kernel maintains
for the threads the virtual data structures to support the virtual memory system open files install signal handlers  and so forth
so that's the conceptual model and if that were that if that were really enforced
it would be nice it would make things simpler for us
but unfortunately in real life this model is not strictly enforced
now although register values are really separate right the kernel maintains separate context for the all the registers
so that that part is good
but since the threads share the the address space
a thread can access the the memory the stack one thread can access the stack of an another thread
okay so although conceptually these stacks are separate and distinct and
in private they're really not
and so this can create some problems
so here's an example of that we'll come back to later
of how this one thread can access the stack of another thread
so here we're defining a global variable called pointer
which is a char **
and then in the main routine on were declaring a local variable called messages which contains
it's a two element array which contains a couple strings
which these will be printed out by by the threads that we're going to create
and then we assign the global pointer to the vet to the address of the array messages
okay so now pointer points to messages
and then we create in a loop we create two threads
each of which executes this routine called thread
and and we're passing an argument
so the P threads will assign a thread ID but in this case we're going to assign our own local thread ID
by passing this loop index
okay so this is an example we talked about this last time
it's it's kind of it's this is perfectly okay there's no race
but it's it's a little weird because we're going to take this index  I and cast it to a generic pointer
okay and then after we create these threads then we'll exit the main thread
now each the thread routine dereferences its argument  to get the local the local thread ID
and then it it declares a static variable count
that we're going to use to count how many times this thread routine is called inside of a thread
and then it just prints a simple message from identifying that giving the local thread ID
and then the message indexed by myid
so pointer points to messages
so thread zero will print hello from foo
and thread 1 will print hello from bar
and then and then we increment the pre increment the counter variable
okay so
although it doesn't you wouldn't you would it looks like we're accessing this global variable pointer
but since that was assigned to be the address of the local variable on the main the main thread stack
we've got this these peer threads accessing local variables on the main thread stack okay
so that I just this is not it you never want to do this as a very bad practice
but I it's a kind of thing that can happen sometimes
by accident you know if you forget that pointer actually was assigned to you know some-some stack address
okay so that so the second question that is how do we map variable instances to memory
now we looked at this when we when we studied linking
but let's let's just review this quickly again to make sure that it's clear to you
so global variables are variables that are referenced outside of a function
and virtual memory the linker when it does symbol resolution make sure that
there's exactly one instance of every global variable in virtual memory
now local variables are declared on the stack inside of a function
without the static attribute
and so in this case each the stack for each thread will contain one instance of that local variable
now
if variables are declared inside of a function with the static attribute
then the scope of that variable is limited to that function meaning no other function can access it
but that static variable is stored along with all the other local variables
so there's any static variable declared inside of a function has exactly one instance in in memory
and if you were to have say multiple functions that declared the same a static variable with the same name
the compiler would would disambiguate those somehow
it would it would append some kind of unique
it would somehow make that name unique
okay so what recall how all these different types of variable instances are mapped into memory
okay pointer is a global variable
so there's one instance of pointer in the address space
and it's stored in the in the data segment
I I and messages are examples of local variables to Maine
so there's one instance of these stored on the stack of Maine stack
and we'll denote those with this notation we'll say variable i
I dot M means variable I is stored on main stack
and messages is stored on the stack of Maine
okay now myid is a local variable declared defined in this thread routine
and so there's actually since there's two of these threads
there's there's now there are in memory there's there's two instances of myid one  one for each stack
okay associated with the stack associated with each thread
so myid.p0 is stored on peer thread 0's stack
and myid.p1 is stored on peer thread 1's stack
ok and now this counter variable the static counter variable has just exactly one instance in in virtual memory
and it sits in the data segment along with the other global variables like like pointer
okay now so the question is
which of these variables are shared and which are not
okay so we can
remember what we said is it's shared if if more than one thread  is accessing an instance of that variable
okay so let's let's just list all the different variables
and then let's look at each of these threads and see if it's referenced by that thread
okay so what about what about pointer
right there's just it's referenced by the main thread right
and what about Pierre threads zero
yeah it's referenced by peer thread zero right here
right here
and similarly for pthread and one
okay so so pointer is referenced by all three threads
now what about count
counts not referenced by the main thread
but it is referenced by the two peer threads
now what about I in main
that's referenced by main of course
but not by but not by either of the two threads
now we're about messages the messages array
okay so that's that's accessed by my main
and indirectly through pointer
it's referenced by each of these  two peer threads
now what about my ID defined in in peer thread zero
okay so that's referenced that's a local variable
so it's only referenced by peer thread zero right it's not referenced by either the other threads
and similarly for for my ID and in peer threat one
okay so given given that definition then
which of these variables is shared
so it's it's really straightforward with yeah
okay so the question is discount count as a share variable and answer is yes
because because it's declared static
it's there's one instance of it in in in virtual memory
and each of the threads references that instance
okay so it's it's shared it's really like a global variable
it's just a scope is limited to the the
it stored the same way a global variable is but its scope is limited to the function that it's defined in
okay so to determine if each one of these is whether
which which of these variables are shared in which one's not we just
we just look go across and for any any variable with its shared by more than
more than one thread then it's shared
so pointer shared
so pointer is shared count is not shared
oh no no count is shared because it's it's referenced by peer thread zero and peer thread one
i's not shared because it's only referenced by by main
so
messages is access referenced by all three threads so it's shared
but my ID is is not shared because it's only referenced by exactly one thread
okay so so pointer count and messages are the shared variables in this program and the others are run share
yes
would like the second process and over s
o she declared my ideas static
with the second process of overridden it yeah that would be a race
okay so that would we just depend on which which thread executed first
so you would really wouldn't want to do that
okay so so we have a very clear notion now of what we mean by sharing
so these being able to share variables like this in this ways is very handy
but you can run into some really nasty problems
that are very surprising so let me show you an example
this is a program
called bad count so obviously there's something wrong with this I'm giving you a little clue
but what we want to do is we want to create we want to create a bunch of threads or a number of threads
and each of those threads will increment a global variable called count
some number of times the same number of times
okay so so we pass in the number of iterations as the first argument
and here's our well here's our global globally shared variable
and you remember what volatile means
everybody remember what that means
so what is volatile what is volatile tell the compiler
yes
[student speaking]
it actually you you're on in the right direction actually tells it tells the compiler never to put that variable in a register
okay so it always it will always read that value from memory or store it to memory and
you do that because of exactly the kind of possibility that you mentioned
so so in this in this case we have
we create two threads but with two distinct calls to two pthread create
each of these threads will will run the the thread routine called thread
and it will pass and as an argument the address of the number of iterations that it should
that it should iterate
now you remember when we were looking when we were passing connected file descriptors
if if we pass an address that was a race
okay but in this case there's no race this is fine
it's fine just to pass the address of number of iterations
so why is it okay in this case but it wasn't okay when we were passing the connected file descriptor
that we got from acceptant to our thread routine
yes
exactly because the thread doesn't modify the value
and that the problem we had before was that our main thread was modifying that connected descriptor on on the next call to accept
but here it's just a read-only variable so we're okay
but you see the how tricky the reasoning can get right there's
you can't do pattern matching to determine whether you've got races or not races
right so you can't just say well
it's always bad to pass the address of some variable to a to a thread routine
okay because it's not it just depends on the context
okay so in this case we're passing the number of iterations and to each thread and
then we're waiting for each of those threads to finish
so this is an example of why you need why you might want to have a non detached thread
because you can't
we want when we check when we check the value of count
we have to make sure that every thread is finished before we check whether we got the right value or not
okay so we wait for each thread to finish
and now since we've created two threads each of which is incrementing count Editors time
we expect count to be equal to two times and ITER's
and if it's not we print my favorite error message
otherwise we with with the value of count otherwise we print okay  also with the value of count
okay so now what's going on in the thread routine
very simple
it dereferences the
the the argument that was passed in and stores it in the local copy of entities
and then it loop senators time
in can increments count each time
so and then returns
so this is very innocuous what could go wrong
and since this is threading since this is concurrent concurrent programming especially since it's threaded programming
what there's the odd lots of subtle things can go wrong
so it turns out this program has a really serious bug
okay because when we run it
when we run it on a Linux box
sometimes if we call it with an argument of ten thousand sometimes
we get the correct answer  two times ten thousand or twenty thousand
but then the next time we run it
we get some weird number 13051
completely wrong
and so what what the heck is going on here
okay so to understand that we have to look at the assembly language
for this counter loop so that
we want to we we need to look at the the  December language for this counter loop in the thread routine
so we'll break it up into three chunks that
the the first chunk is sort of getting ready for the loop
we'll call that the head and we'll denote we'll denote it as H of I  for thread I
and then we'll we'll we'll isolate on these three instructions that are directly related to incrementing count
okay so you see the first instruction moves
it loads the global of the value and global variable count into register RDX
so will denote that as L of I
next it increments RDX
and we'll denote that U of I for update so it updates RDX
and then it stores the value the updated value of RDX into count
okay so into the location associated with the loke the global variable count
and
and then the rest of the the rest of this loop is getting ready for the to do the next iteration
it's not directly related to incrementing count
so we'll just sort of group this all together and refer to it as T of I for tail
okay
now let's look at let's look at
how this how these two threads might be might be executed
and remember in general we can't assume that there's any specific interleaving
so any interleaving of these two threads is possible
no matter how remote it might seem
so let's look at one example let's say we're executing on a single core
so we're only going to do one instruction at a time
and
in this column will show which thread is executing so either thread 1 or thread 2
and then we'll to know which instruction in that thread is executing
either H lus or T
and then this column shows the value of RDX for thread number 1
and this column shows the value of RDX for thread number 2 right
and since that the kernel keeps separate copies of all the general-purpose registers the for each each thread these can be different
okay and then this last column shows the value of count in memory
so let's start executing so initially count is equal to 0
and thread one gets the kernel schedules thread thread 1
so it executes say CH 1 that has no impact on on count
then thread 1 loads the value of count into its copy of RDX
updates it
so now %rdx is equal to 1 and then stores that value in %rdx back to count so now count is equal to 1
now at this point the kernel decides to schedule thread to
sew thread two  begins executing and when it begins executing value of count is 1
so it executes H of I
then it loads count into the art into thread 2's copy of RDX
so now our DX equals 1 updates it
now it's equal to 2 and then stores that value back to count
the kernel then decides oh and then
and then it finishes executing the tail instruction
and let's say we're just doing one iteration of this
and then at this point the kernel decides to schedule thread one since thread two is finished so
thread 1 1 executes the remaining statement that it has to execute
and at this point both threads have finished
and count is equal to 2 which is the value we would expect
ok so this so this is ok
and notice how so this is actually this is an inner leaving that works
ok we get the correct value
and notice how I did
it grouped the 3 instructions that are actually involved in updating count together
and it will call that we'll call those 3 instructions a critical section and I've color-coded them
so you can easily keep track of them
alright let's look now let's look at another another interleaving which is feasible right
but in this case it results in the wrong value
ok so here we start with thread 1 again
it loads it's the value of count into its copy of RDX updates it
but then before it can store it
the kernel decides to schedule thread -
so thread 2 begins X executing
it loads count into its copy of RDX -
and notice count is still 0 right it's it's 1
in the value of in thread one in the RDX
the copy of RDX and thread 1 but it hasn't been updated in memory so
when when when thread 2 loads its value of count
now it's copy and RDX is 0
now at this point the kernel reschedules thread 1 to execute so thread 1 does it store
of its copy of RDX into count
and then finishes executing it the tale instruction
the colonel reschedules thread - which picks up where it left off it updates
its copy of of count
so now RDX goes from 0 to 1
and then it stores that value into count
so all we've done is we've overwritten count out a value 1
and we've overwritten it with a value of 1
so when we finish execution of these two threads count has the wrong value
okay in the
that then the general like the general thing to notice is you see how these critical sections have been interleaved
right in this in this case
this is the first the critical section for thread 1 executed before the the critical section for thread 2
okay but in this case the two critical sections interleaved okay
so let's see another example of that
so here you can see that these are interleaved so
probably suggest there might be a problem yes
[student speaking]
so I'm sorry excuse me
well no okay so the question is would would
I or count count
if we okay it is defined as volatile it didn't I
yeah so that that's why I mean there's actually and the compiler could have compiled this code in different ways right
there is actually an increment instruction that you will increment a variable in memory
so you could have done
the compiler could have generated this this 3 instruction sequence is one instruction and then we wouldn't have this problem
but the problem is that
it's it's it's loading into register then incrementing and then saving
so that the problem comes about because
we can
this this thread can be interrupted before it finishes this three-step sequence
this load modify store sequence
yes
it would wait yeah so it that's right yeah I guess I wasn't clear it
it prevents it from being stored permanently in a register right so
it it if it's it may have to be loaded into a register but then it'll be written back
okay whereas the the compiler would have the option like we've seen it with local variables
right the compiler just it never allocates stack space
it just keeps that local variable in a register all the time
okay so this prevent the volatile attribute prevents the compiler from doing that
okay so let's look at another example
so here thread one starts
it loads it loads count into RDX
then thread two starts
and it loads a count which is still 0 into RDX 2
updates it and then stores it so now count equal to 1
when thread 1 resumes it updates its value of count and RDX and stores that back to count
and so again we have we have the same problem
okay so the
the problem here is that we're interleaving these these critical sections
and you can understand why this is bad
with a nice or graphical technique called a progress graph
so in a progress graph
if we have 4n threads it's an N dimensional Cartesian grid
that characterizes the execution state space of a concurrent threaded program
so in this case each here we have two threads
so it's a it's a it's a it's a 2d coordinate system
so each each axis represents the progress the execution progress of some threads
so the x axis here is thread 1
and the y axis corresponds to thread 2
and then each one of these edges corresponds to the execution of an instruction
ok so we start out in an initial state
and then the first thing we execute is h1
so that's represented by this this arc here
so this this position this point right here represents the state where
we've executed H we finished executing h1 in thread 1
but we haven't yet executed any instructions in thread 2
ok so in general each one of these points represents
sort of the current progress of the program or the execution State
so for example this this state right here represents the state where thread 1
has completed a completed l1
and thread 2 is completed s2
and now the execution of a program is modeled as a transition from one state to the other  and there's some
so from from this and there's there's constraints on how
on how these these states can advance so
from this state(L1,S2)
Y obviously time can't go backwards right so we can't
we can't go backwards like in this direction to the left and we can't go down
okay so we can only go to the right and up
and since we're assuming that each instruction executes
there's only one instruction executing at a time
we can't go diagonally that would be two instructions
all right so from (L1,S2)
the next execution state is either
here if thread one execute or here if thread of thread to execute
okay so you can put all these together to form a trajectory
which characterizes one execution of the program
right and any feasible set of transitions from one state to the next corresponds to a feasible trajectory
so so for example H1,L1,U1,H2,L2,S1,T1,U2,S2,T2
that's a feasible
that's a feasible trajectory
and it's one possible it represents one possible execution or so one set of inter leavings for this program
now these L these three these three instructions l U and s that operate on that manipulate count
form what we call a critical section with respect to count
and the idea is that instructions inside
these critical sections this with receivership with respect to the same global variable shouldn't be interleaved
so we can capture this geometrically by taking the intersection of these critical sections
to form what we call an unsafe region
so in this an unsafe region is is is
the points within an unsafe  region are those those points in an execution where the
critical sections are being or interleaved
okay so for this particular example there's four points within the unsafe region
and if a trajectory ever touches one of those points
then we've interleaved critical section and we're going to get the wrong answer
okay so the idea is to try to stay out of these unsafe regions
and if we do we say that that trajectory is safe so
here's an example of a trajectory that's safe
now this is okay right this point right here is not in the unsafe region
because we haven't executed we only executed h1 here
remember a point corresponds to
and it's the instruction that we've completed that instruction
so then
so here we're skirting the unsafe region
but it's still okay so this is a safe trajectory we'll get the right answer for this one
however
this trajectory is unsafe because it
it enters the unsafe region at this point here
and even though it quickly exited the there's an interleaving there that creates a potential for a correct answer
okay so the question is how do we guarantee a safe trajectory
and this is the this is what we call synchronization
so somehow we want to we want to sort of configure the kernel
so that'll never schedule an unsafe trajectory
so how do we do that
so somehow
we we have to synchronize the execution of those threads
and another way to think of this is that we we we need to guarantee mutually exclusive access to the critical sections
all right so once once the kernel begins once the thread starts executing the first instruction is critical section
we we don't want it to be interrupted by another thread that has a similar critical section
okay we don't want it  to be interrupted
we don't want one one critical section with respect to a certain global variable
to be interrupted by another thread that has all right that's currently within that same critical section okay
sorry yes question
seems unlikely for me that
it okay so the question is how likely is it that you get a correct trajectory
and it happens right you can run it sometimes you do
it just depends usually it's wrong sometimes it's right
and it just depends it just depends on how the kernel scheduled it and you can't assume any particular scheduling
right so if you say if you want to if you want to claim that you would never get the right answer
then you're assuming that the kernel is always going to schedule the unsafe trajectory but
you can't assume that in fact it doesn't sometimes you just get lucky
and it turns out you have to you have to call this function with a pretty big number in order to trip it up
if so the it makes sense right
if usually what what what the kernel does is that
I we can only schedule
we can only reschedule a thread you know swap it out and schedule another thread in
when there's some exception okay so that that passes control back to the kernel
so these exceptions are in two forms either  calling system making system calls
so that'll that'll trap into the kernel so that's a form of exception
or the timer interrupts goes off which transfers control back to the back to the kernel
so the timer the timer is going off on intervals of like milliseconds
right so if we're just doing one iteration it in each thread
when a thread gets executed the chances are very low that the timer is going to go off
while that thread is executing you know it's its little loop
but as we and we're not making any system calls
right so there's there's nothing that will there's nothing we're not we're not passing control back into the kernel ourselves
so the only way the kernel is going to get access  is if the timer interrupts goes off
so if we're doing a very small number of iterations
the the probability that you know say here's the timer interval it's going off at intervals like this
here this the the probability we'd have to
that's thread would have to been scheduled right before a timer interrupts will go off or to interrupt that one or two iterations
so it turns out we have to schedule
we have to call this function with a lot of within ITER's being fairly large
so that the the probability of the timer interrupts going off during that
during that during that loop but gets increasingly large
that makes sense
so the classic solution from this comes from the early 1960s one of the most famous computer scientists
is a Dutchman named as edgeguard Edsger Dijkstra
and he came up with the the classical first solution to this problem which is what we're going to look at
okay and it's it's it's still the first it's it's fundamental and very general purpose
and there's there's been many iterations and variations on this idea
but semaphores were the first and classic solution which we'll look at
okay so a semaphore is that is a non-global
integer that's used as a synchronization variable by two
to kernel functions called P and V
our two system calls called P and V
these P and V are correspond to the Dutch words
but we just you just we just call them P and V right you just have to learn what what they do
so each of these takes as an argument a semaphore
and the P operation has the following semantics
if if s is non zero
then decrement it by 1 and return immediately
and this test if it that it's non zero
and the decrement occur atomically
okay so so they'll never be interrupted
however if s is zero
then suspend this thread
until s becomes non zero
and that thread then is restarted by a V operation
okay so if if P if the semaphore is zero  P just blocks
it just gets suspended until it gets restarted by a V operation
and then after it restarts
the P operation now can decrement s by one and return control to the caller
okay the V operation just increments s by one
and this increment unlike that count
plus plus that we looked at just looked at this that increment occurs atomically
okay so it can never be interrupted
and then after it increments s
it checks to see if there's any any threads that are blocked in a pea operation
so you can think of the kernel just keeps a queue of threads
that are blocked in a pea operation
and the V operation after it increments s it checks that queue for any any threads that were blocked
because when they did the pea operation the semaphore was zero
and then it restarts exactly one of those threads in some indeterminate order
okay in some order that you can't
you can't assume it just picks one using some some selection algorithm
and it and then it it it unblocks the suspended  the suspended process
okay which then completes its pea operation by decrementing yes
okay this seems like really simple but it can be kind of hard to get your head around the first time you see it
so are there any questions about P and V
okay so that the key idea that these definitions of P and V
is that it imposes an invariant on the semaphores
called the semaphore invariant which is s which is that for a semaphore s
being operated on by P and V operations
S is always greater than or equal to zero
okay and that doesn't seem very exciting
but it turns out this is a very useful property that will allow us to enforce mutual mutual exclusion  on these critical sections
so the P and V operations are are provided by P threads
in the form of three functions
there's a Semin it functions which initializes the semaphore to some value
okay so semaphore is can be initialized to any any value greater than or equal to zero
some weight is the P operation and some post is the V operation
okay and because I'm old-school
I provide wrapper functions for those in the in your cssapp.h file called P and V
okay it's also more compact to
okay so recall our recall our buggy program called bad count dot C
which was giving us the wrong answers for count
so how do we use semaphores to fix this program
so the basic idea is to create a semaphore
which is initialized to 1
and so by definition we'll call any semaphore which is initialized to 1
that's used for to provide mutual exclusion we'll call that a mutex
okay and this goes back to the early Dijkstra papers
so we'll associate a unique mutex initialize to 1   for each shared variable in our program
ok so in this case count we have count so we have one shared variable that we're concerned about
so we'll we'll create one new text that will call mutex
and then you surround the critical section with respect to count
with a p/e you call P then you execute the critical section and then you call V
now there's some there's some terminology we'll use when we talk about semaphores
so a binary semaphore is is the semaphore whose value is always 0 1
and then a mutex is this sort is a binary semaphore that's being used to for mutual exclusion
the P operation is called locking
the mutex will refer to a V is sometimes unlocking or releasing the mutex
and if a process is holding the mutex then that means it's been locked but not  not not released
so mutexes and binary semaphore s are always initialized to 1 accounting semaphore
and the mutex is used for mutual excuse exclusion
but you can also use semaphores to count sort of events in the system
and often times for those accounting semaphores have sort of non non values that are greater than 1
okay so for mutual exclusion
we'll to fix our program we create a new program called good count dot c
and here we initialize a mutex
or we create a mutex and initialize it to 1
and then we surround the the critical section which is the 3 assembly language instructions
embodied that implement this count plus plus instruction
we surround it with a P followed by it by a V
and if we do that we always get the right answer
but you know P&V our system calls
so there's overhead associated with these
so they're not free in fact they're orders of magnitude this program runs two orders of magnitude slower than the incorrect buggy version
all right so so why do these mutexes work
so here we've got a progress graph now where we've
we've decorated our program with P and V operations
so we put the P before the critical section we execute  the critical section  and then we call V
and now if you were to look you remember P and V P increments
the sum of P decrement the semaphore V increments of samba4
so if you were just to look at the value of that semaphore for every point  in the execution state space
you'd get these you'd get these values
so here we initialize the semaphore at the origin we initialized it to 1
so the the value of of our semaphore  at the origin is 1
and let's say we just move along
so we're just executing thread 1
so after H 1 the semaphore is 1
we do the P the semaphore is 1 so P just decrement sit and it proceeds
so now the semaphore value becomes 0
and it remains zero until we execute the V
and when we finished executing the V
the semaphore now is is 1 again
okay so if we go through a similar reasoning
if we look at the trajectory to get to any point  in this state space
so let's say let's say this point right here
so to get there we could we could execute thread 1 up to this point  finish the L 1
and then execute h 2
and then do the at this point the semaphore is 0
and then P decrements the semaphore so now it's minus one
but that's that's impossible that can't happen
because P plus remember if if the semaphore is 0 P blocks
it doesn't decrement
it okay so the semantics of the P operation prohibits this  this this transition
it prohibits this transition to the state where the semaphore is zero to a state where it would be -1
and so it creates it creates what we call a forbidden region so these  these points in the state space
where the the semaphore would have a value of -1 are are infeasible
that can never be reached by the definition of of P and V
ok so this this forms a forbidden region around the unsafe region
and in doing so provides mutually exclusive access to the to the critical sections in each thread
okay so if
so this this is the fundamental reason why P's and Vees  can be used to provide mutually exclusive access
so many questions on this
I explained it so clearly that there's no questions
all right good well you get to go you get to get to leave early then   work on your Mallik lab
so
all right so
we'll see you Monday we're going to look at sort of some advanced topics
this was like her first introduction to synchronization
on Tuesday we'll look at more advanced topics in synchronization in ways
ways that you can use semaphores for to
provide other other more interests other interesting kinds of synchronization for your programs
okay