Good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you
and welcome to all those who are watching on videotape as well
I want to clear up I realized after the last lecture
that I didn't explain the idea of peak memory utilization very well to you
so I want to just explain that it's an important idea and I want to make sure that  that we have it clear
so if you recall  recall from  we have we're executing a series a sequence of requests
R0,R1,R2,
RK up to our n-1
and at any point in time after K 1 k + 1 requests
we have HK
which is the the heap size
after k1 requests
now we have a PK which is the aggregate
the the sum of all of the payloads
after k + 1 requests
okay so what we're trying to do with this this PK measure
this aggregate payload is at any point in time so
as we as we execute requests one after the other
the sum of all the payloads in the heap
is going to either increase or decrease right so if we execute a an allocate
then the size of the payloads will increase
if we execute a free the size of all those  allocated payloads will decrease right so
so as we're executing this the sequence of requests these
the aggregate the sum of all the payloads is going to be increasing and decreasing
okay and so what were what we're capturing with the sum of all these payloads is like a perfect allocator that has no overheads
and and even more so one that we can
where we're allowed to compact blocks
so the sum of all of the the payloads is the minimum possible heap size
or it's the minimum possible number of bytes required by those allocated blocks
okay so it's very very aggressive and it's impossible to achieve
but we're going to use that as sort of our best case
okay
and so to measure a peak
peak memory utilization
after
K+1 requests
which will denote U of K
that's going to be equal to
the the max
for all I less than or equal to K
of our aggregate payloads
divided by
the size of the heap after after k+1 requests
okay so what what we're doing with this max is
we're remembering the high-water mark
you know as our as our aggregate payloads
increase and decrease we're remembering the high-water mark
right so that was sort of the worst that was like the biggest set of payloads that we had
and then so the max is remembering his room is remembering that high-water mark
and then we're dividing by the total size of the heap in order to get an efficiency measure
okay so so this max
PK is kind of this is the best we could have done divided by the total the total heap size
okay so yes
[student speaking]
well that the allocator keeps track of of how big the heap
is so that's pretty easy right
so as every time it every time it does every time it calls s break
it just that that adds to the size of the heap and remember we're
we're assuming that the heap in this case is always increasing okay so
but even if even if we allow the heap size to decrease
could just if the allocator is controlling the size of the heap by calls to s break
okay so is that clear
so for UK the higher the better
okay and for any sequence of allocates and freeze
this max PK will be the same
okay that's constant right
but what what varies is H of K and that depends on how efficient your  your allocator is is using the heap storage
okay yes question
[student speaking]
so what we're doing is at any point in time
after we're after K +1 requests
we're about we're evaluating the utilization of our heap up till that point so it should be K
[student speaking]
for I I less than or equal to K
oh I'm sorry
yeah sorry good good catch so that should be an eye right we want to look at all the  all the for all the requests that came before
okay any other questions
okay all right so last time we looked at some simple the basics of dynamic storage allocation
today we're going to look at some more sophisticated techniques using
different data structures to store the free list primarily
we'll look at implicit allocators
so we'll get a sort of a brief survey of how garbage collectors work
and we'll just look at one just just one very simple kind of garbage collector
but it will give you an idea of of what that means
and then we'll finish up
we'll finish up by looking at all the ways you can get yourself into trouble
by using dynamically allocated storage
so once once you once you use once you start dynamically allocating storage
things can go really bad really quickly
and so we'll go over some of those some of those bad things that can happen and
try to alert you to those so you don't do them in your programs
okay so we looked at how to store a free lip free list in this sort of implicit form by just  walking the entire heat
and and thereby sort of being able to visit all the free blocks
but we can do better
if we actually have a EE if we store the free block the free list is using as a doubly linked list
so in we call these explicit free lists
so the idea with an explicit free list is that
we put pointers
we put the pointers that implement the the doubly linked list
inside the the body of the of a free block
say where the old payload used to go so
allocated blocks look exactly the same as they did before right
there's a header boundary tag optional boundary tag footer
and then this the payload and any padding
free blocks though the allocator and the allocator is not allowed to touch anything in the inside the
the the payload of an allocated block
but free blocks are free right nobody's using them
and so we the allocator can put the
the pointers that implement the data structure inside the what was the old payload
so logically this is just a simple doubly linked list okay that you've all seen before
but actually these things can be anywhere in memory right
and so you know here we have
we have a block of size six
and it has a four word pointer that points to some other link
and it has a backwards pointer that points to
this block which happens to be have a greater memory address than  then it
okay so just the idea is you can't
you know unless unless you make unless you go to great pains to maintain
this sort of address ordered structure
these these these blocks can be sort of scattered anywhere in memory
several times on that long
oh yeah so this is after several
you know just sort of indefinite number of Malik's and fries and
yes
[student speaking]
oh yeah good question it's like
so the question is what would happen if you free to a block that was in between two free blocks
and so you have to coalesce it gets a little tricky and I'll show you in a second
good now allocating oh yes questions
[student speaking]
so the question is what happens with locality
so you still get you still get block locality
you know use blocks are still contiguous
so if
but if if you're scanning sort of a set of allocated blocks it would be better
if you could keep them all contiguous right that so that's really
and so there's a you know that's a trade-off I don't
it gets difficult if you think how can you maintain
so you don't really care about the locality of free blocks right you're just walking a linked list
well no I shouldn't say that that's
if you're walking that list if you hit one one free block
it would it would bring in a whole page so it'd be better
if you were walking if the list you know if as much of that list was contained within that page
so even that's so you would benefit
you could benefit eat with both allocated blocks because applications would be using them  and with free blocks
because the allocator would be walking that that free list
so question so even
though say you only need even though say you're like alkane interest constructor if you know the feature can allocate a thousand of them somehow let me out the other day you're going to try to help you knowledge it didn't work
that's a really good question
so the question is could would it be possible for an application to  sort of give hints to the allocator
that would increase that improve the allocators performance or memory utilization
the the answer you absolutely could
but it's if you did it wouldn't be a general-purpose allocator
so like malloc is a general-purpose allocator
so it and it provides no there's no option
it doesn't provide any arguments in its interface for passing that information in
but it absolutely if it had some knowledge about the future behavior of a program that could benefit
right so especially I consider you always have this decision when you place an allocated block
whether to split that block or not
well if you knew that you were going to get a request
you know for if you split that block and and you knew that you were going to get requests
coming in the future first for sizes of the original block then you wouldn't want to split it
because then you would want it you would just keep it unsplit and then
when you freed it then you'd have a block that would be the right size for that that future request
and so it's you can absolutely benefit from that
and so although you can't if general-purpose allocators there's no provision for that kind of hinting
but there's nothing to prevent an alligator from doing predictions based on the the previous pattern of requests
you know so if you're getting a pattern of requests it's alternating large block small block large box small block
you could you could exploit that maybe maybe predict that the next request will be for a you know if it
if the previous request is for a large block the next one might be for a small block and you could
that's good question any any other questions wizard yes
I don't know I
so the question is are there are there intelligent alligators that do that kind of prediction
and if there are I don't know of them but I wouldn't I wouldn't say no
yes
what would happen you end up with a free buckets of block just like just a single block
oh well so the question is what if you ended up with a free block
that's a single block  by two allocated blocks
well in fact I mean that's one of the invariants that a good alligator has to maintain
you should never have two contiguous free blocks
right the alligator should always be coalescing as much as it can
and if it if it does that coalescing
if it if it always does that coalescing then then there will never be two contiguous free blocks okay
yeah it's question
[student speaking]
oh you'll see when we it comes into play when we free a block
because you have to sort of stitch up
when you free a block you have to sort of stitch up the the linked list and
so you need both you need both pointers
you can do it with singly linked lists
so in your in the K in our book there's a an alligator that uses a singly linked list
but the the disadvantages that free requires a search
so it requires a search from the beginning of the list to find the previous block
and there are questions these are good yes question
[student speaking]
okay so the question is for memory utilization
how does the header and footer count towards memory utilization
and so those those are overhead  that decrease memory utilization
okay because they're not payload so when we were computing memory utilization
we're doing it by we're using the payload the aggregate payload to
to to estimate our utilization or to compute our utilization
so anything that's not payload sorry is is overhead
okay was also one word so we had if all of our payloads were one word and our overhead
was was one word then there'd be 50%
yes if you have the book this pointer to the next and previously block you still
need yeah so the question is do you still need a boundary tag if you have
these these next and previous pointers and the answer is yes absolutely
and you'll see in a second why
yes
okay that's a really good question
so you know what do you do if you have next in previous pointers
what happened what happens if there's a request for a smaller a smaller block
so the answer is that all of those things the the header the footer the next and previous pointers
impose a minimum block size
so if you have a one word header one word footer one word pre even one word next
then your your minimum block sizes is four bytes
and that would be with a zero a zero size payload
so you can never allocate a block smaller  than your minimum block size
so that's very good very good question
so it makes a difference right even though
even though we're you know it looks like we're getting these
it looks like we're getting these pointers here for free
but we're not really because of this minimum block size  requirement
yes
their weight of course to allocate a
gigantic block and export Malecha give you specifically parts of that
so say c1 CY allocate 100 trucks
can you allocate the side 120 today you just work against one space to let you use it right
but if you wanted to like take the first half make them take second have taken integers or something
and 50 say all the stuff might program ridiculous
it's like here explicitly asking for that one gigantic block
yeah okay so
the question is can you just get a get one large block and then split it up
and I guess you're assuming that the request would be four equally sized objects right so
this and and that's a really good strategy actually
so if you if you know or if you think that your workload is going to have
no you can't do this in general-purpose allocators
but for like a special-purpose allocator
if you know that you're going to be asking for objects that are all the same size
like compilers for example may maintain abstract syntax trees
and and they're allocating nodes dynamically and those nodes are the same size
so if you can you can exploit that by just allocating a large chunk
and then allocating all the objects of that size out of that chunk
it's very efficient you don't even need pointers or anything all you need is a bit vector
to tell you which chunks are allocated in which chunks are free
and then and you also has a side effect you'll get that contiguous
that contiguous access so if a program access those those objects like
to be part of a linked list there was something that it was going to traverse
you could allocate those in order and contiguously
now with with a general-purpose allocator where you don't really know
what's going to be requested that
it's probably going to allocate also a vector-based
absolutely you could do that you can make general assumptions about the  sort of behavior of your programs
and you know you could you could run traces or like in the case of malok lab you could look at the traces
but that's no that's a really good thing you know you can't
you're you can't just like do if statements to say well
if the size is 42 and then the next size is 24 then I know it's this trace
but you can look at a trace and say whom there's an interesting pattern here
I'm going to account for that pattern I'm going to optimize for that pattern
and that that would just and that's perfectly valid that's just like taking advantage of
your workload right that's what we do in systems all the time
yes
but can we divided up in and at the end of the first part
Oh Oh so the question is why can't we
why can't we sort of have separate areas of the heap for the pointers  and the payloads all right
join them up with pointers
oh why not okay so the question is why not why can't we split up payloads
and link them together with pointers
the answer is that the applications expecting a contiguous block
you can't allocate or can't put anything in the payload
right it all I can do all it's allowed to do is return a contiguous block of the size of the application requested
and app once it does that it can't touch it okay
all right good good
all right so let's look at how we'd allocate and free
once if we have this this explicit list how we would allocate and free blocks
so allocating is pretty simple
we'll have so here's our sort of a graphic of our free list
so we have four word pointers and backward pointers
and the idea is we want to allocate out of this middle block
so
we allocate the block of the size that we need
and then we just update the forward and back pointers of the the previous and next blocks
to point to this new free block
okay so that's pretty simple we're just we're updating one two three four five six six pointers
okay now it gets it gets trickier when we have to free because
because we require coalescing
so when you free a block
that's that was previously allocated
the question is what do you do with that free block right it wasn't in the free list
because it was an allocated block
so now that you've freed the block where do you put it
which you've got to put it somewhere
so that the simplest thing is is this LIFO policy
so the simplest thing is just put it at the beginning of the list
so the last block freed is the the first block allocated if it did fit fits
okay so that's so-called LIFO
now this is simple
because you're always doing the same thing you're just putting the block at the beginning the list
and it's constant time you're just updating a few pointers
okay but the studies suggest that the the fragmentation can be worse than the alternative technique
which is to keep the blocks ordered by address
okay so why not if you if you if you choose this address ordered policy when you when you free an allocated block
you're going to somehow figure out you're going to somehow place that block in the list
so that the previous block begins at a smaller address
and the next block begins at a larger address
right so this generally involves some kind of search
right you don't you're just given this allocated block
and then somehow you've got and you know it's address
and so now you've got to somehow search the the free list
to find the you know the proper place to insert it
now I suppose you could do better if you had some kind of
so if you could speed up that search with some kind of  balance tree that would be one option
right but then that the the problem we always run into with balance trees and
usually one student at lis somebody always tries to implement malloc with some kind of balance tree red-black tree or something
and it seems like a really good idea
but you have to realize that you're you're competing with with other techniques  specifically segregated lists
that are very fast they have very small constant factors
and there's even though even though ordered lists are I think
it's usually nlog(n) to update an order tree a binary ordered tree
the constant factors can be can be quite large
and so usually get nailed up with the constant factors of maintaining the tree
and you don't get help that the search time is log(n)
but as we'll see with segregated lists
in the in the limit has it in the limit as the number of different size classes increases
the the search time approaches constant time
and if you if you have size classes that cover ranges of powers of two
then the search time reduces to log time anyway
because the the size of each classes are now logarithmic the log
so you know I would suggest on
you know just doing the simple thing usually whenever you're you're dealt with
sort of large design space like malloc it's you're better off doing the simple thing
and then optimizing only when you see that there's that you need to optimize
okay so remember last time we talked about this trick to to eliminate the boundary tag footer and allocated blocks
that's an example of an optimization you should defer
so that wait you know wait get do the simple thing and then try to improve incrementally by bayi
by you know this this optimization or another optimization
so there's this this phenomena of a lot of lot of programmers make the mistake of what we call premature optimization
so try to think of all the fancy things they can do
and then they put all those in at the beginning
and before they even know that it needs to be optimized
okay so the sort of the way you want to work on this and any any sort of complex
problem like like an alligator
is to you know first do fairly simple things and then look and see where
where the slowdowns are your inefficiencies are and then just sort of
hit those one after the other and optimize only for the things that are necessary
and this is a good example of that
okay now to get to your question about freeing
freeing is tough because we always have to do this coalescing right
because of this invariant that we can never have to free blocks  to adjacent free blocks
so let's go through each of those four cases that we went over last time
and see how we would do it
now that we have this this this explicit free list
so here we have the root of our free list
pointing to the first block in the free list
there's an all back pointer and then that
there's a null prief pointer and then the next next pointer points to some unspecified block
and so we have this yellow block which is allocated
and now the application is called free free with a pointer that points to the beginning of this block
so what do we do
well this case is pretty simple because there's no coalescing
because both the predecessor and successor blocks  are are allocated
okay so we just this newly freed block now becomes we're going to do a LIFO policy
so this becomes the first block in the free list
and so we update the root to point to this
this newly freed block and we update the forward pointer of that block to point to what used to be the first block  in the heap
now I'm going to be careful
it's a little bit confusing
because we've got sort of two notions of like previous and next right there's the
you know given some given some block
there's the predecessor block in memory which may or may not be allocated or free right
it may or may not be in a free list
and there's a successor block
okay so we'll use predecessor and successor to distinguish adjacency in memory
okay and we'll use pre even next to denote adjacency in the free list
okay so this this block is the next block for the current block
and it has no previous block okay
all right now what about case to remember case to the predecessor block is free
and the successor block is is allocated
and now we want to free this
what was an allocated block  denoted by yellow
and we have that this this successor this predecessor block is part of the free list
right so it has it has previous and next blocks
that are just part of the free list
and so our route points just the first block in the list and then eventually
you get to this free block which points to this free block which points to this free block
ok so what we have to do then
is we have to coalesce these two these two blocks into one big free block
okay and then we have to splice it out and stick it at the beginning of the list
ok so what that looks like conceptually is we we
we coalesce these two blocks now to form this one free block
and then we splice it out by
having what was the what was its previous block now point to what used to be the next block
okay of the current block
okay so this
the pointer from this block now points to this block
okay and then the so we've effectively spliced that that current block out of the free list
and then the route we have the route point to that block
so that's now the new first block of the list
okay and then we have to update what used to be the first block in the list
so now it points back to the the newly freed coalesced block
so that cleared everybody it yes
so with the route be a global variable it could be or it could be
there's there's two ways to do this right it could just be a global variable
or it could be a it could be a struct that  of like previous and next pointer
so sometimes it's easier if you keep the same you know when you're doing a linked list that
the route if you just make it the same as all the other nodes it can simplify things
but yeah it could be a global variable global scalar in the allocator
okay so case oh now one thing one thing that comes to mind there is like
there is an optimization that we could do
in this case do you see when we when we coalesce
we could just lead that block right there in the free list
right we didn't although we've adopted
so the examples I'm going to show you are assuming a LIFO policy for insertion
we could just leave it there right that and just don't update anything
just increase create this newly coalesce block and then mentally
we don't require in this case we wouldn't require any free list manipulation
okay but that would be that would be one of these optimizations right
that now
case three if you recall is the case where the the predecessor block is allocated
and the successor block is free
the successor block is free
so in this case what we have to do is we have to create
we have to coalesce the newly freed block with the with the successor block
and then we have to splice it out in just the same way we did in case two
so we splice it out of the the list
and then put it at the beginning of the list by pointing the root at it
and then updating what used to be the first block in the list
updating its back pointer it's pre pointer to point to the  newly coalesced block
okay so it's this is completely symmetric with the case that we looked at before
but now we no longer have
it's a little bit trickier if we just wanted to leave this block in the free list
we'd have to update all these pointers to point back
to the beginning of the newly created block
okay so there's
so in this case there's no performance
optimization right we're still updating the same number of pointers
whether we put it in the beginning of the list
or if we if we splice it or if we leave it there
and now case four is the
that's the case where both the predecessor and successor blocks are free
so we have to apply the same splicing technique  to both the the predecessor block
and we have to we have to create this new coalesced block
and then we have to splice
we have to we have to sort of splice it out by updating
two different sets of previous and successor blocks
so when we're when we're finished with that
that the this newly coalesced block now is the first block  in the in the heap
the four in the free list
and we've spliced it we splice it out from these two different parts of the of the free list
okay so any questions about
this is this is where you really
it looks it looks really simple to do
but I guarantee you this will be
some the hardest
It's only like 200 lines of code
but some of the hardest code you'll have to write because
you you're sort of free of the C's types us that you have to do everything by explicitly casting
these pointers are just in the middle of arbitrary blocks
and
so it looks simple with the diagram but you're going to have to be really careful when you do this
in fact what I would suggest the
best suggestion I can give you is
if is to start with the implicit list allocator
that we describe in the book which is too slow to get any credit
it's a terrible allocator
but it contains all the basic ideas
and then write function write a function called insert block and write another function called remove block
that inserts a block into the free list and removes a block from the free list respectively
and if you if you write if you abstract it like that
if you use that kind of abstraction it's pretty simple
to to convert the implicit list allocator to an explicit list allocator
it'll still be too slow to get
so then that'll go from like a F allocator to a b- allocator
and then to really make a good allocator like an a allocator you need to use segregated lists
which we'll look at in a second
okay so the explicit lists
now the the allocation time is is linear in the number of free blocks instead of the total size
of the instead of the total size of the heap
so it's this is much faster than that when you have a lot of allocated blocks
it's a little more complicated because of all the splicing business
and and you do need some extra space in your
for these these pointers which increases the minimum block size
and creates additional and overhead
now the link list the explicit list allocators aren't really
efficient enough to be used for sort of general purpose real-life  allocator
but they are useful in as part of a segregated list allocator
so you can have you can have multiple free lists each of which is an explicit list
and this it's fine for that for that application
alright so let's look at our third method which is to create call a segregated free list
which is to have multiple free lists with different size classes
so the the idea is that each
each class of sizes
block sizes has its own free list
and that that class can be singleton so you know maybe a one particular size
or it can be a range of sizes
so you might you might have a number of different
you know if you're if you're if your workload consists of a lot of these small blocks
and you know that there's going to be a lot of requests for blocks
of 1 through 4
you can have different free lists for those small for those small block sizes
and then after that you can go and just do ranges of power of two
so that's a that's a common technique
so here we have a size class that covers blocks from size 5 to 8
and then the another size class that covers everything else
so the idea with the seg list allocators that
so given a given an array of these free lists one each one for for some size class
if we want to allocate a block of size n
then we we go to the appropriate free list
right there's only there's always going to be one free list for any any n
and then we search that list just like we did before
for some size at a block size M greater than n
and then if if we find it then we place
we place the new block
we place the block in that in the block that we found
we split it
and we take this the split block and we put it into the appropriate size class
so that the block that we split off
may or may not may or may not belong to the current size class anymore
right so we may have to move it and insert it into a whatever the appropriate size class is
if there's no block if we can't find a block
then we have to try the next larger size class
okay so it's possible for a given size class
they're just there might not be a block that fits
so I mean one so we just have to we go to the next size
we try the next larger class and chances are we'll find a block that fits there
and if we and you keep doing that until you eventually if you can't find it
you're eventually looking in the size class that that that covers all the rest the last size class
and if then you can't find it then that the allocator has to allocate more memory with by calling s break
okay to free a block you coalesce like before
before and then you place it on the appropriate list
so that's that's straightforward and again you have this option to try to maintain a listed
address order or just do the simple thing and put it at the beginning of the list
okay so say egg list alligators are that by far the best type of alligator
because they're they offer you improvements in both performance throughput and memory utilization
so they're faster they have higher throughputs because the
the individual size classes are  are smaller
then than just like the one giant free list
but also you're searching
you're you know that the the list that you're searching
is going to be close to the size that you're looking for so the chances of finding something quickly
in that in that particular size class  are higher than they are
if you're just searching
on you know a single free list that holds all different size classes
okay so search is faster so that increases increases throughput
but the big thing about egg list alligators is that
like we talked about before they approximate best fit without sacrificing performance
right before if we wanted to do best fit on a single a free list
we had to search the whole free list
and then choose the block that fit the best
in this case we get we get best fit for free
by by virtue of having these size classes
and so this is
you know this is this is how you can improve your your memory utilization
yes
[student speaking] we just allocate and more bytes or
oh yeah yeah good question
so the question is is is is break constant time
it is but it's very expensive
so it's a sis call so it has to pass from user space into the kernel that involves
changing contacts changing stacks
so sis calls
generally you can you can count on assist call being like several hundred microseconds
okay it's a non-trivial overhead
and so in that case you wouldn't want
you you want to amortize the cost of the of the break
by allocating is somewhat larger chunk
but you have to be careful if you allocate too large of a chunk then your memory utilization goes down
so it's a trade-off it's another one of these space-time trade-offs
question
[student speaking]
so where do you store this array of free lists
so you store it in the beginning of the heap
yeah in fact for your malloc lab we require you to do that
we don't know
and the reason is we can't
that that array affects in some small part
depending on how large that array is it affects your memory utilization
and so it should be at the beginning of the heap
okay there's a allocators have been around forever and
that the the classic references canuse 1973 text
and there's also this great paper which you can get from the the books website
from 1995 that does a survey of
you know literate dozens and dozens of techniques like
we're just scratching the surface here
so if you're really interested in this stuff
that that is that papers a fascinating read
and it may give you some ideas for your free lab
ok now so far
we're assuming that the application is responsible for both allocating storage and freeing storage
but there's a form of memory managers called implicit memory managers
that do the freeing for you
so so applications allocate space
but they never have to worry about freeing space the system does that automatically
and so the the idea is to identify so-called garbage
so areas of memory that can never be referenced anymore
and then free up those blocks
okay so what's garbage well here's an example we have a function foo  that Malick's 128 bytes
it stores the address in this pointer P
and then at some point when it returns from foo
this pointer is lost forever right because P is a local variable on the stack
so once once this function returns
that the block of memory pointed to by P is garbage  can never be referenced again
because there's no way there's no way for the program to get get access to that
and so what an alligator will recognize
at some point that this block of memory is is garbage
and that it will free those blocks by calling free
it's the same kind of exactly the same free call
as we've discussed
but now it's it's it's it's called by the garbage collector not by the application
okay so you see this in all different kinds of dynamic languages
and there's there's there's also variants available for C
but because of C's pointer properties
that the garbage collectors for C are conservative in the sense
that there's some blocks won't be freed
there's some garbage blocks that that won't be free
because the allocator can't determine that   that they are indeed garbage
so it has to be careful when it whenever there's a doubt
it it leaves it doesn't reclaim the the allocated block
so it gets to this question of like how does the memory manager know when memory can be free
and you know if we knew
if somehow we knew we could predict all of the future requests
and then if we knew that there were no future requests access that block then we could free it
okay but we can't predict that
okay so we have to
but if there's no pointers
if no pointers exist to a particular block then we know that it can't be accessed
okay and so that we can predict right if there's some way
we can sort of scan the program identify or scan the memory identify all the pointers in that memory
and and see which which blocks are pointed to
and if they're if they're not pointed to by any pointer than then they're garbage by definition
okay so to do this though it's it's it's difficult
so first of all the memory manager has to be able to distinguish pointers from non pointers
which we can't do and see right there just these they're just these integral values
right we don't know it could be it
if we see this large integral value
this large long a 8 byte value
it could be it could be pointing to a data structure it could just be a large integer right
we don't know
and then we also all pointers have to point to the start of a block which is not true and see either
okay so if we have a pointer and we identify that it's a pointer
then we know that it points it points to some block
if it points inside of a block how do we how do we find the beginning of that block
you know how do we know how big that block is
all right so it has to point to the beginning of the block where the header  tells us the size and
the and and and there can't be a way to hide pointers
the point that the property of being a pointer has to be some kind of static
thing that doesn't that can't change
so that's sort of the challenges
if you're thinking about how in the world can you implement a garbage collector
so those are some of the challenges that  that they present
and because of that this is this been a the history of research and garbage collectors is is old
its ancient and ongoing
it's still it's still ongoing today particularly in the context of parallel programs
and garbage collecting programs that are running multiple threads
so there's a whole bunch of these things
that people have looked at going all the way back to 1960
today we'll look at we'll look at the simplest
what one of the simpler variants called mark-and-sweep
and we won't we won't discuss the rest
but if you're interested in them there's a pretty good book that describes that describes these things
all right so how do we build an allocator
so we start by viewing memory as a directed graph
where each each node in the graph corresponds to a block
okay a block a heap block
and an allocated heap block
and each edge is a pointer that's contained somewhere within that block
okay a pointer to another block
and then there's a and then there's special nodes called root nodes
that contain pointers into the heap but they're not part of the heap
so for example pointers that are stored on the stack
pointers that are stored in registers
they point to memory locations in the heap
but nothing nothing and but there outside of the heap
so and we call those route notes
so nothing points to them or at least if something does point to them
we don't care about what it is
okay we're only we're only concerned about characterizing nodes that correspond to memory in the heap
so I we say that a a node or a block is reachable
if there's some path from a root node
from a root node to that block
so and we've denoted those by green
so all of these green blocks in the heap are reachable
because you can start at a root node and just follow some some sequence of pointers to get to that node okay
notes that aren't reachable are called our garbage
because there's no there's no way to get to them from the root nodes
okay so there's no node inside the heap  that points to them
and there's no node there's no root node that points to them
so basically there's just no path from a root node
that'll get you to one of these non reachable or garbage nodes
and since they're non reachable
the application will never be able to reference them in the future
so we can predict with certainty
that that those are garbage and they can be freed
so basically after we free these then they're removed from the graph
so now we can we can build
a simple garbage collector on top of the existing malloc and free package
right so you implement malloc and free just like before
and then you the program
calls malloc just like before
and you just you do malloc exactly the same way until you run out of space
by whatever different definition you want to use of running out of space
maybe you have some kind of maximum heap size you're willing to use
or at some point the OS will just stop giving you virtual memory
when you run out of space
you you add an extra mark bit into the header of each block
so this could be you know we have like three or four spare bits
that we can use in the header
so we can denote one of those as the mark bit
and then we are garbage collection
our garbage collection phase when we run out of space consists of two
two different sub phases one is the mark phase which starts at all the roots
and then and it just traverses this from the roots
it traverses the set of of nodes
that are reachable from the root and it sets the mark bit in each each one of those nodes
okay and then once after you finish marking all of the all of the reachable blocks
then you sweep through the entire heap starting at the very beginning of the heap
and you look for you look for all allocated blocks that aren't marked
KB so they're not marked they're not reachable in their garbage
so first so you do this so you sort of do - you do a search from the from the roots
and then you do a sweep of the entire heap
so let's say before before mark we have before the marks
phase we have a heap that looks like this we have a single root that points to this block
and what we're going to do here we're always going to point to the payload right  of the of the block
it's just a convention that we use
so we're pointing to the beginning of the block
because we know that it's we know that the the header is one one word behind it
and so let's say and in this case
the the edges denote pointers that are contained in the block
so they're not the previous and next pointers that we were maintaining
these are just pointers that the application has put into those blocks
so we have so here we have the root pointing to this the central block
and then there's an and there's a pointer that points to this block
and there's another pointer that points to this block and
and there's a pointer in this block that points to this block
so after we do the mark
and we search this we search these and then
all of the reachable blocks have the mark bit set which is denoted by pink
and so then you see in that and then the the blocks that aren't aren't marked then we can free
and return to the free list
okay so let's look at the assumptions for a simple implementation just to make make sure this is clear
so the application calls new to get a pointer to a block with with all the values cleared
it calls read(b,i) to read location I of Block B
and it uses write(b,i,v) to write a value V into location I of Block B
then each block will have a header word which will address as b[-1]
and then the garbage collector has
it has functions that it uses to identify whether a pointer
whether its input parameter is indeed a pointer
okay so there's some way to distinguish a pointer from an on pointer
and it can get the length of some block
not including the header and it can get a set of all of the routes
so given those given those assumptions
we our pseudocode for the mark step
it takes
so this initially is a is a pointer a route pointer
okay and then we check as our terminating condition
we check to see if that that input is indeed a pointer and if so we return
okay and then then we do a depth-first traversal of the of the graph
so if
and this so we're doing a depth-first traversal of the graph and this is pointer is sort of our terminating condition for that
that depth-first traversal
then we check the mark bit and if it's set then that's another terminating condition
there's no there's no reason to search once we find a marked  marked node
we know that all of will from that node is is marked
so we we can terminate our return and just stop the search
if it's not set then we set the mark bit
and then we look at each word in the block
and we recursively call mark on each one of those words
now each one of those words may or may not be a pointer right so if it's not a pointer
then mark will just return instantly immediately
if it is a pointer then it will continue the recursive depth first search
okay so does that make make sense it's just familiar the familiar def first graph traversal bit
that we all know about
okay and then the sweep sweep takes a pointer to the beginning of the heap
the first it takes a pointer to the first block in the heap
and then some a pointer to the end of the heap
and then in a while loop then it scans the heap each block
if the mark bit is set it clears it
if it's if it's allocated it frees it right
and then it updates and then it gets the address of the the next block
and then just continues until the end
okay so how do we do such a thing in C right
because all of these assumptions I've made don't hold and C right you can't tell a pointer from an on pointer
pointers can point anywhere
so what you could do so the big issue is that
if we get some value
we it even if it is a pointer it could point right into the middle of the block
so given that
so first of all we don't know if that value really is a pointer it could just be a big integer
but it also could be a pointer that's pointing into some data structure
so if it is a pointer how do we how do we find the beginning of the block
so what we could do is just assume that
every value is a pointer
and then we maintain a balance tree to keep track of all the allocated blocks
and so whenever we encounter a particular value
we would search that binary tree to see if it if assuming it is a pointer
if it falls within the the beginning and end of some allocated block
okay if if that condition is true then we assume that it's
pointing that that's a pointer to an allocated block
and we assume that that block is reachable
now the reason it's conservative is because it really may not be a pointer it might be this integer
and we'll we'll assume it's a pointer and assume that
the block that it purportedly points to is is allocated
but it may in fact be not be a pointer and the block that
it points to is garbage
right so what with this with this scheme we would leave some some non non reachable blocks
we will indicate that some non reachable blocks are are really reachable
okay so
so once now that we've got this great tool to dynamically allocate memory
we can use it in our programs
and shoot ourselves in the foot in all different kinds of ways
okay so I'm going to I'm going to try to help  help you out here by identifying
some of the perils and pitfalls that that we can run into with with with memory related operations or operations on memory
and opera errors errors involving memory
are the worst the worst kinds of bugs  to try to find out
and the reason is that they're distant in both space and time
so let's say you write to the wrong memory location and corrupt some data structure
the right doesn't elicit any error
you only find out about that illy that erroneous right
when you try to reference that data structure or that particular part of the data structure
which may be in a part of the code that's way far away from the right that caused the problem
both in space you know in distance you know lines of code it could be a completely different function
and a completely different module
but also in time it may not you know you may do the right
and then eons later other some read and it fails
right so this is a fundamental thing that makes memory related bugs just so nasty
and another big thing another thing that makes them hard to deal with
is people's misunderstanding and misuse of pointers right
so usually an erroneous right is some is
some either a misunderstanding of pointers or an improperly initialized pointer
so it all boils down to these pointers
okay and so I'm going to show you how to understand pointers
okay for the first time in your lives
I don't know about you but when I learned C
I learned about pointers
I just knew about what a few different types of pointers  were by and I did it by pattern matching
so I knew that int *p was a pointer to an int
I knew that int **p was was an array
I knew that int *p
open bracket closed bracket was also an array just a different way to  express that array
so I had a small handful of pointers types that I could deal with
but I had no underlying understanding of what that meant or anything was just pure pattern matching
and I'll bet you that's the way you do it too
all right but that's all going to change today
all right so
in order to really understand pointers
you need to understand the precedence of various operators in C
because the pointer types are declared using these operators
and so my copy of K and R is it has a dog-eared at page 53
this table comes from page 53 of knr
and you should have a paper clip or have that folded over for reference
now the thing to notice is that
function and array and then and these struct these various struct operators
have the highest priority highest precedence
and that and then that's followed by unary operators so the star this is the dereference operator
and then the the address of operator
the they fall right below
the highest the highest precedence operators
and then the binary versions of operators you know that you use in arithmetic operations are below those
okay so just remember
that function and array is higher than star
that too deep the dereference
now the great thing about pointers although they always seem really complicated
is that there's there's an algorithm for
it for there's an algorithm for
constructing an English sentence that explains exactly what what that pointer
what that definition of the pointer means
okay and if you're interested it's in the KN are in Section 5.12
but I'll I'll explain it to you now
now I don't know I don't know how much in this class you're going to remember
okay but I guarantee you're going to remember this as the day you finally understood pointers okay
so all
right so here's how it works
you always start it the this is a definition of a pointer some kind
you always start  with the variable name
and then you use your precedence t
then you look for operators on either side of that variable name
and you choose the one that has the highest precedence
okay so we start with the variable so we say P  is a
then we look to the left and the right
there's nothing to the right but there's a there's a pointer symbol to the left
so we say P is a pointer
and there's nothing more and then we always end up with the the type of thing that it points that
so P is a pointer to an int
right so P is
P as a pointer to some to some integer in memory okay
so we all know that one that's pretty easy
okay what about the next one
you've probably seen something like this
some programs declare our V using this notation
and so this you can have an optional size or not
so so we always start out we say P is a
well now in this case there's operators to the left and the right
remember the array operator has higher precedence than the the the dereferencing operator the pointer operators
so we say so P is an array 13 array of size 13  of
so there's nothing more so we go to the left  of pointers
so P is an array 13 of pointers to ints
so P is an array
of 13 pointers
each of which points to an int
right in this case P is just the name of the array
so by default P
P is a is equivalent is the address of the array
when you reference an array name you're you're you're addressing your ax dressing the address of the first element
okay how about the next one
here we're being if we put parentheses around things then we can be explicit
okay and this is a good practice
so here we're saying P
and we have to look at this one first because of the parentheses
so P is an array thirteen of pointers to ints
so that's the same thing
and here we're just being more explicit
now what about **p
so P is a pointer to a pointer to an int
okay so this is a different type of array
so P is a pointer
to a pointer
to an int
okay and
and typically so this is another way to do arrays
so the same way the char star points to a string
this this can point
it points to it points to a pointer but then you can index on that
each one of those then points corresponds to a pointer
whoops okay
here's another one now P because and because of the parentheses we have to go left
so P is a pointer to an array thirteen of ints
okay so P is an appointee to an array of 13 ints
right now what about this one
f is a function or RF
is it a function or a pointer
F is a function right because of the precedence
so f is if f is a function returning pointer to int okay
ok so if we go
if we go P equal F
then that returns that initialized P to point to some int
all right
and I'm going to do this one let's jump down in the interest of time
totally ridiculous case just so you can see that this algorithm works
all right so X is an array of pointers
to functions returning pointers
to an array five events
and if you ever use anything like that in your code
shame on you
all right so there you go so that's
now you know now you understand pointers
simple as can be and all you need is page 53 of knr is a handy reference
all right so let's we'll take the last five minutes and I'll show you some
some of the ways you can trip yourself up
when you're accessing memory
okay so first is the classic scanf bug
you probably you've probably all done this where you forget to pass it the address of
a variable instead you pass it the address
so scanf doesn't know where to put the you know put the put the data
okay another another common mistake is to read uninitialized memory
so suit you can't really assume that your heap data is initialized to 0
so here we're we're Malachy an array of an ints
and then we're going through and we're doing
we're updating this vector
this Y vector we're reading y[i]
we're taking y[i] = y[i] + A[i][j]*x[j]
okay so we're using we're assuming that Y that malloc returns memory that's all zeros
so that'll get you
it's also easy to allocate the wrong sized object
so here we want to create
an array  of n pointers of n pointers to ints
okay and then for each one we want to allocate M ints
all right so this work we're creating a two-dimensional array
and can you see the mistake which
which line is buggy this one
this one or this one
the first one right because we really want size event star
right so we're we're erroneous incorrectly assuming that intz are the same sizes as pointers
this is a classic
on this this assumption is true for 32-bit code
ints and pointers are the same size but it's not true for 64-bit
and so this is why when you when you port when people port 32-bit code to 64-bit machine a lot of times it breaks
because they have this assumption
okay another way you it's easy to overwrite memory
so here we're creating correctly creating this array
but then when we create each of the each of the sub arrays
instead of I less than or equal to n we're actually
we only created n of these things but we're traversing n + 1
because of this less than or equal
so this is a classic off by one bug
ok another another problem you saw it with the code injection attacks from your attack lab
not checking the the size of a buffer
so get get ass is a classic example of this
so that will get you into trouble
another another classic mistake is misunderstanding pointer arithmetic
all right so if you increment a pointer
then it point it's incremented by the size of the object that pointer points to
right so if you increment an int star  by one
it actually increments it by four
because that's the size of an int
he's got that's a really important distinction
and so people will often
so here it's assuming that incrementing so P is a pointer
and the programmer here assumed that he wants to increment the pointer to sort of traverse it
an array so he he doesn't understand pointer arithmetic
and so to get to the next in increments  P by size event
okay this will really increment it by sixteen not by four
okay overriding memory that's a really nasty one
and a lot of times this can happen if you don't understand the precedence of the of the operators
that you're working with
so this is a heap not not too kind of heap we've been talking about but oh the heap data structure
and this is a this is a function to delete from a heap
and this actually is from my own code I have to admit
and so I wanted to leave I want to delete in it an element
I want to delete the first element of the heap
right and then I want to reify it
okay so I and then I want to return I want to return that
so I I get the first element the heap
I that the size of the heap
or I take the the last element and make that the first element
and and now I want to decrease the size of the heap
because this delete operation will will delete the heap size by one
so notice here we passed size n as a pointer
and when this when this function terminate
when this function return size should be updated dated size as a pointer
the value that it points to you should be decremented
okay that's our intent
and we do it right here with the size minus minus star
so what we want to do is we want to dereference size
and then decrement that value
but because the unary minus minus has higher of precedence than then the dereference
what we're really doing is we're decrementing the pointer
and then dereferencing the value that's
one word less than our size variable
all right so these are nasty
and it would have been much cleaner
if I had just put parentheses around like I intended just parentheses star sized parentheses
alright another another way you can mess up is referencing forgetting the local variables disappear
so if you have a function that returns an address of a local variable no good
okay no good at all
it might be okay for a while until somebody another function  reuses that space
that could be a return address it could be another another functions local variable
another terrible mistake this is a really bad one is freeing a block multiple time
now you know from from your understanding now of malloc
that free actually writes to the heap right it's coalescing it's changing pointers
it's changing size block sizes
so if you free a block that's already been freed terrible things will happen
another thing you can do wrong is to reference a block you forget that you freed a block and then you reference
it so here we free of this block X
and then we're referencing it here
another another big problem is
memory leaks so failing to free block so allocating some block
function and then returning
that block will stay there forever right because it's garbage
okay so there's a there's a number of ways to deal with memory bugs
gdb is sometimes good at least it'll tell you where a seg fault occurs
then you got to track down what the right that
sort of caused that seg fault
the best thing you can do
but gdb falls down whenever you're doing manipulation of complex data structures
it's just simple sort of looking one instruction at a time
what you really need to do is identify any complex data structure like a heap for example
is identify invariance for that structure that that data structure should always maintain
and then you write a function
that iterates over that structure that data structure and checks that all those they're invariants are true
so for example in it
and in allocator one of the invariance is that there should be no
that there should never be two contiguous free blocks
right so your your consistency checker should go through the heap and make sure there's no no contiguous free blocks
or another invariant is that every free block should be in a free list somewhere
right so you would you would you would up your consistency checker would scan the heap count the number of free blocks
and then scan the free list and make sure
that the number of blocks in the free list is the same as the number of free blocks
okay so this idea of a consistency checker is something you'll use in your malloc lamp
but it's something it's also something you should you should use
whenever you're updating any kind of complex data structure
and the and you know about valgrind but the great thing about these heap checkers
ok I'm passionate about heap checkers
or consistency checkers
the really powerful thing about them is you write them to run silently
they don't print anything unless they find that a violation of the invariance
if you write your consistency checker like this then you can use it like a probe
so your program crashes
so you do it you use this heap checker to do a binary search to isolate the cause
so you know you put your you put your heap checker here
everything is ok
and then later the program crash
so now you stick the heap checker here
and now it crash the heap checker detects an in violation
so you know that the problem is somewhere here
and you can just keep narrowing it down so it's just like a probe
surgical probe that you can use to to track down bugs
and so that's if you do this like it's
I don't know how anybody debugs malik without this kind of tool
okay so that's it for today
have a good weekend we'll see you on Tuesday