well good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you and welcome to our viewers on video as well
okay so today we're going to look at some additional issues around the problem of synchronizing threaded programs
first so let's review from last time of a few of the concepts
so recall that a semaphore is a non non- global synchronization variable
it's manipulated by P and V operations
and the P operation takes as an argument a semaphore
if the semaphore values nonzero it decrements the semaphore  and then continues
if the if the semaphore values zero
then it blocks waiting for that that semaphore value to be incremented by a V operation
after the V operation increments after some V operation increments the semaphore
the P operation continues by decrementing s and then returning control to the caller
the V operation never blocks
it it first it increments the semaphore value s
and then it looks in the queue of four to see if there's any processes that are blocked
waiting for that some afford to be nonzero
if if there are then it selects one of those  using some unspecified criteria
and then it restarts that
it restarts that thread that's or that P operation that's waiting waiting on the semaphore
okay and then this the semantics of the P and V
ensure that semaphore values are always greater than or equal to zero
now the first thing we saw how to protect shared variables by by using a semaphore called
the mutex that guarantees mutually exclusive access to the critical sections that are updating that
those variables are structures
and and the the way that we do this is very simple
we initialize the mutex to one and then surround the critical section with a P and a V
now there's a there's other ways that we can
so so here here's an example where we're using semaphore is to provide mutual exclusion
but we can also use seminar semaphores to coordinate access to shared data structures in different ways
and so the idea here before we were using the the semaphore just to protect the access to a shared variable
but we can also coordinate access in different ways by keep and this in this in these in these kind of scenarios
we're using the semaphore to keep track of State to count to count things to keep track of State
and to notify other other threads of changes in state okay so it's a very different usage model
and two classic examples that we're going to look at are the producer consumer problem and a readers writers problem
so let's look at producer consumer first
so the idea in the producer consumer problem is that
you have a resource in the form of a buffer
the buffer has a bounded size
so it consists of n slots and each slot can hold an item
okay the there's a producer thread
which produces items
and then inserts them into the buffer
and there's a consumer thread
that retrieves removes items from the buffer
and then consumes them by acting on them in some way processing on them in some way
so the the synchronization variable the synchronization pattern is that
the producer waits for an empty slot right
so if there's if the buffer is full the producer can't insert an item into the buffer
so it waits for an empty slot
and then when it finds an empty slot when an empty slot becomes available
it inserts the item into the buffer
and then it notifies the consumer that there's now a new item in the in the in the buffer
the consumer of course that has to wait  for an item to show up in the buffer right
otherwise I mean you can't remove an item from an empty buffer
so it has to wait for for an item to be available in the buffer
and when an item becomes available it removes it from the buffer
and then notifies the the producer that there's now an available slot
okay so this
actually this very simple pattern is actually really really useful and shows up in a lot of applications
so for example a multimedia application
in a multimedia application the producer might be producing say MPEG MPEG frames in it in a video
and a consumer would be consuming those those MPEG frames and then painting the screen  appropriately
another important application is in graphical user interfaces
so graphical user interfaces are typically implemented using this producer-consumer model
where the mouse clicks,motions and the in the of the mouse keyboard clicks
those are all recorded as events
they're detected by the system recorded as events and placed into a some kind of a queue
and then up various other parts of the system retrieve items from the queue and and react to them
so for example the graphic system will retrieve
events like Mouse events and mouse movements mouse clicks
and it will paint the screen accordingly right a soda little
it will reflect it will repaint the screen so that the  two so that to show you that the cursor is moving
right or if you change the focus it will it will repaint it
so it's it's a very very common model
and as we'll see later multi-threaded we can build multi-threaded concurrent servers using this this model
so let's see how we would implement producer/consumer on an n-element buffer
so this the implementation requires a mutex  to guarantee mutually exclusive access to the resource of course
and then it requires then two other semaphores counting semaphores
slots is a semaphore that counts the available slots in the buffer
and items is counts the available items okay
and we've can implement it with this this package called s buff
so S buff the s buff package defines a type called S buff
underscore T that packages up all of the data structures that are needed to implement the the shared buffer
so there's a pointer to the the buffer which we were going to implement as an array and
and we'll implement a circular buffer on this array
the maximum number of slots n so the size of the buffer
and then two pointers front and rear to keep track of the the front and rear of the of the buffer
so to keep track of the first and last items in the buffer
and then the three semaphores the mutex and in the two counting semaphores
and then the package consists of these four public functions
S buff an it which creates the is called once to create the the buffer and initialize everything
allocate the space and initialize things and the D in it which which frees up the space
and then a function to insert an item
into the queue and a function to remove an item from a queue and return that item
so in this case items are just in
so to create the to initialize the this buffer
with n slots we first allocate the space for the buffer and n n
we set the we set the size to be the value n that was passed in
we indicate the empty buffer by setting front-and-rear to be zero
okay and so whenever front and rear are zero that's we have an empty buffer
and then we initialize the three semaphore
so the mutex like all meu Texas is initialized to 1
the slot semaphore which keeps track of the number of available slots is initialized to N
and the item semaphore is initialized to zero
okay and D and it is really simple it just frees up the the heap space that we allocated
okay so now let's look at how we insert an item into the buffer
so we call we want to insert this integer item into this buffer pointed at by SP
so first the thread waits for an available slot
okay by doing a P on the slot sim before alright so P will block
until the slots is greater than or equal to one
okay once there's an available slot
then it if then it's going to it's going to update the the rear of the of the buffer
okay so we're going to put this item on to the rear of the buffer
and so it needs to protect that access to that shared buffer  with the mutex
then it does the bike bike by doing a P on the mutex
updating updating our rear pointer
okay so we pre increment it so we increment the rear pointer and then take take the mod of that n
2 to compute the index that we're going to insert the item
okay then we do a V on the mutex
okay so that other other threads can can update that  that shared data structure
and then we do a V on the number of items to notify any consumers
that there's now an item in the in the buffer
so this this V is kind of interesting you think it was kind of like a signal right so you're sort of signaling consumers that now
some event has occurred in the system
now to remove an item it's it's symmetric but instead of
instead of operating on the slots that before it operates on the items semaphore
so to remove an item a consumer first does a P  on the items semaphore
so this now is waiting for an available item it's waiting for the semaphore to be greater than equal to one
when that happens then the P the P returns
and then we do we do the update protected by a mutex
by pre-incrementing front taking the mod n
and then reading that value and returning it and placing it into this local local variable item
then we release the mutex
and then we do a V on the number of slots which
which is an announcement to the to any producers that there's now a new available slot
so any questions about that
so it's a little more subtle
this looks really simple but like all concurrency problems it's actually very subtle
so you can have potential you can have many producers and many many consumers all operating on the same
you know the same the same shared buffer
so this so what would happen if
if we had two two consumers did
a a P on this item semaphore at the exact same time say we're running on two cores
and and we have two threads and they each each execute that P
at the same time on that that same that same item semaphore
okay so even even though they access it at the same time the kernel will make sure that one of them will execute first
okay so the kernel will serialize  those P operations
and it there's no telling which one gets it first but whoever acts whoever runs
there P first will will decrement this
this item semaphore
and then when the next when the next thread executes
its P items will either be zero or nonzero
okay as a result so somebody wins there's kind of a ton of like a controlled race
and somebody wins the race always wins the race because the kernel is serializing
these P operations and it's executing them atomically okay
okay now the the there's a generalization of the mutual exclusion problem called the reader writer problem
so with with the mutual mutual exclusion problem
we were guaranteeing each thread mutually exclusive access to to its critical section
that's updating a particular resource or accessing a particular resource
and we did this the exact same way whether that access was a read or write
okay but that's that's overly conservative in this case
because we could if all we were doing if we had multiple threads that were just reading the resource
there would be no reason to do Ps and Vs on that resource or if we're not changing
if we're not changing the resource for just reading it and there's nobody else writing it
then then there's no need to protect right so it
for readers we can have as many readers as we want all at the same time reading reading the the resource the variable or set of variables
and there's no need for any kind of synchronization at all
okay so the producer consumer is sort of a generalization of that mutual exclusion problem
which enforces mutual exclusion only when it's absolutely necessary
okay so there can be is there there can be as many readers reading the resource
but when a writer wants to write then it
it has to have mutual exclusive access to the resource
okay so this is a kind of thing this is also a very useful pattern
you have in an online airline reservation system you have multiple clients accessing a shared database
okay so as long as those clients are reading the database you can have
they can all be reading at the same time but as soon as somebody wants to make a reservation and update the database
then that update has to happen a mutually exclusive way
you know if you had also if you had like any kind of shared data structure like a cache
in a in a concurrent proxy like that you're going to be writing soon
or if you haven't already started
that cache is being shared by multiple threads
and multiple threads may be reading that cache
but when some when you when you get a new page and you want to cache it
then that that that constitutes a right and that right needs to happen in our mutually exclusive way
now the initial research the researchers that
that pose this readers writers problems
in define sort of several classes of reader writer problems
the first reader writer readers writers problems is an implementation that favors readers right
so the idea is that no reader should be kept waiting
right unless an a writer already has a P as has sort of acquired the lock on that or the mutex on that on that resource
so it in this case
you know say there's a writer waiting to get to acquire the mutex
and another reader comes in
then in this implementation that reader would give priority over the writer
and it would be able to to read the to add to do its read
and the writer would have to wait
and so of court now if multiple readers keep coming in then this could starve out the writer right that
so a writer could be starved sort of indefinitely waiting for all these readers to finish
and it's just based on you know based based on
how the operating system decides to schedule these these various reader reader threads
the the writer could be could be starved out so that's what that's what we mean by when we say that it favors readers
now the second reader saris problem is the sort of the opposite of that so it favors writers right
so any once a writer is ready to to write
then it gets priority over any waiting readers
so in in this case if we have if we have multiple writers
that want to write they could starve out readers
and now there's there's other variants that sort of deal with this starvation issue  potential starvation issue
but we won't look at them here
so the let's look at the solution to the first readers writers problem
so write initially a thread is either a reader in this sort of simplification  or it's a writer
if we look at the writers this is pretty simple
it's just the writers are just doing a peon this semaphore
so this this the semaphore W is the sort of serves as like a mutex that protects the resource  for writer
so it it ensures that there's at most one writer at any time executing its critical section
and it does that by just this this very from this familiar P followed followed by a V
key no readers are a little more interesting
so with a with the reader
we have the shared this global variable called read count which is going to keep track of the number of readers
that are waiting to to read the to read the resource
and there's a mutex semaphore mutex that protect protects the accesses the updates to read count
okay the reads and the rights to up to read count
and then there's this W semaphore
which as we saw here is used to protect the critical section in the writer
and initially both of these are set to one
so the reader in this infinite loop in each iteration of this infinite loop
it is going to increment read count so it protects that that access by by doing a pee on the mutex
which is associated with recount
so only one only one reader can can be
so this this this region between the p and the v constitutes the critical section corresponding to read count
so after the p completes then it
then we increment the read count so now there's an additional reader
alright so we can have potentially arbitrary number of these reader threads
right so this we're indicating that there's there's there's a new reader now
and if read count is one that that means we're the first reader
okay so this is sort of the first reader into the this this implicit queue of waiting readers
so if read count is one if we're the first reader
then we do a p on w
okay which now will lock out any any any future writers
now if there's already a writer that's done it's P of W then this will block waiting for that writer to finish
okay but if there's no writer in inside of its critical critical section
then this P will just decrement the semaphore W
from 1 to 0 and then lock out any subsequent writers
okay after so now after it's done this increment and read of the recount variable then it releases the mutex
so that other readers can can access recount
okay now but it's still holding
it's it's it's it's holding so this is this is kind of interesting right it's it's it's holding the semaphore that
that locks out the writers
but it's not holding the any-any mutex right so the reader now can just can just read
it can do its read
and other readers that are in the same the same section of the code can also do their reads
right so so we're not
so we're allowing multiple readers now inside this critical section
but but no writers
okay so everything so everything works looks like it works good now after after we read
now the number of readers now is going to be we want to decrement the number of readers
so we acquire the mutex on on read count
we decrement read count
and then we check to see if we're the last reader
okay so if there's no more readers
in other words if read count is zero
then with now we can release the mutex for the writer
so that any now writers can can access that resource
and after we release that the writers the writers mutex then we release the mutex for recount
so any questions about about this
so an interesting for you to think about just uh
if you have any spare time is
how you might how you might write a version of this readers writers problem or that
favors writers instead of readers
yes
oh no okay so the question is a mutex allows for multiple readers
the fact that we know the fact that we're releasing this mutex here
that this mutex is only only protecting access to read count
so we acquire it here and we release it here
after we've after we've accessed read count
okay but we're not protecting the critical section of the reader with any with any mutex
except for we're we're keeping writers out by if we're the first one in
if we're the first reader
you commanders like this implicit queue of readers that we're keeping track of with read count
okay so if we're the first ones in meaning
we're the first reader then we we acquire this the p on the writers mutex
now if there's of course if there's a writer inside this critical section then
this p will wait until the writer releases
okay but once once we've acquired this this this mutex w
then we're block we're locking out any writers
okay because they'll any writer that that arrives we'll do a p and it will block right here on waiting for that w to be nonzero
okay so so we're just we're blocking out any writers but then we're allowing any readers to just to access the resource
okay
okay good
yes question
question is blocking slow
it can be depends well first of all you're making a call into the kernel so it's a system call
so you're crossing that boundary and there's always overhead associated with that
and then blocking you're blocked until you know it can be sort of an arbitrary amount of time right
until someone doesn't some thread does a V
so yeah it can't be slow
right it just it just depends you can't it's it's really hard to bound the time that you're going to be blocked
now if you write the program correctly eventually you'll be unblocked
you know eventually some thread will execute a V
but when we're sort of assuming that the kernel does some kind of when it implements its V it does some kind of fair scheduling that
so a blocked a blocked P won't be in its queue for forever right that the kernel does some kind of something that's fair
so it guarantees that a P won't remain blocked indefinitely
other questions
okay so we can kind of put all of this together
and and use the use our producer-consumer model to
to implement a pre threaded concurrent echo server
now so far when we've when we've used threads to
in all our examples of using threads and processes for servers
we created a new thread or process whenever a new connection requests arrived
and then when it went
and then that that thread interacted with the client
and then whenever whenever that interaction was finished it closed the connection and exited
and killed the the thread or process
now that's that's okay but it's it's it's inefficient
because we're this creating and killing threads introduces overhead
so another way to do this is to pre the treads or processes ahead of time  create a pool of threads
where each thread so we create a pool of these worker threads
where each of these worker threads interacts with can interact with a client
okay so instead of sort of creating processes and threads on on-demand
we create a what we call a set of pre threaded or pre threaded threads or pre forked processes
that do the work
so the idea is that we have this master thread in our server
that's waiting for connection requests from clients  by repeated calls to accept
and then when it when this thread receives the connection request
from the client the accept the accept call the accept function returns a connected file descriptor
ok associated with the connection to the client
and then it inserts that descriptor into a into a buffer
ok now remember descriptors are just small integers
that index the descriptor table
right so they can be passed around from thread to thread
because all the threads are sharing the same
the same set that same descriptor table right
so the master thread puts
the repeatedly accepts connection requests and inserts the corresponding connected file descriptor into the buffer
now each worker thread waits for the so in this case the items are descriptors
so the worker threads they're all waiting on this for items to appear in this buffer
okay and when an item appears one of the threads will remove that item
and then use that descriptor to interact with the with the client
over the connected file descriptor associated with the connection that exists between the client  and the server
okay so now we have we have these the concurrency comes in the form of these multiple worker threads
interacting with with multiple clients
and then when a worker thread finishes servicing a particular client
then it just goes and it checks for the next file descriptor in the buffer
okay so this is much more efficient than our previous model where
for each new client we had to create a thread or a process
and then destroy that thread or process once we were finished
okay so we're sort of re amortize that
that we had to go through to create these worker threads  by leaving them running
and then replacing the destruction or the killing of that thread with replacing it with just a simple
as simple and very fast operation of removing an item from the buffer okay
okay so let's let's see how we would we would implement this
and like like all of these server examples it's surprisingly simple right
this is a fully functioning a real server but we can do it in one one page  one page of code
so for this preet we're going to use threads for our concurrent server
and we're going to use the s buff package so we're going to create this
this shared buffer global variable called s buff
and we have listening descriptor and connected descriptor
and we have the client length and client adder that that will be used in the accept call
and we have the thread ID that will be used in the when we create that when we create this thread
so now that we start by we're going to in this program we're going to pass in the port number
so the server is going to be listening on some port
so we passed that port number in as the first argument
so we call open listened FD on our V of one
an open listened FD creates a listening descriptor and returns it
returns the value of that descriptor and listen FD
and then we call s buff in it to to initialize our shared buffer
with with s buff sized file descriptors
and then we create a collection of n threads worker threads
each of which will execute the the thread routine which we've called thread  and no argument
so once we create these all of these threads then we go in this infinite loop
where we call except
on this listening descriptor so in that except we'll block until a connection request arrives
and when it does the accept returns with a connected file descriptor that can be used to to interact with the client
and once we get that connected file descriptor then we just simply insert it
we insert that that connected file descriptor into our shared buffer
and then wait for the connection request  the next connection request
so our servers very efficient right we're just doing an accept and then a very fast insert into the buffer
okay and then we're going to let the worker threads do all the work associated with those with that with with that  that queue of descriptors
now the thread routine first detaches
okay so this is a case where we don't want to run joinable
because we're never going to to join
we're never going to wait for these threads or have any any reason to I kill them  from the main thread
so this so now this this worker thread and in this infinite loop each iteration it removes
an item from the buffer so it blocks until there's an item that it can that it can remove from the buffer
and it sets it to this local variable con FD
and then it calls a helper sort of this this is like the the helper function
that implements the logic for this this particular server and this is this in this case it's an echo server
so this this echo count routine will interact with the client
echoing whatever the client sends us until the client closes the connection
and then when it so whenever the client is finished then
then we close the week we close the our end of the connection and go back and get the next item out of the buffer
and as you point out that echo count is just a placeholder this could be anything
this could be the logic for a web server for any any kind of web service or any kind of service
now
the the to initialize this echo count function
we need to we need to initialize the mutex
so we're so this echo count function is going to have it has it defines a global variable called byte count
so this in this echo server we're going to keep track of the number of bytes that we've received from all the clients
that we're interacting with
okay so there's a global variable called byte count which is shared by all the threads
and we're going to update this this byte count variable every time we receive
something every time we receive data from from the client
and we're going to use mutex to protect the accesses to byte count
okay so we're going to initially have to initialize
we have to call a function that initializes
that initializes this by first initializing the mutex and then setting byte count to zero
and then within echo count itself
there's some we've already seen Sud
we've already seen a way to initialize a package
you know if we have some kind of package of library functions that are going to be used by multiple threads
there's several ways to actually initialize this package
so one way is to explicitly call have the the main thread
call this initialization function once
okay so we've seen that with like the S buff package right the main thread has to call
the main thread calls S buffin at once
okay before any of the peer threads execute any of the worker threads executes
but there's another way we can do this too we can have that the worker threads actually call the initialization function
and we can use this technique provided by by P threads
where we define a static variable so this is a static local variable
but you recall that this is actually treated like a global variable
so it every thread has access to this variable
okay but but its scope is limited to to the disco de cocao function
so no other no other function connect can access  this variable
but each each thread that executes this thread routine has access to it
and and in this context it's treated like a global right
so if one thread updates the value every other every thread sees that same value
okay so so we can use this this mechanism from P threads
but so we can create this
this this variable of type P thread once T  and initialize it to this special P threads value
which is sort of like the P threads uninitialized value
so this is a value that P threads knows about that indicates that
that this this variable wants hasn't been initialized
and then and then we call the pthread once function
passing at this this this variable that we the address of this variable created that we created
and the address of the function to call to initialize
whatever it is we want to initialize in this case the the echo count
the the echo count variable
and so what this does every thread will call P thread once
but only one thread will actually  call the the initialization function
only the very first thread that executes speith read once will we'll call it
the other threads this this P thread wants call will be like a no op
yes question
well that's the other option
so so the advantage of this is that
you can you I guess the advantage is I I don't know that it's just another way you can do it
you I guess it avoids it avoids having to do it in the master thread that
you can you can make your you can make this package sort of self-contained right that
you're not you're not really counting on the master doing anything
but yeah that's that's the other way we could have done it so I just wanted to show you this this
this other technique
okay so once we once we initialize once we once
some thread calls the NED echo count
then we initialize the reo package
for all of our accesses on this connected descriptor
and then we we repeatedly read a line of text from the client
okay and then
in a protected way we increment bite count with the number of bytes that
we received  from the client which is returned by this Rio read line b function
and then we print a little message just to sort of keep track
so we can see keep track of our running total
and then we release the mutex on this on the byte count the global byte count variable
and then we echo that line back to the client
okay so any questions about that
yes question
so the line there's it
okay the question is the line that declares the static variable
once will it only be executed the first time
a thread executes that statement
no it's so the answer is no every every thread will define this variable
and assign it this to this this this P thread once value
okay what will only happen once is the call to a net echo count
okay so the first thread that executes this P thread once call
will actually call an EDD echo count
every other thread every subsequent thread will not call it it'll be like a no op
[student speaking]
yeah uses the ones it's just an opaque
cause the declaration line once it will be selling the flag by resetting in speech
yeah somehow it will but somehow the pthread wants is keeping track that it's it's executed
okay so I I'm really not sure how how its implemented
okay so somehow pthread wants
yeah I guess every you know this
I mean this is just the C declaration right so there's no
the pthreads has no control over declarations right
so every thread will get it every thread will sort of update this static variable
and you're wright if the first thread
the second thread would overwrite this value again
but somehow pthread once  can keeps track of that
okay in a in some way that I I'm not sure about how that works
but this is this is the way you get that behavior
can others there's some other issues around synchronizing threads sort of correctness issues that we have to be aware of
and so I hope your hope you're sort of getting the sense that this threaded programming is is kind of a tricky business right
and so one issue that we always have to be aware of is is is this idea called thread safety
so in general a thread routine can only should only call functions that are that are thread safe
that have this property called thread safety
okay and a function is thread safe
if and only if that function can be invoked by multiple threads at the same time
okay so if we have a function f
its thread safe if and only if its execution can be interleaved by multiple threads
and so we can identify a four different classes of thread unsafe functions
so one classes is the functions that fail to protect shared variables with mutexes
okay so we've already seen that with bad count
that was an example of a thread unsafe that main routine was an example of an unsafe thread function
or no the thread function was an example of an unsafe thread function
because it didn't protect the act the update of the count variable
another class of functions that that our thread unsafe is are those functions that keep track of state across multiple invocations
so if they're storing State in some global global variable private or public global variable the net
that's thread unsafe
because multiple threads will be accessing that State
another way another kind of thread unsafe function or functions that return a pointer to a static variable
so there's there's there's a number of functions in the standard c library
that were written before threads or even on anybody's radar
and so so an example is the C time function
which takes as an argument a time struck two binary time struct
and returns a pointer to a string date and time string
but the address in that pointer is always the same
right so the this function is is defining some kind of static variable
and it's always returned and then it's it's it it's converting that the binary time struct
into it into a string that's always at the same location and it's returning the address of that string
so every invocation returns the exact same address
but with different content at that address
okay and this you know they just they didn't realize that this was a bad thing to do
for threaded programs because nobody was writing threaded programs at that at the time
and then obviously any function that calls and unthread unsafe function is threat unsafe
okay so let's look at these these different classes of functions
okay so the class one functions fail to protect shared variables
and so the fix as we've seen is to use P and V to guarantee mutually exclusive access and thereby protect  the accesses to the variable
so we saw this with that good count program
and then the the problem is it also as we saw with good count is that the synchronization up
operations can be slow so if they're in a tight inner loop
it can it can really slow your program down
okay the class 2 thread on safe functions rely on
some kind of persistent state across invocations of that function
okay so the classic example is the Lipsy rand function
whose in this the an implementation of which is I took from the K in our book
so this this R and this is a pseudo pseudo-random number generator
a pseudo random in the sense that
if you give it the same key it'll return the same sequence of values okay
so this is kind of nice because it allows when you're testing it allows repeatability
so every time you call it if you call it with the same seed you can you're guaranteed you'll get the same results
and the way this is implemented
is that there's at the seed
if there's this there's a seed variable called next
which is used in each iteration of the random number generator
and it's it's defined as a global private
so static makes it private so it's not accessible to programs that are calling
the rand function but it's it's used by the rand function
and so this this variable is initialized to 1
there's a function called s Rand which allows the user to set the seed value
so the the default seed value is one
but if the user calls s ran they can pass in a seed
which will be then which will be which is just would assign to this this next variable
and then each iteration of R
and does an operation on the seed
so it takes that the next value that's going to be used is the is a property of the previous value
the function of the previous value
and then it returns a pseudo-random number
that's a function of that next value
okay so it's relying on this each iteration each time you call Rand
you're relying on the this next value that was computed by the previous time that you called Rand
okay now this is perfectly fine and there's no problem with this
in a non-threaded situation
but what happens if multiple threads now
so suppose you have multiple threads
and and they're each calling this rand function sort of interleaving calls to two Rand
okay the the fact that that Rand is relying on the this previous state
if multiple threads are calling Rand it's going to break the pseudo-random property
so each thread that the the random numbers that each thread gets back
are not only a function of the previous
the seed from the previous time that thread called the function
but also also a function of the other threads that are calling it right
so so if a particular thread calls this random number generator multiple times
it potentially won't see the same sequence of pseudo-random numbers because other threads will be jumping in
okay and
okay so it it's it's not it's not incorrect and that the program will fail
but if the program is counting on the pseudo random property
then it creates a problem okay
so the the solution to this is to rewrite Rand
and require it to require the caller to keep track of this next variable
okay so each caller will keep its own local copy of next and it will pass in a pointer to R and
R and we'll compute that value so now this will be updating state in the calling
the calling thread but this is local state on the on that thread stack okay
so every thread will have its own copy of of next
so we but we have to create a new function and what we'll call it underscore R
the stands for reentrant which is a property we'll look at in just a second
but it's more work for the programmer because now the programmer has to maintain this
this sort of this next value okay
okay another way that threads the functions are unsafe
is this this is are these functions that always retain a return a pointer to some global  to the same global variable
or typically it's a static variable
but they always return the same value each time the same address
okay so you can see this is similar to that race that we encountered before
where we were passing the address of a connected file descriptor to a worker thread
okay so now we're creating a race so let's say one thread
let's say one thread calls this function so for example
C time takes this this time struct as an argument
okay which can correspond to an arbitrary time it could be the current time or just some arbitrary time that the caller constructed
and it returns a pointer to a char star
so it just returns a pointer to a string that represents the date and the time
its own ASCII ASCII string that that represents the date and time
but it's always it's always returning a pointer to the same  the same location in memory
okay so you can see the problem if thread a calls this C time function
with one with top one time struck
it gets back a pointer to the to the character string corresponding to that time struct
but now let's say before before thread a can use that
read that that string another thread calls C time
and that instance of C time will overwrite that
the copy of the time string for that that thread a computed
so when thread a finally gets a chance to access
that time string its accessing thread B's time string and not threat ace time string
okay and it just depends if thread a can get to that and read that variable before thread B
over writes it then everything's fine
and otherwise threat a's accessing the wrong time string
okay so there's there's a couple of ways to fix this like
we could rewrite the the function the c time function to take
as a de nother argument that passes in
the the location the address of the time string
so we could require that the caller to allocate space for the time string and passing the address to the c time function
okay but this has this says this would require us to change all the instances
where we call c time
but we'd also have to change the the implementation of c time in the live in the Lipsy in the library
right and so we can't we don't have access to Lib C source on our system
right so that's that's just not a feasible thing plus it would break every other program
that called C time right so we just can't do
that the another op a better option is to create a new function of our own
okay called C time underscore TTS for thread safe
so we'll create our own sort of wrapper function  for it for the C time
and we'll use a technique called lock and copy to to provide thread safe access  to 2c time
so the way it works is it will write this new function C time underscore TS
which just like c time takes this a pointer to this time struct
but then it adds a second argument
which is a pointer to the threat of threads private copy of the time string
okay so the caller allocates the space and passes the pointer to this  to that to that string
and then within c time we have a local variable called shared the shared pointer
okay so this is going to point to that that that shared global data structure that see time is is accessing
and so first we do the lock that's the lock part of lock and copy by acquiring a mutex
and then we call see time
so only one thread at a time we'll have this mutex
so whatever thread so once once we return from PE
we know that we're the only thread in this in this this critical section
so we call C time the normal lip CC time function
which returns a pointer to this to the same location
and then we do the copy part we copy that that string
to the private string that was passed in just into our function
once we've done the copy then we can release the mutex
and then we return a pointer
we return private P back to the caller right ok so
and we don't we don't this is just more of a convenience to the caller
because programs that are using C time are expecting to get that pointer back
ok so by using lock and copy
we have to we have to make changes we have to write this new function but it's fairly simple
and then we have to make changes every place in our program where we call C time
we have to update those two calls to C time underscore TS
and create this create this local string array
ok yes
it has to be the variable cost
well typically these functions are returning pointers to some data structure
and so they're they're sort of updating the data structure and then returning a pointer to it so
it wouldn't makes I don't know how
I guess it could return a struct and it would always return
now now
I can't think of any I can't think of any reason why they would turn anything but a pointer
because they're they're typically updating some some data structure
and then returning a pointer to it
if they were returning
scalars those scalars would always be returned in EAX  or RA X
all right so actually that would be okay right it would just be
it's the pointer that causes a problem because
it's it's always returning that value in EAX
but it's always returning the same value in EAX always pointing to the same
the same data structure okay good
okay now one-
one potentially significant disadvantage of lock and copy is that
this this copy might not always be as simple as just doing like a stir copy if
if it's a complex diff if the function that you're calling is computing some complex data structure like a nested
you know a struct which contains structs and pointers to arrays
then this copy can get can get quite complicated right
it it would require what we call a deep copy
so that can be that can be very difficult to
but in this case it's simple we're just we're just doing a we're just copying one string to another
okay and then finally the
the fourth class of thread unsafe functions are functions that
call unsafe functions right so it's kind of obvious
and then the obvious fix is to not call thread unsafe functions from within your function
and then you can make it thread safe
now there's a very interesting an
important subclass of thread-safe functions called reentrant functions
so a reentrant a function is reentrant
if it contains no accesses to shared to shared variables
okay so if all the if every variable that it accesses is
contained on the is declared as a local variable and stored on the stack
for that function okay that's called a reentrant function
and because there's no accesses of any kind to shared variables
there's no there's no synchronization required
because every function is is operating accessing its own local copy of all the variables
and if multiple threads execute  two instances of a reentrant function
it's okay each thread has its own separate stack
so you don't need to worry about any kind of synchronization they can run independently
so the reason reentrant functions are so important is because it's expensive to do synchronization
and so what you can avoid it completely with these reentrant function reentrant functions
so they're they're efficient
so as that as the diagram shows every reentrant function is thread safe
but not every thread safe function is reentrant
so we saw that before right when we have a function that accesses a shared variable
we can make it thread safe by protecting it with a mutex
okay but it's not reenter n't because it's it's X it's accessing shared variables okay
now on all the functions in the standard c library which are enumerated in the back of your k and r texture thread-safe
okay but not not necessarily reentrant
and most most syscalls are thread safe with just a with a few exceptions that I've listed here
I don't I don't think I don't think this is complete
but these are just some examples of some notable ones
and so for each each of these thread unsafe functions
Linux provides a reentrant version
which is denoted by underscore R
and then that reentrant version has a different different set of parameters typically
the only exception that I know about is I net n to a which is an episode of an obsolete Network protocol for converting
sort of binary Network addresses to human readable ASCII addresses
but this is this is ops been obsoleted by by other calls
so it's I guess they just never never bothered to create a reentrant version for it
because there's there's other options alternatives to using that
okay another so another thing we have to worry about is we've seen is races
again this is the real Bugaboo in in threaded programs
and it typically involves some kind of unexpected sharing
so in this case I'm going to revisit this
this this incorrect threaded program
that where we introduce introduced a race by passing when we create the thread
we we pass the argument to the thread which is like the local thread ID
we pass an address of a variable that we have stored on the stack
and is Katun the eye that the the loop loop iterator
and so
we've seen that this causes this causes a race so
we incurred we we set initially I is 0 then we create a new thread which is pure thread 0
and then this thread dereferences the pointer to get its local copy of the this sort of local thread ID
but now we've introduced the race
between the increment of I
and the dereferencing of the incrementing of I and the main thread
and the dereferencing of I in the peer thread
so if this dereferencing happens before I is incremented then we're good
but if this dereferencing happens after
we increment I so in other words at when I equal 1
then we get the wrong value in the peer thread for for my ID
so you might wonder I think there was a question before about
you know this seems that the odds of this happening seems so low why why are you even worrying about it
so we actually create just to sort of test this out we wrote a program to see if we could
see if we could actually see this race in practice
and that's one of the great things about like 2:13 is that you we can just try stuff out right so
so we just tried it out
so we wrote it we wrote a simple main thread that creates a hundred different threads
each with then we passed the art as the argument we passed the address of of this local variable I okay
and then in each peer thread we detach the thread dereference
and then we have a function that saves the value so we're we're storing
we're storing that value of I  for future reference
okay so now if there's no race
each of the 100 threads would get a separate distinct thread ID
right so each each value 0 through 99
if we made a histogram of it
there would be exactly one instance of each of each value of I
okay but if there was a race there would be for some values of Y
there would be multiple instances that were encountered in multiple threads
okay so you can see if we go back here
if if if we lose if the peer thread loses the race and I gets incremented before it can dereference
now we've got peer thread zero actually gets a an ID of one
okay and then peer thread one
if there's no race it'll it'll get the correct value of one so now we've got two instances of one okay
so let's look so this is the case
so we've plotted the results for a case where there's no race so along the x-axis sorry this is too small
the x-axis gives us all the 100 values of I 0 through 99
and then the y-axis is the count so this is a hit we're doing a histogram of
for these all the values 0 through 99
so in this case every value has exactly one instance so no race
there was no race in in no races in involved in all 99 are all 100 instances
if we run it on a single core laptop
so now each thread is sort of taking its turn on a single core
it happens a few times right so there's a few times where
the one thread gets preempted and the other thread
begins to run before it can so the peers when one thread gets preempted before I can dereference
the variable so it gets the wrong the wrong value
but it's not very common it just it happened one two three four five six seven times
but now if we run this program on a on a multi-core server
you can see it happens a lot in fact it happens most of the time
so it almost never we almost never get the correct the correct value for for my ID
okay so this is just another example of some of the create the things that can just drive you crazy
if you're not careful when you when you program is and threads with threads
okay and as so as we saw the the way to eliminate these kind of erases  is to avoid
this the sharing of state and in this case by allocating
for each thread allocating a separate block in the in the heap
that will hold the that will hold the the local ID for that thread
and then passing a pointer to that that unique block of storage to the thread
okay so if that if all of that isn't enough to worry about
and by now you should be losing sleep
at the very thought of writing a threaded program
another thing to worry about is deadlock
okay so here a program is deadlocked if it's waiting for some condition to occur that will never occur
okay so let's say a typical scenario right pee
pee is the potential the pee operation is a potential problem because it blocks
right and it's waiting for that semaphore that it's blocking on to become nonzero
well it's it's not too hard to imagine scenarios where
some there's some combination of pees of pee operations that sort of block each other
out okay and make it impossible for the condition they're waiting on to occur
so for example let's say you've got two two threads
that need two two threads one and two
that need two different resources a and B in order to proceed
so they have to acquire they have to do a pee on the mutex
that on this on the mutex that that's associated with
the mutexes that are associated with these two resources
so let's say process one acquires a so it does a pee on a x' mutex
that's one it's okay so it succeeds at it so it acquires that resource
and then it gets preempted by thread to
which acquires B
first instead of acquiring a thread B for some reason acquires B
so now thread a holds the lock on resource a
and thread two holds the lock on resource B
and so now let's say process thread two gets preempted so now
and thread one runs and so now it's waiting
it's trying to tries to acquire
the the lock on resource b-
but threat to our holds that lock
and at the same time thread to tries to acquire the lock on resource a
but process one is holding that right
so they're each so here's the case where thread a is waiting for this semaphore
associated with B to become non zero
so it's blocked in this P operation
and at the same time thread two is blocked in the P operation for for for resource a
neither of those semaphores will ever be released
so thread one and two are deadlocked
okay and it it happened because just there was this innocuous little bug in this case
where one the threads acquired their resources in different orders
so here's an example of a program that deadlocks
and if you looked at this you know the fact that it's wrong and buggy doesn't jump out at you right
so this is this kind of stuff is very subtle
so here's here's a program we're going to create two threads
we've got an array so and we have an array of meu Texas
an array of two mutexes
so we create two threads and we pass each thread
it's a local thread ID so of 0 & 1
and so here we're avoiding the race we're just casting this thread ID to be -  a pointer okay
which is a little strange but it's okay
and then we're waiting for those threads to finish
ok each thread is going to acquire two these two semaphores
these two mutexes
but it's going to do it in a different order
okay so it's going to do it as a function it's going to take the ID
so it's going to sew thread zero will first acquire a mutex 0
and then and then acquire mutex 1-0
so then it will acquire mutex 1
and thread 1 will first acquire mutex one
and then acquire mutex 0
0 ok so if we were to draw that diet and then and then it will attempt to then it will increment count
so this is totally bogus
but it's just to illustrate the problem
so you can see thread 0 does a peon semaphore 0 followed by a peon semaphore 1
and thread 1 does a peon semaphore 1
followed by a peon semaphore 0
and so we can see this that this is a problem very clearly
if we go back to our progress graphs
so if you look at thread 0
it's doing a peon semaphore 1
and of and it followed a peon semaphore 1 followed by a V on semaphore 1
and thread 1 is also is doing a peon semaphore 1 followed by a V on semaphore 1
so if you take if you take the intersection of these two regions
you get the forbidden region for semaphore 1
okay so this is the region that enforces mutual exclusion
so on this on this the resource associated with semaphore 1
and if you do the same thing for semaphore 0 so here in thread 1
we're acquiring semaphore 0 here and releasing it here
and we're in thread 0 we're acquiring it here  and releasing it here
so if you take the intersection of those two
you get this forbidden region for s0
ok now the problem
his right is this region here this so-called deadlock region
because by the rules of
you know time can't go backwards
heart once  the trajectory enters into the this deadlock region
then it's doomed
because there's no once it enters this
once it enters this deadlock region there's nowhere for it to go eventually
no matter how it progresses
every trajectory will lead to to this point here where
it's boxed in and can't and can no longer proceed
so
so interestingly this this sort of this this region back here
on the on the the sort of the tail end of the of these two forbidden regions
this represents states that can never be reached
so these are on unreachable states which may or may not be interesting
and then what makes this so nasty
is that
it's non-deterministic right some programs some trajectories
if they get lucky they'll skirt this deadlock region
and then the program will run fine right
there's okay so if it's trajectory maybe
just by some you know just by some arbitrary scheduling decision
made by the colonel the trajectory
trajectory gets passed the deadlock region in this direction
and then it'll eventually run without any problem
so it's just it's only if the trajectory lands it within the deadlock region then there were that we're in trouble
so so this is the really nasty the really nasty part is
that you may run your program for a million times  and every trajectory
every one of those million trajectories skirts the deadlock region
okay but on the million and first time that you run it
it it enters the deadlock region and then deadlocks
okay so it's it's it's very it's a very tough problem to deal with
now fortunately you it's easy to avoid
if if threads that are acquiring locks on on resources acquire all those locks in the same order
okay so in our example if we rewrite this program
so that each thread thread 0 and thread 1 acquire their locks in the same order
semaphore 0 first followed by semaphore 1
then if that happens and we you can see
it eliminates the debt the potential deadlock region
okay so now any trajectory that we take   will will be fine
because we've eliminated that that that deadlock region
and the the order that we release the locks doesn't matter
because that that sort of affects the the
it affects this or unreachable region you know the size and shape of this unreachable reason region
but it there's never the order that we release the locks can never introduce a deadlock region
okay so that's it for today
hope you all have a very nice Thanksgiving holiday and we'll see you on Tuesday