good afternoon everyone welcome to 213
it's good to see you just a reminder
that your attack lab is due tonight at
11:59 p.m. you have one grace day for
this for this lab and cache lab we'll go
out it right about the same time now
it's going to be a little tight for cash
labs it'll be due next Thursday so you
might want to you might want to get
started on that soon
b2 last lecture we learned about the
memory hierarchy and the idea of caching
today we're going to look at a very
important kind of cache which is a which
are which are called cache memories and
they're they're very important to you as
a programmer because they can have such
a big impact on the performance of your
program so if you know about these the
existence of these cache memories and
you know how they work
as a programmer you'll be able to take
advantage of that in your programs
so last time we looked at that the
memory hierarchy is a collection of
storage devices with smaller costlier
devices at the and faster devices at the
top and slower cheaper and much larger
devices at the at the bottom and then at
each level in this hierarchy a the
device at level K serves as a cache
holds a subset of the blocks of that are
contained in the device at the lower
level at level K plus-1
now recall the general idea of caching
so we have a memory it's an array of
bytes and it's it's we we break it up
arbitrarily into a collection of blocks
and these this memory is larger slower
and cheaper and so it's and it's much
larger than than a cache which is
smaller faster and more expensive and
which holds and which holds a subset of
the blocks that are contained in the
main memory and then blocks are copied
back and forth between the cache in the
memory in these block size transfer
units so for example if our program
requests a word that's in contained in
block number 4 it asks the cache to to
sent to return the word that's contained
in block 4 the cache looks and it's at
the blocks that it's the subset of the
blocks that it's stored discovers that
block 4 is not there so it asks the main
memory to send it block 4 which it does
and and then when it when that block
arrives at the cache the cache stores it
but potentially overwriting some
existing block similarly if if our
program asks for a data word if that's
contained within block 10 the cache
looks sees that it doesn't have that
block so it requests that block for
memory which copies it into the cache
which overwrites an existing block now
subsequently if if our program asks for
a request or if our program references a
word that's contained in block 10 for
example then the cache then we have a
hit and the cache can return that block
immediately without going through the
expensive operation of contacting memory
and fetching that that block from memory
now there's a very important class of of
caches these so called cache memories
which are contained in the CPU chip
itself and are managed completely by
Hardware and they're implemented using
fast SRAM memories and the idea for this
cache which is is right next to the
register file is to hold frequently
access blocks or blocks from main memory
that are accessed frequently okay so
hopefully because of the principle of
locality most of our requests for data
will actually be served out of this
cache memory and a few cycles rather
than in this that rather than from this
slow main memory now cache memories are
managed completely in Hardware so this
means that the heart there's there has
to be Hardware logic that knows how to
look for blocks in the cache and
determine whether or not a particular
block is contained there so cache
memories are have to be organized in a
very kind of strict simple way so that
the logic the lookup logic can be pretty
simple so this is very all cache
memories are organized within the
following way you can think of that you
can think of the cache as an array of s
equals 2 to the S sets ok
each set consists of e to the to e lines
where each line consists of a block of B
it equals 2 to the B bytes of data a
valid bit which indicates whether these
these data bits are actually that the
bits and the data block are actually
meaningful right it's possible they
could just be random bits like you know
when you first turn on the machine
there's nothing in the cache but those
bits will have values right that they'll
lead to be ones or zeros but they won't
actually correspond to data okay so the
valid bit tells us if these if these be
bytes actually mean anything and then
there's some additional bits called the
tag bits which will help us search for
blocks which I'll show you in a minute
now when we talk about our cache size
we're referring to the number of data
bytes that are contained in blocks and
so each cache has there's s sets there's
e e blocks per set and there's B bytes
per block ok so the total cache size C
is s times e times B ok now so there's a
lot of terms to sort of keep straight
and it's very easy to get to confuse the
difference between lines and blocks and
lines and sets okay so we'll go through
some examples and hopefully these will
see these will start to make more sense
now let's look at in general how we how
the cache Hardware implements a read so
when our program accesses when our
program executes an instruction that
references some word in memory the the
CPU sends that address to the cache and
asks and it asks the cache to return the
word
the word at that address so the cash
takes that address this would be a
64-bit address in case of x86 64 and it
it divides the address into a number of
of regions which are which are
determined by the organization of the
cache okay they're determined by those
parameters s sets the s the number of
sets a the number of lines per set and B
the size of each data block so the low
order bits there are B low order bits
which determine the offset in the block
that that word starts at okay the next s
fits are treated as an unsigned integer
which serves as an index into the array
of sets okay remember we just think of
these as think of this cache as an array
of set the set index bits provide the
index into the into this array of sets
and then all of the remaining bits all
of the remaining T bits constitute what
we call a tag which will help us when we
do our search so the cache logic takes
this address and it first extracts the
the set index and uses that to as an
index into this array to identify the
set that if this block is in the set I'm
sorry if the data word if the block that
contains the data word at this address
is in the cache it's going to be in the
set denoted by the the set index okay
so first it identifies which index to
look in
and then it checks the tag it checks all
of the lines in that set to see if
there's any any of those lines have a
matching tag that a tag that matches the
the T the tag bits and the address okay
and if and it checks to see if the valid
bit is turned on so if those two
conditions holds if there's a line
anywhere in the set as of where the
valid bit is is is one and there's a
matching tag then we have a hit okay
then the block that we're looking for is
contained in this set okay if we once we
determine that with that we've we've
identified the block then the cache uses
that the low-order B bits to determine
where that where the data we're
interested in begins okay within that
block all right let's look at a more
specific example for a the simplest kind
of cache which is when e equals one when
there's only one line per set okay so a
equal one one line per set this kind of
cache is called a direct mapped cache so
here we have s sets each set consists of
a single line and now suppose our
program references the data item and a
particular address the CPU sense that
address to the cache the cache takes
that address breaks it up into these
into these three fields in the in for
this particular address the the block
offset is four and the set index is one
and then there's some tag bits which
we'll just denote with with is a color
pink so the cache extracts the set index
which is one and then it uses that as as
the index into the set
and then it can just it just ignores all
the other the sets if the block we're
looking for is is in the cache it's
going to be in this inset number one
then it does the comparison of the tag
bits and the valid bits and assume that
they assume that valid bits on and that
it matches then it looks at the block
offset which is four and which tells it
that the the four by four by ten suppose
that that's what the instruction was was
referencing the four byte in begins that
offset for so now the cache takes takes
this int and it sends it back to the to
the CPU which puts it in the register
okay if the tag doesn't match then the
old-line if the tag doesn't match then
there's a miss and in that case the
cache has to fetch the block the
corresponding block from memory and then
overwrite this block in the line and
then it can serve then it can fetch it
can get the word out of out of the block
and send it back to the processor okay
now let me ask you a question just to
see if kind of check to see if you're
following along with this so if there's
a Miss and the cache has two requests
the block for memory
fetch it from memory and then overwrite
the the block in the current line does
it also have to change the tag bits or
do those stay the same so does the do
the tag bits that were in this line get
overwritten with a different value or is
it the same same different
say different now why would it be
different
we haven't changed yes I'm sorry
oh it it almost certainly has different
data but does it have a different
address
exactly it missed it missed because the
tag it missed because the tag didn't
match
if the valid bit was false and the tag
match then then that would also be a
miss oh then you wouldn't okay that's
right that's okay good good good okay
great
all right let me do a little let me do a
really simple specific example of a how
direct map cache works I want you to
understand in real detail how this would
work but I also want to make a point for
about the weakness of direct mapped
cache --is and why why you would want to
have more than one line per set okay so
we this is a really simple our met we
have our memory system consists of 16
bytes ok so it's not a very useful
system with 4 bit addresses and and it's
broken up into blocks of 2 bytes each
our cache consists of 4 sets with one
block per set
now our 4 by our fort bit addresses
because be equal to that's 2 to the 1 we
only need 1 block offset bit right
there's only 2 bytes in a block so the
byte we're looking for is either at 0 or
1 okay because we have 4 sets we need to
set off set index bits and then the
remaining bits are always tag bits in
this case there's just one tag bed all
right now let's let's suppose that our
program executes instructions that
reference the following memory address
is 0 1 7 8 and 0 and these references
are reads that they're reading one byte
per read okay
like I said this is a really simple
system
so let's look at what happens now we
start out our tag our initially our our
cache is empty valid bits are all set to
zero and now the cache receives the
request for the byte that's at address 0
so it extracts the set index bits which
in this case are 0 0 so these so it's
going to look in set 0 for and in this
case since valid is 0 it's just it's
it's a Miss ok so it fetches that block
from memory sticks the block so this
memory this is the DS it this is using
array notation for memory so this is
like the the bytes that extend from
offset 0 to offset 1 inclusive in memory
the tag bit is 0 and the valid bit is 1
ok now the next the next address that
comes by is for address 1 well that's a
hit right because we that block the
block that contains the byte at address
1 is already in the cache the tag and
the tags match okay so we're good that's
a hit you now we get address 7 so the
cache extracts the set index bits which
in this case are 1 1 or 4 or 3 rather
looks in set 3 there's no valid bit so
that's a Miss and it loads the the data
from memory
that spans bytes 6 & 7 in this case the
the tag bit is 0 okay so we record that
we record that in our metadata okay the
next reference that comes by is 8 now 8
has a set index of 0 0 0 but that's
currently occupied by
block zero one and we can tell that
because address eight has a tag of one
and the the existing block of the block
at the earlier address at address zero
has a tag of zero so that's a miss so
now we have to go fetch the block
containing byte number eight into memory
so now we have bytes eight and nine and
we in our new tag bed okay now the next
instruction is for byte 0 and we just we
just replaced we had that it we had that
in our cache and we just replaced it so
so it's another miss so that's
unfortunate and it's the only reason we
missed it is because we've got just one
line per set right so we were forced to
overwrite that that block containing
bytes the block zero one when we when we
missed on on block eight nine okay so
this and you see there's plenty of room
in our cache we've still got we've got
two two lines that we haven't even
access right so we've our cache is
plenty big but just because of the sort
of the low associativity of our cache
and the the sort of the pattern the
access pattern that we were presented
with we've got a Miss that really was
kind of unnecessary so oh yeah sorry
six so when we referenced when we
referenced a seven it's actually the
it's at offset one in that block six
seven okay since our blocks are two
bytes they'll always start on an even
multiple
any other questions okay so this so this
sort of is the reason why you have
caches have higher associativity higher
values of e so let's look at and and so
for for values of e greater for values
of e greater than greater than 1 we
refer to them as a way so she set
associative caches so here e equals 2 so
it's a 2-way it's 2-way associative so
let's let's suppose we have a 2-way a
2-way associative cache so here we have
we have our array of sets and now each
set contains two lines ok instead of one
line and suppose we're presented with an
address with the following form we're
looking for the word that begins at an
off set of four inside our block at
within set number one okay so the cache
expects tracts that set index so this is
set 0 this is set 1 this is set to
throws away all the other sets and now
in parallel it searches it searches the
tags it searches for a matching tag in
both of these both of these lines and
ant a valid bit so if we get a matching
tag and a valid bit true then we've got
a a then we've got a hit
now that yes yes
oh it's a very good question so there's
there's hardware logic that does that
compare and it's and that's the reason
that as as the number of as the
associativity goes up that logic gets
more and more expensive okay it's like
something like you're kind of doing some
kind of tree search and so that actually
is the limit that's why I mean because
in general right that if you take this
to the limit there's just one set with
there's just it's we call that a fully
associative cache so there's just one
set and now any block a block can go
anywhere right there's no constraints
now where you place a block but the
because of the complexity of that that
fully associative search those are very
rare in fact you we do see we'll see
fully associative caches caches but
their software caches okay so in
software and so the the complexity the
hardware and sort of doesn't doesn't
doesn't it it's not worth it's not worth
the complexity of the hardware for the
penalty of having a lower associativity
okay but there are some systems later on
when we study virtual memory the in a
virtual memory system the DRAM serves as
a cache for data stored on the disk and
as we saw last time the penalty for a
Miss if you have a cache on DRAM and you
miss and you have to go to disk the
penalty is huge for that and so because
of that it's worth it's worthwhile
having very complex searches search
algorithms in particular in a virtual
memory system that the DRAM is
implements a fully associative cache
where blocks from disk can go anywhere
we'll get into that later when we look
in in virtual memory but you're right
you'll see in real systems nowadays that
the number goes up right because feature
sizes are going down and designers can
afford to implement more expensive
hardware but the the largest
associativity are
Intel systems that I know of is 16-way
associative l3 caches and then the
others are eight ways so she tips so
that's sort of the order of magnitude
that's state of the art right now okay
so then once we've identified a match we
use the set offset bits in this case
we're accessing a short in so four is
the offset within the block of this the
two byte short int which then we can
return to the processor alright so let's
do that same simulation that we did
before but this time with a two way
associative cache now memory system is
the same but now instead of one set we
have two sets and I mean I'm sorry
instead of four sets we have two sets so
the cache this is the same sized cache
but we're just going to organize it
differently okay instead of one way
instead of a direct mapped cache with
four lines containing four lines one
line per set we're going to implement a
2-way associative cache where we have
two sets with two lines per set okay so
each case there's just four there's four
total lines question
like oh so that that comes in with the
request somehow and I actually don't
know the details of that it may I guess
there so it could ask for just there
could just be a default sighs maybe it's
always it's always a 64-byte word and
then the processor extracts that the
current bits I actually don't know the
details of that but it either comes in
on the request or or there's a standard
there's a standard size that the
processor then parses out we'll just
assume that the cache knows the what
size to return yes how do you decide
which block to replace that's that's a
really good question so there's a lot of
different algorithms the most the most
common algorithm or a common algorithm
is least recently used so by locality
you you want to keep the you want to
keep blocks in the cache that are being
used a lot and so if a block isn't
referenced for a long time by the
principle of locality by sort of the
inverse locality principle it's it's
likely not to be addressed referenced in
the near future so so that's one that's
one algorithm that you just keep track
of and and I'm not showing there needs
to be additional bits in the line to
sort of keep like sort of virtual
timestamps that but that's that's a
that's sort of the general way you do it
just try to keep the things that are the
blocks that are being accessed the most
frequently most recently yes
okay the question is what determines the
block size that's determined by the
design of the memory system so that's a
that's that's a fixed parameter of the
memory system so when the Intel
designers decided to put cache memories
on their processors they decided that
the block size would be 64 bytes sorry
so the block size comes the block size
comes first then then you determine how
big you want your cache to be okay and
then and you determine the associativity
okay and then once you've determined the
associativity and you know how big your
cache is then that determines the number
of sets okay
so basically all of those the
the the number of lines and the cat and
the capacity the number of lines per set
is sort of a fixed high-level parameter
design parameter the size of the cache
is a is a is a high-level design
parameter and then the number of sets
then is induced from the from that okay
yes
ah that that's yeah how does so that's
that's the replacement policy how does
it so the question is how does it when
there's multiple lines in a set how does
it determine which to over overwrite and
that was what that was the previous
question probably maybe I should have
repeated it so you try to pick a line
that that was least recently used so
lines lines that haven't been accessed
recently are good candidates for
replacement because because of the sort
of inverse locality principle right that
they haven't been inverse referenced
recently chances are they won't be
referenced again it
oh yeah there's additional bits that I'm
not showing here that you have to so so
when you replace a line in the set if
that data is has changed then it has to
be written back to memory and that's
another bit I haven't shown yes
ah so the so yeah so this is a really
this is really tricky parameter writing
it's it's a it's a high level system
parameter that's that it goes on for
years
so the idea you want to have blocks in
order to exploit spatial locality right
think about if you're going to go to the
trouble of if you have a miss in cash
and you're going to go to the trouble of
going all the way to memory to get some
data you want to you want to amortize
the cost of fetching that data by
fetching more than one byte that that's
the motivation for blocks because by by
the by the principle of locality in
spatial locality in particular if you
reference a word inside of a block
chances are you're going to reference a
nearby word which will also be an
epilogue okay so blocks the whole
purpose of blocks is to exploit spatial
locality now if you make your block too
small then you don't you don't amortize
you don't get the same amortization
right you maybe get one you bring the
block in so there's a reference you get
a miss you bring the block in there's
another reference nearby you get a hit
because the blocks in memory but then
the next reference is in a different
block because your block sizes are too
small right so you kind of want to make
blocks big as big as possible but
without slowing the system down so if
you made your block size too big it
would just take too long to bring that
block in plus plus now your blocks that
your blocks are taking up bits in your
cache memory so now there's no room for
other blocks right so it's a really it's
a really tricky design problem right and
I if we're doing it taking an
architecture class then we would we
would sort of dive into the you know how
how architects make those design
decisions but in general that's what
it's kind of a balancing act right
were there any other questions yes
Oh the question is every time there's a
miss do you have to do you have to
select a victim line and override it
yeah I don't know of any caches that
that don't do that now we'll see when we
look at rights we'll see there's an
option of whether we're only looking at
reads right now but with rights that
question does come up okay and if if you
wait and in a couple of slides we'll go
over we'll go over that any other
questions okay so let's look at this
this two-way associative cache now
there's there's one block offset bit we
only have two sets so that we only need
one set index and then the remaining two
bits are tagged so let's go through our
trace so address zero has a set is in
set zero right here that's a Miss so we
load that into memory with the reference
to address one that's in set zero and
that's a hit because that that byte is
in is in our block the reference to
seven is a Miss that's in set one so we
load that and we were just picking
randomly pick one of these two over
right because they're there the cache is
empty the next reference is to address
number eight which is in set zero now
here's here's the difference between the
direct mapped cache and this 2-way
set-associative cache when we when we
reference address eight that block has
to the corresponding block has to go
into set 0 because of this zero set
index bit but we've got room now because
we are set to have room for two lines
instead of one so when we load that in
well if we have an available empty slot
we'll put it there we won't overwrite
anything right so if possible always try
to overwrite empty empty lines so now
we've got in this set we've got block 0
1 and block 8 9
so when we get our reference to block to
address zero whereas before with the
when we had a conflict miss in the
direct map cache now we can we can
satisfy that that request it hits in
memory and week and the cache can
satisfy it from from the cache instead
of going to memory okay so that makes
sense okay now what about rights so
there's multiple copies of the data
right we're sub setting as we move up
the hierarchy we're creating subsets of
the data in the caches so what do we do
if we do a write to a word within a
block that's currently in the cache okay
we have we have two options we can write
that block immediately to memory right
we're we've got a block that's like this
big and we're updating a little chunk of
it so we can we can either do the update
and then flush it to memory immediately
so that memory always mirrors the
contents of memory always mirror the
contents of the cache okay but that's
expensive right I mean you know memory
accesses are expensive the other so the
other option is what what's called write
back
so in this case when we write to a block
in the cache we don't we don't flush it
to memory until we elect that particular
line as a victim that's going to be
overwritten and only then only then when
we're just we sort of defer the writing
to memory until the last possible minute
we defer it until just before the cache
would overwrite that that data block
okay so that's called right back and for
right back you need to have some an
extra bit in the line that indicates
whether that that blocks been written to
so the algorithm is when when the cache
identifies a particular line to
overwrite it checks the dirty bit on
that
fine if it's set then it writes that
data to back to disk okay if the if the
data hasn't if that block hasn't been
written there's no point there's no need
to write it back because it's the same
it has the same value as the copy of the
block on disk okay now so what about so
that's a right here now what happens if
we have a right miss so we're doing a
write to memory and the word that we're
writing is is not contained in any block
that's in our cache so we have two
options we can do what's called write
allocate so we can treat it if if
there's a Miss we can do sort of the
symmetric thing that we did with it with
a hit which was create a new a newline
possibly overwriting an existing line
and then write in so we could so we
could create that cache enter that cache
line fetch it from memory and then do
and then do the do the right okay so
this is sort of symmetric to reads right
then so every right if it misses when
the write finishes the that block will
be in the cache and if we do a
subsequent read we get a hit okay so
that's the reason you might want to do
that the the other option is just to
don't allocate a an entry in the cache
don't allocate a new line just write
write the data directly to memory you
don't really need to understand the
distinction between these two things
different caches use different policies
for your own mental model a good model
to use is just to assume write back
write allocate so just assume that we
won't we won't copy the data to disk if
there's a hit we won't write it back to
disk until the last possible minute and
every time there's a write miss what
will create a new entry in the cache
okay so that's that I think that's sort
of the simplest model that and it's a
reason it's a reasonable model that you
can use regardless of the particular
cache implementation
now in a real system so far we've only
looked at we've only assumed that
there's a single cache but in a in real
systems there's multiple multiple caches
so modern core i7 Haswell architecture
from Intel contains multiple processor
cores so 4 is a typical number for like
desktop systems 8 8 to 12 is typical for
server class systems these processor
cores can each execute their own
independent instruction stream in
parallel and each processor core can
contains general-purpose registers which
that's level 0 in the cache and then two
different kinds of l1 caches the data
cache the l1d cache and the eye cache is
the L which is the instruction cache and
these are these are fairly small 32 K
bytes they're eight-way associative and
they can be accessed in a very small
number of cycles the next level of the
hierarchy is is the L is an l2 cache
which is still fairly small 256 K bytes
same associativity and it has a slightly
longer access time and and it's unified
in the sense that the l2 cache contains
both data and instructions ok so that's
all within a single core on the chip and
then also on the chip but external to
all the cores and shared by all the
cores is at l3 unified cache which is 8
megabytes and 16 Way associative with an
access time that's like 40 to 75 cycles
so if if there's a Miss in l1 then the
l1 sense or tries to sends a request to
l2 to try to try to find the data in l2
since l2 is a little bigger maybe maybe
the data hasn't been
flushed out of l2 yet if l2 can't find
it it sends a request to l3 to see if
they can find the data in l3 if l3 can't
find it then it gives up and it goes off
chip to to memory yes question
yes name memory is this that's it's the
DRAM built of DRAM chips it's it's
separate it's in a separate separate set
of chips on the motherboard connected by
those that IO bridge that we and the bus
various buses then that we talked about
last time and for all different for all
of these different caches that block
size is 64 bytes now there's a number of
different ways to I think about the
performance of caches my most most
common way is using a metric called the
Miss rate so what this is the fraction
of references that Miss so we're very so
I thought and it's it's 1 minus the hit
rate so typical for caches to work that
Miss rate has to be pretty low and and
fortunately because of locality these
miss rates are low another another
metric is the hit time so if if we do
have a hit in the cache how long does it
actually take to sort of look up the you
know do the lookup to determine that
there was a hit and then return the
value okay so for for l1 and in an Intel
system this is four clock cycles ten
clock cycles for l2 and then there's an
additional cost if so you always have to
pay the hit time right the hit time is
the best you can do but if you have a
Miss then it's you pay the hit time
because you have to do the search and
eventually you're going to have to
return the word back to the requester
but you then you have this additional
cost which you have to go which is going
to the the memory
ready to fetch the data okay so that
that Miss penalty that's what called
miss penalty is on the order of hundreds
of cycles for main memory but at other
levels of the hierarchy it can be huge
so the miss penalty if you if you have a
cache in main memory
that's caching blocks that are stored on
disk the the Miss penalty is enormous so
it's kind of interesting if you think
about it that performance is the
performance of these systems is very
sensitive to the miss rate much more
sensitive than you would think and in
fact 99% hit rate is twice as good as a
97 percent hit rate yes
yeah they hit so the question is does
the hit time include the time tax to
access the tag and yes so the hit time
is the time it takes to just to search
to determine if that item is is is in
the cache and then return it
yeah so the yeah so the the miss the
Miss penalty is the time it takes for
the cash to fetch the data from memory
so that's all the latency you know going
across the buses the time it takes the
memory to respond to the requests the
time it takes the data to flow back over
the buses back to the the cache so the
time for a Miss is going to be the hit
time plus the Miss penalty that clear
so I mean imagine suppose there's a hit
time of one cycle and a Miss penalty of
100 cycles that those are reasonable
numbers so the the average acts I asked
access time if you have 97 percent hits
it's the hit time plus the percentage of
misses times the Miss penalty so that's
four cycles for the average access time
but if we just increase the the hit rate
by two percent the average access time
drops by fifty percent a factor of two
all right so why why is this stuff
important why why should you care about
it so cash is that we as we've seen are
these these they're automatic they're
all built in hardware there's no part of
the sort of the visible instruction set
that lets you manipulate caches and your
assembly machine codons programs so that
it all happens behind the scenes
automatically in hardware but if you
know how kit if you know about the
existence of caches and you have this
general idea of how you can work how
they work then you can write code that's
cache friendly in the sense that your
code will will have a higher higher miss
rate than code that that isn't cache
friendly so the idea is to you want to
focus on making the common case go fast
don't spend your time on code that sort
of code that doesn't get execute very
much so look at look at the most
commonly called functions and then
within those functions look at the inner
loops of those functions because it's
the inner loops that are executing the
most right so you can as a first
approximation you can just ignore sort
of stuff if you have nested loops you
can ignore stuff that's going on in the
outer loops and just focus on the code
in the inner loop now what you want to
do is try to minimize the misses in the
inner loop okay so repeated references
to a variable is variables are good
especially if those are local variables
right so remember if you declare a local
variable and see the compiler can put
that in a register right if you're
referencing global variables maybe not
the compiler doesn't know what's going
on so it can't put that ref it can't put
the reference to that variable to see in
a register okay so repeated references
to local variables stored on the stack
are good because those will get turned
into register accesses you'll never go
to memory okay also stride one accesses
two arrays are good
and they're good because of the
existence of these blocks right so the
only way you'd know that stride one
references our good is if you knew that
caches have the 64-byte blocks okay so
the and stride one one reference will
have half the Miss rate as a stride to
reference because if you're doing stride
one references the first reference to a
word and a block will miss but then
subsequent references will hit right and
you'll hit if you're doing a stride one
reference you're going to hit every
every word in that block if your drive
if you're doing stride two references
you're only going to hit every other
word right so you'll only get you'll get
sort of half the so you'll missed at
twice the rate so
so basically the point I want to make to
you is that our understanding of caches
allow us to sort of quantify this this
qualitative notion of locality that we
developed the last time right the last
time we looked at we said if it's doing
stride one references that's good if
it's if we're doing if we're accessing
the same variable over and over that's
good but if we understand caches now we
can quantify it in terms of miss rate
all right so let's finish up the rest of
the class we're going to look at the
performance impact of caches on your
code okay and why why you need to why
you need to know about these things and
that the impact that they can have so
there's a very interesting function this
actually plotted on the cover of your
your text book that we call the memory
Mountain I learned about this from a
graduate student here at Carnegie Mellon
back in the 90s who developed this
notion made Tom Stricker
and what it is it's a the memory
Mountain plots a measure called read
through put or read bandwidth which is
the number of bytes read from memory so
if you have four if you have a loop and
you're scanning over a vector so you
have a vector of say say double words
and you're reading those elements from a
vector one after the other the read
throughput is the number of megabytes
per second that you can that you can
perform that task at and the memory
Mountain plots read throughput as a
function of the temporal and spatial
locality in that loop okay so in a sense
it's looking at a wide range of locality
options or characteristics in a program
and it's plotting the performance of
that memory system on that across that
range as a two-dimensional function so
in some ways the memory Mountain is a
kind of a fingerprint right every system
has its own unique memory Mountain that
we can measure right by writing a simple
program
and so the idea here is that to
construct the memory Mountain we write a
program called test
oh shoot
for some reason it's not okay all right
so when we when we when we build a
memory Mountain we're given a vector
that consists of a collection of double
words and then we write a loop that
reads those words that read some number
of words in this case
hmm
there we go so it reads it reads Elam's
number of elements right so we've got
each of these double word elements with
a stride of of stride okay so if we have
a stride of one I know that was kind of
redundant huh so if we have a stride of
one then we'll we'll have our loop wills
was sort of looped through and read
these elements until we've read Elam's
number of those elements okay and then
we'll do it again and then that warms up
the cache then we do it again and do
exactly the same thing so if we're doing
this with a stride of two then we would
be reading we would read this word zero
or LM - LM 4 and so on okay so well then
what all we're doing we're just for wide
range of strides and a wide range of
sizes we're scanning over this vector
and just recording how long it takes to
to do that read and then convert we
convert that into megabytes per second
and in order to I just wanted to show
you this this is we don't need we're not
going to go into detail about this but
this is actually how I generated the the
cover on the book and in order to in
order to use to exploit the parallelism
inside the intel processor like you
learned about last week there's there's
a lot of parallel functional units in
order to exploit those i i did 4x4 loop
unrolling so I'm actually doing sort of
four scans in parallel but the general
idea is just what I've showed you here
and this this 4x4 this 4x4 loop
unrolling is just an optimization but I
wanted to show it to you because it
actually it's the exact same principles
you learned about last week when
Professor Brian talked about
code optimization so what we do is we we
call this test function with these
various ranges of Elam's and stride and
then we measure the performance and we
get this beautiful picture this
beautiful function to me it's beautiful
I don't know does it look beautiful to
you so on the Z our z axis is plotting
read throughput in megabytes per second
ranging from 2000 megabytes per second
up to 16,000 megabytes per second this
this axis is measuring is stride so
going from stride 1 up to stride 12 and
this axis is so as we as we increase
stride we're decreasing the spatial
locality alright
and this axis is the size axis so we're
going from I think 16 K up to 128
megabytes so this is the number of
elements we're going to read each pass
through so as we as we increase the size
we're sort of decreasing the impact of
temporal locality because word as we
increase the size there's fewer and
fewer caches in our hierarchy can hold
all that data and so this so we've got
spatial locality decreasing in this
direction and temporal locality
decreasing in this direction so as a
programmer what you want to do you want
to be up here right good spatial
locality good temporal locality because
you can get like 14 gigabytes per second
measure agreed throughput you don't want
to be down here which is only about 100
megabytes per second where you're
reading out of memory right so the
difference between reading all of your
data from memory and reor reading it
from some part of the the caches is huge
it's enormous
ok so because you're 213 students you'll
be up here and all the students that
didn't take 213 they'll be down here and
I've actually had I've actually had
people several people write back to tell
me about their experiences you know in
internships and jobs after they left CMU
where they were given some code that
that was down here and they recognized
the locality issues and they got it
you know better up here or close at
least better
so this is this this picture this
so-called memory mountain has all kinds
of interesting features first of all
there's these what I call ridges of
temporal locality where these ridges see
these Ridge lines if you think of this
is like a mountain you see this
Ridgeline and you see this Ridgeline and
here's another Ridgeline and then here's
a here's another one these correspond to
different levels in the hierarchy so
this this top Ridgeline is where you're
reading directly out of l1 and it should
be perfectly flat and it's so fast that
we're getting like measurement jitter
performance jitter right but it's it's
and this little drop-off here is a
measurement artifact it it should it
shouldn't be there it should be it
should be flat and go all the way to the
wall back here and then here this this
ridge line is where we're accessing l2
this is where we're accessing l3 and and
here's what we're accessing mostly from
memory so you have these ridges of
temporal locality and then you have
these slopes of decreasing spatial
locality so you see the slope here as
work so as we're moving from the from
the top of the slope down to the bottom
we're decreasing our spatial locality so
we're getting less benefit for these
blocks that we're bringing in all right
so you can see the we're getting less
benefit out of the cost that we went
through of importing of fetching these
blocks and once the stride hits the
block size now every reference is
hitting a different block and so and
then it flattens out then you get you're
getting noes benefit from spatial
locality and similarly here is where
this this this slope is where we're
reading from l3 and and and it flattens
out always they always flatten out at
the at the block size which is a stride
these are double words right so it's
stride of eight is
64 bytes so once you exceed a stride of
eight then you're no longer you're
missing every time in it in a different
block there's this this interesting this
one puzzled me for a while
you might be wondering like how come
like over here is we increase the size
we can sort of we're sort of getting the
we're sort of as we increase the size
we're doing most of our references out
of caches that are lower in the cache
hierarchy okay but except when we're
doing stride one references you can see
all the way up to right at the end right
before it exceeds the size of l3 it's
flat okay and it's it's running at the
l2 rate alright so here's the l1 rate
and then it drops off and then it's
running at a constant l2 rate until the
data no longer fits in l3 so I think
what's going on here is that the the
hardware the cache the the cache the l2
cache hardware is recognizing or maybe
it's an l1 but some some some logic in
that in the cache system is recognizing
the stride one reference pattern right
because it sees all the addresses it's
rough it's recognizing that stride one
pattern and then it's aggressively
prefetching from l3 into l2 so that
those so it's fetching ahead of time
it's anticipating it's saying look I've
gotten five stride one references in a
row I'm going to go grab a whole bunch
of blocks and load them all up because
by the principle of spatial locality
those blocks those blocks are going to
be referenced in the near future so this
was really neat and this only happened
within the last couple years so the
Intel engineers are always hard at work
and maybe by the time the time we do the
next the next edition of the memory
Mountain those systems will recognize
stride 2 and you know other stride
- but from this data it appears that
it's only recognizing stride one ok so
you can real you we can improve the
spatial and temporal locality of our
programs in several different ways that
one way to improve the spatial locality
is to rearrange loops and I'll use
matrix multiplication as an example so
here's a sort of a simple matrix
multiplication in code where we're
multiplying a times B and adding it
we're taking what's in of the IJ element
of C and then to that we're adding the
sum the inner product of Rho I of a and
the row J a column J of B okay and then
so we're going through and for each IJ
in this matrix C we're computing an
inner product and then creating that sum
so we can actually turns out there's a
lot of different ways to do matrix
multiply and this is we can permute
these these loops in any of six
different possible permutations so this
is a permutation where it's I followed
by J followed by K but five other
possibilities are feasible and so we can
actually analyze those those different
permutations and predict which one will
have the best performance okay so what
we'll do is we'll look at the inner loop
and we'll look at the access pattern of
the inner loops and it's in the access
pattern on arrays C a and B
okay so let's look at the ijk
implementation that I just showed you so
as always we focus on the inner loop and
if you notice this inner loop is doing a
row wise access of column a and a column
wise access I'm sorry a row wise access
of array a and column wise access of a
row B so row wise of a column wise of B
we don't really care about C because
it's out it's not in the inner loop
okay so just ignore that so given our
assumption that we can hold in this case
we're assuming that we can hold for four
of these integer elements in a in one
block so the row wise access which has
good spatial locality will miss one
every four accesses okay the very first
reference will miss and then the next
three will hit and then the next
reference after that will hit a new
block okay so so one out of four
references to a will miss but because
the access pattern for B is column wise
every every act every reference to B
will miss okay so the average number of
misses per loop iteration is one point
two five okay the ji K version is
exactly the same pattern ki J is a
little different here we're doing row
wise access of B and a row wise access
of C so that's good right so now we've
got stride one accesses on both B and C
and the reference to a is outside of the
loop so we don't care about it so so
both B and C will miss one quarter of
the time okay so the total average
number of misses per loop iteration will
be 0.5 that's pretty good and I KJ has
the same similar behavior now J ki is
sort of the exact opposite j ki does
column wise access of a
and column-wise access of seaso right we
know that's a stinker right and and we
qualitative well you know it's bad and
we can compute that it will miss a one
time per loop iteration so that will be
two total of two misses per iteration
and kji has the same bad pattern okay so
if we look at all these permutations you
can see that ijk and ji k miss 1.25 have
1.25 mrs. K IJ has 0.5 misses and j ki
has two misses so clearly it looks like
ki J and its brethren are the best
option the only difference is that k k
IJ has this additional store so there
might be a question that is that going
to create is that going to slow things
down well it turns out in systems in any
kind storage systems rights are much
easier to deal with them reads can you
think about why that might be true
so writes you have a lot more
flexibility than you do with reads
I mean yes
that's exactly so you can you have
options you can do you can write back
defer you can defer writing until the
value the value that you're written is
actually used but when you read an item
you're stuck you can't do anything until
until you get that data so it turns out
that that rights don't really that this
additional store doesn't really hurt us
and so when we measure these on a modern
system you can see that that the Kate
kij which has the the fewest number of
misses has you see we're getting like
one miss what we're plotting here is
cycles per interloop iteration so each
each iteration is taking about one cycle
which is really good this i JK pattern
which is kind of the intermediate 1.2
misses that's sort of in between and the
JK I which has two misses per iteration
is the worst ok so what's interesting is
we could actually just by doing a little
bit of analysis simple analysis we could
actually predict what this what this
graph would look like okay in the last
last ten minutes of the class we're
going to look at how to improve temporal
locality now so what we did with with
when we rearranged our loops with in the
matrix multiplication what we were doing
was in improving our spatial locality
right but we didn't we didn't really do
anything to improve the temporal
locality to improve temporal locality
you have to use a technique called
blocking and this is important to
understand because you're going to need
it in your cache lab for one thing but
it's also a very general technique
anytime you need any time you're having
issues with temporal locality okay so
we're not going to go into too much
detail this code but what I did I
rewrote the matrix multiply so that it
operates you know a two-dimensional
matrix that you can really just think of
it as a contiguous array of bytes so I
just rewrote this code to operate on a
contiguous array one-dimensional array
and then I'm doing the indexing
explicitly here so here at CI times n
plus J this is an N by n matrix
so what I'm doing is I'm I'm accessing
the I'm computing where the I throw
starts and then I'm going to the J
column of that row and then accessing
that element all right so let's but it's
the same idea as before so let's look at
the Miss rate for this this is just our
original this is our original unblocked
matrix multiplied so what we're doing is
we're we're computing C 0 0 and we're
doing that by taking an inner product of
row 0 and column 0 oops
so if you look at the we're assuming
that the cache the cache blocks holds
eight doubles and that the matrix
elements are doubles then we're going to
miss one eighth of the time okay so in
the first iteration we're going to miss
the first iteration does n of these
things
and since we're missing n over eight of
the time what we're missing one block
for every eight eight references for
each for the first iteration we're going
to miss n over eight and since there's n
for each element for each block I'm
sorry and then oh so this is the number
of blocks and the number of misses and
then we have n elements so that the
total number of misses is nine over n
divided by eight misses for the first
iteration okay
the second iteration will have the same
number of misses because of our
assumptions about the the size of this
array so this these rows are way too big
to fit in the cache so we never get any
we don't get any temporal locality okay
so the total number of misses is nine n
over eight times the number of elements
that we're updating which is N squared
okay so our total misses is nine over 8
times n cubed
now let's rewrite the code to use
blocking and so you can look at this
code later but it's much simpler just
just to look at it pictorially so what
what we're doing instead of updating one
element at a time we're updating a sub
block a B by B sub block and we're doing
that just totally analogously to when
our original case where B equal 1 this
this B by B sub block and C is computed
by taking an inner product of the sub
blocks of a set of sub blocks in an a
with a set of sub blocks in B and for
each one of those we're doing a little
mini matrix multiplication so we're
taking we're taking this sub block times
this sub block plus the second sub block
of a times the second sub block of of B
plus the third sub block of a times the
third sub block of B and so on okay so
we're doing the same inner product
operation but instead of scalars we're
doing it with these little sub these
little tiny matrices ok all right so
let's look at let's look at what happens
to the Miss rate when we do this so
there's there's n over B blocks in in
any row or column and since there's B
squared items in each block B times B
there's B squared over 8 misses for each
block okay
and so then and then since there's
there's n over B blocks in each matrix
and there's two matrices there's two to
n over B times B squared over 8 misses
for this first iteration so that that
works out to be an NB divided by 4 and
the second iteration has the same as the
same miss sort of same miss rate so the
total number of misses is the number of
the number of misses for each iteration
x times the number of elements in C that
we're updating okay which is n over B
squared so that all works out too it's
still in its n cube divided by 4 B so in
our first case with no blocking although
that the number of misses is
asymptotically the same but there's this
pretty this big difference in the
constant factor so for no blocking it's
9 over 8 for blocking it's 1 over 4b
we're now we can we can just sort of
drive that down by by increasing the
block size so this gives us some some
control but we still we have we can't
make the block the blocks too big
because we need to fit three blocks in
cache at any one point in time ok so the
reason this is a dramatic difference
right and the reason for this is that by
doing the blocking we're sort of
exploiting once we load a block into
memory we're sort of reusing its items
over and over again so we're exploiting
more temporal locality and matrix
multiplication has this into this
implicit locality because the
computation is order n cubed but the
size of the data is n squared right so
so we must be reusing some data items
right the problem with our scalar
approach is that we we were when we were
reusing them they weren't in the cache
ok
all right so the point that I wanted to
make with you is that cache memories
although they're they're sort of
built-in automatic hardware storage
devices and you can't really control
them if you know about them you can take
advantage of your knowledge and exploit
exploit them and make your code run
faster okay and the way you do this is
like I said focus on the inner loops do
is try to do try to do accesses that our
stride one and try to maximize to to
maximize spatial locality and try to
maximize temporal locality by reusing
local variables which can then be put
into registers okay so that's it for
today good luck with your attack lab if
you haven't finished it and don't forget
to get started on cache lab this weekend