so we've now gotten through all the lectures on machine code
and we're starting to talk about...
okay now that you know this stuff what can you do with it
and this lecture is along the lines of that
this is sort of what you are now empowered to do now that
you can look at an understand machine code
this material is a little this actually there's a whole chapter
of the book chapter five on performance optimization
and we're only going to do one lecture on it and we don't have any labs
unfortunately that really get you to push your limits on this which is too bad
because it's a very interesting topic and one I think you'd find yourself well equipped for
there are typically a few small exam problems that are sort of based on some of the material here
you'll find in old exams
but really the idea is how can I make programs run fast
given that I I sort of know what algorithm I'm using
and I've perhaps gotten a program that runs
how can I make it run faster and one of the the themes of it
is you can sort of do this in layers you can sort of first of all do the stuff to avoid
a sort of
things that make programs run slow across a wide variety of machines  and just make your
and I would describe it as making your code more compiler friendly
and we'll talk about what that means
and you have to have some understanding and appreciation for what compilers are good
at and what they're not good at to be able to do that
and I describe these is the kind of things that you should just be in the habit of
when you write programs writing this code that I'll describe is compiler friendly
and then the next level is okay given that I've sort of taken away
the things that really shouldn't have been there in the first place
now how can I make my programs run faster
in particular how can I adapt it to the capabilities of the the types of machines
that this program is going to run on
and that can again go from ones that will generally make programs run fast
across a wide variety of machines to ones that become very specific and very specific
is a risky thing because even in the world of  say x86 machines
there's quite a variety of them that are available at any given point in time
and they evolve over time as well
so you can make a program run really fast on one particular model of one x86 processor
but it might not that if you're trying too hard
you'll find your effort is sort of wasted when you move it to another
on the other hand these general ideas I'm going to describe actually work across quite a range of machines
so and I'll talk about that more as we go along
so it used to be in the bad old days that
if you wanted a program to run fast you had to write an assembly code
and that's just plain not true anymore and if anyone tells you it's true
it's because they're full of it it's just not true
unless except for the exceptional case where you're running on a very small resource constrained machine
such as a very small underpowered embedded system
so let's just assume that we're going to use a compiler
and we'll assume for this course we're going to use GCC because it's generally available
it's not actually the best compiler out there Intel makes a compiler that costs money to license and stuff
but it's it really can do some amazing things and other compilers exist
but GCC is sort of a a good enough compiler for most people
but there's some features of some things that sort of puzzle compilers that they don't really understand
compilers don't really understand for example that the numbers you're using
when you say it's an INT might actually range over a much smaller set of values
and they have a very hard time understanding memory referencing patterns
and the effect of procedure calls
and so in general what happens with the compiler is it
has a whole sort of cookbook of optimization strategies
and some recipes for how to try out different strategies and apply them
but in general if it ever feels like this code is something that
it doesn't feel confident about being able to make certain transformations
that it just won't it will keep things sort of a more direct implementation of exactly what you described
and we'll show examples of that as we go along
so the thing about it optimizing compilers it always has a fallback position which is to not optimize
and sometimes that will get in trouble if you want your program to run faster
and the compiler just in its own conservative white decides not to do that optimization
and one of the tricks that you'll find is pretty useful
now that you can read assembly code is you run the compiler
you see what optimizations it does
and if it doesn't make something that you expect it to be able to do you go back and figure it out
so it's very common by the way to rewrite your program in the same language
and sort of tune it in and up to make it run faster to make it more compiler friendly
that's there's nothing wrong with that
as long as you don't then just totally obliterate the program and make it totally illegible
so let's just describe some sort of general optimizations
and you've actually seen versions of this in some of the assembly code we've already looked at
oh and I'll use mostly sort of examples from multi-dimensional arrays
because those are actually fairly easy optimization type of tasks
but these applied to other types of program as well
so you saw before when we described how to do array indexing in multi-dimensional arrays
that the old style of code was if you had a a variable sized array
it was up to you the programmer to write the formula
of how you convert row I column J into a position in a one-dimensional array
so remember it's just the number of columns times the row number plus the column numbers standard one
so that would give this would be pretty typical code
then it would give you a notation like this
if you wanted to set one row in array a to the values in a one dimensional row of B
this is a code you'd write
and the main observation is within this loop
the only variable that's changing is J
and so from the array perspective your this computation n* i··
if it gets repeated over and over again within this loop
then you're just wasting it's a wasted effort
so you can do what's called code motion
which is to pre compute the value of n*i outside of the loop
and then use it over and over again inside and compilers will generally do this
when they can detect for example that it's a array access code and it has this technique
it will generally do optimizations like this
if you set say an optimization level of 1 or higher to GCC
and we can see this in fact this is this code that I ran it through GCC using optimization 1
and you see as this read instruction shows it boosted this multiplication outside of the loop
and it's a little as if you actually this code does even more
it turns the code into something that looks more like a pointer code
accessing array a and stepping through that element by element  of the array
another one and we've seen this already that when
GCC turns a multiplication or a division by shifting and adding an operations like that
multiplication or division by constants
we've seen examples of that and a similar one would happen if
if we took that program I showed before  and applied it to every row
so we want to set for array a we wanted to set every one of its rows to the value of the one dimensional array B
then again if we we took that code we boosted the end times I in there
so now the inner loop is good but you realize that this multiplication isn't necessary either
because what we're doing from I equals 0 to I equals 1 to I equals 2 is
is we're just increasing the parameter ni by we're adding m to it
so we can and that's called a reduction in strength we've taken a multiplication and turned it into addition
because there's some predictable pattern of how this variable ni is going to be updated
another example and again array indexing is a good example for optimizations
imagine we had a image that we represent as a two-dimensional array of pixel values
and we want to do something that's what a filtering operation
where we want to take the sum of the four neighbors of a given pixel north south east and west
and average those together or sum them together
and so the natural way you'd write this and see is to say I want usually i
n images you count from the top down and so
you'd say this is the the pixel above
this is the pixel below this is the pixel to the left and this is the pixel to the right
and if you do this in and just compile it straight through
unfortunately it appears as if there's three different multiplications by n
i-1, i+1 and i
and if the compiler isn't too clever it won't realize that these are related to each other
and it will issue three different multiply operations just to do this one pixel thing
whereas if I'm a little more clever
and this is one where I manually rewrote the code
so the compiler would pick it up
I'd say well if I on so I and J is I times n plus J
and I can get the the pixel above the pixel below by shifting that
off setting that by a value of M
and then it will issue the code this will compile with the code with just one multiply
and in general by the way multiply used to be a very expensive instruction
nowadays is enough hardware resources that it takes about three clock cycles so it's not a huge deal
but anytime you can take three multiplies and use just one instead that's generally a good idea
question
so the question is what if you're trying to optimize for space
and there are a lot of optimizations that will
make your code be bigger at the expense of in order to go faster right
this one though I'd argue this is actually shorter code right
and just look at the number of instructions so
and usually so code you know that used to be a bigger concern when memory was sort of
you know back the original IBM PC had 640 kilobytes of memory so
in its maximum configuration and that was a big deal to actually buy it that much
so you know back then that was a big deal memory but nowadays memory
the size of the program is usually a pretty small fraction of what you're dealing with overall
but it's a valid question
okay so that just shows you an example and in general compilers are pretty good at doing
those low-level optimizations like that if you write the code in a way that's reasonable
but there's some other ones that the compiler and even a the fanciest compiler you can buy
might not be able to figure it out
and so I like to illustrate this with when the first term we ever taught 2:13
I was looking at some lab a code
that some of the students wrote and I was horrified about this code
and I showed it to the TAS and none of them figured out what was wrong
and I've shown it to many other highly-trained C programmers professionals
they go looks ok to me
so let's figure out what's why I was horrified by this code
so the idea of this code is supposed to be pretty straightforward there's a string s
and I want to convert that string all the characters in it to lowercase
so I'm just going to read through the string and for each string position
test that character and if it's somewhere between upper case a and upper case Z
then I'm going to shift it to being between lowercase a and lowercase Z otherwise I will change it
so pretty straightforward
but if you run this you see that
if you go up to half a million characters
which might sound like a lot but it takes 240 or so so  so four minutes to run this code
and you go well that's a pretty big string
it's really not a big string you should be able to do lowercase conversion of a string
and a lot less than four seconds
and you also notice this growth is nonlinear it's quadratic
it's growing as the square of the string length so this is not good
and unfortunately it's the kind and by the way this is one of the that is very easy surprisingly easy
to have programs that have some hidden performance bug
that makes them run quadratic and you run test
and you test for strings of 10,000 or less
and it doesn't look like a big deal because the run time is insignificant so
but then all of a sudden it hits a really bad case
so this is a there's something wrong here
so what's so bad about this program well
the key is I went in a test like this of calling sterlin
so the way it's determining whether it's reached the end of the string
is by calling sterling to figure out how long the string is
and the now and remember if we do the conversion of a four loop
into a go to form like you've seen there's various ways to convert it
but all of them the test gets built into the loop
so the main feature of that is this call to sterling will happen every time you go through the loop
and people overlook that fact
when you look at the different parts of a four loop
the initialization only gets executed once
but both the tests and the update get incremented  get applied every time you run through the loop
so if that's getting called as many times as there are characters in the loop  in the string right
and now how does sterling work remember and see the only way you know how long a string is
is to step through the whole thing and find the null character at the end
so sterlin itself is a linear time operation in the string
and you're doing that and so you're doing n calls to a function that takes time n
if the string is getting shorter as you go but not very fast so
basically that's quadratic performance
and that explains why you get that runtime
so in particular if I just make the following little change
I introduce a local variable called Glen
and I pre compute sterlin
because the string isn't the length of the string isn't changing I'm just changing the characters
in this string um then so the the program will do the same thing
but now the runtime is so short it doesn't even show up
it's it's maybe a second to do a million characters it's just not a big deal at all
as it should be it's just running through
and so that's just an example one of many that I've seen in my career where
something that that seems almost insignificant turns out to be a serious performance problem
so why couldn't a compiler figure this out
why couldn't a smart compiler
look at the original code
and say look you know this is what the programmer wrote
but I know a better way to do it I'll pre compute sterlin in advance
well there's a couple reasons one is actually if you look at the code for strlen
you see that it's actually modifying the string
and strlen at this I mean the the code here is modifying the string and we're calling sterling on it
so you'd have to be pretty careful to do the analysis the compiler would to figure out that
even though the string is changing
the result you're going to get from sterling is not going to change
so that's a one reason
and the second is well and how do how does the can the compiler be sure which version of sterling
is actually going to get used
you remember and see each of the files gets compiled separately
and only afterwards does it all get brought together  in the linking phase
and some of that even happens after the program gets started
so even though there's a standard strlen function
it's not necessarily the case that that's the one that will actually get used in the final program
so the compiler really can't be sure of that
in particular imagine I provided a sort of customized sterlin function like this
that is keeping track of the sum of the lengths of all the strings that it's been called on
or some other side effect like that that
well that that program would produce a very different result than if
if I whether or not I make the optimization
so the compiler has to assume that
sterling is just a black box that does whatever it does
and can't make any assumptions about what how
what side effects it might have and so forth
so it won't make that optimization on any machine  even with the best compiler
so that's just an example that and you can tell that I've gotten kind of sensitized to this
so that I spot these but a lot of people don't
um so let's look at this
let's see
oh this is another bad example a bad coding example
of imagine I want to compute for a two-dimensional array a  and a one-dimensional array B
I want to make B be B sub I be the sum of of all the elements in row I of  a
so again this is a fairly obvious kind of way to write this program that you say
say well B I cook 0 and I'm going to just accumulate it I'll step through the row and accumulate all the values
and of course we know now we could improve this by moving i*n
out and so forth I'm not trying to illustrate that
but what you'll see in the program this is in the inner loop
and we've looked briefly at some floating-point instructions
and remember that the main feature of them is
the move instructions look like the move ones you're familiar with
except when we we put floating-point data in one of these %xmm registers
so the main thing you see here is it's reading from memory
it's adding something to it and then it's writing back to memory
and what that memory location corresponds to B of i
so what it means is every time through this loop it's having to do a memory read and a memory write  of B
in addition to the memory read of a
even though presumably B of AI is the same of value that you just updated it to
well in the previous execution of this loop right
so why do you have to why do you read it why do you write it out
and then read it back in increment it and then again copy it back out
why does it have to go keep jumping back and forth between memory and registers  over and over again
well the reason is because in C you can't be sure
that there isn't what's known as aliasing and I'm demonstrating it here
imagine if row B is just declared to be that
okay so imagine and you can do this and see this is legal C code
you can make one memory data structure overlay another data structure
that's referred to as aliasing when too soon as separate parts of
the program are referring to the same locations in memory
and the C compiler has no way of knowing
whether there's a lot of work and optimizing compilers to detect aliasing possibilities
but in general as to assume aliasing might happen
so imagine this aliasing happened so that array B can corresponds then to this row of array a
well then of course its initial value is 4, 8, 16
but if you trace through what this code will do
it has a sort of odd behavior that is probably not useful for anything
but it just demonstrates that what will happen is as this as B gets updated
it's effectively changing a and it's changing then what's being read during the summation
and so this is a real possibility in C
and so the compiler when it's given code like this
it has to assume that the these two memory locations might court overlap each other
so that's why it's carefully writing it out and then reading it back in over and over again
and so if I just rewrite this code by introducing again a local variable
and accumulating in that local variable
and then only at the end do I sign that to B sub
I then you'll see this exact same loop all of a sudden gets a lot simpler
it's just a read floating point read an ad to do that
and we'll see in fact the memory is actually one of the limiting perform performance limiters in a program
so this is won't be a significantly faster
and again that's something that you as a programmer would hardly think is a big deal
but the C compiler can't do that in general
because it can't determine in advance what possible aliasing there can be
so as is these two examples say sort of get in the habit of introducing local variables  and using them
and it's your way of telling the compiler don't call the same function over and over again
don't read and write the same memory location over and over again
just hold it in a temporary one
and then it will automatically allocate a register and store it in that register and everything will be good
okay so that's sort of the the kind of what we call optimization blockers the kind of things that
you as a programmer can make a difference on
and the main blockers are memory referencing aliasing and function calls
and sort of understanding what might happen in that function call
and so now what we're going to do is transition
question equals three of this seem to be I think these two makes a distinction
oh no no this is Alan C code
I'm sure this is known C code because it ran
so this is initializing calling it an array B remember these are in stars these aren't two-dimensional arrays right
so this is saying a is now a
think of it as a linear array of four elements of nine elements
and a plus three is just to go in three
so this is it is declaring B is not a pointer it's an array
but remember with an array you can refuse that the name of that array
as a reference to a pointer a readable reference not a writable reference right
[student speaking]
right for this exact code well I'll double check it
this design of the seafront language use null terminated strange instead of like hot dogs ice cream
so the question is why to see use null terminated strings
and it it does and it might be a bad decision for multiple reasons right but
I think in general think of C was somebody who had or a couple people
who had been writing a lot of assembly code and wanted to lift up that level
so they weren't writing the same stuff over and over again
but not thinking in terms of how can I be the most abstract possible
so they were trying to provide sort of a minimum layer on top of machine level programming
that would let them write code that could run from one machine to another
so in everything they do they sort of use the most simple representation and don't assume any kind of
there's no array you know most languages would have array bounds checking
and array would be a data structure that would include its size you know range of values and stuff and
see just doesn't so everything about see is suit at the minimum
and you know it's been around for a 40 or something year so
[student speaking]
no Pascal does not proceed see no as simply not true
Pascal was created as a language for teaching by this phone and Nick was very
and it was very much an instructional language
so it was really designed to help students who needed help
and C was designed by professional programmers
to let them write their code and not get in their way
so they're very different theory between the two languages right
yes what's that
I'm sorry F oh yes that's a mistake there
I'll double-check this or people could check it I'm pretty sure this code is okay though
if not you can certainly say double star B equals a plus three and that would work right
question
you think what
you think this is 28 yeah well I'm not going to try and execute it here
but let's check it you and I will check this code out
and we'll fix it if it needs to be fixed okay thanks for pointing it out
yeah
no that doesn't make any difference at all in this code
no know where it's allocated makes no difference at all here
so I'll check that might have to be double star B equals a plus 3
but I this was a while ago that I wrote this code Oh double-check  it number
ok so anyway sets the sort of end of the story for for simple
simple Optima and they are simple optimizations it's just you have to get in the habit of doing it
ok now what we're going to do is go a little bit fancier than this
and as I said this becomes somewhat more system dependent but
pretty much nowadays all processors are have similar implementation
they all do what's known as out of order execution
except for the most primitive micro controllers
and so this is a the kind of optimization oh sure
you'll find well this general approach will work across quite a variety machines
so what I'm going to do is is do this by a series of examples
starting from some not very efficient code and making it run faster and faster
and we'll get a speed-up of around 40
just in doing what we're doing
so as I'll start by saying well assume I have a data structure
that looks like the way Pascal implements arrays
sorry I have nothing against Pascal
we used to teach it back in the old days but um
so a typical way you'd implement an array in a language is
you'd provide both the values that are stored in that array
and then there'd be other information associated with it for example what size it is
and so this is sort of the sort of nice abstract way to do it
and you write code that makes sure that if you ever try to exceed the bounds on the array
you'd return an error signal
and so this particular function you're seeing
is what I want to retrieve an element I passed an a pointer
and then that value the pointer gets used to retrieve the value from the array
and the return value of this function is then to 0 or 1 0 meaning failure in one meaning success
and I'm writing it this way that I use a datatype I'll call data underscore T
and that way I can run this I can compile this code
using different definitions of data underscore T to get in so long floats and doubles
and we'll see how the performance characteristics of those shift with the different data types
and the benchmark I'm going to use is a fairly simple one
it's just to for a an array or one of these vectors
I just want to combine all the elements of it either compute their sum or their product
and again I'm going to use macros here ident and up   and define those
so that op is addition and the identity value is 0
or the OP is multiplication and the identity element is 1
so that I can compare addition in multiplication
so that gives us sort of eight possibilities here
two different operations in four different data types
and so this is written in the sort of most straightforward manner that
I'm using this function called get vac element
to retrieve the successive values of this array
and then performing this operation on them
so now to express a performance of this
we're going to use a metric I introduced called CPE
which stands for cycles per element
and the idea is that usually when you write code that say steps through a vector
anything that has sort of some linear performance as you get bigger
you don't really want to know for exactly it takes this many seconds or microseconds or nanoseconds to do an operation
you kind of want to know often more what's its overall performance characteristics
and also it turns out when you're doing low-level code optimization
it's much more useful to think in terms of clock cycles of the inner clock of the processor
rather than an absolute term such as nanoseconds
because whether a processor is running at two gigahertz through 2.3 gigahertz
I don't really I have no control over that as a programmer
but I can control sort of it the low-level
how many clock cycles are being used for different parts of the computation
so that's why it's called cycles per element
and you can think of it as and this shows some actual measurements
but typically a function like this get what I showed the combine will have some overhead
a fixed amount that's associated with setting up the loop
doing the top level call and all that stuff
and then some component that's linear in the size
and so what I want to know is the slope of that linear component
I'll and that will determine that's what I'll call the cycles per element
the sort of incremental cost of adding one more element to the array
so now if I run this function
I showed you and I'm only showing I'll mostly only show four results
because it turns out whether it's int or long or float or double
is not going to actually have any effect on performance for most of the cases
so if I just run this code through a compiler
and don't do any optimizations it takes around 20 cycles per element
and if I turn on optimization level 1 which is sort of the first serious optimization
it takes the time in half
so I'm down to 10 clock cycles per element just by changing the compilation
and that's using the most unoptimized code I could think of here
and then I won't go through it all but using sort of the kind of things
I described earlier of sort of cut away some of the redundancy in this program
you can get it down to something a little bit simpler
and so one thing instead of you saw before I was making a call to this
get Veck element and every time it did that it went bounds checking
and it's kind of silly to keep bounds checking the same array over and over again
when I'm stepping I'm using its length as the determinate of how many elements to access
so if I'm willing to suit a forgo bounds checking
what I can do is introduce a function that will just give me the actual data storage part of this vector
and skip over all the other stuff
and so I can write a loop that and I introduce you know local variables and all the kind of things we described
and accumulating temporaries and things like that
then the program actually gets a lot faster
again with this is everything from here out is optimization level one
and so it drops it down to a little over a clock cycle for integers addition of
or three clock cycles up to five clock cycles for double precision multiplier
so that's pretty good I've sort of definitely improved things
but the question is well is that the best  there is
and first and well so try to understand what is it about these numbers three five
and this seems to be something close to one point two five
so where those numbers coming from and does that indicate some fundamental limitation in my program
well in order to do that you have to have some understanding of the underlying hardware
and there's a really good course you can take I think it's called ECE 741
that will tell you everything you ever could imagine wanting to know about processor design
and you actually design processors like this
but I'm assuming you're not going to do that for a while
because you have up seven prerequisites to do before that happens
so let me just give you the simple version
and this is sort of a an idea of what a processor has looked like since about 1995
so this is old stuff but it's enough actually to really understand it
it's so hard it's really the details are pretty massive
and so it's not even taught for example 447 is the ECE is the computer architecture course
and they don't really go into this kind of design here
because they're pretty hard they're actually hard to design on your own
but the the basic idea is you think about a program as
is the computer just reads in an instruction does whatever it says to do
reads in another instruction does what that says to do
and that has nothing to do with how programs actually execute
what they've built up is this massive hardware infrastructure
to make a program run way faster than
it would if it were just doing one instruction at a time
and it employs a technique that's called superscalar out of order execution
and the idea is roughly speaking it it takes your program
if you think of your program as a linear sequence of instructions
and it just sucks in as many of those as it can
and it pulls it apart to realize that certain operations
don't really do on each other so I can start one even though it's later in the program
than the one I'm working on right now because they're independent of each other
and it's extracting what they call instruction level parallelism choices where
even though your program is a linear sequence of instruction
buried in there is actually a sort of forest of different computations that need to be done
some which depend on each other and some which don't
and then it has a bunch of hardware
and so that's up here this upper part shows this idea of of fetching instructions
so there's a cache memory a high performance high speed local memory
that is just pulling in your instructions as fast as it can
and those instructions are then feeding a big pile of hardware that will  extract out of it
these low-level operations and figure out which ones depend on which others
and then the there is a set of functional units in this part of it
that are able to perform these low-level operations to do arithmetic floating-point operations
to read data from memory to store data back to memory
all using a cache which is something you're going to learn about fairly soon
how what all this cache is but think of this as a high speed copy of some of the data memory
and and so what this this logic tries to do is keep a forking out
spawning off operations based on your  program
and keeping these as busy as they can be
doing different fragments of your code doing different instructions in a different order from before
and it turns out you think of a register as a little the set of registers is a part of memory that  get read and written
it turns out that in executing a register now just becomes the name
of something that one instruction produces and some other instructions consume
it's a destination for some it's a source for other
and this whole a bunch of stuff here just sort of magically passes
the results of one computation to the input to another computation
based on register names without ever storing them in a and a explicit register file
there is a register file when things kind of settle down they get stored away
anyways there's a lot of stuff going on here
but the main thing to think about is your machine has resources to do multiple operations  all at the same time
if you can somehow structure your program so that those can all get used
so this is as I mentioned it's called a superscalar instruct  processor
is one that can do more than one instruction every clock cycle
and actually Intel started in 93 the very first Pentium could do two instructions at once
but then a little later they came out with one called the Pentium Pro
which is sort of the basis of all modern processors
and the lead architect by the way was a CMU graduate
but this out order execution is the model that's used nowadays
so the other thing is those functional units are more complex than you think they might be
and that they have what's called pipelining
and the ideas of pipelining is imagine you can break up a computation into a series of distinct stages
a simple example is if you want to compute a times B plus C
you first do the times then you do the plus
but it actually gets more than that you can take something like multiplication
and break it up into smaller steps
that can be done one after the other
in a way that and then if you have a separate dedicated Hardware for each of those stages
then you can do what's called pipelining which is
when one operation moves from one stage to the next
a new operation can come in behind and start start its thing
so this example shows imagine I had a three stage pipeline multiplier
and I want to do this computation a*b, a*c  and now multiply those together
so the thing to observe is that a*b and a*c don't depend on each other in any way
so I can do them both and I don't have hardware to do them simultaneously
but I have them enough to do one right after the other
so I can feed the first computation into the first stage a*b on step time step one
and then time step two it will move on to stage two
and times step three it will move on to stage three
but now I can start a*c in the time step two
because this stage became available
once a*b moved from stage one to stage two
and so I can follow right behind just one clock cycle behind this other operation
now a P times one times p2 obviously depends on both of these products
so it can't start until a times C is completed
and then it will run through the pipeline without anything else
so overall then we've done what would have normally seemed to be nine steps worth of arithmetic
in a total of seven steps here because of pipelining
question
what's it if you had like in this a a picture here
if there were different multipliers in these different places yes you could do
those two completely independent of each other
[student speaking]
yes this is all in a single core of a single processor  multi-core is yet another
this is a lower level parallelism than you get through multi-core
and it's present except in the sort of lowest n lowest powered embedded processors
some version of this exists
and most of the time your hardware is not being fully utilized it's one thing you're going to learn from this
so that's the idea of pipelining it it's  a sort of like parallelism
but it's not that you have multiple copies of resources it's that you have
this ability to stream operations through a single Hardware resource  in close succession to each other
and so as well which is a little bit more recent than the sharp machines
but not that much more
is one of the most recent versions of the Intel x86 series
and the functional units include there's a lot of functional units that can do different things
but when you add it all up there's a possibility of it doing  two loads in one store
for integer operations two floating-point multiplies one addition and one division
they can't all happen at the same time because there's some are share functional units
but the point is there's really a lot of equipment there that can do stuff
and also you can measure how an instruction now has
two characteristics and operation is how long does it take from beginning to end
but also how closely spaced can two in stations be  because of this pipelining
so you see that most to them take some number of clock cycles to perform
but they're also pipelines so that you can do a series of them
just one cycle apart
the only different ones that are does you'll notice the division
is both very slow and it's not pipelined
and division is a very expensive operation on most machines  relatively speaking
um so what I claim then is is these these characteristics then
provide a limit on how fast our program can run our original program in that
I have a series of multiplications for example of integers here
and this shows the code for it
and the result of I need the result of one multiplication before I can begin the next
so there's a three clock cycle bound here
and you'll see that in fact my measurements all correspond to
what I'm calling the latency bound of these machines which is just based on
how much time it takes from a beginning of an operation to the end
and the reason is we considered diagram the computation being done by this program
that it's doing a series of multiplications
and I require the result of one multiplication before I can start the next
in general if you look at this loop code
it has to compute ECX
the updated value of it before it can now start the next one
and so that's why even though this I have a PI point multiplier
my program itself limits me to of the sequential execution of all the multiplies
so let's see if we can't get beyond that bound that latency bound
well there's a fairly common technique that
you might have heard of before that's called loop unrolling
and the idea of loop unrolling is just that you
rather than executing one value within a loop you execute a multiple ones
and so this code shows unrolling by two
and what it says is I'm going to step through this array  two elements at a time
and within each of the inner group I'm going to combine the values  from di and di plus one
and I have to put in some extra code to finish off
what happens if the original rate was a von wenk
but you get the idea and
this idea I showed this code of of two
but you could imagine this applying for different values of loop unrolling
so will this help us any well
when I run it I get that the integer addition got a little faster
but the other ones didn't improve at all
so this one is going faster
because basically the old code is the overhead of the loop indexing and incrementing was enough  to be slowing me down
because it's already close to a clock cycle
so I just managed to knock that down to be at the latency bound of this particular instruction
but it didn't have the other ones because I still have this sequential dependency
in order to get my new value of X I have to first
do one computation and then do the other before I can begin another one
but this shows me the way I could make a very very small change and change performance fairly dramatically
what if I take these parentheses and shift them to the right um
what would that make any difference
and lo and behold yes you find that
and I'll call that transformation unrolling by two computing a one element at a time
I'll talk about that in a minute
but I'll use this lowercase a to say I've done an associate ivities formation
and you see all of a sudden my time's dropped in half  for these three cases
so something's going on
um and so let's see why that isn't and now I'll introduce
it and so if I take my picture from before
and think about what those computations employ you'll see that
right now I've changed the structure of the computation
so that I'm pairwise combining each element of pair of elements of the array
and then accumulating those into the overall computation
so I've actually that shifting of the parentheses fundamentally changed
how I'm doing my computation
and you can see now that this critical path which is what determines
in this case the the performance limitation
just got shorter by a factor of two
and that's why I'm now running twice as fast
for for the operations not for energy or addition
but for the other three operations I've cut by a factor or two
just by that shift now there's some good news and bad news here
the good news is if this is integer arithmetic
we know already you know that  a two's complement arithmetic is associative and commutative
so it really doesn't matter for both multiplication and addition
so it really doesn't matter what order I combine these elements in
I'm going to get the exact same answer no matter what
but you also solve for floating-point that's not the case
so with floating-point that shift shifting these parentheses
because of rounding possibilities and even potentially overflow
you might get different values results from these computations
but then again if you think about you know is that really going to happen chances are no
that it's not really going to affect the outcome of your program
but it's enough of a change that most C compilers or most compilers period
will not make any change that changes associativity
because they're very conservative when it comes to floating-point
so that's something you as an application programmer has to have to know well enough is
this a valid can I do this transformation without messing things up
and now without I'll say is now there's a new set of bounds
so a bound is what would appear to be sort of the best you can do based on some constraint in the program
and before it was saying well the latency
the total time through a given for a given operation was abound
and now I say well there's an even more fundamental bound which I'll call the throughput bound
which is just based on I only have so much hardware out there
and I can only a pump it so fast
so for example these two that the throughput bound is one
because I only have that actually becomes limited by the requirement
that I'm having to read from memory
and I have two different load units
oh no I'm sorry I only have one multiplier for integers in one for  addition
the throughput bound for these two actually is just a half
because it turns out there's some odd part of the hardware design that has two 14-point multipliers
but only one floating point adder
and we'll see that we can actually make this multiplication code run faster than addition code
and over here again my limit will be that I only have to load units now to be
and I have to read for every element I'm computing I have to be reading one element from memory
so I can't get below
that okay so but we saw this transformation now is let us
break out of this latency limitation and get something closer to throughput
and here's another technique that can be used to again sort of get more parallelism going
and I call this multiple accumulators
the idea is let's a imagine that
we have the odd-numbered elements and the even-numbered elements in the array
and we can we can compute separate sums or products of those two sets of elements
and then the very end combine them together
so this is another form of and associativity transformation
you were changing the order in which we combine things together
it's just that we're doing it in the suit of odd-even manner
or in general every I do it by some by some parameter I
it has the same issues that if it's integer arithmetic it's fine
if it's floating-point there's a risk of of changing the behavior of the program
but you'll see that again we get a cutting in half here and
a little bit below one for integer addition
and again we can think of it by looking at these pictures
of what are the what gets computed
and you see what we're doing is we're computing here all the even numbers
even numbered elements being combined and here all the odd ones
and the very end we're combining those together
and so we can generalize this if we can
unroll by a factor of K of L
and we can accumulate K results in parallel
and we can use various values of L and K for it
in general has to be a multiple of k
and so you run it out and you can get for floating-point
why you can actually get it down almost to this throughput bounds of 0.5
this is incorrect this is integer addition I should say in tradition
you can again get it down to around 0.5
and in general by sort of picking the best parameters
I can get very close to the throughput bound of this processor
so I've been able to take something remember it originally was  20 clock cycles than 10
and now I'm getting it down to one or fewer clock cycles per element
so now just as the final step is okay is that as good as it go actually no
you remember when I talked about floating-point I mentioned
that there's the special set of registers
that are on x86 that we're called xmm registers on the sharp machines
and now this has well this newer generation have something called ymm registers
which have the feature being twice as big as xmm registers
so in particular these registers are are 32 bytes long
and there's a new version coming out within a year or something they call avx-512
where the register is 512 bits so that's 256 bytes  long
no it's of to 512 excuse me it's 64 bytes right
64 bytes so it'll be twice as big as these
and as I mentioned before you can think of these as a way of
operating on 32 individual characters
or I can treat them as floating point
and we saw before that you nowadays the
the regular floating point makes use of Ceuta the low order  for 8 bytes of these read jester's
but there's also instructions called vector addition
where one instruction has the effect of doing eight floating-point additions at once unload data
and on double precision this counterpart does four of them at once of these
and the that hardware is there it's just sitting there waiting to use and it seldom gets fired up
to really make use of it
but so that floating point multiplier that can do
a floating point multiplication in three clock cycles and is fully pipeline
you can actually do eight fighting point multiplications in parallel and pipelined in three clock cycles
and as I mentioned the shark machines has an earlier version where the numbers are half of these
so it can do for single precision or two double precision at once
and if I write code that uses that what I call vector code
then you can see I can drop by a factor of about four across the board here
and make it run much faster
so this 0.06 is really 0.0625 right
it's doing 16 operations per clock cycle on that
and can't quite hit the vector throughput bound
but in general making this thing run much faster
and so the people really worry about
and you can imagine these instructions were introduced for things like video processing image processing of sound
sort of signal processing where a performance really matters
how fast you can display an image how fast you can rotate something
you know how fast you can perform graphics makes a big difference
in video games are one of the big drivers but even for sort of other operations you might do an image
and so these instructions were really designed to do it
and people write code for those kind of applications
get pretty good at writing code in a way that they can do this vector I what's called vectorizing
and unfortunately so the Intel compiler will actually automatically do some of this for you
a GCC they attempted to implement it and
it didn't work very well so I think they discontinued it
it turns out there's a web aside
so this is on the web from the books web page that describes
how to do this programming if you're interested
there's extensions to GCC that are very funky really weird stuff
but you can write code
that then will get compiled down to make use of these kind of instructions
and that's how I did it and how I got these performance results
okay so that shows you if you really want to it
but that's very machine specific that will only work on
well you have to you can actually tune it so it's easy to compile it   to go between different machines
but it's still a fairly specific and very specific to GCC in fact
so that sort of shows you though if you really want to push it what you can do
now let's uh get back to one of the thing
I told you about how you can if you think of your program as a very long linear sequence of instructions
then the thing is trying to grab as many of those and pull them apart as fast as it can
but of course you know your program is actually typically a loop
and there aren't many instructions in that loop
so how is it turning that into a linear sequence
well that relies on an idea of how do you handle branches
so typically the program you know fetching ahead grabbing instructions
and it will come to a branch instruction a conditional jump of some sort
and there is a dilemma because in general this branch could either
I'm sorry either be taken meaning it will go to the branch target
or it could do what's called fall through meaning it it the test fails and so it just continues execution
and there's no way a priority to know what will happen these can often be data dependent
well and so the way this is handled on a modern processor is by doing
what's known as branch prediction which is essentially just guess
which ways this branch going to go is going to be taken or
not and you predict and then you start executing along the predicted direction
but do it in a way that if you make a mistake that
you haven't caused your reparable harm to the program
and we'll see what that means
so what really happens then is up here there's a lot of logic
that's trying to suck out instructions
and then there's a branch unit that's being basically coming along later and saying
yeah you're okay you predicted that correctly so you can keep going
or it will throw up a flag and say oh wait a minute stop
your misprediction you miss predicted this branch way back 100 clock cycles ago
it's not that long ago but
some number of clock cycles ago you've got to fix it
and so so the hand-wave jumps then becomes more a case of of
guessing up here and then either confirming or  denying that guess down below
so in general then if you it will predict it one way and begin executing
so a mansion for example in a loop like I've shown you
that you predict that the branch will be taken that you'll go back to the start of the loop again
that's actually a pretty good guess
it's a good guess extol you hit the end of the loop
but let's just guess that way
and so the program will just keep guessing that the branch will be taken
and by that means by all those guesses basically create this long linear sequence of instructions
that can be pulled in and executed
and in general some of them will be fetched and some of them you'll actually have done
the operations that are called for in the instruction
and then what happens is if if the flag goes up they say no this was invalid
then what will happen is it will go back and cancel
all the instructions that have been fetched and executed
and the way it does that is you'll notice not all these instructions only modify registers
and it has multiple copies of all the registers
going back these are the registers
these are the values that I'm sure of these are sort of speculative values  appending updates to them
and so when it comes time to cancel it just cancels out all those pending updates
and goes back to values that it's certain of
question
the there's a big block they call the register renaming unit which is sort of
multiple copies of of all the registers as they get accumulated
[student speaking]
it has many more will typically have several hundred reg of these
sort of virtual registers to keep pending copies to the actual registers
[student speaking]
what it does it stores you know here's the old value
here's the first update here's the second update here's the third
and it keeps track of all that you can imagine why this is not a
something you learn in a one semester course right that
to keep track of all those different things flying by and make sure that it works
is a pretty tricky business
but the conceptually it's a pretty simple idea
that it just races off does a lot of things based purely on speculation
and then only if it makes a mistake it goes oh
and it sort of rolls back
to as if it had only executed up to a certain point
and then it moves forward
and starts in going the correct way
so end up and so and it can get away with this it's very interesting tricky stuff
but you remember we talked early in the course
about the difference between using conditional moves and conditional jumps
to implement conditional operations
and conditional moves can take place totally within the structure of this pipeline
but a conditional jump if it's an unpredictable branch
the problem is it might go off executing  and make do a lot of wasted work
but even worse than when it gets back and has to restart
it takes a while to sort of fill up all the the buffers in the system
and get the whole thing running at full steam ahead
so that kind of finishes up then the the way I describe it is
first of all don't do anything stupid even and stupid is probably it was too strong a word
don't do sort of keep in mind there's certain things that you should as a programmer be doing all the time
and they're not obvious
and then begin thinking about tuning and getting some instruction level parallelism
and I describe it as for the machine but as I said pretty much all processors nowadays
it's a class of machines and so these general techniques will work
that those ideas of changing the associativity
they'll work whether it's a you know the ARM processor built into my cell phone
or the x86 processor built into your laptop  or one of the shark machines
they all have the same general of implementation structures
so these techniques will work across across all of them
okay that'll do us for today