good afternoon everybody welcome
good to see you
today we're going to continue our study of exceptional control flow
by looking at some higher level mechanisms known as Linux signals and see non-local jumps
now we're going to spend most of our most of our time looking at signals
because they have a lot of subtleties the semantics can be kind of confusing
so we're going to we're going to spend most of our time there
and I'll mention the idea of non-local jumps but
for details on those you'll want to look in your textbook
and in the slides at the Supplemental slides at the end of this the slide deck
now to motivate the notion of signals
I want to want to talk a little bit about shell programs
now as we mentioned last time there's only one way to create processes on a Linux system
and that's using the fork call
in fact the all of the processes on the system actually form a hierarchy
so that the very first process created when you boot the system up is the init process
which has a process ID of 1
and then all other processes on the system are descendants of that of that init process
now the init process when it starts up it creates daemons
which are long-running programs that provide services typically so for example of a
web server it other kinds of services that you always want running on the system
and then eventually it creates login so called login shells
which provide the command-line interface to two users
so when you log into a Linux system
what you eventually get to is that is a login shell
that's expecting you to type commands
now the login login shells execute programs on your your behalf
so when we type something into the shell
say we type the LS command we're asking we're asking the shell to run the executable program called LS
and so what the shell will do is it will create a child
and then it will execute LS within that child process
and it's possible that that process may create other other child processes
so a shell is an application program no different from any other program
that executes programs on the behalf of users
okay the default shell for Linux is called bash
but there's there's other shells that that were created on earlier  with earlier versions of UNIX
SH was the original shell called the Bourne shell because it was created by Stephen Bourne
and when berkeley came out with their distribution of Unix
they created a shell called the CSH
now the the execution is in a shell is a sequence of read and evaluate steps
so first a shell prints out a prompt
and then it waits for it waits for you to type something in on the command line and hit return
okay and typically what you're what you're typing in
is a is a command which is just the
so the first thing you type is a command and then you follow that with optional arguments separated by spaces
okay so once you hit once you type in a command and those optional arguments and hit return
the shell checks for the end of file character which is a Ctrl-D to terminal
and if so it exits otherwise it evaluates that command line
and the evaluation consists
and then when it returns from the evaluation it just does the same thing over in it
now the evaluation consists of the following kinds of steps first
it parses the command line
and bite and and in the process so it takes the command-line which in this example is in buff
and it produces argv array okay where argv[0] is a command
and then argv[1] and argv[2] and so on are the optional arguments
and the convention in a shell is that if the command line is terminated
by an ampersand then you're asking the shell to run that job
to run that command in the background meaning
the shell won't wait for that job to finish
before it goes through its next read stub
if it if the the line that you type doesn't have an ampersand
then you're asking the shell to to run that job in the foreground which means the shell will wait
so so first we parse this this command line into an argv array
and we return whether or not it was terminated by an ampersand  D so BG for background
if argv[0] is null then that means we just hit a we just hit return right so as an empty line
so we'll just return and just ignore those
now a shell also implements what are called built-in commands
so various things like jobs bg, fg
are examples of built-in commands which are just implemented in the shell itself
so if you type if the first thing you type
if the command you enter is a built in
then the shell will it will check that it will check argv[0] for a to see if it's a built-in command
and if it is it'll just execute it whatever whatever it is you asked it to do
okay otherwise if it's not a built-in then that means that that you're asking the shell to run some program
okay so in that case the shell will fork a child
and then the child will execute that program  by calling execve
passing as the first argument the name of the command
and as the second and third argv and and the environment respectively
now exactly if you recall from last time never returns  unless there's an error
so it checks so we check it the return value for execve
and if it returns less than zero fact the only time it will return
if it does return it will always return -1
but we're just being careful here
so we check that for a an error and in in print and error message if we find an error and then exit
so once the once the once the parent gets control again
then it waits for that foreground job to terminate
okay so if it's not a background job
then it waits for it to terminate by calling waitpid
and waiting for that child that foreground job to terminate and then and reaping it
otherwise if it's a background job it just prints say a message and goes on
so this is really interesting right that
there's really the only difference between a foreground job and a background job is just that the shell
does a waitpid on that job or not
right so there otherwise there's really there's really no difference
now what's the prob there's a problem with our example show
and that the problem is that we're we're doing the right thing for the foreground job
we always have to reap these children so they they so that
they're their state can be released
but we're not we're not doing anything to reap any background jobs
right when if the background job so if not BG
we're just printing a message and then we're returning
and then we're continuing with this read evaluate step
and never never going back and and taking care of that of that background job
so this is a problem because that the background job will eventually become
if we have enough of those jobs we create a memory leak that could crash the system right so this is an error
so what are we going to do about this
well it turns out that exceptional control flow will help us solve this problem
and what happens is that the kernel will notify
the shell when when a any of its children terminate
okay and then the shell can can then react to that and issue a waitpid
okay and this this notification mechanism that the the kernel uses is something called a signal
so a signal is a small message
that the kernel delivers to a process to notify it that there's been some event in the system
now so this is very similar to the exceptions that we studied the last time
right except it's it's it's all implemented in software
now kernel signals are always sent from the kernel
but sometimes they're sent at the request of another process
right sometimes the the kernel will notice that there's some event
other times another process will ask the kernel to send a message to some other process
now that we say that it's a small message
because the only information that's contained in a signal
is its it's a unique integer ID
and the fact that it was it was it was delivered okay so
that's so there's nothing else in a signal except except that it arrived
and that it has some some some unique ID
now examples of these are the sigint
so signals have this I this unique ID and then they also have a name
so the sigint is what the when you type control C at on the command line
the kernel sends a signal to every any processes in the foreground
and the default action of receiving a SIGINT is to terminate right
so this is how if you're running a foreground job you hit Ctrl-C
you get the prompt back because it kills that job
sigkill number nine can be used to kill terminate any program
so these two have sig ant and sigkill have the same effect on the programs me that they kill the program
the the unique aspect of sig kill is that there's no way to ignore it or override it
okay so this is like the failsafe
as we'll see there are there are ways to to catch and ignore other signals like sigint
SIGSEGV is the our favorite segment
segmentation violation so if you if you access a region of memory that's protected or or not legal
then your program will the kernel will send your that process a sigsegv
okay signal and that the default  the default effective that is to terminate the program
sigalrm is a way within your program you can arrange for a signal to be sent to yourself
so you can say inside your program send me a sigalrm signal  in three seconds something like that
so this is a way to do things like you can set up timers you can set up timeouts like if you want to
X if you want to set a timeout value and you're doing some some some work and
you want to guard against that that work taking exceptionally long time
you can you can you can use sigalrm to set a timeout
and then a very important one is as we'll see that would be very important for our shell is the sigchild signal
which the colonel sends to a parent every time one of its children terminates  or stops
okay so this as we'll see now
we'll see this is how we're going this is how our shell that is going to actually reap
it's it's all of its children right is by taking advantage of the sigchild signal
but before I can show you that
we need to go through a number of concepts around signals
okay like I said the the semantics of signals
it's probably one of the thorniest aspects of Linux
it was it was developed very early in the the lifespan of Linux when
and it maybe wasn't as clean as it could be right so
in order to get a handle on signals we're going to be very careful about defining terms
and very careful about the way
we talk about them
so we say that the kernel sends or delivers a signal to some destination process
and it does this by setting some state in the context of the destination process
now nothing happens except that some bits get changed in the destination process context
okay there's no there's no impact of immediate impact of sending a signal
now a kernel sends a signal
either because it detected some event in the in the system like
that like a child process is terminated for example
or another process has asked the kernel to send
to deliver a process on a signal on its behalf
and there's a number of ways to do that one of them is with the kill system call
it's kind of an unfortunate tournament
I mean the so kill is a general way to send signals
and the the impact is not as is sometimes not to kill the program right
but for some reason they chose to to call it kill
now the destination process receives a signal
when it's forced by the kernel to act in some way to react in some way to the delivery of a signal
okay so these are two very different things sending a signal set state in the context of the destination process
receiving a signal is what happens when the destination process is is finally
forced by the kernel to act in some way to react in some way
now some possible ways to react are to just ignore the signal
okay to terminate the process
or to catch the signal by executing a user level function  called a signal handler
so in this case when we when we catch signals it's very similar to the the
and executes a signal handle
it's very similar to executing a an exception handler in response to some kind of event in the system
now the difference is that exception handlers are in the kernel
signal handlers are actually just in your C code okay there
and they execute in your in your process
so the so the way to think about if if we catch a signal by executing a signal handler
we have our process executing instructions
and then the signal is received by that process
so the kernel passes control to a signal handler
which is also just in the code that's executing in the current process it's just a function  in our in our C code
the signal handler runs and when it returns it eventually returns back to the next instruction
and then then we continue
okay so it's it's it's just like kind of like an interrupt right we just temporarily pause
what we're doing in the in our code to execute this this handler before just continuing on
okay now we say that a signal is pending
if it's been sent by the colonel but not you have received
okay so if at any given point in time there can only be one pending signal of any particular type
okay so this has very important consequences for using signals
because you can't cue signals up right at any point in time there's there can only be one pending sigchild
signal for example or sig sigint signal
and if a subsequent sigchild signals say is sent
it just over writes well you can think of it as it has no impact
it's just discarded right if there's already a pending signal
so they don't they don't queue up in any meaningful way
now our process can block the receipt of certain signals
okay now it can't stop signals from being delivered
but it can stop it can stop the process from having to react to the route to that signal when it's received
okay so block signals can be delivered but they won't be received until the signals
unblocked
and pending signals are received at most once
now the colonel keeps track of these pending and blocked
signals in bit vectors that will call pending and blocked
and pending represents the set of pending signals
right where each bit in the pending bit vector corresponds to some particular signal
okay so this is why they can't be queued right because
there's only one bit for any signal Kay there's only one bit in the bit vector
and if we and when we deliver a signal we're just setting will set that bit the colonel will set that bit
we deliver another signal of the same type it'll just set that bit again which has no has no effect
now the colonel sets that the bit in pending when the signals delivered and it clears it
when the signals received
and the colonel also provides mechanism for users to block signals  blocked bit vector
so the block bit vector is the same size as the pending bit vector turns out it's just a 32 bit int
okay and it can be set and cleared the bits
and that can be set and cleared using the sig proc mask system call
okay now that the blocked in the linux literature the blocked bit vector is also called the signal mask
okay now we want to look in a little more detail about sending and receiving signals
so let's start first with sending signals
first we need to understand the idea of a process group
so every process belongs to exactly one process group
and those so here I'm showing a shell that's in process
it has a process ID of 10 and a process group ID of 10
the shell created a foreground job
which has a process ID of 20 and a process group ID of 20
and then all of the children that this foreground job
created have the same process group ID of 20
so these these process groups can be set by a system call set called the set process group ID
and you can and you can fetch that process group using the get process group system call
so you can see in this example what what this shell is done is it created a foreground child
so it created this child and it it changed the process group ID
to be equal to the process ID of the child
and then when this child created other child children
they just inherited the same process group ID
okay now this this notion of a process group is useful
because it allows you to send signals to groups of processes at the same time
and you can do that with a program called kill
which is typically in /bin directory
and that the kill program you can use the kill program to send an arbitrary signal to
either an individual process or all the processes in one process group
so let's look at an example this program
this Forks program creates two children
and with each of which has a process group of 24817
and of course they have different process they have different process IDs
and so if we if we do a PS we see these two
we see these two processes running
and these just go into loop so they'll just they'll just run continuously
okay now we can
we can use kill to to kill an individual process
for example so if we call it the first argument
indicates what signal you want to send
so in this case it's its signal 9 which is the sigkill signal
so kill -9 is is a very typical
usually if you want to kill processes you just kill -9
and actually one of my favorite Auto lab nuke names for 213 was the nickname was kill - 9 15-213
so but then then the second argument is the if it's is the the process ID
so this is asking this is asking the kernel to kill process ID 24818
by sending it a cig kill signal
now if the if the process ID is is preceded by a dash
then it sends a signal to every process in process group -
then it treats this argument as a process group
and it sends a signal to every process in that process group
so in this case it will send a signal to both of these both of these children processes
and then afterwards we if we do a PS we see that those processes are gone
okay that it really did work that way
now another way to send signals is by typing either control C or control Z
at the to the command line
control C causes the kernel to send a signal to every job in the the foreground process group
and control Z causes it to send a signal to every job in the in the foreground process group
the default action for SIGINT is to terminate the process
the default action for the sig tea stop is to suspend the process stop it
until it receives a sig cont a signal
so you can see an example of this here we have a program that
creates a parent and a child running in the foreground so the parents running in the foreground
now when we type control Z to the command line
the shell notifies us that it's suspended that process
and if we do a PS we can see the parent and the child indeed are suspended
so the PS indicates that it's suspended or stopped using T
now next we type in the built in the shell built in which is fg
and fg restores those those suspended jobs to the foreground
so after typing fg now we're running this our program again in the foreground
and then we can kill it by typing ctrl-C
which which elicits a SIGINT whose default action is to terminate
and then when we do a PS we see that indeed  that's that they're gone
now the third way that we can send signals is by using the kill system call
so here's an example of how that works
so in this in this example we're creating end children
now each of which goes into an infinite loop
and we're recording this the process ID of each child that we create
and then in it we go in another loop we go through
and we we kill each of those child processes with by using the kill function
passing it the process ID and the signal that we want sent to that process
okay and then we do our due diligence and reap each one of those
children that we've terminated
now this isn't strictly necessary because we're going to exit as soon as this 412 function
returns we're going to exit the code so but we're just being
you know careful here and maybe a little pedantic but
okay now now let's look at how we process receive signals
now suppose process a is running along executing its user code and then
there's a control passes into the kernel because of some exception
now that exception can be either a timer going off
they've been interrupts or it can be a trap user calls a system call
okay but it's always caused that the trap into the
or the transferring control into the kernel is always caused by some exception
so at this point the kernel calls its scheduler function
and it decides to to do a context switch from process a to process B
and it gets processed be all set up and right before it returns from that exception
and right before it's ready to pass control back to back to process  the user code and process B
it checks for any signals that any pending signals
okay and it does this by computing a bit vector PNB so pending non blocked
which is the logical and of the pending bit vector
and the inverse of the blocked bit vector
okay so PNB is a list of all the pending signals that aren't blocked
okay so these are all the pending signals that should be received
if now if pnb is all zeros then there's no pending signals
so it just returns it passes control back
it passes control back to process b which can continue executing
however if if PNB is nonzero then
it chooses the smallest nonzero bit in PNB
and it forces process P to receive that signal the corresponding signal
the receipt of the signal triggers some action in in the process
and then we repeat that for all the nonzero signals K that  are nonzero bits that are set in PNB
and finally when we've gone all through all the non zero bits
then we pass control to the next instruction in in the in in process P
so the receipt of a signal always triggers some action
which is either the process terminates
the process stops until it's restarted by a sick can't signal
the process ignores the signal
ok so that's there's always some predefined default action
but we can modify that that default action by using a function system call called signal
ok so we can now signals a little that's another sort of misleading kind of term just like kill right because when we
when we send a signal to a process we don't always want to kill it
and signal doesn't actually signal anything
it just it just modifies the default action associated with some something
okay so if the signal function takes out a signal number
and and then specifies a change in the default action for that signal
and those default actions can be either to ignore the signal
ok ignore signals of type signal
revert to the default behavior for that signal
or we can we can give it or it can be the address of a user level signal handler
which is a function that we've declared in our C program
ok it's there's nothing special about the function it has a certain prototype that has it takes a single argument
which is the signal number so when that function gets called in in response to receiving a signal
that argument will be set to the signal number
so calling signal with a and specifying a signal handler is called installing a handler
and then executing the handlers referred to as catching or executing
they were handling the signal
and and this this handler then is just like an exception handler
when it when it returns it will be when it's executed it will interrupt the
whatever is currently executing in the process when it returns
it will return back to that point and continue executing
okay so here's a simple example of of installing a handler
so here in main where we're going to install a sigint handler
which is called sigint underscore handler which is defined up here
and the prototype for this function is returns nothing
and it takes a single integer argument which is the signal number and returns nothing
okay and after we install that handler
then we're going to execute the pause this call which just waits for a signal handler to execute
ok so pause terminates the current or suspends the current process
until a signal is received and a handler executes in that process
and then pause then pause returns
so we're going to wait until the SIGINT happens
so sigint entry call is when we type ctrl-c
so when you're doing your bombs did did you panic at some point and try to hit ctrl-c to get out of it
okay so that snarky message you got that was
we did that by installing a signal hello SIGINT handler in in in your bomb
okay so when when you type ctrl-c that elicits a a SIGINT
when that SIGINT is received we printed this message and then eventually  let you exit
now signaler signals are another examples of concurrency
now we've seen concurrency earlier in the form of processes
right concurrent flows overlapping in time
okay logical flows overlapping in time  by definition are concurrent
now with with processes the because they have separate address spaces
those concurrent flows never interfere with each other
right so in some sense processes are very easy to deal with
and we don't really have to worry one process doesn't have to worry about being interfered with by another process
in fact you have to go to great lengths to share like to share things between processes
you have to use specific system calls in order to say share memory between two processes
now signals are another form of concurrency this is the second time in this class that that
you've experienced concurrency
and so a signal is just a concurrent flow it's just a logical flow a sit
so a handler is just another logical flow that runs concurrently with your program
right so we're let's say we're executing a while loop in process a
okay that while loop is is executing
and in process a receives the signal
which causes a transfer of control to this handler
this handler executes so this is a concurrent flow
that overlaps in time with the while loop in process a eventually this handler returns
and we return for the back tip to back to process a
now one of the reasons signals are so tricky is because of this this overlapping concurrent flow
this this concurrency because the signal handler runs in the same process  as the main program
so it shares all the global variables of that program
okay so you're that signal handler is a function
that you've declared and it has access to all all the state all the global state in the program
okay and the existence of the shared global state can create real problems
and we'll get into more details about some of those problems
so another way to look at these signal handlers disking as concurrent flows
is using this this context switch diagram
so suppose we're executing in process a
and now at some point a signal is delivered to process a
now nothing happens right just just the pending bit gets set in process a at this point
now at some point there's a transfer of control into the kernel
and the kernel decides to do a context switch from A to B
and now B gets to run for a while there's another transfer of control to the kernel
and the kernel decides to schedule process a
and now right before it returns control to process a
it notices that the the pending bit for this signal is set
so it causes process a to receive that signal
so that executes the handler code
when the handler returns it returns for brief briefly to the kernel
which then transfers control back to the the next instruction that  the process was going to execute
now handlers are also tricky because they can be interrupted by other handlers
so suppose we have our main program  that catches a signal S
which causes a transfer of control to handle or s
and then we'll handle RS did you have a question okay
well handle RS is is is executing
the the program catches a signal T
which causes a transfer of control to the handler first for T
and when then when at handler returns it returns to the point to the
to the to the instruction and handle or else that was where it was interrupted
and then handle or us continues its execution and eventually
return back to the the point in the main program where it was interrupted
now signals that the colonel always blocks
pending signals of the type currently being handled right so
a handler for a signal of type T can't be interrupted
by the receipt of another signal of that same type
okay can be as I showed in the previous slide it can be interrupted by a signal of another type
but not by a signal of the same type
so that's sort of an implicit form of of blocking
but there's the kernel also provides a system call that allows you to explicitly block  and unblock signals
in the form of the sig proc mask function
and then there's associated so this allows you to block and unblock a set of signals
and then there some support functions that allow you to create those sets
so just think of these as bit vectors
and these functions will set in set and reset the bits and those those bit vectors
so let's see how we can use sig proc masks to temporarily block and unblock a signal
so this is going to this is going to turn out to be very important for you
when you working on your shells that which is your next your next lab assignment okay
so what we do we'll use Sigemptyset to create an empty mask so this is a mask with all zeros
okay with with no elements in the set
and then we're going to add a single element to this set which is sigint
and now we temp we have some code that we don't want to be interrupted by the seed of sigint
okay so we want to temporarily block the receipt of sig n signals
and we do it by calling sig proc mask with the command
say I want to block I want to block the signals
that are spent that that are in the set specified by mask
and I'll assign the so this will become my new mask
so this this becomes the new blocked bit vector
okay or the not the this  the new signal mask
and it makes a copy of the old one and stores it at at the address specified in the third argument
so at this point after we returned from sigprocmask
sig n signals are blocked and they won't be received
and then we so we can execute this code knowing that we won't be interrupted by receipt of a sigint
and then we can restore the previous block set by using the cig set mask  in stopper ation
and passing in the previous mask that we that we saved up here when we when we initially blocks again
okay so signals and signal handling is a really tricky business
and there's sort of three things that make them
so tricky and kind of nasty really
one is that you have to be very careful to write handlers that are safe
okay so there's you can write signal handlers that are unsafe in the sense that they'll create a deadlock in your program
okay or you can or you can write signal handlers that will that will corrupt a global data structure
that's being modified by the main program
so I mean imagine imagine your main programming is updating some some data structure like a linked list
and right in the middle of updating that data structure when it's when it's no longer consistent
the program gets interrupted by the receipt of a signal
and if that signal handler is updating that same data structure reading that structure or modifying it
then it's going to encounter it in an inconsistent state  and and and you're in trouble
okay so this the fact that it's the fact that it's it's it's it's easy to write signal handlers
that are that are unsafe is is is one aspect of that makes them tough to deal with
another aspect is they have this funny semantics that signals aren't cued
and so if you're not if you're not really careful about this
it's very easy to use the receipt of signals to count events
and you can't do that if signals were cued you could use
you could use the receipt of a signal to count events in the system but you can't do it because
their signals aren't cued
and then a third a third aspect of signals which makes them tough is that
they're not even they're not even portable across different versions of Linux
okay so if you use solaris or some form of bsd it's not necessarily
the single handling semantics aren't necessarily the same as they are in Linux
okay so we'll we'll look at all three of these in a little more detail
and first we'll start with writing safe handlers
so let me give you some guidelines for how to write safe handlers
and this is just a collection of fun this is just a
collection of sort of collected wisdom from from various sources
but it covers a lot of aspects of signal handlers
so the first guideline is to keep your handlers as simple as possible for example
the simplest possible handle I can think of just sets a global variable and then it returns
okay and in fact cert the CMU cert provides guidelines for sort of compliant programs
and this is the only signal handler that they allow this is the only compliant signal handler
one that just sets a global variable and then returns
okay guideline number one call only functions in your handlers that are that have this property of async signals safety okay
okay and we'll look at this in a second but I want to point out that printf s printf Malak exit
functions that are very common and commonly used are not safe
okay guideline number two is to always save and restore error no on entry and exit
so you know error no is a global
global variable that's set when there's whenever there's an error in a system-level function
so you need to save and you need to save and restore it on entry and exit
so that it doesn't get overwritten if you're interrupted by another handler
okay if you're accessing any shared data structures
inside a signal handler that are also accessed by your main routine
then you need to temporarily block signals while you access that data structure
both in the main routine and your signal handler
right and the reason for this is what I described earlier
if your main routine is updating that global data structure and then it gets interrupted
and the signal handler is reading that data structure it's going to find it in an inconsistent state
and bad things will happen
okay you want to be sure to declare your any global variables that are shared between signal handlers
and the main routine as volatile
okay the volatile attribute will prevent the compiler from putting that that value in a register
so if you declare a global variable as volatile
it will always be reads and writes will always go to and from memory
okay so this is very important right you might if you don't declare these global variables at volatile
and the compiler chooses to put to put one of those in a in a register
then you may miss that variable being updated
so suppose suppose your signal handlers is setting a global variable
and now suppose your main routine is spinning waiting for that global variable to get set
well if it's in a register the write to that variable will just update the register
right and so your main routine is in danger of just of spinning forever not not seeing the change right
okay so always use volatility so that they're not stored in registers
and then if you have fun if you have a special kind of global called a flag
which by definition is a variable it's only read or written not incremented or updated  it's just read or written
if you have if you have a variable with that property then you can declare it with this SIG atomic tea tribute
and if you do that then the system guarantees that reads and writes to that variable will be atomic
so you don't have to in other words you don't have to protect accesses to the shared
two accesses or references to those global variables
okay and so by this by atomic which means that the the read or write of that flag will always happen in one uninterruptible step
okay one uninterruptible load or store particular
now in practice on most systems this SIG atomic T is an int
so you can you can read or write an int with one one instruction okay so it's it's atomic
but if you want to be portable you declare it with sig atomic T
and then it'll it'll work on none it will work on all systems
okay we mentioned this property of a sync signal safety
now a function is is safe to be used inside of a signal handler
if it's either reentrant okay or if it can't be interrupted by signals
and will a reentrant function as we'll see when we study threads is a function where all of its
all of the data that it accesses is on its own stack
okay so no global variables no pointers to global variables everything's stored on the stack locally
okay so that means you can be it's called reentrant
because you can write have multiple instances of that function
and they all have their own separate copies of all of the variables that they're they're using
now the POSIX standard guarantees 117 different functions to be a sync signal saved
these include underscore _exit,write,wait,waitpid,sleep,kill
but unfortunately there's some very popular functions that aren't on this list  printf,sprintf
things that you really want to use
and in fact write is the only output function that's a sync signal safe
so this is kind of a problem because
especially when you know you something you'd often like your signal handlers to output information
but you can't if you want to really be pedantic and careful you can't use printf in fact
it's possible to write a program
and I'll try to I'll try to it's possible to write a program
that does a tight loop of printouts in the main routine
and then a steady stream of interrupts which execute a handler which also does a printf
the printf call has to acquire what's called a lock on the terminal
okay each printf inside that that library function
it acquires a lock which means only one instance of printf can write to the terminal at a point in time
if another if another function tries to acquire that lock it has to wait `
until whatever function owns the lock releases it
okay so a lock prevents a lock is a way for to get mutually exclusive access to two shared resources
so if we have a tight loop in our main routine with executing printf
imagine what happens if one of those printouts acquires a lock on the terminal
and then gets interrupted not by the receipt of a signal
now within the signal handler it calls another printf
and that printf tries to acquire that lock  and it blocks forever
because nothing's going to release that lock because the the main routine was interrupted by the handler
so you have what's called a classical a classical condition called deadlock
which is we have a process waiting for an event that will never occur
in this case the the printf and the signal handler is waiting for a lock to be released that will never be released
so it's interesting you can try this it's
it's it's not too hard to to create this deadlock situation
so to deal with this I really didn't want to tell you guys
that you couldn't have any output in your programs and writes a very difficult thing to deal with
so so I created a small little library called the safe i/o library
consists of three routines and they're available to you in the csapp.c file
which is distributed on the website
and it consists of three reentrant routines
sio_puts prince/princess string
(sio_)putl prints a long
and sio_error prints a message and then exits
okay so you can safely use take my word for it you can safely use this in your in your signal handlers
so if we were going to rewrite our sigint_handler from the from the binary bomb
we could rewrite it like this and now we have every function is is a sync signal safe
all right now signals are also tucked because of this this funky non cueing semantics
of and so it's really easy to make mistakes
when you have an implicit assumption that
the that the receipt of a signal it can be used to count the occurrence of an event
so let's look at this let's look at this example program
we install a sick child handler
okay and this is actually this this sort of close the loop member we talked about our example shell
we're wondering how are we going to reap those those background children
well we do it by installing a sick child handle like we're doing in this example
so this here we have a program that installs this sick child handler
and then it creates n different child processes
where each child sleeps for a little bit and exits
and then it spins until the C count variable  becomes zero
that the parent I'm sorry the parent spins until the C count variable becomes zero
now in the in our child handler we we have a global that's
that's initialized to zero ccount
and then we wait we're going to wait so this child when the child handler gets called that means
it's called because we received a sick child signal
okay so in our in our handler we're going to reap that child by calling weight
and we're going to Dec and then will decrement ccount
okay so once all of the children if then have been reaped ccount will be zero
and then the parent can exit this this while loop
okay now in this particular example N was 5
but will you run this code we only the handle or only gets called twice
okay so the the message handler Reap child only gets executed twice right
which means the handler was only called twice
we created five children we terminated five children
but we only reaped two
okay so that the problem is that when we the problem is that we assumed
that the receipt that the that
the execution of the child handled our correspondent to the single receipt of a single sick child signal
okay when when in reality
we had in reality multiple sick right
we had in reality multiple sick child signals were delivered to that child
which kept overriding that at bid in the pending bit vector
and the delivery of those signals didn't didn't have didn't cause any reaction in the process
until that process was was just about ready to be rescheduled
and only then was where was a signal received
but even though like say three signals were delivered only one was received
okay so you can't use events in this case we're using event
we're using signals to count  events which in this case is the termination of a child
okay so the receipt of a signal in this case
it only indicates that at least one child terminated
right not not one child terminated
all we can infer from the receipt of that signal is that at least one child has terminated
okay so to fix that when we receive a sick child
we have to put we have to put the weight that's reaping on our children
we have to put that in this in a loop
so we have to assume that the receipt of a sick child
if we get a sick child there could be multiple terminated children
that we have to that we have to reap
and so we put we put that in this loop and we execute this loop
until there's no more terminated children in which case wait will will
will exit with an error code of -1 and a error know of a child
so this isn't really an error it's just it just means there's no more terminated children
so we check as long as if our error knows naughty child  then we have an error
otherwise we terminated normally as we expect it
now if we run this code
now we we see that we reap all five children as  as we should
okay so let's the litany of problems with signals first
it's easy to write handlers that aren't safe
second it's easy to get the semantics wrong third
they're often not even portable across different versions of Unix
so there's some older systems I don't know if any
there's some earlier versions of Unix that after you catch a signal it restores the default action
so you have to reinstall the handler every time
well every time a handler gets called you have to re-install that handler by calling signal inside the handler itself
we don't have to do that for for Linux systems
on on some systems when you have so-called slow sis calls
for example read
you know if you do a read system call
the kernel doesn't wait around for that data to arrive it's
it you know it sends a request to the disk controller and that schedules another process
right so in a way that the read call is sort of and then only when the data arrives
and the interrupt comes in announcing that the data arrives
does that read call finish and then restore and return
so you can think of read is actually kind of broken up into two parts right
then and so that functions like read these kind of functions are called slow sis calls
and on some systems if the process receives a signal
before a slow system calls has finished
the kernel will will just abort that system call and return from that system call with an error
okay so from users point of view you're doing a read call
and it returns with this this e enter signal this e enter error
you did nothing wrong you just happen to have the bad luck of being interrupted by some signal
and so in your user code you have to check for that
and if if a slow system call like read is interrupted by signal you have to redo it
so you have to put which is really a pain right because you have to put these these read calls in a loop
and keep keep looping until it succeeds
and finally some systems don't block signals of the type being handled right
so that the solution for this is a replacement for signal
so the problem is with the signal syscall
and the solution is a newer syscall called sigaction
which provides a mechanism a replacement for signal
that provides a mechanism for portable and predictable signal handling
and so what I've done what I've done is created a rapper called uppercase signal
that takes the same arguments as that the signal call
but inside it calls the sig action function to get portable signal handling
and so it's it's not really important to go into detail about this
the point is in your code you always want to call uppercase signal using the  rapper that provided in csapp.c
and then if you do that then you'll always block signals of the typing
handle the system will automatically restart
slow syscalls that have been interrupted by by signals
okay so fortunately there's an easy fix for this
now let's let's finish up with them
there's some interesting I mentioned that signals are difficult
because of these the fact that they're they're concurrent flows
so I want to look at some sort of subtle issues that you can run into because of this concurrency
and and I want to talk about how to identify those errors and how to fix them
so here's a program that this is like a simple shell program
that maintains a jobs list right so every time it creates a new child
it adds it to the jobs list and every time that child terminates it removes it from the jobs list
okay so so our simple show just in a loop it just creates a child and then executes the program  within that child
and then in the parent it correctly blocks all of the signals temporarily while it adds the job to the job queue
and then it unblocks and then it unblocks those signals
okay so this is correct and that it's it's protecting access to this the shared job queue
because that that that job that job queue is also manipulated by the sick child handler
so when when a child terminates and the parent receives the sick child
this handler runs
and this handler goes through and it reaps all of the children potentially terminated children
and then for each one it deletes that that job from the job queue
all right so here's a classic case we have two concurrent flows our main routine
and our our signal handler
they're each accessing a shared data structure in this case the the job queue
okay and they're there correctly blocking signals while they update this this job queue
but this program has a really subtle and nasty bug in it
can you see what it is
what's the sequence of events that would
cause this program to to fail
yes
exactly that's exactly it so is it possible that the the child process
could terminate before the parent has a chance to add that job to the queue and the answer is yes
right we you cannot make any assumptions about the execution ordering of the child in the process
or about how long they run right
so it's it's it's very possible
that the child can connect after after the four control returns to the child instead of the parent
and then the child terminates before the parent ever has a chance to to add that job to the job queue
so now what's happened is that the the child is deleting
a deleting a job that hasn't been added to the job queue  right
now when the parent finally gets around to running it adds that job to the job queue
and that job will never be deleted
right so this is the kind of subtle nasty horrible kind of bug that you run into
when you're dealing with concurrency
trying to keep track of all of these interleaving of events
can just make your head explode all right
now and it happens and Sigma it happens with any kind of concurrency
where you have concurrent flows accessing shared resources and signal handlers are no different
now we'll look at principled ways where we can deal with this kind of sharing when we study threads later on
but I just want to point this out to him scare you a little bit
all right so here's how we would fix that
what we have to do is somehow avoid the avoid the the avoid the  possibility of the child handle or executing
before the parent can add the corresponding job to the job queue
now we can't control whether the child executes first or the parent execute first
and we can't control how long the child runs
but we can control when the the sigchild handler runs because we can block signals
okay so what we'll do
we'll modify our program -
we'll use sigprocmask to block sigchild signals before we create the child
okay so at this point after this invocation of sigproc,sigchild, signals are blocked
okay then we create the child
and before we do execev
since we don't know that child may may need to reap its children right we don't know if it we
by default children inherit the the blocked
a bit vector of their parents okay so when this child runs
F after it returns from fork at this point right after the fork sigchild is blocked in the child as well right
so if if we didn't do anything if and the child created children
and tried to reap you know reap them with a sick child handle that sick child handler wouldn't run right
so that would be a problem
so in the child before we execute that the program itself we unblock sigchild
and this was an example that I was alluding to last time
how it's useful sometimes to separate creating processes with executing programs right then
so this allows us to get our our signal mask set up the way we want it before we run our program  in the child
so now even if the child terminates early
the sigchild handler won't run until after we've added the job to the to the job queue
because we don't unblock sick child until after the until after we call a job
okay now there's another
so this this sort of scenario be very relevant to you when you do your shell lab
okay so you want to be careful not to not to make that mistake
another another thing that you you're going to need to do in your shell lab
now you remember in our simple our simple shell example we did the weight
inside the main routine so we waited for foreground jobs using wait
but now in a real shell we're going to have our sick child handler do all the all the weights call all the weights
and it week so we can't put the weight has to go in the sigchild handler can't go in the main routine
okay so if it so high if we can't put a weight in the main routine
how are we going to how are we going to detect that our foreground job is finished
okay so somehow so what we could do we could define in the sig child handler
when we read the foreground job
right we've created a foreground job when we read that foreground job
we could set this global flag
we could declare the process this process ID
a variable PID as a as a global flag
and then just assign the process ID of the of the of the foreground job
okay so in this this is an example of a handler it just all it does it sets a flag and then exits
and then in our main routine okay we want to we want to block sig tile just by just like before
okay to avoid that that race condition between the parent and the child
and then we create the child
and then and then in the and then the parent we set PID to zero
okay then we unblock sigchild
and then we wait for the sick child handler to run and set PID to non zero
okay okay everybody see that I mean this so this is correct right
but it's extremely wasteful right
we're spinning we're using valuable processor cycles in this in this tight spin loop
just executing over and over and over and over and over and over  for who knows how long
okay so that's not a good that's not a good solution alright
so let's look at a couple other things we might might consider
and that have been considered by generations of 213 students
so one thing you might think well I'll just instead of just putting a semicolon here
I'll pause
and then I'll wait for the sig child handler to run
and then I'll go back up and I'll check
I'll check PID again
now you have to put this in a loop it still has to be in a loop
because we have other signal handlers in our program we have a SIGINT handler
so it might be if we do the pause here and this again comes in and say get Sigyn handler runs
that would cause us to exit the pause function and go back up
so we have to keep checking PID because we're not sure
we have to keep checking for the specific signal handler sick child handler to run instead of other handlers that might run
but this is actually wrong
because it has a race can you see what the race is
what's wrong with this there's a good chance that this thing will block forever
yes
yeah that's so the the problem the problem with this is like
so if the signal if the signal is received after PID is checked
but before the pause executes
okay which is possible right
it's unlikely but it's possible
if that if that signal is arrives here
then the handler will set PID to non zero and
then we'll execute the pause
and the pause will be blocked forever waiting for a signal that will never arrive right
because the sync child signal already already came
very subtle right
so this code looks okay it looks benign but it's wrong
and and and your program would just hang forever
so we say well okay that's no good
we could replace the pause with asleep so we could say let's let's check PID
and then sleep for some predetermined amount of time in this case one second
and then go back up and check PID again
so this while this is correct it's way too slow right we're asking the system to wait for a second which is an eternity
and there's there's forms of sleep nanosecond where you can wait instead of units of seconds
you can wait in units of nanoseconds
but that what value do you use right
if it's it that so that's if you choose a value that's too large then you have this problem the slowness problem
if you choose a sleep time that's too small
then you have the other problem that it's inefficient
so the solution is to use six suspend
which is the last last thing we're going to look at today
so six suspend is a function that takes a signal mask
and it's equivalent to an uninterruptible version of these three statements
so we block the signals that are specified in the signal mask
and then it's atomic in the sense that
after that this this these two statements can't be interrupted they're always executed together
okay so we blocked these signals
and then we execute the pause
okay so there's no chance
of a signal interrupting this program in between the sigprocmask and the pause
okay and then and then when a signal does come in and
the execution of the handle or causes pause to exit then we set the mask back to what it was before
okay so the proper way then to wait for a signal
is to use sig suspend in the following way
so here's our here's our program again
we before we create the child's we block sigchild
then we create the child
and now we're going to wait for the sick child to be received
now sick child is still blocked
okay so there's no danger of the sick child handler running
okay so we set that global variable to zero
and then while it's while it's non zero we repeatedly call sigsuspend
and sick suspend is using the previous mask
that was set up here so sick suspend is using the mask
where sigchild is unblocked
okay when we when we entered this first sigprocmask,sigchild was unblocked
so this allows inside the sigsuspend sigchild is unblocked
okay so it allows for the the handler now to be received  or to be executed
okay so in it and it does it safely
because of the uh the atomic nature of those those first two instructions
so once the so it's possible that the the implicit pause inside of sigchild
could be interrupted by say another signal like SIGINT
okay in which case we'd loop back up we notice that PID was still zero
and we go back into sigsuspend with with sigchild unblocked
okay so that makes sense to everybody
and now so this is exactly the behavior we want where we're not wasting resources but we've eliminated the race
okay so that's it for today if you're interested non non-local jumps are this weird thing and see
that allows a function to return to some other function that didn't call it
okay but it's described in your textbook and also in some additional slides here if you if you're interested