well hello everyone
interesting how far fewer seats are filled than at the beginning of the course
so that of course we're in the final stretch of this course
you're working on the last lab
and the material that we're covering both this lecture and next lecture are not on the exam
and you don't need them for your web so at some level you could just tune out and skip it all
and if your only purpose in taking this course is to pass it
or to get some grade in it and that's it well go ahead to now
but on the other hand the material we're talking about is very relevant to where computers are today
and where they're going in the future
and so if you think about the longer term
and whatever your investment is in the computer industry and computer technology is
then I think you'll find these very worthwhile
but so think of this more as the icing on the cake
you've learned the hard stuff you've you've done the grinding part
and now you get to think beyond the sort of narrow confines of the course material and and think bigger
but that's really the way you should be viewing this lecture in the last lecture which will be on Thursday
so today what we're going to talk about is parallelism
and the issue is that
that
Wow
that PowerPoint is a product made by a certain company in Seattle that
it's not always reliable but
the issue is as you know nowadays when you buy a computer you don't get just one CPU on the processor chip
you have at least two on a typical laptop
even my phone has two cores in it and as well as for graphic processing units
and a typical the the next generation of iPad will be a six core processor
so these have become not just the the sort of specialized domain of of high-end machines
but actually there all the time
and actually we'll talk some next time why is it that instead of having one fast computer
you get to a medium size medium performance processors on a chip or more
and that that's actually a really interesting technology issue that I'll talk about next time
but it's the way it is so you can think of it when you write a program
ah and it runs as a single thread
then you're basically not making use of the computing resources that you have available to you
so the natural thing is well could we make our programs run faster by doing multiple threads
so you've already learned
or you're in the process of applying a multi-threaded programming
as a way to
deal with a concurrency of external events
there's multiple clients  who want to make use of a server
and instead of serving one and then another and then another if you can handle them all
it's sort of a an external use of concurrency
but what we'll talk about today is more in internal use
can I make use of multiple threads running on multiple cores  to make a program run a single program run faster
and the message behind that is yes but
and what I mean is it is truly possible and people spend a lot of time making programs run faster by using multiple threads
but it's harder than you'd think it should be and
it's fraught with as you probably already experienced programming bugs
but also it's just really darn hard to get the kind of performance out of a multi-core processor
that you should would think it'd be available
so we'll talk about some of that
and then we'll finish it up a little bit understanding of
how how when you writing concurrent programs you want to think about the state of memory
and how that's a challenge for multi-core processors or in fact any concurrent concurrent system
so there's actually two sources of concurrency on a modern processor multiple cores
which is you have actually a multiple CPUs on a single chip
but there's also something called hyper-threading
which is in my experience less useful
but let me go through this
so this is what a typical modern processor looks like processor chip
is that there's actually on a single chip
there's multiple independent CPUs
and each of them has some part of the cache hierarchy
which is private to that particular core
and then there is another part of the cache hierarchy that's shared across cores
and then they all have a common interface to main memory
so if these cores are running and this is what happens a lot is
they're running programs that are completely independent have nothing to do with each
other then they more or less just exist and run and they're happy as can be
they are caching parts of their own state
and you know sometimes this cache will get polluted by the junk from other programs in terms of performance
but it will matter with functionality
the trick when you're trying to do multi-core programming as a parallel computing thing
somehow getting all these cores working on parts of different parts of a single problem in a way that
makes it so that you get the performance out of it
they don't spend all their time basically arguing with each other about who has access to what
and also they're not stepping over each other and messing up each other's state
so hyper threading is a little bit more into the deep works of how a processor operates
you'll recall from the lecture on a performance or what's chapter 5 of the book
that a modern microprocessor looks absolutely nothing like the model that you get by looking at assembly code instructions
the model of assembly code is you execute one instruction
then you execute the next one then you execute the next one
modern prostitutes don't do that at all
they haven't done it for well they haven't done it that way for 30 years
and since 1995 so since 20 years
they do it in this totally different way
which is sometimes referred to as out of order processing and  so just real quickly
but the basic idea is on the processor chip there's multiple functional units that are capable of doing different types of operation
there's ones for integer arithmetic these ones for floating-point arithmetic  and so forth
and then there's separate blocks that interface to the memory actually to the cache memories
and they're both loading meaning reading from the memory and storing writing out to memory
but these units are sort of operate independently
and what happens is there's a block of logic which is actually enormous with huge block of logic in an x86 processor
that reads the instructions out of the instruction stream
rips them apart into little pieces keeps track of data dependencies and control dependencies
and then schedules all the various operations in your program  on these different functional units
so we talked some about that of in the context of how can you write up program that will sort of maximize
how much is going on down here  by writing your code in a particular ways
so all this is an introduction to say
this is how you have to understand what hyper threading is
so in a single execution mode there's basically one instruction decoder
and it has its own set of state here its own program counter
its own queue of operations that it's already decoded and haven't completed yet
it has its own set of registers they're actually not registers like you'd expect they're they're highly virtualized registers
but all this state is there to help to service the execution of one thread of execution
with hyper threading basically what you do is
the idea that is to say 90% of all programs don't really make use of all these functional units
especially if you're blocking on a load
because there's a miss in a cache
then all these arithmetic units are sitting there without anything useful work to do
oh and so why don't we just double up
or quadruple upper K times up
the state associated with the decoding and control parts of the program
so that you can have multiple threads running
and sharing these functional units among each other
so they're operating really independently their states are not intertwined
but they're sort of making more use of the available hardware for performing functions
and so that's called hyper threading that's an Intel term
you also sometimes hear call SMT simultaneous multi-threading
and in my experience and we'll see here the numbers
it doesn't really make that big a difference
but it turns out to be in the sort of large picture things
a relatively inexpensive feature for them to throw on to processors and so they do
and so nowadays at least with an x86 processor usually have to weigh hyper-threading in them
so given that if you look at our shark machines which are a little bit old there's sort of 2010 era machine
but they were high-end machines in their day
and so they still actually are more powerful than
what you'd buy as say a desktop and way more powerful than as a laptop  that you'd get today
so they're actually pretty decent machines
and actually we'll talk next time about why computers aren't a lot faster than they were five years ago
that's actually an interesting technology thing
so that they their server class machines so they have multiple cores
and they have eight of them which is a lot you can buy ten core machines x86 machines on a single chip
but I don't think you can get more yet
so these were fairly advanced machine of their day
and they also have two-way hyper threading
so in theory
you should be able to get sixteen independent threads running
sort of 16 Way parallelism potentially out of a program
if you can keep everything working and keep bad things from happening
so let's give a really trivial application one that should be very simple to make run in parallel
that says imaginary we want to sum up the numbers between 0 and n-1
which is by the way a really stupid thing to do because there's a very simple closed-form formula for it
which is good in the sense it will let us check our work
but it's a completely stupid application
but it just shows you this idea
and so what we're just going to do is is block off
if we have n way parallelism we're just going to split our range of numbers n ways
and just have a single threads sum up one n of the numbers
and then they'll collectively sum together the result  in some way or another
so this is about as easy a parallel program as you could imagine
so let's do a 1 version which is said well gee I understand how to use threads
P threads and I know about these things called semaphores or mutual exclusion
so what I'll do is just all I'll have one place in memory
where I'm collecting the sum over all n values
and for a thread to be able to add to that
if it will lock it it will get a mutual exclusive access to it  increment it and then unlock it
and we'll just let all the threads go helter-skelter locking and unlocking this
so the code for that's pretty easy to write it
it's a here's the the code of course all threaded code looks a lot messier than you think it should but
in the end it's a fairly straightforward code
so in particular
this is the thread routine is
passing through this weird Varg pea structure that you do with with threads
the way you pass arguments to a thread routine
but basically it's figuring out where is the start and end range of the numbers
then adding for all i between the start before the end
I'll lock that acquire a semaphore lock
I'll increment this global sum and then I'll release the lock
okay so pretty much the style of code that you've been working with
and what you find is actually this is really a bad idea
so running as a single thread
it takes 51 seconds to do that
it would be by the way if you didn't lock and unlock because it's only one thread
you'd blow this away it would take just a couple seconds so
and then you see as you add more threads it actually gets worse
and especially if you jump from one to two
you increase by a factor nine how much time  it takes
and it always starts to get better as you get up into eight threads and then it gets worse again
so the reason is that locking  unlocking is a very time-consuming task
and basically you can think of is that you if you have that map of the multi-core processors with all their private caches in one shared cache
these threads are basically fighting with each other for control for that one memory address
that they that they're incrementing
and it has to grab the control away from one core to your the core
that's accessing it do the lock unlock
and then it gets grabbed back for it so it's a miserable performance for cache
huge overhead for the semaphore activities
and just really a bad thing all around
and so lesson one is semaphores or mutexes are very expensive
and if you're trying to do low level parallelism
you don't want fine-grained locking at that level otherwise
you're just completely sunk
and so that's not the way to do it
I won't go into it but there's quite a bit of literature about what they call lock free synchronization
which is a way to avoid semaphores but get the effect
and they wouldn't work in this context either those
just if you've ever heard that term
those are generally designed for
examples where you expect relatively little contention  between the threads
and so you try and be optimistic and then roll back if something bad happens
this is a case where nope
all those threads are going to be pounding that one memory location and they're really fighting for it
and so there is no good solution to that problem
the other thing I'll point out is this jump here shows you that
hyper threading isn't really helping us here
going from the fact that we slowed down from 8 to 16
means we can't really make use of 16 threads in this application
8 threads are better than 4
but obviously all that's kind of a waste of time because this is just really a bad idea all around
so
let's do something different
let's have each of them accumulate their own sum for their own sub range
and we'll give up so we'll have an array of accumulators
where the each thread is incrementing only a one element of this array
so they're not fighting with each other directly for it
but they are fighting for if you think about it for the same cache line
because an array is typically stored and so it's not totally nice
ah but this it gives you a pointer to this idea
if if we could sort of move into a private state
the stuff that we're making the most direct access to
then we'll get better performance
so this is the thread routine
and that the point is that there's some global array called pesum
but it's only incrementing the the part of it that sort of assigned to this particular thread
and here you do see a performance improvement right
so one thread takes 5 seconds remember before it was 58
so that shows you just the advantage of the cost of semaphores right
there is a factor of 10
and you see you are actually getting an improvement all across the line including up to 16 threads
you're still getting an improvement
it would flatten out should have just shown the number 432
but it would flatten out at this point
but it actually is getting some advantage out of hyper-threading as well
so that's good it's not an amazing speed up
so you can think of what they call the speed up is the performance of it running on a single core  versus the performance on n cores
and in the ideal case it goes n times faster
and we're not quite hitting that
well but here's you've already learned that it's generally bad to be accumulating into a memory
and so why not do the thing we learned before
which is you accumulate in a register and you only update the memory when you're done with that
so let's just do that and I'll call that the local version
I'll just increment a sum which is a local variable
and only when I'm done
then I'll store it in the global array
okay so it's functionally equivalent to the one we just showed
we're just moving instead of accumulating in a global array we're accumulating in a register
and here you see a pretty big performance improvement
so blue is what we showed with the the global array red or orange is  what's this local variable
and so you see it's actually interesting we're getting a performance improvement
as well although it bottoms out at eight
and it actually gets worse when you go to sixteen
and this is showing that hyper-threading isn't really helping here
because basically the the single thread is just accumulating
as fast as it can and adding to a register
and so it's making pretty good use of what functional units it uses and putting multiple threads
sharing it isn't really helping
at least not on the shark machines
this actually might be different on different machines
and actually if you recall from the performance optimization we found that if you're just doing a bunch of additions
you can make use as associativity and get more accumulation in parallel
so you could actually speed up this program just the single threaded version of this program pretty well
but anyways it shows it okay this is starting to look like
your your a your single threaded performance is pretty good and B
you're getting some useful speed-up out of parallelism
but as I said this is like the easiest example in the world to parallelize so if you can't do it here
then then life is pretty hopeless as far as multi-threading
so let's talk about as I mentioned this idea of speed-up
so speed-up is just defined to be the time for a single-threaded program
divided by the time for for P threads running
or actually will use it P cores instead of P threads question
[student speaking]
yes generally the scheduler has some kind of go balancing built into it
and it will tend to especially in a case like this where the threads are sort of grabbing and running
making they will generally get spread across the the cores
so that's a pretty the Linux scheduler is pretty good at
that when you have more threads than there are  cores
then then it basically starts scheduling them  in some cyclic order
and you you won't you'll
at best you will not get any advantage
and in a worst case you actually start slowing down from having more threads than are
there good question
so there's really two versions of speed-up
one is if I take my multi-threaded routine and run it with one thread
and then I met do it with P threads or cores
I can get a speed-up
but actually the truer thing is if I take the best-known sequential algorithm for performing this task
with the best implementation of that
and then I compare it against my parallel one
and so that's referred to as absolute speed-up
which is the the best measures you know you give both sides the opportunity to do the best implementation that
they can and then you compare it
and then what's referred to as the efficiency is
how close to the speed-up get to the ideal speed-up which is if I'm running on P cores
I should be P times faster
and you'll see that we're
you know the question of hyper-threading versus not we're sort of here we're saying no you don't
we're not trying to gain from hyper-threading
you can play this game various ways and you can argue back and forth
whether hyper-threading should count
so for P is P the total number of possible threads or the total number of cores
it's really a something to argue back and forth about
so the point is the efficiency though is is measured as how much do we do relative to ideal
and so this is what you get for this code the local version of P some
you'll see that our efficiency numbers are   somewhere in the hi somebody range
which is good but not great
it's pretty good actually if you can get 75 percent efficiency
you're doing better than most but again that's because this should have been the world's easiest program to parallelize
so and the best speed-up we're getting is a factor of six out of eight course so
again that's pretty good but this really should be something you can do well
so that just gives you a flavor of what parallel computing can be
so now it's sort of back off and talk some general principles just like the speed-up
there's a fella named Jean nom Dahl who coincidentally just died a few weeks ago
he might have seen it in the news
he was one of the original pioneers at IBM in their mainframe computers
then then at some point he in the 60s
he started his own company called um dal computers
and they were like they were the the cool company in mainframe computers
if that could ever be considered cool right
and he built a competitor's to IBM that absolutely drove them crazy
because they had a virtual monopoly they actually were subject to antitrust suit
so um Dahl was a sort of the the rebel who broke away from the mother company and started a competitor
and he made this very simple observation that's called Alma's dolls law
which is basically junior high level algebra to think of this
but it's actually a fairly perceptive point
about what's the possible benefit of speeding up something
and this is discussed in the book
you know this isn't just for computers it's any process that you want to speed up
and it's a very simple observation which is suppose there's some fraction of a system
that I can make go faster and I'll call that fraction P
P is some number between zero and one point zero right  100% 0%
and let's suppose we take that part that we're going to make run faster
and improve its performance by a factor okay
then we can just very simply talk about what will be the benefit of that performance
so we'll call it T sub K
and what it says is the fraction P  of the time will be reduced by K
but the fraction that you can't change a one minus P will remain at its old time
and that's um dolls law that's it that's the whole thing
and one interesting measure
is what if K were infinity what if we had unbounded resources to speed things up
and what the observation is the best feed up you'll get is a 1-p
and so just think it this way if you have 10% of it that you can't change
the other 90% you make infinitely fast
then your performance improvement will be a factor of 10
that's really all it's saying right pretty straightforward idea
so this has sort of direct implications in
so the example is suppose that we can improve the performance of some system of 90% of it
and we can speed up by factor 9 and that number is chosen to make the numbers work out
then we'll get it best at 2x performance improvement
basically what it says is the part of the system that you can't speed up will become your bottleneck
and that's just the way it is
so the implications for this repair while programming are fairly obvious
that if we can take our application and chop off some fraction of it
and make it run K times faster by running it on K cores
then the part of it that's still running sequentially will come to will limit the ultimate performance
we can get so that's not really an issue for this summation problem
because it really does divide into as many independent tasks
as as you have numbers and
as you can see you can make them run
but many other applications do some part of it that I can't really make know parallel
so just as an example and just for the sake of this class
you know an example of a little bit more involved a problem in parallel programming and multi-threading
let's think about sorting a bunch of numbers
so we have n numbers and we want to sort them
and we have some number of threads
that we can do this with is there way we can speed this up
and you think about it's not that clear how you do it
there's actually a vast literature in parallel sorting
and those you've taken or won't take the class 210 will be exposed to a lot of this
but I'm just going to do a very simple version which is quicksort
so quicksort is for example the
the C library program Q sort quicksort it was invented in the early 1960s or 1950s by a guy named Tony Hoare
who also founded a lot of the fundamental logic of program
so he's like an amazing person still alive today lives in Cambridge England
but if you ever have a chance to go to a talk by him do so he's amazing person
anyways the idea quicksort is very simple and this is sort of the basic sorting algorithm
you grab some element from the array that you're trying to sort
that's called the pivot
and then you split the data so that you look at the elements that are either greater or less than the pivot
and potentially also equal let's just assume all the elements are unique here
so you just split it into two piles one is the lesson once a greater
now you creatively you recursively you sort those two piles
by the same method and when it's all done you end up with everything sorted
one nice thing about it is it can be done in place meaning if you have an array of data
you can do this all just by swapping elements around and not have to use any extra space
which you would for example with merge sort
so this is a fairly simple algorithm and just to visualize it then
you have some block of data X array and you want to sort it
so you pick an element called the pivot and there's various strategies for doing that
and now you just subdivide X into three parts
L the left hand R the right hand meaning less and greater than P
and then you place P in the middle
and then you recursively when you're doing this for in a sequential code
you'll pick one of these two usually leftmost or rightmost whatever doesn't really matter
and you'll recursively you apply the same method to to the left side and
and ultimately after enough recursions you get to the point where L has been sorted
and that's shown in this kind of a swishy color thing
and call that L
and same with
you'll do the same thing now with the right hand side
and when you're done this is usually done in place
so you just the L part works on one array part of the array and the are part on another
and when you're done they're in sorted order
the very simple sort and generally has very good performance
so this is what the code for it looks like which is usually you have is a special case
if there's only one or two elements
and then you do this partitioning
so this routine of splitting it between the left and the right hand part is handled by a function called partition
and then if there's more than one element in the left side
you sort that and if there's more than one element in the right hand side you sort that
and then when all these recursions are done then the array is sorted
so pretty typical code and we won't go in the trickiest part writing the code is
how do you make this partitioning go fast
but I won't go into that just imagine it happens
so this algorithm actually has a natural version of parallelism
which is in my sequential version I was sorting both first the left
and then the left of the left and the left of the left of the left and kind of working my way
until I got that whole array sorted
and then I was coming back and I was working on the right
and then the left part of the right and the left to the left to the right and blah blah blah
and doing these recursions because the way the codes written
right I am doing the full sort of the left-hand part
and only after that is sorted then I'm doing the complete sort of the right-hand part
so the point is it's it's an algorithm where I'm working just on one part of the array of the time
but there's a very natural recursion of parallelism here that says
okay I've got two parts they each need to be sorted
let me just fire off two threads and let them do with that
and that's the so it's what you call divide and conquer parallelism
it's a very natural kind of parallelism it shows up in this code
so basically I'll do the same thing as before all at
the top level will be a purely sequential process of partitioning
and but then assuming a partition comes up with some non-trivial split
then I will recursively begin fork off to threads
each of which will be responsible for the other and
so we'll sort of look like I'm working on the two parts in parallel
and eventually both sides will end up
now this picture isn't really quite true and that it looked makes it look like
they're all kind of synchronized together and I'm doing a you know kaboom down like this
in a strict way but in fact they're not it's very asynchronous
the left part is one thread the right is another
they just go at their own pace and at the end I'm just going to wait for it all to complete
but there's no strict temporal ordering on how that all occurs
so the way I'll write this in the code is available on the course website
I'm only going to show you a glimpse of it
it's a non-trivial amount of code it takes to do it
but basically what I'm going to do is have a bunch of a pool of threads
that are ready to work and that's a pretty typical way you write threaded code
because actually the the initiation of a thread is a non-trivial amount of computation
so usually what you do is
you say I've got this many cores
I'm going to create a set of that many threads
and they will each work by sharing a task queue
so some agent that is a forking off work for the different threads to do
they will do the work assigned to them when that's complete they'll come back and say ok I'm ready for something new
and it will give them something new
so I've there's a little bit of code a very rudimentary code there of creating this task model and task scheduling
so the basic rule will be any given task
any given thread then at any given time has been assigned sub sub range of this array  to be a sorting
and it will be specified by the base meaning the starting point of this particular range
and then the number of elements that it's a told it's sort
and one other thing I'll do is
once I get down to this array being small enough
I'll just sort it sequentially
and and we'll see how big that block is or not is actually performance
parameter that you can use for tuning the program
so the point is that you don't want to take this down too far
because the the sort of overhead of threads is enough that
when you get to fine-grained you're actually going to start losing performance
so assume that it's bigger than that I've been given some block there
what I'll do then is I'll run the partition step
this thread will run it a partition step just using the exact function  I showed you or didn't show you
and then as long as and then I will us create and add to the task queue two new tasks
a one de for the left part and one for the right part
and then the scheduler that will assign two threads to handle those two parts
and so that code will that's exactly how the code is going to work
it's going to keep reusing the same threads over and over again
to but at any given time they'll be given a range of places
what typically will happen is they'll run their partitioning step
and then say okay I've done my job now assigned to new to new threads to do this
and that's the general scheme of it or they'll say this is a small enough block
I'm just going to sort the darn thing
okay so that's really all the code does it's online
if you're interested in this kind of stuff it's um I think it's pretty well written code because I wrote
it so this is sort of that the
somewhat simplified version of the code say
initialize my task queue scheduling system
create global variables of describing the beginning and end of this array to be sorted create a new task queue
and then this is the main function the TQ sort helper
is given some range of  of addresses and a pointer to the task queue
that's used to manage these tasks
and then uh
when it's all day we'll just wait till all the tasks have completed this is at the top level
this isn't part of any recursion this is the top level code
and then it will free up the data structures
and then this is the the part of it that actually does the real work
it will say so now the TQ sort helper is the part
that's a scientists to sort some particulars poises from
the the starting address the base and some number of elements
and so this is what each task will do
and it says okay if this is a small enough block of elements
I'm just going to call my serial quicksort to do it
otherwise I'm going to
oh it's a little bit Messier this okay
now otherwise it's going to spawn a task to do the sorting
let's see
I was a little mixed up this is a high level
so the actual splitting occurs in this thing which is where it
so this is the actual thread routine
and what it's saying is run the partition here
and then call this TQ sort helper which you just saw on the left and the right parts
of it so just to review then the actual spawning of a task is done by this helper routine
but then that what it calls is the the thread routine is
what does the work here and what it will do is
it will do the partitioning within that thread
and then it will just throw back and add to the task queue two calls to this helper
but as that kind of so between these two routines you can see it's doing this idea of a divide and conquer parallelism
so this is a performance running on the shark machines
and this is a fairly straightforward I'm just taking some number of random value two to the thirty-seventh
that can't be right
finish this is numbers not to the thirty-seventh right you agree with me
to the 37th is 128 billion roughly
so this number is not right I'll have to check it out
and now what this x axis
so the y axis just denotes how long does it take to complete
by the way one thing if you're used to measuring performance based on CPU time
that's not useful when you're talking a parallel computing you really want to talk a elapsed time
the time that you'd get from looking at a clock  and measuring it and dealing with whatever inefficiency occurs
there so these are actually the elapsed run time of the entire program
and you'll see that it varies according to this thing called the serial fraction
the serial fraction is just at what point do I slide between a serial quicksort  or keep dividing
so how big does the array need to be
as a fraction expressed as a fraction of the original array
before I I will go into recursion
if I were actually to write this a real application I wouldn't do it based on a fraction
I'd do it based on a block size to say  anything smaller than a thousand elements or some number like that
but this code just happens to be expressed this way
but the thing to notice that's interesting is you'll see here
if the fraction is 1 it basically says I won't split this at all
I'm just going to call a sequential quicksort
so this is a purely sequential version of it
and what it shows is if I once I start -
I'll be willing to sort of split this up and do parallelism
I start making run faster and faster and faster
I'll and then I get into this trough
and now if I start going finer and finer grain then I'm running into the problem
where the thread overhead is more than the advantage I'm getting by doing the parallelism
and I'm faster to run that block bigger sort just use a sequential algorithm rather than parallel
but the good news here is this is a pretty long trough here
so it means is if you're trying to tune this program
it's not that hard you're not going to pay a huge penalty if you don't know a parameter exactly
so as long as this is a huge range right 30 from a 32 to 4096
it's a factor of of a lot to the fifth and 2 to the 12th is 2 to the 7th fact 128
see how I do my arithmetic and powers at 2
anyways it's roughly at you know 128 so several orders of magnitude decimal orders of magnitude over which
you get pretty comparable performance
so that means from a performance tuning point of view it's not that hard to do
and you also see we're getting a pretty decent speed up
on our eight core to a hyper-threaded machine
we're getting up basically out 7x performance
and hyper-threading really isn't helping us at all is part of the lesson here
but if you just think of it as eight cores then that's pretty good
so there is an obvious place here where there's  a Nam Dolls law issue going on
if you think at that first top-level split
the first call to partition is being done over the entire Ray by a serial sequential process
right that
so at the very least that is not going parallel at all there's going exactly one thread is doing the initial partition
and then that splits into two so at most you have two threads worth of parallelism
and then the next level down at most four
and so you really don't you have to get several levels of recursion down
before you're really running on all the course that you have available
so you'd think that that's limiting your speed up and
it does and that's part of the reason why our best performance is
a factor of seven and not a factor of eight or more
so there's quite a bit of work as I mentioned on how to speed up performance including how to make quicksort go faster
so there's a vast body of literature on parallel sort
so one thing I tried was to say okay well let's try and do this partitioning
step they least the top couple levels let's try and do a parallel version of that and
so the idea is you pick one pivot element
but now you fire in this example for threads
and each of those four threads runs a partition step on on one-fourth of the range
and it don't generate their own versions of left and right
and then you globally figure out how many are in each of these sub ranges
and then you tell each thread okay now you copy your part of it over to the relevant section of the array
but the good news so there's some amount of synchronization that goes on there
but you can imagine that this partitioning step
once when you're running it is completely independent of across the different threads
so it's getting a almost ideal speed-up
so I implemented this and tried and I couldn't make it run faster than the original code
and I think the the problem with this was  the copying the cost of copying data
here was even though it's being done by multiple threads
and getting pretty good performance out of the memory system
because you're doing sequential you know all the cache issues are pretty good here
but that's just enough extra work
that has to be done for this parallel code that doesn't have to be done
the sequential code is totally in place
meaning not using any additional storage not copying
and so that's just enough of a penalty on the parallel part
that it didn't really improve performance at all
so that code is shown as part of the code on the course website
but like I said I I banged on it quite a bit and trying to tune it
and squeak it in various ways and could never make it
so I got better overall performance out of this program
and so that's again a lesson and that's one of the unfortunate lessons is you can spend a lot of time
trying to make a program run faster  and get absolutely nowhere
and it's frustrating because you put in a lot of work
and you know it's a pretty cool idea and you'd love to publish a paper about it or tell your friends about it
and it just goes nowhere and it just sits there
there's nothing unfortunately there's not an accumulated repository of the bad ideas of computer science
don't waste your time trying this
that people can talk about so
this is just a lesson to learn
so anyways that was my experience with that
again other people have spent a lot more time this is one of the most common applications
that people try to do parallel programming for
so some of the lessons from this is you need a good strategy
for how you're going to get parallelism out of your application
and I showed you two basic versions one is partitioned into K parts
they're more or less completely independent of each other
or something like a divide and conquer strategy where you can keep splitting it
but the two splits that you create out of that can go concurrently
these other different types of parallelism -
in general you want to make the inner loops you can't have any synchronization primitives
in there it will just run too slow
um dolls law as I mentioned is always sort of lurking in the background of
if you can always feed up a part of your program then the other part will become the bottleneck
but the other thing is like I said you can do it
you've got the tools you've learned with with P threads
and your knowledge of programming and your understanding of cache memories and things like that
you've got the tools you need to be an effective programmer of this kind of thing
but you have to and there's nothing that beats sort of trial and error and testing and tuning experimenting
if there's some parameters that need to be set
then you want to run experiments will sweep through the parameters to try and figure out
what the setting should be
so that's sort of a little bit about parallel programming
let me just finish this lecture with a little bit of sort of classic issues about concurrency
that that are critical when you're dealing with
these systems based on what you call a shared memory model of computation
so multi-core is an example of conceptually multi-threaded computation remember
you're you're working within a single virtual address space
and you have private stacks
but the more global the heap memory is completely shared across threads
and so that's what you call the shared memory programming model
and that's what we've really been looking at this course
so there's a certain interesting question about called memory consistency models
and here I'll illustrate it with a very simple example
imagine we have two global variables a and B
and we have two different threads
and so the first thread is going to write meaning assign a value to a
and it's going to read meaning print the value of B
and the other thread is going to do the opposite it's going to write assigned a value to B and print the value of a
and so now the question is what are the possible outputs for this program
and so there's a model that sort of the accepted standard called sequential consistency
which means that these events can occur
well that these that within a single thread things have to occur in the sequential order of that thread
but across threads whether write a a write B occurs first is completely arbitrary
and similarly whether writing of B occurs
between these two actions or before is all too arbitrary
so what what it means is you can take two different threads
and you can interleave there their events  in anyway
but you should be able to pull out of that interleaving
the sequential order of either of both of the two threads
so when you do that you end up you can enumerate in the example like this
all the possibilities you can say well look it
first is either going to be right a or right B
let's pick right a
so now the next event will be either a read of B or write of B
and then if I if I do write a write read B
then I've completed this thread
and so now the only possibility is to write to B and read a and so forth
you work out all the possible things you get six different event orderings
and then what will be printed is well first of all whether you print beer before a
would depend on the relative ordering of those two threads
so that's shown I'm showing the B value in blue
and the red value in in red the
I'm sorry the a value in red
and you'll get these different
possibilities these are all the six possible outputs of this program
but you'll see that there are two two other outputs one could imagine that won't arise
one is to print 101 in other words to have them both print
the original values of these two variables
and that's impossible because
I have to have done at least one right
before I can reach either of these two print statements right
so it's not possible for these to still be in their original values of
when I hit these print statements
and whichever order I hit these two
so those two are impossible
so that's the idea of sequential consistency that there's
some very large number but of possible outputs of a program
but in any case they can't violate
the ordering implied by the individual threads
so you'd say okay that seems like pretty obvious thing
but actually if you think from a hardware perspective it's not that trivial to make that happen
so let me just throw a show you a scenario of multi-core Hardware
that would violate sequential consistency
assume that each of our threads has its own private cache
and so if I execute this statement
what I'll do is I will grab a copy of a from
the main memory and bring it into my cache
and I will assign this new value to it
and similarly a thread to will grab a copy of its of B and and update that
and now if I do my two print statements
if thread two picks up the value from the memory
not knowing that thread one as a modified copy of that value  then it would naturally print one
and similarly if if thread one picked up a copy of B from main memory it would print 100
so we'd see exactly this unallowable execution and the reason is
because each of these threads have their own private copies of these variables
and they're not properly synchronized
but you could see in a hardware scenario it would be easy to build this hardware and make that mistake
so how does it work in a in a multi-core processor well
they have a trick they call it Snoopy caches
and it's a little bit like the readers writers of synchronization that
you're working on for your proxies
that you want to make it so that if everyone's just reading some shared value
they should be able to get copies into their own caches  to optimize the performance of it
but if one of them wants to write to it it needs to get an exclusive copy of it
and lock out any other thread
from accessing that either to read it or to write it from long enough to make the update
and so
they have a protocol where they tag actually and these tags are at the level of cache lines typically
so the tagged cache line in main memory with its state and the typical state would be invalid
it's shared oryx its exclusive
so shared means that there can be a copies of it but they can only be read-only copies
and exclusive meaning that it's exclusively available to a single thread
so this is built into them the hardware of a multi-core processor
so what will happen that is in order to do a write to a thread one will acquire an exclusive copy of this element
and that actually tagging happens down here at the main memory and in the cache both
oh and similarly if if thread two wants a to write to B
it must get an exclusive copy of that
and then when the read occurs what happens is actually this cache
miss will send out a signal on a bus a shared communication medium saying
I want to read a
and instead of the main memory responding to it actually it will
that result will be supplied by the other cache
and it will convert the state of this element to being a shared element
locally but you'll see that the main memory element isn't updated yet it
goes through the whole right-back protocol you've already seen
and sometimes it will update that there's different implementations
but this is why it's called a Snoopy cache is
that it basically thread two is is peeking into or getting it access to information
that's available in thread ones cache
and so now thread two will correctly get a copy of a
that's in this shared state
and the same goes would be it will snoop over and thread two will one will get a readable copy
these are now all marked as shared State
and so if if either of them want to write
they'd have to now basically get exclusive access to it
and that would have to then disable
the copy and the other in the other location
so you can imagine this protocol being non-trivial actually to get right and to implement
and it gets way more complicated than this with all the variations on it
so but it's become the norm in in multi-core hardware design
but it's actually part of the factor that limits  the core count on a processor
because just the hardware involved in keeping the consistency across the caches is non-trivial
it has to work very fast we're talking at the cash rate access speeds
so there's not a lot of time involved in there
so actually implementing this stuff making it run
making it scale across say eight cores 10 cores 16 cores is not a not a trivial thing
but that that goes on in the background and so you can for most systems nowadays you can assume that
there's some memory consistency model that you can program to that's supported by the hardware of the system
and that this serial serializability that's referred to as sort of the the easiest to understand
there's others at a little bit more nuanced
well guess that fell off the bottom here and doesn't seem right
that's it
okay so just to wrap that up then
it gives you a flavor of and
you can see that getting programs to run fast through multi-threading is not not easy
you often have to rewrite your application you have to think about the algorithm you have to worry about debugging
it as you've already discovered at both the
the shell web and the proxy lab that concurrency where you can't predict the order of events
makes it much more difficult to debug code
so all these factors come in
and you have to have some understanding of the underlying mechanisms that are used
and what their performance implications are
so in particular let me just observe here that
if I'm like doing synchronization
across threads like you saw that original one where they are fighting over this global
variable P 'some whatever it was called
you can imagine these the caches
in this battle with each other to try and get exclusive access to this single memory of value
and because each one is running as fast as it possibly can
but each one requires getting exclusive copy writing to it  and releasing it
so that locking mechanism is flying back and forth between these caches
and it's really not very fast so
that's the kind of thing is why
and also you know as an application programmer you're making calls semaphore call
bounces you up into the OS kernel which is a cost involved
so this thing has all the bad all the things that make programs not run the way you really like them to
so that's one of the challenges in parallel programming is how do you actually
make use of the parallelism that's there
without getting bogged down by the cost of the various mechanisms of control
oh so anyways this is part of what you have to appreciate and understand as a programmer
is how these things work at a level deep enough that you'll have some sense of what makes programs run faster or slower
where the mistakes could want
so that's just a little little flavor of a much bigger topic
so that's it for today