Hello everyone.
大家好
I'd like to welcome you all to this fall's this terms.
很高兴和大家在秋季学期见面。
Instance of this course is officially either 15 to 13 from computer science
这门课涵盖计算机科学15-18
or 18 to 13 from Electrical and computer engineering.
和18-13的电子还有计算工程。
But a large number of people enrolled in this course one calls 513 which is for graduate students.
但是很多同学通过513注册这门课程
And to be totally honest you're not supposed to be here
老实讲不赞成你们在这里。
An because you're supposed to watch the videos the lectures by video later.
因为你们应该稍后看视频课程。
But we're not checking any cards so I don't really know who you are.
但是我们将不会点名所以我不知道你是谁。
Oh anyways this course is as you can see a very popular course on campus.
另外正如你们所看到的这门课在校园里非常受欢迎。
We  are over 700. 700? 600 shouldn't exaggerate
我们有超多700个学生？600个应该不夸张。
Students on campus enrolled in one of those three versions of the course.
在校学生参加的三个版本的课程之一。
Which if you think about a university of the size of CMU that's like about 5% of total student population.
如果你考虑一下CMU的规模，这个数字大概占总学生数的5%。
So we're very glad to have you here and this games too.
我们很高兴你们能在这里。
I should let it begin.try that it's better.
我们应该开始了。试一下很好用。
My name is Randal E.Bryant.
我的名字是Randal E.Bryant。
And my co-instructor is Dave O'Hallaron.
我的合作导师是Dave O'Hallaron
And those names might be familiar if you have been in bookstore.
如果你去过书店可能会熟悉这些名字。
[laugh]Because the book was written by us.
因为这本书是我们两个写的。
We actually wrote this book we started 213 as a course in 1998.
我们其实从1998年213课程开始写这本书。
I know that you are children and all that stuff.
我知道你们那时还是小孩。
But out of response for a new type of course that you'll see today.
但是你将会看到新课程的反响。
That sort of giving people a in-depth understanding of systems.
这种让人们对系统有深入的了解。
But more from a high level or programmers perspective.
更多的是从更高的层面和程序员的角度。
And we'll talk some about the philosophy of the course later.
之后我们会谈论这门课的哲学。
So this book as you see just came out its third edition last March and that's the required text for the course.
正如你们所看到的这本书三月（2015）第三版才刚刚出版，这也是课程所需要的。
And there is nothing you can do to avoid buying that book.
所以你没有办法避免购买课本。
And it's not because we're greedy I actually we take the money we get from royalty for students in this course or
不过我们更愿意将这门课课本的稿费
Any CMU course and we donate it to CMU.
或者CMU的其他课程的稿费捐赠给CMU。
So we're not actually making any money out of you buying the book.
所以我们实际上并没有从你购买这本书中赚钱。
But it's a simple reality that the new version is different than the old we expect you to be using the new version.
但是，新版本与旧版本有很大不同，我们希望你们使用新版本。
there are no electronic copies there are no pirated versions so you basically have to buy the book.
没有电子版本，没有盗版，所以你基本上不得不买书。
I don't really apologize for that because I know you or your parents who somebody's paying a lot of money for you to be here and
我并不真正道歉，因为我知道你或你的父母有人为你付出了很多钱，
So the price of the book is really a relatively small amount relative to that.
所以这本书的价格实际上是一个相对较小的数额
And this course by the way is not some courses serious.
顺便说一下这个课程不是一些课程严重。
Oh yeah this book you might want to look at it once in a while but actually the course has nothing to do that.
或许你想在课上看一看这本书，但最好在上课不要这么做。
This course the book and the course are one they're very tied together.
课本和这门课非常紧密的联系在一起。
There'll be parts of the book that we don't go into all the details that are in the book sometimes.
本书的一些部分我们并没有详细介绍书中的所有细节。
But we expect you to be able to figure it out.
但我们希望你能弄清楚
And so really the course in the book are tied together and they very much the progress of the course.
所以书中的课程是紧密联系在一起的，而且这也是课程的巨大进步。
The topics covered how it's covered everything about it is consistent with the book.
这些话题涵盖了如何涵盖它的一切与本书是一致的。
we wrote the book because of the course think of them as course notes.
我们写这本书是因为这门课，将它视为这门课的笔记。
so and the reason why we are teaching this term by the way we haven't taught together in several years.
我们已经交授这门课很多年了，这也是为什么我们在这个学期使用这种方式授课的原因。
But because this is the first roll out of this book and not only is it being used here but it's actually used by about 250 schools around the.
但是因为这本书第一次推向市场，它不仅仅在这里使用，全世界大概有250学校也在使用这本书。
And many of those people are also going through the same activities of teaching from this new edition for the first time.
而且这些人中的很多人也是第一次从这个新版本开始进行相同的教学活动。
And so we wanted to make sure all the material for the course was sort of put in order and things.
因此我们要确保课程的所有内容都是按顺序排列的。
Because other universities and other colleges use this material...this supporting material we've developed.
因为其他大学或学院使用这些资料...我们开发的参考资料。
so that's the course and today is the first election we're sort of doing a tag team here
I'll talk the high level what the course is about what the main themes are and Dave will talk more about the logistics
so we refer the the saying we have that when
the very first time I typed the number of this course into a text editor I realized
I've typed those five digits many times in my career because it's the zip code of CMU one five two one three.
so that's where we come up with the same.
so there's a few things about this course for the most part you know in your normal undergraduate curriculum.
when you've learned programming you've been very much separated from the realities of the Machine.
you you just think about code just you put some text into some little box somehow.
and outcomes of behavior that it hopefully is what you intended the program to do .
the purpose of this course is to give you enough understanding of what that box is doing when it executes your code.
and through that to help you become better at what you're trying to do.
so some of the outcomes is there's really two types of outcomes from this course.
one is that if this is the only systems course you ever take in your whole life.
you will get useful material from it you will learn tools tricks methods that will help you.
if you ever are in involved in software development large-scale.
software engineering projects systems hardware design any aspect of of computer technology.
this will help you be better at what you do.
you'll understand what programs do how they work what the machines that support them do.
why sometimes they work really well and why sometimes they don't work so well.
well it also is intended as it's sort of stepping stone into a whole number of other courses at CMU.
that will give you more in-depth understanding of computer technology.
but our sort of specialized by topical area whether it's computer networking or operating systems or embedded systems.
where you'll take the sort of ideas from this course and be able to then learn in a somewhat narrower but deeper sense what's really going on .
and so it really is trying to serve those two goals of making you more effective giving you useful ideas and tools right away.
but also preparing you for later courses.
so we talked about this is sort of what's why what kind of stuff will you learn from this course.
it is to go through a series of what we call great realities places where sort of computers meet up.
real-life computers get meet up against your expectations and maybe they're not quite the same.
so one of them is and the first part of the course is going to take a fairly detailed look at.
how numbers are represented in computers and you'll learn some things.
that are on one hand surprising and another hand will start to make sense when you understand it better.
so a simple case is four numbers.
I don't know when it was but it was probably in about eighth grade algebra.
that I learned that if you square a number it will be at least zero  if it's not an imaginary number.
so a either an integer or a real number you'd expect to square it and it to be a positive value or perhaps zero right.
and that's actually generally true with floats a representation of floating-point number.
but with integers or int you know the computer representation of integers it's not so clear.
so for example a few square 40-thousand on most computers then you'll get whatever that should be as you'd expect.
but what if you square 50,000 so you could do this in your head but I actually built into this laptop computer.
so I'm going to go ahead and use it.
amm...
and use a tool which on UNIX systems is called...
Linux systems is called GDB but on Macintosh OS X it's called LLDB they're pretty much the same program.
you will get to know this program really really well this term.
so like I said a few square 40-thousand.
you get
what you'd expect
but let's change this to 50,000.
and you get a very peculiar number that doesn't look anything like you'd expect 50,000 squared to be and in fact it's negative.
and so that might just seem like well there must be a mistake or something no that's.
that's just the way it is because this computer is expecting numbers to be represented as 32-bit values
and the bit pattern that you get when you do this multiplication happens to be the representation of a negative number.
so that's a an example of where your normal expectations about integer arithmetic may or may not hold.
on the other hand...there are some places...
like if I try to do the same thing multiplying 300 by 400 by 500 by 600.
then all of a sudden I also get a number that clearly is not what you'd expect because the same thing has happened.
I've gotten an overflow it happens that it's overflowed to a value that's positive not negative.
but it still is obviously not the integer product of those four numbers.
on the other hand one thing you'll find is even though this arithmetic is not a normal sort of integer arithmetic.
it actually has some well-behaved properties.
so for example if you look at...what I've done is I just moved the 300 around from the beginning of the product to the end of the product.
and so now if you think about how associativity and commutativity works.
I'm basically multiplying these four numbers in a different order.
but what you see is you get the same funny-looking result no matter how you do it.
it so what you can say from this is integer arithmetic is commutative and associative.
so it obeys some of the conventional mathematical properties.
it just isn't what you'd expect it to be it's not am a normal sort of mathematical integer arithmetic.
so the cartoon here shows an example that's a similar possibility we get to it.
oh I guess it comes at the end.
so then the next question is is a addition associative right can you order the the numbers.
and as you probably might have figured both in the integer arithmetic.
even though as this potential for overflow it is associative and it's commutative too.
but for floats it's not really quite the same.
because the range of values you can get in floating pointers so extreme that some numbers kind of disappear on you.
so the example I'll show without having to use a computer to do it.
it is if you take a big number and subtract it from itself.
you'll get zero so if you add that to 3.14 you'll get 3.14.
but if you take those two numbers and you reorder the...
how you combine them so that that 3.14 compared to -1e20 is so insignificant.
that that result gets turned into -1e20.
and you add that to 1e20 and you end up with zero  so it's not associative.
and so what you see is the both these number systems have some peculiarities.
and it all comes down to the fact that they use finite representations of things that expanse.
so there's some compromises in how those work.
and what the compromise is you can overflow an integer and run out of room.
and in floating point numbers you have roundoff problems where you sort of drop the digits.
that are significant you can also overflow floating point but the more common problem is roundoff .
so this is shown in this cartoon this idea of overflow of somebody counting sheep.
which in the u.s. is in English language at least a way to fall asleep and when he or she goes from 32,767.
and then increment set by one gets -32,768.
and we'll see exactly why that happens but basically the numbers are going.
up to the larger value can represent and then when it goes one more it becomes a negative number.
so these are really important under things to understand I mean.
90% of the time maybe you can just get by writing programs and not worrying about.
whether your numbers are going to exceed their possible range.
but they sometimes when this could be really important if you're like you know controlling a rocket.
you really don't want the positive thrust to become negative or something like that.
so you can see you there this could be an important consideration.
similarly there's well-known instances of security vulnerabilities.
where somebody wrote code that sort of expected a positive number in some place.
a clever person figured out if I supply a negative number I can fool the system and give it to do bad things
so these are the kind of corner cases that you need to understand better.
if you're either working in programs where it's really really important that it worked correctly.
or you're really worried about security vulnerabilities.
anytime you have possible four corner cases you have to understand these nuances better.
similarly for floating-point if you're going to use floating-point for serious computation.
whether it's scientific research or for designing bridges or nuclear power plants or something .
you better understand what the characteristics are.
so that's our first one and we'll spend a couple weeks talking about numbers.
number of representations and their properties here
the second is we're going to spend a lot of time in this course learning about machine level programming meaning.
what the instructions are that actually get executed by the computer.
and that can be described in assembly language which is a text version of it.
or an object code which is the actual bit level binary encoding of instructions.
and we'll learn a fair bit about that and spend a fair amount of time seeing.
how code that you write in C gets turned into machine code and how that gets executed on the machine.
one thing I'll say is it historically courses like this would teach assembly code by having you write.
programs in assembly that do various things not usually very interesting.
because it's a lot of work to write assembly program.
this course is much more about taking the assembly code that's been generated by a compiler.
A C compiler and looking at it and understanding it that's a different set of skills than you need to write it on your own.
in particular we're going to look at the language of of Intel processors
the most recent versions of them are called x86-64 the 64-bit version of their instruction set .
and one thing that's new in this course compared to previous ones
we used to teach 32-bit stuff.
this course is 64 bits all the time.
another one that we'll talk about a fair amount that is really fairly visible to programmers surprisingly visible is
it's aspects of the memory system so modern computers have a very complex.
layered memory system to try give you to hight performance in high capacity at the same time.
and there's some results of that system that can mean that.
if you program write a program well it might work really well.
if you don't it could run very poorly because it's not making use of this hierarchical memory system.
so and also there's a lot of bugs that show up especially in C programs.
that have to do with memory referencing errors and so understanding.
what those errors are what their manifestation is how to prevent them as a big part of the course.
so for example if I define a struct that contains a two integer values A in an array.
and a double precision floating point number d.
and if I this function fun you'll see what it does is it's given an argument i.
and it sets the element of a to some strange-looking value.
so as you know I should really only be either 0 or 1 with this code.
because that's the range of possible values of this array a.
but we can try other things too so...
in particular if you run it on either one or two you'll get what you'd expect.
that you assigned a 3.14 to element D of this structure.
and when you read it back you get the same thing.
and in fact but now if I set a of two to this number.
all of a sudden you'll see that my floating number.
which seems to have nothing to do with a has changed
and if I do that same thing with
I equal to three you'll see I get a number that's closer to two then to 3.14.
and if I keep going well nothing much happens util.
I hit six and then the program crashes.
so something interesting is going on here.
at least something quirky is going on.
and the reason is again it has to do with how data is laid out in memory and
how its accessed and one of the features of C and C++ .
it doesn't do any bounds checking on a race it will happily let you reference .
element number five million of a two element array and not complain.
but the operating system might complain as it did here.
and it in this particular structure and we'll see more about how structures are implemented and weighed out.
but basically the two if each of these uh walks in this vertical chain represents four bytes.
so the two elements of a each are four bytes.
D is eight bytes and then there's some other stuff in the other beyond them.
that's not actually in the structured. zone
so you'll see that if I reference either a[0] or a[1].
then I will just modify that array as designed.
but when I'm calling fun(2) or fun(3) what I'm actually doing is altering the the bytes that encode this number D.
and that's why you saw the sort of funny numbers come out it.
as I go up at some point when I hit 6.
I'm modifying some state of the program .
that it's using to kind of keep things organized most likely how it keeps track of allocated memory .
and that's causing the program to crash.
so this is a pretty good demonstration of a why C programming can drive you crazy.
because as you saw it doesn't do bounds checking so it's easy to write code that does invalid stuff .
it's also often the case that you'll cause some problem and
it has a sort of action a distance feature that you can modify some think you're modifying some data structure.
what you're doing because of the way things are organized in memory.
you're changing something totally unrelated somewhere else in the program you'd imagine they're not just one apart.
but they're 10,000 apart and things might just run fine for hours days or weeks.
and then always say at some point that data that got corrupted.
a long time ago gets accessed and something goes wrong.
so this can be some of the worst nightmare debugging nightmares.
that exists on earth is to try and figure out memory referencing errors.
so this is actually one argument not to program in C or C++ and it's a valid argument all.
but also as a person who's right in a lot of C programming.
you just get more experienced and you know at times that you should actually put bounds checking in your own code.
and there's also tools available that will help you sort of bullet proof your code so that it will detect these kind of problems.
so it's not like you have to change languages but it is a particular feature of these languages.
and so understanding sort of the Machine level representation of data structures and how they work is very really makes a huge difference
in your ability to deal with these kind of vulnerabilities and things of ulnar abilities by the way also from a security perspective.
the the fourth sort of theme we'll cover in the courses  getting performance out of programs.
other parts of the curriculum in CS do much more emphasis on getting the right algorithm at the right data structure.
and that's really well and good it's important stuff I don't deny it.
but they some amount of the sort of low-level optimization that you need to do.
that you need to understand what the system does.
what makes it run well what makes it run poorly.
in order to be able to do that kind of optimization.
so the example we like to use is
these two functions do exactly the same thing in terms of their...their behavior.
what they do is copy a matrix or array from called source SRC to a destination DST
they're both size to be 2048 rows 2048 columns two-dimensional arrays
and you'll see that the program's do the obvious thing you have a nested pair of loops to do the row and column indices.
and you just copy from one source element to a destination element.
the only thing that's different you'll see is that the two loops.
their nesting is different the nesting order is different.
one case I'm going kind of row first.
going through all the rows and then the columns and the other is for any given row.
I'm copying all the columns that's really the only difference between these two programs.
but what you'll find if you run it on a typical system ..
It's that one is much faster than the other.
in this particular machine we ran it on it was about close to 20 times difference in performance.
so something fishy is going on if the same program that differs only in this seemingly
insignificant way a way that has no effect whatsoever on its functionality
can have this much performance difference.
and so to understand this you need to stare at the cover of the book.
because basically you're two different points of this strange-looking picture that's on your book.
and since there's no axis or labels on it it makes no sense whatsoever.
but it's there so what you see is this picture shows four different memory access patterns.
I won't go into the details.
what the throughput measured in megabytes per second.
on basically a copying program was. and
without going into the details what you'll see is these two functions sort of sit at different points in this memory access pattern.
the one that goes through a row by row is much better than the one that goes through column by column.
as a result you're getting a lot better performance and it has to do with this memory hierarchy
and what they call the cache memories.
that you're getting way better performance out of it in one case than the other.
so that's explains what the cover of the book is about.
we'll talk about it more later in the course.
and then a final part of the course talks more about not just getting computers to run little programs in isolation .
but getting computers that talk to each other over networks.
implement services like web servers and other functions like that.
which of course is where most of the world of computing sits today.
it's not just isolated machines but computers they internet with each other over the networks.
they're embedded controllers that are interacting with the physical world.
so really the the world of computers is a much richer environment .
and we'll cover at least some aspects of that in the final part of this course.
so as I mentioned the other feature of this course.
it will get you ready for other systems courses you might take  at CMU.
and here we've listed actually a subset of the courses.
at the university that require this course is a prerequisite .
and they're mostly in computer science and ECE.
but you'll see it's quite a range of different courses.
and each of them builds on to one or multiple aspects of the material you learn in the course .
so the reason why we make everyone take this course including incoming master's students.
It's that all these other courses at the University have come to rely on students being familiar.
and having done the work of to 13 or 513 as a prerequisite .
and they can build on that material and sort of cover more ground as a result rather than having to do.
what would otherwise be somewhat remedial work on it and
in fact one of the part of the genesis of this course was the people who taught
the operating system course a 410.
sort of complained that they were spending too much time at the beginning of the course
talking about some very basics of machine programming.
Dave and I said oh well we can cover that .
so that was part of what got this course started.
I mentioned that the course has a sort of perspective that's very different from traditional systems course.
most systems courses including that whole array you saw there we're about
how do I build some particular feature how do i implement an operating system.
how do I design a pipeline microprocessor
those it's all important stuff to know
we really want the people who are out there building operating systems and designing microprocessors to learn how to do it.
on the other hand is a way to sort of get new into this and get the introduction and get the experience
we find it more useful to take what we call a programmers perspective.
meaning understanding what you as a person who sits in front of a computer screen types code.
I need to know about that machine you're typing code for in order to be effective at doing.
it as opposed to somebody who some day going to be designing the the actual machine itself.
so that by taking that perspective it gives you sort of an understanding so
now when you go off to implement it you'll actually know what these features are.
why it's important to implement them well.
but also that's by doing this programmers perspective it
lets you right away get tools that you can use in other places.
where you're writing programs are doing anything related to it. and be more effective at that
so this programmers perspective really gives this this dual benefit to it.
that we feel is very useful and students who've taken the course in the past have expressed that as well.
so as I mentioned we have two instructors  for the course
and they also happen to be authors and the longest.
we've probably taught this course more than anyone else.
but it's also taught by other people on campus as well.
so what I'm going to do now is hand my pair of microphones over two days.
all right welcome good afternoon it's great to see you.
my name is Dave O'Halloran.
and I'm just delighted to have the opportunity to be one of your instructors this term.
this course is one of the reason I'm so excited to be teaching. I just love this course and the real
the reason is the the opportunity of represents to have an impact on people's lives .
so we really believe that the material you learned this semester .
can have a really positive and long-lasting impact on on your careers
and it'll help you not only with your future classes but also future positions you have
and I hear this from people all all the time from CMU students.
students around the world who have taken the equivalent of 213 it at their schools
I even though a couple years ago we were interviewing a faculty member tenure tenure-track faculty member.
who went to did his undergrad at CMU
and then went off to Stanford got his PhD at Stanford and was coming back to you know join the faculty.
and he told me that 213 changed his life in our interview .
now I don't know if he was trying to butter me up.
but I I think I believe him he he said it changed his whole life in the sense
that it gave him a research direction you know he didn't really know what.
he knew it kind of like computer science but it didn't really know what direction to go.
After he took 213 he knew they wanted to to do his word was life's work in systems.
now it was just remarkable right to come down and tap we ended up actually hiring him.
he told me that everybody in his lab at Stanford all of the grad students had a copy of the book on their desk
from and they were from all over you know all different schools
and so I mean I even I was in a bookstore in Beijing a couple years ago right outside the PKU campus.
I was up on the fifth floor trying to see if I could find a copy of the textbook.
and I I found the English version in one aisle and
then a couple miles over I found the Chinese version.
I was I was going through the Chinese version.
and this guy taps me on my shoulder
and I turned around he says oh man that that book is really good
you should the English version is tooI was over.
and I mean it just blew me away to be to be in the head of someone like.
halfway around the world it was just that it was just one of those moments.
so I'm not trying to boast I'm just trying what I want I want to give you the sense of.
what it what an opportunity this course represents for Miranda and I to to have
what we hope will be a really positive impact on on your lives.
so let me we have kind of a kind of a funny organization for the course.
in response to that just the the tremendous demand we have we found that we have for it
so there's there's actually three course numbers but it's all the same course
okay it's the identical course 513, 15-513 is for our master students.
and the 15, 513 doesn't have a formal lecture so there's no seats assigned to it
it instead we'll videotape the lectures and
we'll make those available on the course web web page for our graduate students.
the reason we do this is just because in the past well we we didn't have enough seats for everyone
and there would be cases where there might be a hundred 150 Master students on the waitlist
they wouldn't be able to get into the course
and we we didn't really want that because they need this course for to take other courses
so that's the reason why we have this this sort of does not meet version of 213,513
because we can admit as many all the master's students that that need to take the course.
now 15-213 and 18-213 or are for undergraduates in computer science and ECE respectively.
the undergraduates will go to lectures and recitations okay in person graduate students will watch videotapes of those
but otherwise yes[students question]
yeah we're making them available to everyone actually.
sorry and lecture
lecture slides as well everything's available on the course web page.
so you'll be doing the all of students will have equal access to office hours
the staff mailing list and everybody does the same labs and the same exams
okay so it's just a question it's just a matter of whether you're good a lecture in person or if you watch it on video
in fact if you know since it's available to everybody if you miss lecture it'll be there
on the webpage  you can catch up which I know you'll probably do
actually I know most of you will never miss class right but the few of you who do now you'll be able to watch the video
okay all right this is the one part this part I hate
I love teaching that this is the one part teaching that
none of us really like but we have to talk about it and that's academic integrity
if you're new on campus coming from a international school.
if you're an international student new on campus
there might be different notions of academic integrity
and different notions of cheating at your undergraduate school your old school.
so if you're new on campus pay very close attention to this .
because at Carnegie Mellon we take academic integrity very seriously.
okay it's not a wink wink nod nod we're very serious about it.
we want you we want everybody doing their own work to preserve the integrity of the courses so
so what exactly is cheating?
so if you share code with anybody either copying,retyping.
if looking at somebody's code like if you look at somebody's code on the screen
or if you give somebody a file all of those
all of those examples of sharing are cheating.
if you describe your code like line by line to somebody that's cheating
if you coach somebody line by line that's cheating
searching the web for solutions just the act of searching is cheating
right and this is a this is a real problem for us in particular
because the course is I offered all around the world and
people either maliciously or or sometimes just they're proud of their work and
they post it you know for employers on like public github sites
so it's it might be tempting to to search for these solutions.
but even the act of searching is cheating
and definitely if you find some a solution in and use it.
that's cheating even if you modify it afterwards and I
just want you to remember I can I know how to use Google just as well as anybody else right.
so I I can search for solutions too.
so copying code you know you might be tempted to copy code from someone who took the class you know in a previous semester.
don't do it that's that's cheating too.
now what's not cheating so you can you can help each other use tools.
you know somebody's having trouble using gdb or you know they have
questions about how to run use a text editor.
that stuff's all great you help each other out using the tools.
how to log in the shark machines all of that kind of stuff and
you can help you can discuss sort of high-level design issues and that's probably a good idea.
yes, [student question]
yeah yeah did you take it a previous semester.
[student question]
oh okay yeah the question was if you took it in a previous semester can you use your work and the answer is yes.
you can also talk to each other about high level you know design issues.
you know how are you using an explicit list or using a segregated list for your Malik lab.
that kind of stuff is is is okay a high level okay.
low level not okay
basically what we want you to write your own code
this is not you know it's kind of a cut and paste world these days
right you look stuff up on Google's Stack Overflow you cut and paste it.
but that's not that's not the way we do it.
here we want you to do the work yourself.
we want you to enjoy the experience of figuring things out  and learning how to solve problems
now the consequences for cheating there's a single sanction.
if you're caught cheating you'll be expelled from the course with an R
there's no exceptions alright if you drop the course we'll just reinstate you and then flunk you.
[students laugh]
it's really uh it's a very serious very serious penalty.
because we just take it we take it so seriously at it sub.
it's just something we don't want your to do.
we have amazing tools to detect code plagiarism.
we have amazing tools to detect plagiarism.
that are resilient to renaming reformatting.
they operate at a very deep syntactic level.
and so just please please don't do it.
we have I think 18 TAS will have office hours almost every day of the week.
there's plenty of opportunities and ways to get help start early.
if you get stuck start early enough so that if you get stuck you can go ask for help.
we have but automatic extensions built-in if you need more time I'll talk about that later form of grace days.
but please please whatever you do don't cheat.
it's just tragic when it happens last last fall 25 students.  were expelled from the course.
some were expelled from the University because it was a second offense.
many were sent home I talked to students who were like the only person in their family to go to college.
the only person in their village to go to college and they were going home without without a degree and  it's just tragic it's just.
so please please please don't do it .
do your own work and it'll be a wonderful experience.
okay let's Randy mentioned the the textbook is computer systems a programmers perspective third edition
you can know there's a whole bunch of supporting material on the on the books website at http://csapp.cs.cmu.edu/
and as Randy mentioned this this book really matters for the course
because actually the book came out of the course
the book is the course of course it's the book.
and so it'll it will really help you love it
the labs that we do come directly from materia we discuss in the book .
so what I would encourage all of you to do.
and I'm not sure if anybody has ever taken this advice but I say it every year.
anyway because I believe it
but I think a really good strategy for studying and preparing for this course would be to read each chapter three times.
read three times work the practice problems.
so we have littered throughout the book or practice problems with solutions at the end of the the end of the chapter.
and these practice problems are like little sort of bite-size morsels just kind of
just to kind of check your kind of a sanity check of your understanding of the material
so I think if you read this if you read the book each chapter three times and work the practice problems.
you would be an excellent way to go through the semester and prepare.
the other book we use is the Kearny Hannah and Richie's classic C programming book
I think this is still this was written a long time ago
it's still the best book around I think for C it's.it's a beautiful.
example of technical writing it was one of the inspirations I used
when I was writing the book you know I tried to find that same clarity and precision
that they turn Hannah and Ritchie have in their book.
so this is a this is a really good book.
I mean this is kind of book it's it's a reference.
but it's a kind of book you can just read from beginning to end.
and get a really good understanding of C.
there's four main components to the course.
there's lectures where we go over the high level concepts recitations where .
which meet once a week for an hour led by a TA.
and the purpose of the recitations is really to help you with the labs.
so it's very practical and hands-on.
there's seven of those labs and these are really the heart and soul of the course
this is where all the real learning comes in I think
when you actually have to do this stuff
and that's why we take the cheating parts so seriously .
because if you do these labs you're going to learn an incredible amount of really cool stuff.
if you don't do them you won't learn anything.
so each one of these labs is 1-2 weeks each
and involves typically some kind of programming or measurement
there's also two exams a midterm and a final.
the exams are proctored they're online proctored in Wien and and gates.
what we do for the exams is we have like we take like four days.
from 10:00 to 10:00 and then you can sign up.
and then we have like multiple clusters that are Network isolated.
and then you can sign up for a slot like a 6-hour slot .
and the midterm is like nominally like an hour eighty minute.
exam it's the same exam we use we gave when we used to have people sitting in person.
so it's nominally like 80 minutes but we give you like a five or six hour window to do it
okay so there's so you can sign up any time any day that there's a slot
okay so there's flexibility so you can kind of tailor it to your schedule.
and we I think we've also removed all the time pressure  right so which is .
you can go back you can check your work you can  just kind of relax.
not be worried about how quickly you do it.
now there's many different ways to get help
the main source of information is the course web page
that's http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~213
all the information is there.we've got a complete schedule of lectures and assignments.
we don't change it that's it's fixed and so you can look at that and and plan your semester.
knowing that those dates won't change.
we've actually even got all of the lectures posted ahead of time for
for the other instructors around the world who are using the book
so we needed to get them all already
there's also news at the at the very beginning there's sort of news
if we need to make announcements we'll post it there
we don't use either blackboard or Piazza in the course
instead we have a staff mailing list
that you can send mail to if you have questions.
and all of the TAS and all of the faculty are subscribed to that staff mailing list
and so we'll all see it
and we usually we try to have you know really fast feedback right
so there's so many people looking at at your emails
that chance is very high you'll get on and answer back quickly
the the disadvantage of having this advantage of this mailing list is that it allows us to control the message.
and control what we're it's what feedback we' re giving back to you.
the disadvantage is that we often get the same question over and over again
so for that we've established a FAQ if we find we're getting same questions over and over
we've established a FAQ on the course web page.
for it sort of organized by labs so you can see the answers to frequently asked questions
we have office hours they were still trying to we were still trying to meet with the staff and
figure out the exact office hours
but what we're thinking now is that we'll have office hours six days a week every day but Saturday
they will be at the same time and same place every day so from 5:45 to 8:30 in WeH in a queen 5207 cluster
we'll have two 13 TAS there to to help to answer your questions
so you don't have to make appointments
I mean you can't make an appointment to see any staff member of course.
but you don't you know that at the same time same place every day
there's somebody you can go to for help
okay for our labs and exams every assignment
every lab is a single person so we don't have any group projects
we want you to do the work yourself
now you know it's important to work in groups
and you will learn how to work in groups
and other classes see us classes
but not in 213 we want this is a kind of a core course we want you to figure stuff out yourself
all of our handins will be due at 11:59 p.m. on either a Tuesday or Thursday
you can see which on the schedule page on the course webpage
and all of our handins are using Autolab.
where you know you've probably used it for some of your other classes.
but it's a Auto grading service that allows you to get instant feedback on your handin
so when you hand it in you get feedback right away .
the exams like I mentioned are going to be a network isolated clusters held over multiple days
you can just sign up for a slot that's available now
what usually happens if we offer like the exam Tuesday Wednesday and Thursday
the Thursday slots fill up immediately
I guess I should try to sign up soon if you want
but people always seem to want to defer to the end rather than.
and if it's me I'd want to get it over with but
so I just that that is sort of a constraint right that
you can only sign up for slots that that available
okay now you know we make mistakes there's we always make mistakes especially with so many students
so we there's a  a specific process for appealing grades
if you think that there was a pitcher the work wasn't graded properly
so what you do after after either an exam or after your labs are graded
you have seven days to file an appeal
and appeals have to be in writing and hardcopy.
okay so there's no we won't consider any email any appeals via email
it has to be in writing and hardcopy
and you give those to me
if I'm not there you can just slide it under the desk
what the reason we do it that way is it allows us to treat  everybody fairly
we get all the appeals together at once
and then we can treat everybody the same way rather than just sort of doing them one at a time like
now for our labs we have ten machines that were donated by Intel called the shark machines
so initially our first version of 213 and I
I guess we started using Intel machines in 1999.
we used to alpha processors for the first year
I like to fish.
so all of our machines work they were called the fish machines right
they were freshwater fish
and then we upgraded a few years after that and those were the saltwater fish machines
and then we upgraded like in 2011 to these Nehalem class servers and
And run out of fresh water fish and saltwater fish
so the next grade up was sharks right
so every fish is it's named after some kind of shark
but these are the same machines that that you know that auto lab uses grading right
so there's some consistency for performance-
oriented labs like milk lab
and you can access them that they're you the names are listed on the course webpage
and so you can SSH to a specific machine
they're all identical if you have an Andrew account you've already got accounts on the machines right so there's nothing special to do
or you can just SSH to sharp that ICS and you'll just randomly put you on on one of the shark machines
okay if you have any trouble logging in just send send mail to the staff mailing list
okay we know that during the semester things come up
grandparents died especially near the near the final that's harsh
but that things come up right and you've got your very busy
you're taking a lot of courses so
instead of sort of dealing with requests for extensions
and you know all these special cases what we do
we give you five grace days
that you can then spend as you wish
so if you hand your work in late one day late you'll automatically consume a grace day
okay we don't allow you to sort of allocate the grace days
you spend one of your grace days by handing in late.
so if you have a great day left then you hand in late
you'll spend that grace day but you won't be penalized for the late hand in
so we have five grace days over the entire semester
and a maximum of two grace days for the assignments
now we're going to set up since the first three assignments are kind of not as programming intensive
and don't take as much time
we're not going to allow any grace days for those
because a one grace day one sorry one grace day and then for the the latter for labs
which are much more intense we're going to allow you to a max of two grades days
and the reason we're doing this is because we don't want you to burn your grade these grace days are valuable
they're critical especially later in the semester when it have you really  dizzy
so we don't want you to burn up your grace days early in the semester
and this happens every semester
and it and then when Malik lab comes up there's no grace days left.
it's really sad to see that.
so we're going to limit you to one for those first three
just to help you save you from yourself
now if the the
the nominal late penalty if you don't have a grace days 15% per day.
and we don't allow any handin its three days after the due at all.
so that our lab shuts off
now if there is some kind of catastrophic about
then you know please contact us  for an extension right so why not
you know we try to be reasonable
but most of the most of the most of the reasons that for requesting extensions
you can handle yourself about using your grades days
and just I mean this is this is advice I give every semester too
but it's people often don't don't pay attention but or
just they're unable to but but really you for every one of these assignments you want to start early
and the reason is you need to give yourself time to to go seek help if you get stuck
because the nature of these very programming intensive assignments like we have in 213 is that you're going to get stuck
and often it's very hard to to bound the time you spend on on some of these assignments
you know it's not like problem sets where you can kind of predict you know this will take
others will take me like three hours to do do these problem sets for
a lot of the 213 assignments it's very difficult to to sort of manage your time and bound your time
so for that reason you really want to start early to give yourself a chance to get help when you get stuck
now in the lecture hall you're permitted to have your laptops
but we ask you not to send email or instant messaging or cell phone texting or anything like that
if you hear we want you to to be attentive and engaged
your presence in lectures and recitations is voluntary so we don't take
we don't take role at either of those
we encourage you to come but it's not required and no recordings of any kind except this one
okay the exams and labs are weighted equally 50% midterms 20 finals 30 .
final grades are based on a straight 90 80 70 scale
now rough outline of the semester
the first three labs cover programs representations of programs and data.
data lab is how we teach you about bit level representations of data.
so you'll sell collection of puzzles and see like a puzzle might be is a little function.
that you have to implement like absolute value
so a function that returns the absolute value of its input argument
the kicker is that we restrict the set of operators that you can use
and it has to be straight line code no conditionals or loops
and so to solve these puzzles
so imagine how you might try to solve absolute value without using an if statement
right the normal way to do it would be if X less than 0 return X or negative X
see I told you we make mistakes
but imagine how you might do that without using conditionals and only using bit levels C operations
right so this is how this is how this is our way of teaching you
how data is really represented in the machine
now the bomblab which you've probably heard at this is
this is a kind of famous all over the world now and at CMU .
the bomb lab is the way we teach you how to read and understand assembly language
and a bomb just briefly a bomb is it is a C program that consists of a collection of six phases
and each phase wants you to type something in at the keyboard
if you type in the what it wants you to type what it expects you type
then you've diffused that phase
and it goes to the next phase
then you have to type what that phase
once if you defuse all the phases then you've diffused the bomb.
however if you type in the wrong thing
then the bomb explodes by printing boom.
and you have to try it again
and the kicker is in either case when if you explode the bomb
or defuse a phase that information gets sent to auto lab
if you expand we use the defusing string that that your bomb sends us and
we check it out on a copy of your bomb that we keep on the server
that's another thing every everybody gets a different bomb slightly different bomb
so we check so when you defuse when you defuse a phase the auto lab takes the string that it
that your bomb sends us and then compares against the local copy of your bomb
if you explode phase you lose half a point
so there's a real consequence to exploding your bomb it's very very tense right
until you learn how to use GDB to set a breakpoint
before the function that sends the information to the server and
we want you to do that right
so a bombs are really the bombs really beautiful it's kind of fun it's kind of like a
it's it teaches you how to read compiler generated code
because the only oh the kicker is sorry that
the kicker is we don't give you the source code all we give you is the binary the binary bomb
so in order to defuse a bomb you've got to fire up gdb
single trace through the find where the code is for each phase single trace through that code.
and sort of reverse engineer and figure out what it wants you to type in
and then you'll quickly find out where that function that explodes the bomb is
and you'll put a breakpoint there
and so we want you to do that because
the bomb besides teaching you how to program assembly language
it also teaches you sort of organically how to use gdb
because you really can't do it if you don't use if you don't run gdb
and then the the third lab is this is a new lab
this semester the randy's develops called the attack lab
and we developed this lab specifically for 64-bit architecture
so this is a reflection of the change from 32 bits to 64 bits and
and this is so we're really excited about this one you'll learn how to
you'll learn how to write exploits using return to a sort of a modern technique called return to return oriented programming
which is kind of the modern modern way that hackers deal with the fact that stacks in newer machines move around
and are prohibitive and make it impossible to execute code on the on the stack
so this is a brand new labs really I think it's really going to be really going to be neat
in the memory hierarchy when we study the memory hierarchy we
we have a cache lab called the cache lab
where you'll build your own cache simulator so this is how
you sort of learn how this hardware that Randy was mentioning called cache memory works
you'll build a simulator and see for that.
and then you'll take a small transpose function
and you'll try to make that that code run with as few misses as possible on your simulator and
this will involve sort of understanding of how the memory hierarchy works and how to exploit it
the part of the course where you we sort of transition from hardware
to interacting with the system software  that the operating system.
there's sort of a concept that we call exceptional control flow  that exists in all parts of the system
and it sort of represents that intellectual transition from hardware to software so
this is how this was sort of a key idea that allowed us to kind of smoothly
move from from hardware to software in some intellectually consistent way
and so the idea is that you cover an exceptional control floor like low hard
low-level Hardware interrupts and exceptions
and then at the higher level sort of involving hardware and operating system software
is the idea of an operate of a process context switch
so this is this is where you start to learn what processes are
and how to how to ask the kernel to create in
at the next higher level or a software form of exceptional control flow called a signal
so this exists solely on the Linux kernel .
and then and then even at a higher level at there's an application C language
version of exceptional control flow call set jump and long jump
so this this notion of exceptional control flow kind of exists
in all parts of the system we covered all at once
and the lab that we use  to sort of exercise all these ideas
is called the shell lab
and in the shell lab you'll write your own linux shell which is really cool
so that's the program the command line program that you interact with whenever you log into a Linux box
you're going to write your own.
I don't look for me that was really exciting when I could like write something that looked like a real shell
it was pretty
neat the next area is well study is called virtual memory
virtual memory is a sort of combination of hardware and software
that presents an abstraction to you of this very of memory is a very large array of bytes
when in reality memory is a hierarchy of hardware and of cache memories and DRAMs
virtual memory provides a very high-level abstraction as just a linear sequence of bytes .
it also does provide a lot of a lot of other useful abstractions
that make many different parts of the system much easier to manage
ok so we'll learn will learn about virtual memory we'll learn how it works
we'll learn about the performance impact potential performance impact that has on your programs
and and we'll also learn how to manage that large pool of memory
that it makes available to you
and the lab that we do that the lab where you'll do that is called malloc lab
and in the malloc lab you'll write your own malloc and free functions
ok so you'll you'll reimplementation ality of the Lipsy malloc and free
and this is a maybe a maybe it's two pages of code
but it'll be a guarantee it'll be the most sophisticated difficult two pages of code you've written
not only because since it's managing the memory system you can't use all of
I mean C doesn't have many C doesn't help you out a lot
with abstractions for data structures
but when you're writing but at least it does give you ideas like struct unions
that you can use to structure your memory
when you're writing a malloc package you can't use any of those
you have to write exclusively on pointers and casting
because you malloc package is working at such a low level
and so it's a very very difficult piece of code for that reason
but also the design space for malloc is is enormous
you have many options they all have implications that
that trade-off performance and and memory efficiency and finally
in the last part of the course
we we deal with i/o input/output
so so far in the course we've just talked about sort of running programs on machines
in the last part of the course we'll talk about input and output
sending data into and out of the machine
so we'll look at basic concepts of Linux i/o
well and since I think the most interesting form of i/o is networking
which allows you to talk to machines anywhere in the world using the internet
we'll also talk we'll learn how to do network programming
you'll learn how to write programs  that use the sockets interface
which is the basic interface for the internet to talk to machines any potentially any machine in the in the world
and that's really
I mean once I can still remember when developing this course I had two windows open on my machine
I was SSH into two different machines
and I wrote a program to send a message like hello world from one machine to the other
and when that hello world appeared on the second windows like so exciting
I mean if you're a nerd it's really exciting
but just the thought that that could have been at any machine right
that could have been any machine that is just like opens up a whole new world
okay all of our all of our handins are using a system called Auto lab
which was developed here and you can access it
if you if you were on the roster as of this morning if you go to the Auto lab link
then you'll see this course listed on your page.
if you're not enrolled you won't have an auto lab account.
and you have to be enrolled to get an auto lab account
so if you if you want to try to wait it out and wait for people to drop
I'll make the first couple of at least the first assignment due available from the course webpage
so you can work on it without actually handing in to Auto lab
but at least you can keep going
okay if you are enrolled actually I didn't update this but I updated the Auto lab accounts today
now one final thing if you have waitlist questions
please don't don't send email to the staff
because we don't control the waitlist
so you should contact one of these either Cathy Catherine or Zara depending on which class
okay so that's that welcome again looking forward to a great semester
and we'll see you on Thursday
[Applause]