Good afternoon everybody
welcome
it's good to see you
so today we're going to study a arcane area of computer systems known as floating point
which is the way that computer systems represent the real numbers
so you're all familiar with decimal you know something like 3.14
and there's a similar idea with with binary numbers
okay so what does a fractional binary number like 10111.01 represent
and how does that work
well it works just like the fractional decimal numbers that you used to
so you have a in this case it's a it's a binary point
and to the left of the binary point
you have bit positions to representing powers of 2
so 2^0,2^1,2^2
so 1/2.I'm sorry.
1,2,4 and so on
and to the right of the binary point
you have 2^-1=1/2. 2 to the minus
2^-2=1/4, 2^-3=1 /8 and so on
so we can represent that any fractional binary number
using this notation where we sum each the bit at position k times 2^k
ok so it's really works exactly the same way as with base 10 just with base 2
so let's look at some of these values
so 5 and 3/4 we would represent as 101.11
so this is before plus 1 is 5
+1/2, +1/4
ok so 2/4 + 1/4 is 3/4. so 5 3/4
ok so that's pretty simple
2 7/8 is 10.111 so that 10 is 2 of course
and then .111 is 1/2.
so 4/8 + 1/4(2/8) + 1/8 okay so 7/8
and 1 7/16 would be 1.0111
so that the 1 to the left of the binary point is 1
and then we have 1/4 + 1/8 + 1/16
so 1/4 is 4/16, 1/8 is 2/16 and 1/16 so you add those up you get 7/16
okay now notice that for some of these numbers
this bit pattern 101.11
if we shift it to the right to get 10.111
we've divided by 2 right so we've taken 5 3/4 and divided it by 2
and it works the other way too
if you shift to the left you multiply if you shift to the left by 1 you multiply by 1
and these numbers that are all ones to the right of the of the binary point
are these are numbers that are just slightly less than than 1 okay
so well when we want to represent those
we will sometimes refer to those numbers of that form is 1- ℇ
and epsilon just depends on how many bits you have to the right of the binary point
so epsilon gets smaller the more
the more of those bits you have there it gets closer to 1
and epsilon gets smaller the more of those bits you have
now there's a there's limitations in this kind of representation
so first of all we can only represent rational numbers of the form x/2^k
we can only represent numbers of that form exactly
other numbers have to get have repeating bit representations that can't be represented
with a finite number of bits that we have in a computer system
so for example things like a 1/3 is this repeating representation
1/5 and 1/10 or other examples of that
now the other problem we have is that
we can only...
there's only so many bits to the left and the right of the the binary point
so we're kind of
if we move the binary point to the left
then we don't have as many we can't represent as many large numbers
we can only represent small numbers
but we have more precision to the right of the binary point
so we can represent more fractional values
just the range of those values will be much smaller
similarly if we move the binary point to the right
we'll have a larger range of values
but we won't build represent as many fractions
okay so there's this there's this kind of trade-off
and floating point is a representation
try that  enables us to move that basically to move that binary point to represent
sort of as wide a range as possible
with as much precision given the number of bits
the finite number of bits that we have to work with
so that the float and floating point is this sort of shifting binary point right
this floating the floating binary point
now up until 1985
a floating point was just a disaster and
and every computer manufacturer had their own representation
you couldn't and it was just terrible because you couldn't predict
what would happen if you moved your program from one machine to another
the behavior would be different the rounding would be different
it was a very difficult situation and people really
computer scientists in particular really disliked floating point
in 1985 IEEE which is the professional association for electrical engineers
introduced a and it's also a very important standards body
they introduced a standard floating-point representation called IEEE floating point
which was then adopted by all computer manufacturers
so now the situation is much better
everybody supports the same kind of floating point representation
which is what we're going to learn about today
so the floating point has the form
it represents numbers in a this is like a scientific notation
it represents numbers of the form (-1)^s where s is a sign bit.
times a significant M
ok times 2 to some exponent e
ok so all of the numbers that we can represent in floating point  have to be represented in this form
so the sign bit s determines whether the number is negative or positive obviously
the significant M and this is sometimes sometimes called the mantissa
where the M comes from
the significant M normally is a fractional value in the range between 1 and 2
and we'll see why that is in a second
and then the exponent E weights the value by some power of 2
okay so this is encoded either 32-bit or 64-bit
in the following way the the sign bit s is the most significant bit
and then this is followed by some number of
by some number of bits called the exp field
which encodes the exponent E
but it's not identical to E it encodes E we'll see how that works
and then the frac. and then that's followed the remaining bits are the the frac field
which encodes M but isn't identical to M
now we are...IEEE  floating point has provides two different kinds of floating-point
the single precision 32 bits and so-called double precision which is 64 bits
there's this funky Intel extended precision
which is non-standard and we won't talk about it anymore
and so in the single precision 32 bits
you have one sign bit. there's always a sign bit.
you have 8 exp bits and you have 23 frac bits
in double precision you have 11 exp and 52 frac bits
now there's a number of different kinds of floating-point representations
the sort of the default and sort of the common representation is called normalized
so called normalized values
and normalized values are
all the values where the exp field is not equal to 0
and not equal to all zeros
so everything all zeros and all ones are special kinds of numbers we'll look at second
so the exponent
this exponent e remember our numbers are (-1)^s
times M times 2^E
the exponent e is encoded as this biased value
which is the called exp
so the X the exponent e is Exp - Bias
and exp is the value
capital exp is the value of the exp bits
the bits in the exp field treated as a positive number
okay so capital exp you just look at it as an unsigned
7-bit in case of single precision 7-bit number
okay now the Bias=2^(k-1) - 1,where K is number of exponent bits
okay so for single precision we have 8 exponent bits
so 2^8, 2^(8-1=7) so 2^7=128 - 1 is 127
ok so the bias for single precision is 127
and similarly for double precision it's 1023
okay so you just have to memorize this formula
the exponent e is the exp field
interpret it as an unsigned number minus the the bias
this is kind of a strange thing the first time you encounter floating-point
it seems kind of odd right so why not
I mean we've already learned about two's complement
that's a perfectly fine way to represent positive and negative numbers
okay we have exponents that are negative and positive right
so why not just use the exp field to represent
why not just use a two's complement in the exp field to represent those positive and negative exponents right
so it turns out that the reason they do this is
is that...
and if you think about think about this and we'll come back to it
but if we encode the the exponent e using this bias representation
the smallest negative exponent is represented by all zeros
and the largest exponent is represented by 01111
so the smallest, the number with the smallest exponent
if we were just to compare the bits
using a just some kind of unsigned representation just comparing the bits
treating it as an unsigned number
by using this biased representation
we can just compare two floating-point numbers just as unsigned
we can treat the whole floating-point number as an unsigned integer and compare two numbers
and get a true comparison
so the exponent uses this this sort of biasing encoding
and then the significant is encoded with an implied one
so and this is where they are. this is where the normalized
in the normalized representation comes from
that we're always going to represent our numbers
so M we're always going to normalize M
no matter what the number we want to represent
we're always going to normalize m as one point something
and then we adjust the exponent accordingly
so if the value we want to represent is 100.01
we're going to shift it over and it will be 1.00
okay and then we'll adjust the exponent to represent that shift
okay so the  bits in the frac field xxxx...x are
all of the numbers to the right of the binary point right
so there's always this implied one
but we don't even encode it we just throw it away
because it's always there right
so this is a little trick just to get it one more bit for free
okay so the the xxx bits in the frac field
are all of all the bits to the right of the binary point after one point the one point
and this is,the so this is the smallest fractal is all zeros
which corresponds to a significant of 1.0
a frac field of all ones corresponds to 2-ɛ
so that's 1.111...
so let's look at let's look at an example
so let's look at how we would encode 15213
which our favorite number in two's complement in floating point
so the if we represent that so it's an integer
and we represent it using these bits take my word for it correspond to the integer 213
so now we want to convert it we want to normalize it
by expressing it as 1.110 and so on  times 2^13
okay same number we just normalized it
so that there's always this leading 1
so the significant M is 1.11011 and so on
the frac field is everything to the right of the binary point
so we just,we throw this,we throw this one away
and we just take the the values to the right of the binary point
and then we Pat it out with zeros 2 to get the 23 bits that we need for single precision
ok so now we've got our frac field
the exponent
so in this case right E is
we're multiplying by 2 ^13.so E is 13
so we want to represent the value 13 using this bias encoding
so the bias is 127
and so the exponent the value of the exp field should be 140
because if we take 140 - 127 we get 13
okay so 140 is represented using these 8 bits
and that becomes our exp field
okay so the resulting floating-point number
and of course it's a positive number so the significand bit is zero
so the resulting floating point number has these eight
the 8 bits and exp field that we computed by subtracting 127 from 140
and then the frack field are these bits that we
we got here by just taking everything to the right of the binary point
so this
so let's look at this exponent just a little bit more
because I think can be a little confusing
so in our example
if we want to look at the range of exp
so what's the smallest value of exp
what's the smallest value of exp
no way,no doughnut, don't confuse the encoding with the value it represents
exp is just the encoding.so what's,
what's the smallest value of Exp
0 that's right
okay and the largest value is? is what?
it's... what's the largest value?
yes
[student answer the question]
well the largest value would be remember it can't be all ones
right so the largest value would be 2^8 - 1
so okay so the largest value would be 01111...
0 followed by 7 ones
so that's a 2^8-1 is ...
255 good
okay so then what's the range the of e
which is the actual value that we want to encode
okay member use this we have this definition
so we have the range of values for exp
we have our bias
so what is the range of values for e
this is the actual exponents that we're encoding
so what's the smallest exponent -127 good
right.because that's zero is our smallest exp-bias which is 127
okay so the smallest value of e is 127
and the largest value of e is ?
so if we take the largest value of exp that's 255-127 = 128
okay so the numbers that we can represent using this bias notation
will have the smallest exponent will be 2^ -127
and the largest exponent will be 2 to the raised to the power 128
okay so you see what's going on here
so we have a range of values for e
here's the largest value,here's the smallest value,here's 0 right in the middle
these are the values we want to represent this biasing is like a shift
we've just now we're shifting up by 127
so that now the smallest exponent is represented by 0
okay any questions about that
now these these normalized values always have this implied one
okay which... when we want to represent numbers closer to zero
that limits us right
so there's another type of floating-point number called the de norma, denormalized value
which is characterized by an exp field of all 0
and in a normal in a denormalized number or de norm there's no implied one
okay so the the significant M is represented exactly is encoded identically in the frac field
so there's no implied one
and all of the numbers are the form zero point something something something after them
and the exponent value e instead of you remember for de norms we subtracted bias from exp
for D norms we subtract the bias from one
okay now if we just use the definition
we use for normalized numbers that would be
the exp would be zero
so we don't do that instead
e is 1 - bias
and then the significant is coded with an implied leading 0 instead of a leading one like a like I mentioned
so when exp is zero and also I mean
we think about it. if we only had denormalized numbers
we wouldn't be able to represent zero right because there'd always be a 1 in there
so the D norms allow us to represent zero
and they allow us to represent values that are very close to zero
so when the exponent is zero
and the exp field is zero and the frac field is zero then this is the zero value
and so this is nice because all zeros represents zero
which is you know sort of which one
there is the sort of weird thing though that
if you have a the sign bit is one
and then your frac and exp is zero then you have negative zero
so you have this kind of odd situation where there's a positive and negative zero
okay and other values if exp is zero and you have a non zero frac
and those are the equally spaced numbers that are closest to zero
now there's a couple of other special values
when exp is all ones and frac is all zeros.
this represents the value infinity
so this is a value that that we get
when is some kind of addition or multiplication and we overflow
so in floating point always overflows to the special value called infinity there positive or negative infinity
so it's different from two's complement right where
you sort of overflowed into in this modular way back
just back it round into the range of numbers
in floating point we just overflow to the sticky value called infinity
and then everything we do on that remains infinity
so for example if we did a
if we did 1 divided by 0
or minus 1 divided by minus 0 we'd get positive infinity
if we divide 1 by 0 negative 0 we get negative infinity
the fourth the fourth kind of special case special number is the case where
the exponent again is all once but the frac is nonzero
in a non zero value
and this represents what's called not a number so this is
this handles cases where there's no there's no answer
there's no feasible answer for example if we you know try to take the square root of -1
what we'll get back is not a number
so - I think it's helpful to to visualize these the number line now so the
we have positive zero negative zero  sort of right next to each other
and then to the right of that are the positive D norms
and then those those sort of transition into the normalized numbers
and then you have infinity positive infinity
you have a similar similar situation on the for the negative numbers
and then negative and positive not a numbers
so I think the you know you probably you've probably discovered
the really good way to try to understand these numeric and
coatings is just to do examples with only a few number of bits
you know if you if you want to understand like for example in two's complement
if you want to understand T min and T Max and
and how they relate to each other
just do a three bit two's complement system you
you know imagine just have a system with two's complement of three bits
and then you can just enumerate all those all the possibilities and you can see
and then you see where you know the T min is actually one greater than T Max
you know so if you add one to t max it actually overflows into T min
similar thing for floating point it's I would really encourage you to do this
just try some simple examples with
a sort of tyent with a small number  of exp and frack bits
so in this case we're going to look at a floating point system based on IEEE
that has 4 exp bits and three frack bits
as always the sign bit is the most significant bit
followed by exp followed by frac
okay so this is identical to IEEE floating point except for the size of that  exp in fractals
so it's actually small enough that we can now just enumerate these values
and now you can, you can start to see why these weird
definitions for the exponent in the denominator
so let's just look at
so we will sta
seventh possibilities possible
combinations of exp and frac fields starting with zero
okay so when exp is all zeros
that's a de norma right by definition
and then we have the three frac bits  or all zero
okay so remember the exp is all zeros
right so the for de norms the, exponent value is 1- bias
our bias here is 7
okay so 1 - 7 gives us a value for the exponent of  -6
so we're going to take the frac
the bits in the frac field times
so M is 0
so M in this case is 0
times 2^-6 gives us 0
so this is our representation of 0
and like I said it's really it's nice that it actually is
if we just treated this as an unsigned integer
which is it would be 0
okay so that's kind of pleasing
now let's look at the very next number right
the X exp is still 0 and we've just bumped up frac by 1
ok so again it's a 1 - bias which is -6
and now this,this frac field represents this is 1/2 1/4 1/8
so it represents,so this is a value of amaz it is 1/8
so 1/8x2^-6(1/64)=1/512
so in this floating point system the smallest nonzero number
we can represent is the denormalized representation of 1/512
the next smallest number is 0
okay now let's look at, so let's take, let's bump this up by one
so now we get a we get a frac field of 010
so this represents 1/4
so M is 1/4 that significant is 1/4, times 2^-6
so 2/8 times 1/64 is 2/512
okay so the the numbers were just it by incrementing this
by incrementing are significant we're increasing the numbers by 1/512
now the largest d norm in this number system
is the case where the frac field is all ones
and so this encodes 1/2 + 1/4 + 1/8 which is 7/8
and then our value is 7/8 times 2^-6 or 1/64 that equals 7/512
so this 7/512 is the largest denormalized number we can represent in this system
and now if we bump our number up by one the the frac field resets to zero
and now  the exp field goes from 0 to 1
now because the exp field is non-0
this is no longer a denormalized number.it's a normalized number
okay so now we're changing the definition of e
from 1 - bias to exp - bias
so what's exp in this case ?
1-7,the bias is -6
so lo and behold it's the same exponent as the previous denormalized number
so this is actually very clever by the IEEE folks
because you get the spirit,you get this nice smooth transition from de norms to norms to normalize
so you can see that our exponent e is is -6 still
and now,because we're taking 1 - bias.
7 and  are significant now remember this is a normalized number
because the exp field is non-0
they are a frac field of all zeros represents a significant of 1.000
okay so this normalized number this the smallest normalized number
represents is 1.000 which is 8/8 times 2^-6(1/64)
which gives us 8/512
so we've made this nice smooth transition from 7/512 to 8/512
and I'll do one more
I don't want to
so if we bump keeping the exp field 1
if we bump our frac field from 0 to 1
now this represents the the significant of 1.0, 1.001 which is eight
which is 8/8 + 1/8
so that's 9/8 times...and then the value is 9/8 times 2^-6(1/64) which is equal to 9/512
okay
any questions about that?
question back here
[student question]
okay the question is why is..why do you choose the bias that to be 2^(k-1) - 1
well go back to my my finger diagram here
so this is the range of exp fields that you want to
this is the range of e that you want to represent with 0 in the middle
okay and so you want to bias
it so that this is halfway 0 the smallest exponent is halfway to 0
so you want the bias to shift it up
so it's the smallest value of exp corresponds to the smallest exponent
right so 2^(k-1) - 1 is just giving you a value
that's halfway between the smallest exponent and the largest exponent
okay
that's good.any other questions?
okay if we take a little smaller six bit format same thing
as we did before just different numbers of bits in exp and frac
and then we plot these on the number line
you can see that the values are very dense around zero
so they're very spaced very closely together
and then every time you increase the exponent by one
the numbers are spaced twice as far apart as the previous
the numbers that were represented by the previous exponent
so you can see like in this little example
you see these
these values here are all equally spaced
now these four values are equally spaced and they're right next to each other
and then you see this jump in the spacing that represents an increase in the exp field by one
and then that spacing doubles as we go out
and you can see it even better here this if we zoom in
these blue values or D norms
and then we have the the next set of normalized values where the frac field is 1
they're spaced the same right we saw this when we kept increasing by 1/512
and then we increase the the exponent by one and the spacing doubles
okay so this like I mentioned this encoding has some pretty nice properties
the floating point zero zero zero is encoded as integer zero which is nice
and with the exception of not a number,with the exception of not a number
you can compare any floating-point numbers
including infinity by just treating it as doing an unsigned comparison
so that's really nice too
um now if you, when you add and multiply floating point numbers
right we're dealing with a limited set of bits here
so if we take two numbers encoded as floating-point
and we add them together there's no guarantee  that we'll be able to fit all those bits
in the bits we have available to us
there's no guarantee that we'll be able to fit the the bits and the result
so what we do in this case is
you can imagine the model you want to have a floating-point operations
addition to multiplication
It's that you add or multiply you do the addition or multiplication
and you compute the exact result
you just assume that you have an infinite amount of number of bits
and then you round use the technique called rounding to get it to fit into the of the available bits
so the the effect
is like you doing say x + y is getting the precise value of x + y at an infinite number of bits
and then rounding into the available bits
so let's look at this idea of rounding
it this can be confusing the first time
you see it requires you need to think about it carefully to get it right
now in IEEE there's four different kinds of rounding
there's round towards zero round down route or round to minus infinity
round up to which is rounding it to positive infinity
and then the default case
which is the only one route we're really going to consider
which is round to the nearest even
and this is what IEEE does by default
you can,you can
if you go into assembly language you can change the rounding
but we're not going to consider it any more.yes question
[student question]
I'm sorry
there is right because there's one
so the question is there a distinct negative infinity and a distinct positive infinity
and there is they have the exact same bit representation
except the most significant bit for negative infinity is one
and for positive infinity it's zero
yes question
[student question]
why is nearest even?
oh I'll show you let me go over the others
the question was about nearest even.yes
[student question]
well that was the exception right  the right
that's right so so aside from infinity you can't do that comparison
positive infinity works right but not negative so you're right
but good point
let's look at these rounding modes and I'll explain why the neuro Steven works
but let's look at so rounding towards zero what we're going to do
we'll use dollars so we want to round to the nearest dollar
towards zero just anything less than you just round towards zero
so dollar forty would go to one
a dollar sixty would go down to one
a dollar fifty to one
two fifty would go to two
-150 you round towards zero
so that would be negative one
round down or towards negative infinity
it's similar the only difference is that
for negative one point negative a dollar
fifty you drown towards negative
infinity which would be minus two
rounding up is symmetric to round down
the interesting case is round to nearest even
interesting because it's what I Triple E floating point actually uses
so the idea here if you have a value that's less than half  then you round down
if you have a value that's more than halfway between two dollar amounts you round up
the route that nearest even part comes when you have something that's exactly halfway
then what you do is you round towards the nearest even number
okay so in this example a dollar forty
because it's less than half rounds down to one dollar
a dollar sixty is greater than half so we round up to two dollars
a dollar fifty right in the middle we round up to the nearest even
dollar amount which is two dollars
two dollars and fifty cents we round down to the nearest even
right if we round it up it would be three which is it odd number
and minus a dollar fifty we round two we round down to minus two dollars
so the reason we do this the reason they chose this is that statistically
if you would imagine
if you have a uniform distribution of sort of numbers
they're going to round up or down about 50% of the times
so there won't be a statistical bias rounding up or down one way or the other
so that's the reason they did that
now you can apply this you can do this rounding to any to any value
so in the last example we did it to the nearest dollar
but let's suppose we wanted to round to the nearest hundredth using round two even
the default round two even mode
so we want to round to the the nearest hundredth is this second position this
first do we have tenths then hundreds
so if we have a value 7.8949999
that's less than halfway
halfway would be any number that had a five followed by all zeros
so 49999 is less than that
so we would just round down to 7.89
even though 9 is odd
the only time we're going to apply round 2 even is when we're exactly halfway
okay our next example 7.895001that's greater than halfway
right if this was a zero it would be exactly halfway so we round up to 7.9
here's the interesting case where we have 7.895 followed by all zeroes that's exactly halfway
so now we apply the round to nearest even rule
eight nine is a Nega is an odd number so that doesn't work so we round up
and we do that basically by adding a five here
so five and five is ten and then that carries over
to the next position and nine and one is zero nine and one is 10 so that carries over
and so 8+1=9 so the result is set of rounding up is 7.90
okay is that clear do you see
there's a very mechanical way when you round up
it's always it's a very mechanical like that
you always just add the half-way number in this case five
and then just propagate it out just do the addition and that will give you the nearest
the nearest that will round you up to the nearest hundredth in this case
okay now the last case 7.885 followed by all zeros
that's another number that's halfway between two numbers rounded to the nearest hundredth
so in this case eight is even
so we just we round down and to round down we just truncate
just throw these bits these these digits away and we get 7.88
so there any questions about this
question back here yes
[student question]
yes that's so the question was if
numbers that have the same exp field
will those numbers be equally spaced on the number line and the answer is yes
yes question
[student question]
all the time in the last example otherwise it would round up
yeah the only the half way values are always in this case because it's base 10
the the half way number in base 10 is 5
and then it's always the half way number in this case 5 followed by all zeroes
you'll always have that the half way, if a value is halfway between
like 200 it'll always have that form
alright now we can do the same thing with with binary fractional numbers as well
now a binary number is even
if the least significant digit is 0
ok we only have 2 digits right so odd is 1 and 0 is even
and the halfway so the halfway value is going to be a 1 followed by all zeros
ok that represents exactly halfway
so it's analogous to the base 10 example
except where the halfway value is going to be one followed by all zeros
so let's look at some examples
so suppose we have we want to represent 2 3/32
and suppose we only have four bits to do that in
okay well to represent that exact we need seven bits
and so we have to round
okay so let's look at
so we're going to round to this two bits right of the binary point
and so let's look at all the bits that follow that
so since it starts with zero
this is going to be less than halfway
so since it's less than halfway we just truncate
just chop those out and the result is 10.00
now our next example is 10.00110
so if we look at these the bits to the right of the
to the right of the the bit we're rounding to
since it starts with one and it's not followed by all zeros
that's greater than half
so in this case we have to round up and so the way we do that
that is we take we take one and we add it to this leftmost one right here and
add just do the addition and the result is 10.01
now let's look at 2 7/8
this is represented as 10.11100
now here's that halfway marker that we were looking for
it's a 1 followed by all 0 so this is exactly halfway
so now we have to round to the nearest even
number now that if we can't just truncate because then it would be an odd number
right we would end 10.11 is an odd number
so we have to round up
and we do that by adding,we do that by adding a 1
right here it is to this less leftmost red bit we add one to that
and then just do the addition
and we end up with 11.00 which is three
so the nearest value to 2 7/8
the nearest rounded value is that is 3
okay last example 2 5/8
we have the same halfway marker again 100
but in this case the hundredths bit
are the 1/4 bit is 0
so that's even so we can just truncate we just throw those bits away
and the result is simply 10.10
it makes sense
so it's very mechanical mainly you just need to be able to recognize that halfway marker
and then figure out if you need to round up or down
if you're going to round down just truncate
if you're going to round up add a 1 and just propagate it to get your result
okay now we won't spend much time I just
want to mention a few things about multiplication in addition
so if we multiply two numbers
so we have different mantises significance and exponents
and suppose that the result is Mx2^e
the sign bit will be the XOR of the two sign bits of the two operands
the significant m will be the multiplying m1 times m2
and the exponents are added right
because they just missed by the rules of exponents
so if M >= 2 and this is a normalized number
we have to put it in the range between 1 and 2 by shifting
to the right and incrementing the exponent
if E is out of range then we overflow 2 to infinity
and then if M has too many bits we have to use round 2 even
to fit it into the available fragments
ok addition so suppose we're trying to add two floating point numbers
conceptually what you do is think of those numbers as fractional binary numbers
you want to line up the binary points
line up the binary points then do the addition
and then normalize the number
so that the normalized the significant so it's between 1 & 2
and either do that by shifting shifting right or left
if he is too big then you overflow
and then you round the the bits and M to fit into the available frac field
now remember when we the first day of class
we talked about what you call these great realities
that ints aren't really integers and floats aren't really reals
just as we saw when we looked at two's complement representation of integers
it's not exactly
they're not exactly exactly like real integers
and operations on them aren't exactly like real integers
but they follow very predictable mathematical properties
okay that are similar to integers but not quite
so the same thing holds for floating-point numbers
they follow very predictable
they have very predictable mathematical properties
but they're somewhat different from the reals
and the big thing is that
the big thing with addition is that it doesn't associate
okay it's commutative but it's not associative
and this usually happens when you're dealing with numbers
that have very large dynamic ranges
so if you're trying to add and subtract really big numbers with really little numbers
you run into this this problem of non associativity
so the example was if we take 3.14 +  2^10
2^10 is so is so much larger than 3.14
that when we ,the bits that would be 2^10 + 3.14
the the bits that represent the 3.14
you know there's bits way out here that represent
there's one bit out here that represents 2^10
then there's a few bits here they represent 3.14
and there's just not enough we don't have enough bits to represent all those
so we have the 3.14 goes away
so adding a big number to a little number essentially gives the big number
and then if you subtract that big number you get zero
now if we change the the associate the
if we take this big number and subtract it from itself we get zero
and then so the result will be instead of zero as before we get 3.14
so other than that you you have all of the things
that you would normally expect
closed under addition it's commutative there's a additive identity of zero
except for infinities and Nan's there's an additive inverse
you can take for any number there's
there's an inverse that will give you zero when you add it together
and you get Monotonicity，
monotonicity between values except of course for infinities and ends
now multiplication has simha's it's similar
you get it's closed generally under multiplication it's commutative
but it's not associative and it doesn't distribute over addition
and it's the same so here you can see we're taking two to xx x - 2 xx x - 2 xx and then so that gives infinity
but if we reassociate and we take
I'm sorry to to the (1e20*1e20)*1e-20
well this first multiplication is infinity
and anything you do with infinity is just infinity so the result is infinity
however if we reassociate and multiply to xx times 2 to the minus xx
that gives us 1 and then x - 2 xx and so we get 2 to the 20th
so the big takeaway point here is that
a floating point floating point is an associative
ok now is that a problem
it's something you have to be aware of and
but generally I mean I I've done a lot of scientific computing in particular modeling
earthquake ground motion in Southern California
so basically we would we would build models of Southern California in the computer
and then we would shake them
and then we would see how the ground moves in like Los Angeles
and those that's shaking we used a numerical method called finite elements
and it was all it used all floating point single precision floating point numbers
and we never ran into a problem this with this associativity right
we would do we would do operations in different orders
we couldn't always guarantee that we would do the operations in the exact same order
but we never ran into a problem with this because
nature and generally in general is kind of smooth right that
if you look at the you know if one part of the ground is shaking like this and
you look at the next part it might be shaking a little more or a little less
but you're not going to have like huge differences
and so we never ran into those kind of problems
but in some so if generally if you if you're simulating natural phenomena
you don't often see these kind of huge dynamic ranges
but other times you know if it's not non natural financial
maybe financial systems they use floating point
then you might see this larger dynamic the numbers and it might become a problem
so as a programmer you just generally have to be aware of this
you have to have a good sense for the dynamic range of your numbers
and you have to keep in mind that if you reassociate or change the order of things
you may not get exactly the same exactly the same answer
okay no see gives us two different kinds of floating points
so they the float is the IEEE single precision and double is the IEEE double precision
now you remember when we did casting between ints and unsigned values back and forth
the cast never changed the bit representation it just changed the way that
in fact it never even changed the the be what the a
how the a oh you manipulated those bits
it's really just a how were interpreting and how we're viewing those those values
however when you do cast between floats and ints and doubles
the bit representation changes
right so a cast here has a dramatic effect on the actual bits themselves
now if we go from a double or a float to an int
it's going to truncate the fractional part and give us the
give us the the integer part and then round to fit
oh actually no there won't be...
okay so think about this how many there were you said 23 23 frac bits and float
and I forget exactly how many in doubles
doesn't matter it's some number well no it does matter
let's so for a float if we cast a float to an int
we're casting 23 something that we can represent with 23 at most 23 frac bits into a 32 bit
it so we won't will never lose so we won't we'll never need to do any rounding
but double-precision has 52 bits
okay so there we may not be able to fit the represented integer into the int
so they'll have to be some rounding
sorry PowerPoint crashed
okay right now if we cast,if we cast from an int to a double
there's will have will have enough debt so we won't lose anything right
the 32 bits will fit in the double precision frac field
and but int to float has there's more bits than an int that then
there are in the frac field of a float
so we'll have to do some rounding right so the
so casting works the same way as any other operation
you can think of it as just taking the assume you have an infinite number of bits
get the exact result and then round it to fit into the available bits
all right so let's the final thing I want to do today is
sort of test your understanding do solve some puzzles to test
test our understanding of these properties of floating-point numbers
so imagine that we have three values X as an int F is a float and D is a double
and then we're evaluating the C, C expressions
so x is, x == (int)(float) x
yeah[student answer]
how you can edit out the.you can edit out that other stuff
okay all right so what do you think if we so
if we take X which is an int cast it to a float
and then cast that back to an int will that always be equal to X
no
right as we lose some bits right we don't have enough frac bits in float
what about if we take X cast it to a double and then cast it back to int
well we always get equivalent value yeah
because we have enough frac bits and none in double
now what if we take a float F cast it to a double and then cast it back to a float
well that always equal the original F
yeah what about the converse though
what if we take the double D cast it to a float can cast it back to a double
no
how about this, how about if we take F,
negate it and then negate that again will that always equal F
yeah because we're just toggling a bit right
okay how about 2/3 equal 2/3.0
no because 2/3 is 0
and 2/3.0 is a is a floating point value 2/3 the floating point representation of 2/3
okay how about if the double D is less than 0
does that imply that D*2 is also less than 0
yeah even if no matter what even if 2*D overflows
it will overflow to negative infinity which is less than
which is less than zero
okay how about does the double D greater than F imply that -F is greater than -D
yeah that's that monotonicity right and again it's just...yes
[student question]
oh that's a good question I think it'd be a float
I think if we if you put there's an annotation and see to to give it a double
but actually I'd have to check that out that's....enough yeah that's a good question I don't know
we'd have to check not to go and look in the C guide
how about it is d squared the double d squared always greater than or equal to zero yes
and how about does D plus F minus D always equal F
no because of a lack of associativity
okay so that was that was that was fun right
floating points always fun
so anyway that the big thing is just to realize that floats aren't exactly really reals
but they have very predictable properties
and that they're not associative or commutative they're not associative and
so you have to be careful about that
all right we'll have a good weekend we'll see you on Tuesday