welcome good to see you
today we're going to begin a transitioning from
how our programs interact with hardware to
to how they interact with software in particular system software
and we're going to start that investigation by by studying and learning about a process called linking
which is how the system builds builds your programs ok
so we're going to study the the process of linking
and then I'm going to show you a really cool technique called library inter positioning
which it which allows you to use linking to actually intercept on function calls in in libraries like the standard c library
so it's a very very powerful and interesting technique and it's all enabled by by linking
so let's start with a simple program
this program consists of two modules a main.c and sum.c
sum.C takes as an array as an argument and a length N
and then it sums up the elements of that array and returns the sum  back to the caller
main.c calls the sum function
using and passes it a two element array of intz
and then returns that and then returns the value received from some
yeah we that that's kind of an odd thing to do to return your your exit status like that
but we just did it so that the compiler wouldn't optimize away all of our code
I know let's look at what happens if when we want to compile those those two modules
for each of main.c and sum.c
the GCC calls a series of translators on that on those modules on those .c files
first calls the C preprocessor CPP
then it calls the the compiler the actual compiler which is cc1
the compiler generates assembly which is then translated by the assembler AS
and resulting in a .o file called main.o
similar things happens first for sum.c
so after after the after these three translators work on the code
we have two object files two .o files
the linker takes those those .o files
and put some links them together
sort of smashes them together to form a single executable called that
we can then run then we can then load and run on the system
so the main.c and sum.c they are called source files
these .o files are our object files that
we are separately compiled
but and we call them relocatable object files because they can be combined together
to form the fully linked executable object file
so why do we do it like this you know why why do we allow this so-called separate compilation
you know why don't we just have like one big you know one big file that with all of our code in it
well there's a couple reasons the first is is modularity so by by allowing you to break your code into smaller pieces
you can put related functions into separate source files
you can define libraries of functions
so it's just it's just good technique and it allows you to kind of break your code up into nice to nice modular pieces
the other reason is efficiency
so if if we if we've broken up our program into multiple chunks
if we change and if we if we only need to change one of the chunks
we don't have to recompile the all the other all the other modules
right we can just recompile the one module that we changed and then link them all together again
right so it's it's efficient in time it's also efficient in space
because you can take all of say all of the functions in the standard c library you could put them all together
but then the only functions that you actually get compiled and linked into your program are the ones that you actually call
ok so you can you can save space
you don't you know normally you use only a small subset of the standard C functions and
so you there's no there's no point in linking all of those functions into your code if you don't need them
alright so what do linkers do
well there's two main there's two main tasks that a linker performs
the first is called simple resolution
so programs define and reference symbols
okay that what the linker refers to as symbols and these are global variables and functions
okay in the names and those those objects they're referred to as a symbol
so here we're declaring we're defining a symbol called swap
here we're referring when we call swap we're referring to that symbol
okay that's a reference to the symbol
and here we're defining a pointer to an int called XP
so we're defining XP and we're initializing it to the address of X
so we're referring that's a reference to X
okay so the symbol definitions are stored in the object file by the assembler
in a symbol table which is an array of structs
where each truck contains information about the symbol
like the name of the symbol its size and where it's located
now what we mean by symbol resolution is that during the linker plinking process
the linker associates each symbol reference with exactly one symbol definition
okay so it's possible in multiple
you know why is this an issue well it's possible like in multiple modules
you may declare a global variable with the same name
the linker has to decide which one of those definitions  to use for all subsequent references
now once once the linker is associated a unique object
with each a unique symbol definition with each reference
then it does the second step which is relocation
and during relocation it merges all of the modules together
into a single into a single executable object  module that can be directly loaded
and executed on the system
so when it when it when it does this merging
it has to it has to figure out where each each symbol each function and each variable is going to be stored
okay and this is called relocation
because initially functions are just stored at some offset in their in their object module
right because that the linker doesn't know where those functions are actually going to be eventually a loaded into memory
so before before relocation the address of a function in the object module is just its offset  in the in the module  and similarly for data
during the relocation step the the linker decides on
where each symbol is going to be ultimately located in memory one at X when the program executes
and it binds that that those absolute memory locations to the to the symbol
and then and then it goes and looks at all the references to those symbols
and it updates those references so that they now they point to the correct address
okay so figure out where stuff is going to go
for each definition figure out where it's going to go and for each reference then update that reference
so it now points to the right spot
so let's look at what what these how these steps work in more detail
before that we need to we need to define a few things
so there's there's three kinds of object modules that I've alluded to
there's the dot o file which is a relocatable object module this is the output of the assembler
okay and it's it's not it's a
binary file but it's it's not in any
form that can be directly loaded into
memory it needs to be manipulated by the
linker before it can be actually used
there's the executable object file which
is generated by the linker these are
called a dot out files sometimes
historically the very first Linux
systems the executable this sort of the
default name that they the developers of
UNIX used the default name for their
executables was a dot out so that's just
sort of a historical reason that it's
it's it's called a dot out and then
there's another type of object file
called a shared object file or dot iso
file which is a sort of modern a modern
technique for creating shared libraries
and we'll look at those we'll look at
those later today
now object modules come in a standard format called elf format
and it's it's a unified format for .o files for executables and for .so files
they all use the same format the same general format
so this while these these elf binaries are
their binaries they're very structured
ok and they're broken up into sections
the at the beginning is the is a header
that defines things like the size of the word the byte ordering
whether it's a .o n a .out or a .so
so it just provides some sort of general information about this about this binary
and then there's what's a so called segment header table which
is it only it's only defined for the executable object files
and it indicates where all the different segments of the code
are going to go in in memory so where does your stack go where do your shared libraries go
where does your that you're initialized and uninitialized data
where does your code go right so all these all these various sections are defined in the segment header table
and then there's the code itself which is is called the dot text section for sort of arcane historical reasons
so dot text is always code
and then that's followed by read-only data
such as the jump tables in switch statements
so text and read only the dot text and dot ro data have the property that they're
they're both read-only you don't write to them
then that's followed by the data section
which is contains space for all of your initialized global variables
and then there's a section called BSS
which contain which defines the uninitialized global variables
now this doesn't actually take up any space because they're uninitialized droids
ok but there there are entries in the symbol table for them
and in it at when this program gets loaded these variables are going to need
they're actually going to have to have space allocated for them
BSS is another one of those sort of arcane names that cope goes all the way back to the 60s
for there was an idea of instruction called the block started by symbol
I think a better way to remember what it means is better safe space
ok so you can if you have a separate section for the uninitialized variable since uninitialized
you don't have to you know they don't have to consume any room in the in the .o file
ok there's also a section for the symbol table
this contained like I said it's an array of structs for procedures global variables
and anything defined with the static attribute
and each one of these each one of these symbols gets an entry in the symbol table
and then there's two two sections called them that contain relocation info so this is the notes
when that when the linker went and identified
all the references to symbols it put a little note to say I'm going to have to remember to fix this
the reference to this symbol up when I when I actually create the the executable
so a relocation entry is just like a note that the linker or
that it's a note that the assembler makes to the linker to say hey you're going to have to fix up this this reference
because I don't know I don't know where this symbol is actually going to be stored in memory when it's when it's loaded
okay and then there's a debug section  that contains
information that relates line numbers to in the source code to line numbers in the machine code
okay and so this is called debug and this is what you get when you compile with dash G
and then there's a header table that that tells you where all these different sections start
now to a linker there's there's three different kinds of symbols
global symbols are defined in some module m
and they can and they can be used by other modules
right so I mean did you notice when we if we have a program that consists of multiple modules
and we compile each one of those modules into a dot o file
will be calling functions that aren't defined that are defined by other modules right
okay so those but there's no error though that the compiler doesn't doesn't throw an error
because it's assuming that those are defined in other modules and
it assumes the linker will be able to find them in and determine the address
so anything that's defined with that any global either
either global variable or function name
that's defined without the static attribute is a is a global symbol
okay now and then external symbols are kind of the flip side of that
external symbols are symbols that are referenced by some module
but defined in some other module
okay so in our in our in our little running example when when main .c code
called the function some it was referencing an external symbol
okay and then there's there's local symbols and these are symbols that are defined and referenced within a module
okay and those you create that this is not this is different from local variables
okay the linker you know local see variables are managed by the compiler on the stack
linker has no idea about local local see variables
okay in this context when we talk about a local symbol
what we're talking about is is either is a global a global variable
or function declared with the static attribute
whose that can only be referenced from within that module
so we say that the scope the scope of the a function or global variable defined with the static
attribute is limited to the module that it was defined in
okay so this is in C this is how we do abstraction
and this is how we can create sort of private functions that
and pup private functions that can't be called from from outside that module
okay so for instance if we want to make a library and see
of functions we want to make a collection of functions that
other programs can then call it link into their program and call
the functions that we want to make visible to to other programs are defined without the static attribute
and the functions that we want to have private and just be internal
we declare what the static attribute okay
and that way we get abstraction and we get hiding information hiding
and we're only exposing data and functions that that we want that we want to expose
all right so let's look in detail how the symbol resolution step works
we recall our example our example program
so here we're referencing a global called array
that's defined within main.c
here when we here we're defining main
a global called main
here we're referencing a global called sum
that's defined in sum.c
and val is a local c variable on the stack and linker knows nothing about that okay
now an or doesn't know anything about IRS which are also local variables
now let's just let's make sure that we understand the difference
between local static c variables versus local non static c variables so
here we're defining a local static variable called int
within this function f
now because it's local its scope is limited to this function
so this variable X can only be referenced within function f
and similarly for this definition of X and function G
can only be referenced by by function G
now what's but because it's declared with the static attribute it's not stored on the stack
it's actually stored in in the in dot data just like a global would be
so it's it's like a global in the sense that it's actually stored in dot data rather than the stack
but it's like a local see variable in the sense that its scope is limited just to the function that it's defined in
okay so what what the compiler will do it'll allocate space for each definition of X
so this and it'll give it some name to disambiguate it so maybe it will call this one X dot one
and maybe this one X dot two
so these symbols are allocated in dot data because
because they're initialized and they get symbol table entries just like just like any other symbol
okay so I said that during symbol resolution
the linker associates each reference each symbol reference to exactly one unique symbol definition
now how does it do that if there's multiple symbol definitions across all the modules
so to understand this well will will will define symbols as being either strong or weak
so strong symbols are either procedures or function function names or initialize global variables
weak symbols or uninitialized global variables
okay so int foo here is a strong symbol
because it's initialized we're initializing it p1 is strong by definition
foo is is weak in p2.c this this definition of foo is weak
because it's uninitialized and the definition of p2 is strong
okay so that the rules that the the linker uses are the following
multiple strong symbols not allowed so that's an error
okay so that means that if we if across multiple modules we declare a function with the same name
the linker will throw an error that's not allowed
given a strong symbol and multiple weak symbols if the linker will always choose the the strong symbol
now remember if we initialize a global variable
and we if we declare a an initialized global variable across multiple modules that's an error
because those are strong symbols okay by rule one
but if we have one strong symbol and multiple weak symbols all with the same name
then the compiler will choose the strong symbol
okay and it will associate all references to that symbol will go to that strong symbol
and if there's multiple weak symbols then it just picks an arbitrary one
and this this is we'll see can be problematic now you can override with this GCC flag called no common
and if you if you declare your function with this no common argument
then multiple weak symbols will throw an error in a linker
all right so why do we care about all this stuff well it turns out
if you're not aware of this stuff you can you can run into some really serious problems
that are just perplexing and confounding right so
linker linker errors are like the worst kind
they're the hardest kind of debug because people aren't usually aware of what's going on inside their linkers
and usually it's only like the very best programmers that really understand
you know how these linkers work and what kind of errors they can throw and how to debug them
so let me show you some examples of of these these kind of errors
all right so we have a program we've word we have two modules
so each of these rectangles corresponds to a module
and we're defining p1 in each module so
that's too strong symbols that's an error
okay now here we've we're defining p1 and p2
so we're okay but now we've got two week symbols both are integers variables called X
so and if these modules are referencing X the linker will just pick
it will just pick one of these to serve as the definition
but is is this really what you want
now in this case it doesn't really hurt anything because X is declared in both modules as an int
all right so it'll just be it'll just be some integer sized variable
that and it'll be it'll be somewhere
and but it doesn't really matter which which one the linker chooses
but we start to get into trouble if if we declare these weak symbols  with different types
so here we've declared an int X in one module and a double X in another module
so if we write to X if the linker just arbitrarily chooses this  this symbol definition to use
now this is a symbol that of length 8 of size 8
if we anywhere in this program if we if the linker chooses that then anywhere in the program
those references to those references to X will be to this double word  this double word
even even in this module if we reference X it'll be an 8-byte right
so it will overwrite Y with the
hi order excuse me
oh no it's completely it's just committal just pick one
arbitrarily and you don't know I mean it
alright here's now this is here's a problem we've defined a strong symbol X
because we've initializes so the linker will always
will associate all references to X to this integer sized this integer sized symbol
so if we write
oh yeah right so so rights to X here
this will be a double in this module but it will overwrite Y in this module
so that's really nasty
and here we were defining a strong symbol X
so references to X in the second module will always get it will refer to this initialized variable which might not
so it might not be what you want right
you may you may be assuming that it's uninitialized in your code
okay and then you get the the ultimate nightmare scenario is suppose
you know because we're following a standard ABI we can compile our code with multiple compilers
and this actually happens in some oh yes questions
[student speaking]
oh yeah actually you're right
it will it will still take preference and and you'll be writing a for by quantity
which is is what you want so that slides not quite right
so oh yeah what is the point of doing the static versus non static
if it's always being referenced just locally in constantly what is the point of declaring  it's time
-is it it stores it in like
-no no no it's
if you reference up if you reference a a variable
that's you mean so a variable is defined in your module
and then you...with the static...right
oh they're both they're both local
so you do this if you want to value two to retain
from if you want if you want that variable to retain value from invocation to invocation
so suppose you it's usually a bad idea as we'll see when we study threads
because it makes your code non thread safe
but like early like random number generators
would it would compute a pseudo-random number
and then it would store it in a static variable
and then use that as the the starting value for the next the next time you call that function
so whenever you want values to to persist across function invocation to reduce static
yes something really crash
well wait a minute let me
let me get this straight rights to X and P 2 will actually correspond to the memory
look that it will actually go to the memory location I'm sorry I I need to amend that
so rights to X in P 2 will be 8 bytes
because the compiler you know the compiler knows that it's a double
but it'll go to a memory location that's I that's only 4 bytes
because X because the linker chose the strong symbol
okay so so the rights to X and P 2 will actually overwrite Y
ok I'm sorry yes question
that's just usually the way it happens
you know
no no no global variables go in in data they don't go on the stack
but usually if you define local variables in a function
it will put them it will allocate them one after the other on them on the stack
okay all right so all this discussion about
these these weird strong weak symbol rules that the linker have
it's another reason to avoid global variables if you can
now if if you if you need to declare a global  see if you can declare it static
because that'll limited scope to the the module that it's declared in
so that's a good idea if you can do it
and if you define a global variable initialize it
so that you'll you'll you'll find you'll discover if you have multiple
initialize global symbols with the same name in your code
and then if you want to it's always good practice
if you're referencing an external variable to tell the compiler about it by using the X turn attribute
all right
so now at this point the linker has associated every symbol reference  with some simple definition
now it has to take all those object relocatable object files and smush them together
and create like one one big executable
so suppose with our example a little running example
each main.o and sum.o contain a code and initialize data
sum.o doesn't have any initialize data it just has code
and then there's their system code that actually runs before and after your program so
when when your program run it actually starts executing a startup code from  from lib see
that that sort of initializes things and then the last thing that it does is it calls main  and passes it arcs RC and RV
okay and then when you're when your program exits
well that's a cyst call but if your program if your main function routine does a return
then it returns back to that startup code which then doesn't exit okay
so so this is just and so this this consists of of text and data as well
and so when we when the linker relocates these these object files
it takes all of the the code the text sections from each of the modules
and puts them together contiguously init in the dot text section for the executable object file
ok so it just puts them together in some order that it determines
and it creates a combined dot text section in the executable
that contains all of the system code and the all of the all of the code defined in the modules
and then it does the same thing with the data takes all the all the dot data
sections from the various object files and puts them together
in in one combined data section in the executable
and it also emerges the symbol tables and in the debug information as well
now when it just the act the act of sort of
relocating these these object files requires the linker
to figure out where it's going to actually store these
these these different these different symbols when the system gets when this program gets loaded
so it it has to pick an address for main that
that function will start at some absolute address
it's going to have it's going to do the same for swap so for all the all the data arrays right
and but the problem is is that when this code is
is is compiled the compiler doesn't know what addresses the linker is going to pick
so the so the compiler creates these these reminders to the linker called relocation entries
which which are then stored in the relocation sections of the the object file
and these these relocation entries are instructions to the linker that's something
that there's a reference to a symbol that's going to have to be patched up
when the the code is actually relocated and merged into the executable
so let's look at a couple of these a couple of examples so in
our in our main.c module there was a reference to this  to this global symbol called array
okay and then there was also a reference to this this this global symbol sum which is the function
so the the compiler creates two relocation entries
the first one for the reference to the array a
so here we're moving remember EDI is the first argument
so remember our sum function takes the address of the of array
of the input array as its it's argument
so this move we're moving the address of the array into EDI for the first argument
but the compiler doesn't know what that address is going to be
right so it just it just it just
it just moves in it an immediate value of 0 into EDI temporarily right so you can see this is all zeros
the bf is the move instruction and then there's allsey rows in for now
and then it places this relocation entry in the in the relocation section of Maemo
and it it says it says to the linker at addre at offset a
so these let me remind you these are our main.o
module only contains one one function
so that function starts that offsets zero in the in the code section
of the module in the dot text section of the module
if there were other functions in this module they would they would follow immediately after
ok and it so you can see what what the compiler is it's just all it's just generating offsets of these instructions
from the beginning of the dot text section
and it it includes this relocation entry which says  to the linker hey
when you're relocating main.o add offset a in this dot text section
you've got a reference a 32 a reference to an array in the form of a 32-bit address
ok so that so eventually the linker is going to have to patch up these
so this is address 9 this is address a
it's going to have to patch up the four bytes starting at address a
with the absolute address of the symbol array
and then similarly the reference to the reference to
this the reference to this function some
the compiler has no idea where some
actually will end up it doesn't even know what module it's in or even if it's
even if it is defined in a module
so in this case it just it does a call with all zeros
and then it adds this relocation entry that says to the linker
at offset F you've got a four byte pc-relative reference  to a function
to assemble called sum
and then it this is sort of a arcane detail that but and it includes
there's an option to include a bias in the in the offset
and since we're using since calls are since calls are always resolved using pc-relative addressing
the value that's going to be placed here at these four bytes that offset F
is going to be an offset from the current or I p value or program or counter value
and since the program counter always points to the nest get next instruction
it includes this which is four bytes away it includes this
this offset of minus four
so if it sits I I talked about it in detail in the book if you really want to know  how this works
but just the point here is that there's enough information for the linker to actually fill in the right address
so now if we look at the relocated text section
so if we if we compile this code into an executable and then we use object on to to disassemble it
then what you see is this this reference here
where we move the address of the address of a into EDI
those four bytes which were original zero have now been updated with the the actual address of array in in memory at runtime
okay so the linkers decided that the array is going to go at address 0x601018
and then it's it's actually patched that the four bytes in the cup in the in the move instruction with that absolute address
and the call to sum is is it's also been updated
but this one's interesting right that
so the the address it's been updated with the PC relative address of five
okay so when this program runs
this call instruction
what it will do when it when it determines when it computes the absolute address of of the function sum
it will take
it will take the the current value of the program counter which is the next instruction so 0x4004e3
and it will add to it whatever whatever value is in this immediate field
okay which is a two scomp you interpret it as a two's complement integer so it can go
it can be relative you can go - or or +
in this case it's saying that the function that you want to call is that is is at 4004e3 + 5
which is 4004e8 which is the address of some
okay and so the linker the linker does that the compiler has all the smarts
the compiler computed the relocation entry
the linker is just blindly going through each of those relocation entries and just doing what it's told
okay but the net result is that now all of these these references have been patched up with with valid absolute addresses
now once the linkers created a an object file
that object file can be loaded the code and data
and that object file can be loaded directly into memory with with no further modification
ok so the if you look at all of the read-only sections in the executable
so there's this init section which
we're not to worry about that that all the code is in the dot text and things like jump tables are in our Oh data
all of this data can be loaded directly into memory as is
okay so these bytes can just be copied directly into into memory
and that that forms the so called a read-only code segment
the the data in the .data and BSS X sections can also be copied directly into into memory
and in the case of the variables and data they'll be initialized to a value that's stored in the symbol table
so we're drawing our our memory here
this is the this is the the memory address space that every Linux program sees
and we're drawing addresses starting from 0 and going up increasing as we grow up
and every program is loaded at this the same address  0x400000
and so the the code comes directly from the object file the data comes directly from the object file
and then that's followed by a runtime heap
which is created and managed by malloc
so when you need dynamic dynamically need to allocate memory
like using malloc that memory comes out of this heap
which starts immediately following the the data segment and grows upwards
the stack is at the very top of the the visible
memory that's available to application programs
the memory above that is is restricted to the kernel
okay so if you try to access those memory locations you'll get a seg fault
and then the stack as we know grows down so this is managed and created a run time
and then there's this region somewhere in this huge gap between the stack and the heap
there's a region for shared libraries so the dot Esso files all get loaded into this this memory mapped region for shared libraries
now that the top of the heap is indicated by this global variable
maintained by the kernel called break BRK
and the the top of the stack as we know is is maintained by the general purpose register RSP
now there's a little bit of a this is a little bit of a simplification
if you actually look at the addresses returned by malloc
there's actually a there's actually two heaps
there's a heap up here and in the high memory that grows down
that's used for large objects very large
you know if you mount like a whole bunch of space and then the heap that grows up is  is reserved for smaller smaller objects
so I'm not really sure why they do this
I think it allows them to have separate allocation algorithms for large objects and small objects
okay so one of the one of the real advantages of linking is that allows us to create libraries of things
so it's always something we want to do as programmers we always
we always want to create abstractions and then present those abstractions to to users
right and we do that by creating libraries defining an API
yes
I think it just is no no it
actually that's a good question I the things I've done it just grows until it runs out of memory right there
so I don't think actually that's a really good question I mean I've
I've done those experiments and it it eventually reaches some limit
yeah I don't I don't know it's a very large number
but I so you know as programmers we always want to abstract define api's
implement package up those api's and make them available to to other programmers
so how can we actually do that how can we make commonly used functions available to other programmers
well one thing given what we've learned so far you could just take all the functions
and put them all in a single big C file right
and then programmers would just link that C file into their into their programs if they want to use them right
another option would be to take that might get kind of unwieldy if it's a big library right
lipsi has hundreds and hundreds of functions
so another option would might be to just take each function put it in a separate file
and then compile them all together and compile and link them all together
so this is more space and time efficient than then our first option
but it seems like it would be burdensome on the programmer because
the program would have to know where all the all these functions were and put them in make files
it'd just be a lot of you know this you could end up with a ridiculously large  command line to GCC
so that the one solution to this problem is that
the first solution that the developers of Unix came up with us
something called a static library
so the the idea where the static library is that you create this archive  called a dot a file
which is  it's just a collection of .o file where each .o file contains a function
ok so you take all the functions in your library you use option two to create a bunch of .o files
and then you use a program called an archive or AR  to take those .o files
put them together in a all together in a big file called an archive
out with a with a table of contents at the beginning that tells you the offset of each one of the .o files
ok so an archive is just this concatenated collection of .o files
and then and then you link you pass that archive to the to the linker
and it only takes the .o files that are actually referenced   and links them into the code
right so it's a more efficient way you can have a huge archive
but like Lib.c but if you only call printf
the only dot o file you get is printf .o
okay so the way this works is
as before we take
now we take all the functions we want to put in our library
we run them through our translators to get .o files
we pass those to the archiver to get a the archive
so in this case Lib CA
and which has this code for printf that we might want to use
right and so we can we can we can recreate that archive anytime we want
so if one of these functions changes like say printf changes
you just rearchive the dot recompile printf and then re archive all of the .o files
so in Libc it's it's about 1500 object files
and it's archived things like printf scanf simple integer math  and there's also a math library
which has you know several hundred common functions for things like
floating point math sine cosine tangent etc
these libraries the convention is that a library always is prefixed with Lib with Li B and then a
nd then sort of new some indication of what it what it does
so now let's see how linking with these static libraries would work
so I've created a little example here
I've created a library called libvector.a
and it consists of functions that manipulate vectors
and this is a real simple library it just adds
there's a function to add two vectors x and y together and and return the result in Z
and then another similar function that will do pairwise multiplication of two vectors so
x[i]*y[i] equals z[i]
now I compile these two programs and pack I want to package them into an archive called lib vector a
and then in my in my main program I'm going to call one of those functions advic
to add these two vectors x and y together
so now what happens when we compile this this program
we've already we've constructed the archive lib dr. a  from addvec.o and multvec.o
and we pass that archive to the linker along with our main 2.0 relocatable object file
and we also pass it libc.a
which has the definition of which contains printf.o
and anything else that printf.o my call
so these three the linker detects the reference to advic the function addvec
and so it just pulls addvec.o out and and ignores the rest
similarly for printf.o and then it compiles all those
main main.o addvec.o and printf.o all together into this fully linked executable
called prog to see for compiled time
so we're doing this we're doing this link we're doing this this linking at compile time
when we call a GCC now
what the linker does when it's when it's using static libraries
it scans all the dot o files and dot a files in order on the command line
so you're just typing GCC and then a list of dot o files and davay files in some order
so so during the scan it keeps a list of the current unresolved references right
so if let's say let's say it looks at main dot o first and there's a reference to printf
that's an unresolved reference because print is not not defined in main.o
so that goes in a list of undefined references
and at some point or another as as each new .o file or .a file is encountered
the linker tries to resolve its list of Unruh of references with the symbols that are defined in that .o file or ,a file
and then if there's any entries in the list at the end of the scan then there's  error
okay so that the key here is that the linker will try to resolve these references from left to right on the command line
and so this is another sort of important thing for you to know as programmers
because the order that you that you put your files on the command line actually makes a difference
okay so you can get sort of weird baffling linker errors if you if you use the wrong order
so for instance suppose we've got
a function an object module called Lib test
that calls a function that's defined in in lmine.a
okay so these - else - big L period that that says to look for
to look for a library files in the current directory
that's what the dot look there first and then look in the normal places that you look
and the the -l that's a it's like an abbreviation
we could replace this with just the fully spelled out lib mind ed
okay but you'll see this this  -l used a lot
so so Lib test calls a function that's declared in in Lib mind.a
so the linker looks at it looks at the unresolved symbols in libtest.o
and it detects that there's this unresolved function let's say it's called foo
I know it's it's called Lib fun
so and it puts it on the list and then it goes on to the next command line entry  and that's live mine.a
and in there it finds it finds this symbol of libfun
and it it resolves the reference to that - Lib phone - the actual address the relocated address
now if we switch the order and we put lmine on a first followed by libtest.o
well there's there's no unresolved references in this library
right it's just the collection of function definitions
so it there's no unresolved references so the linker looks at that that's all good
and then it looks at lib toss zero and now there's an unresolved reference to two libfun
but we're out of we're at the end of the command line
so that's a linker error
so you get this you get this really cryptic error message
and if you didn't know about this ordering rule you wouldn't have any idea how to debug
it okay so the static libraries are kind of the old fashioned solution that
the modern solution is to use dynamic libraries or shared shared libraries
so the reason the reason there's this sort of newer form of libraries
that static libraries have some some disadvantages
so every if you compile with static libraries
then every every function that uses printf
which or every program that uses printf has to have a copy of printf
okay but almost every every program uses printf right
so there's a shared shared libraries allow provide a mechanism where there can just be one
wherever there's just one instance of a shared library  member like like printf
and every program running on the system will share that one copy
so that's the that's sort of the big big disadvantage is this potential duplication
so shared libraries are different in the sense that they contain
code and data that are linked and loaded into the program not when it's not when it's compiled
and linked and into a executable object file
but actually when the program is loaded into the system
so linking of references to shared library objects is deferred
until the program is actually loaded into into memory
until the executable object file is actually loaded into memory
and this can either and it can even happen
it can happen when the program is actually loaded into memory but it can also happen at runtime anytime at runtime
so you can be you can be running a program
and that program can arbitrarily decide to load a function that's declared in a shared library
okay and I'll show you that it's really cool
now these things are often called they're called shared libraries
they're called dynamic link libraries like in Windows they're called DLLs
.iso files they're all referenced the same thing
okay so that this like I said you can the the dynamic linking can occur when the program's loaded or
after it's loaded and actually running
and there's this sort of big deal that shared library routines can be shared by multiple processes
and we'll look at this this will make sense when we look at virtual memories
so don't don't worry about that now
but but here's how the process works
so we've first we have to create instead of creating an archive
we create a shared library so our live vector routines
instead of creating an archive a file we create a shared a .so file
using the using the shared argument to GCC
so we take our two input functions a addvec and multvec
and share it says to create and we're telling GCC to create a shared library  and place it in libvector.so
okay and so and there's also that the the C the C developers have created a punctured library called libc.so
that contains printf and on it and other standard library functions
so we take our program main2 this is the same program that calls advic
and we compile it into main2.o
and we pass main2.0 and  these .so files to the linker
now the linker doesn't at this point it doesn't actually copy let's say we're using advic or printf
it doesn't actually copy those functions or do anything with them  in the executable
it just makes a note in the symbol table that those functions will need to be the
references to those functions will need to be resolved  when the program is loaded
okay so it it puts in a relocation entry that says fix this up when you load the program
so it's partially linked but it's not fully linked
you can't take that you can't take a program you can't take a executable file
that was dynamically linked and loaded directly
what you what you do is the loader which is the execve system call
and we'll learn more about that but just this is just a cyst call that loads
loads executables into memory and runs them
the loader takes the executable
and then it takes the the shared .so files
that this program needs k it also made when the linker also made a note of which .so files  it needs
so the loader calls the dynamic linker which takes those .so files
and then actually resolves all the references to any on any unresolved reference
okay so the the address of addvwc the addvec and printf functions isn't determined until
the program is loaded and by that and it isn't determined by the dynamic linker until the program is loaded
so that the dynamic linker does it goes through a similar process that the static linker did
sort of fixing up references to add back at references to to printf
and then at that point the binary the binary is in it is in a form that can be executed directly
so question yes what if you look the part where did like where is that like if you include violence and use anger and greed zero actually
if okay the question is what happens if you include a file
so includes are handled by the C preprocessor
so they're gone they're long gone by the time the by the time the linker gets around to it
okay so the C preprocessor just takes sharp sign define sharp sign include
and and interprets those and outputs another C program
so if you if you include a file the C preprocessor just takes that file and just expands it
and the output C program contains an expanded version of all the files that you include it
okay now what's really cool is that you can also do this dynamic linking at runtime
so what I showed you before we're doing it at load time
but you can also arbitrarily decide to to load link and
call a function from a shared from a from any function defined in a .so file
and the way you do it is there's a there's an interface called the dl open
that's in Lib C that allows you to do this
this and so let's say we want to this is this is our main program and just like before we want to call addvec
okay but addvec now is defined in it in a .so file
the exact same .so file that we generated before
when we compile so we'll call this dll.c when we compile this program ddl.c
we have no we have no idea that it's going to call a function from from Lib.so
we just compile it as though a standalone C C program
within this program though we declare a pointer a function pointer called addvec
and we give the prototype for this function
it's pointers city so it's a two input arrays the output array on the size
and then first we dynamically load the shared library that contains the function we want
so we call dlopen and we say load up this this .so file into memory
so that I can call a function
but don't resolve you know don't worry don't worry about the
resolving the references to it functions until I actually tell you too
that's the lazy part
and so what what this deal open returns a handle
that that then you use in subsequent calls okay
so if we don't if the handle is null there was some kind of error like maybe maybe this data so file does exist
so once we've opened that .so file then we use dlsym with the handle so this
and then we we give it as we pass as a string the name of the function that we want to invoke
and we get what we get back from dlsym as a pointer to that function
and then we can we can use that function just like any other function so we can use that function pointer
and we call it just as though it were a statically defined function
so you can see this is real very powerful technique
okay so looks let's finish the the last little bits of the class
I want to show you it to try to convince you that linking is is actually interesting which is kind of a hard sell sometime
yes question...yes...no it's that's how you know
no you just it's it's declared as a function pointer
and you then you just you just you just use the name of the function you don't have to dereference it
or you just you call it you call the function by just using that that that function pointer name okay
just like I did
if you dereference it I just get back a pointer value
you get back the address of that function
all right so it's kind of a hard sell to that to convince you that linking is is interesting
but I'm going to try
ok so there's there's this powerful technique called inner library inter positioning
and the goal is to intercept function calls from from libraries
and do something intercept them for for some reason
right so what we typically want to do is intercept a function call
maybe record some to some statistics or do some error checking
and then call the real function as intended
right so so the idea is we're going to create wrappers
and when the program when a program calls a function what we're going to do is we're going to execute its wrapper instead
okay and we're going to do it without changing any of the source
now there's a lot of reasons there's a lot of applications for this
that the neatest one that that I know is that these Facebook engineers
so we're trying to deal with this year-long bug in the Facebook iPhone app
and nobody could figure out what was going on
and they figured it out using library inter positioning
they figured out that there was something in the network stack writing to the wrong location
they figured it out by intercepting all the calls from their Facebook app  that did rights
so things like write write to the EP right
so they just they intercepted all those calls and then they were able to
to when they looked at the arguments and how those functions were being called
they determine the air
you can also use it for monitoring and profiling like
so if you want to know like how many times different functions get called you can you can do you can interpose
we use it for for generating address traces
so you're malloc when you do your malloc lab later in the semester
you're going to be evaluating your malloc using a traces
that we generated from real programs using this inter positioning technique
right so we we enter post on all the malloc and free calls in like Netscape
and then we just recorded what addresses and and sizes
Malik was was returning and what what blocks free was freeing up
and we just created a trace of those and and then so let me show you how you would do this
so the idea let's say we have this main program
and the idea is to trace all the malloc and free calls
so there's one malloc call and there's one free call
and we want to know what these addresses are and we want to know what these sizes are
so we can do this at either compile time link time or run time
to do it at compile time
we first write wrapper functions called my malloc and my free
where my malloc call most the real malloc function
and then it prints out the the size that it was called and the the address that malloc returned
okay so this when we run our program it will it will print out these all these addresses
and it does the same thing for free
and then here's the trick in malloc.h
we we define malloc to be my malloc  okay and free to be my free
and then we give the prototype for it so the compiler doesn't get confused
and then we can PI might we compile my malloc C into a .o file
and then we call week then we complete we call our program
which is is our main program int dot C for inner positioning
and we call that and here's the trick
we call it with the - cap I argument
and we say look for any include files in the current directory
okay so this was similar to that el - cap el argument
but because we tell GCC to look in the current directory first
so this is sort of where the inner positioning happens
this because when it does that it's going to it's going to find a
it's going to find a library called malloc.h
I mean .h file called malloc.h
and so all the calls to malloc will be translated by the C preprocessor to my malloc
so when we run this it prints out the the trip malloc and free trace
now we can also do this at link time
so we can tell C in order to do this we had to get access to the
we had to compile the program we didn't have to change it but we had to compile it
we can use link time at our positioning if to avoid that that that compilation
so the way this works we define our wrapper functions with this special name underscore underscore wrap malloc
and this calls the real malloc function and then prints out the information
and then at link time then we do the inter positioning by calling the linker with this special -WL  argument
and so what this does the the -wl flag to GCC says hey
take what follows the argument that follows replace all the commas with spaces
and then invoke the linker with this argument
okay so what we're doing is passing a linker arguments to the linker
and this - - wrap argument to the linker
it tells the linker to resolve all references to Malik as underscore underscore wrap Malik
and all references to underscore real Malik - should be resolved as Malik
okay so anywhere in the program what we call Malik it'll be resolved to underscore underscore wrap Malik
and it will invoke our wrapper and then the wrapper calls real Malik
which which by because of this flag resolves to the the actual Malik routine
now here you can also in the really the really amazing thing
is you can also do this inter positioning it load timer and run time  when the program is loaded
so you don't even need access to the dot o files all you need is access to the executable
right and for every program we have access to the executable
so think about that we can take any program
and we can interpose on its library calls at runtime
so the way we do this is we write the wrapper function now uses the dlsym call that we saw before
and we call it with this special function the special argument called next
and we silver and what this is saying is get the address of the real malloc
okay so and we're going to we're going to trick the linker into looking first
to our our implementation of malloc
but here we want the real one so we're telling it to get to look in the next place its next place that it would normally look
and and and fetch the the address of malloc
so the result is a pointer a function pointer called mallocp
and then we can just call that function to get to call the Lipsy Malik
and then print out the the data
okay we do the same thing for free.st. we use dlsym in exactly the same way for free
and then the inter positioning now happens when the program is loaded
so notice we built this our main program now in tar for run time inter positioning
we built it I'm sorry we created our .so file mymalloc.so  using the shared argument
and then and then we we compiled int
int.c into this executable called intr
but notice there's no mention of mymalloc.so anywhere
and now the inner positioning happens when we actually run the program
and we do it we we affect the the inner positioning by setting an environment variable  called LD-preload  to mymalloc.so
and so what this is a environment variable that tells the dynamic linker
to look first in the the value it looked first in the the value of LD preload is a list of locations
look first in those locations when to resolve references
and only only later look in the normal system places
so we're saying to look in mymalloc.so unresolved references first
and then and then we're invoking so this is in bash this is how you initialize an environment variable
so we're initializing it to mymalloc.so and then we're loading and running the program
and so the LD so all the references to malloc get turned into the references to the wrapper function
the malloc function that we defined in in our program okay
so that's uh so that's it so that that inter positioning is a really cool technique
and it's only it's only possible because of linkers so
alright so good we'll see you on on Thursday and good luck with your cache labs