all right good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you
so today we're going to look at an idea called exceptional control flow
that's a very important part of making modern systems
and it exists at all levels of the system from the lowest level Hardware all the way up to software
so the idea is when when you turn on a computer from the very from the very first time you turn it on
on it just does execute one instruction after another until that you turn it off
okay and if each core if you have multiple cores
then each of those cores are executing instructions one after the other
now the the sequence of instructions is called the control flow
okay and the the actual sequence of instructions that the hardware is executing is called the physical control flow
now normally normally this control flow
that executes just one instruction after another just sequentially in memory
and we've so far we've seen two two mechanisms for altering the control flow
so that it's it's not so that we're not executing just the next instruction
so that's branches and jumps and procedure call and return
okay now now jumps and call it branches jumps call and return
those are reacting to changes in program State
so when you do a branch you check the control condition codes
and then based on some the results of that comparison then you then you do the branch
okay but it real system needs to be able to adapt to changes in the system State
okay so for example data arrives from a disk
or some network use types control C
okay the program executes an illegal instruction
okay all of these represent some change some kind of change in the in the system State
and we need some way to react to that
that so this the so what we need is we call this exceptional control flow
because it's sort of outside of the normal control flow that we we see in our programs
now exceptional control flow or ECF exists at all levels in the system
from the very lowest level of hardware
at the very lowest level  we have what are called exceptions
and these are changes in the control flow in response to some low level system event
so this is a or and by event we mean a change in the state
now exceptions are implemented using a combination of hardware and os software
which we'll see in it in a minute
but these these exceptional control flow exists at higher levels too
so in the a process context switch is an example of exceptional control flow
that's also it's implemented by a hardware and the operating system kernel
and it so a process context switches we'll see later later today
you're executing you're executing your code in the current in your current process
and then all of a sudden this the system is executing code from another process
right so your process gets like suspended
and so there's a so that's a form of exceptional control flow
where you're executing statements instructions within one one process and then
all of a sudden you're executing statements instructions in another process
um at a higher level are totally in software
we have the idea of a signal
and this is implemented by operating system software and we'll learn all about signals next lecture
and then even higher at an even higher level you have non-local jumps in C
which are just implemented by the C run library
so this allows you non-local jumps allow you to break the normal call and return pattern
so from one from within a function normally you can only return to the the function that calls that called you
non-local jumps allow you to within a function break that
and return to some other some other function or some other part of the code
so we'll look at signals and non-local jumps next lecture
today we're going to look at exceptions and processes
so an exception is a transfer of control to the operating systems kernel
where the kernel is the memory resident part of the operating system you know
so an operating system provides all kinds of programs like
to list files to change directories to list the current processes
so all of that stuff constitutes the operating system
the kernel is the part of the operating system that's always resident in memory
so an exception is this really low-level transfer of control to the operating system
because something happened in the system
so you're executing your code user code
and then something happens some event so by event we mean there's some change in the system state
in response to that there the exception transfers control from from your user code to code in the kernel
which is called an exception Handler
and then the kernel responds to that change in some way
this is called the exception processing
and then there's three there's three things that can happen after the kernel handles the exception
it can return and re execute that the current instruction
okay and we'll see this is this is useful for things like page faults   allows us to implement virtual memory
it could return to the next instruction
which I've shown here or it could abort
now exceptions are implemented by hardware and software
so the the actual transfer of control
you know the change in the program counter or IP is is is done by the hardware
but the code that executes as a result of that exception is set up and determined by the operating system kernel
so every every type of event has a unique exception number
which serves as an index into a jump table called an exception table
okay and so when when event K happens
then the hardware looks uses K as in as an index into this table
and gets the address of the exception handler for that for that for that exception
and so every time that event K happens that handler handler K is invoked
now there's a different kinds of exceptions we distinguish them as being asynchronous or synchronous
asynchronous exceptions happen as a result of changes in state that are occurred outside the outside of the processor
so these are called interrupts
and those changes in state are are the processor is notified about those changes in state by setting a pin on the on the processor
an external pin called the interrupt pin
so this is the kind of when see a disk controller finishes doing a direct memory access
and copying data from the disk into memory
it notifies the processor that it's finished that copy by setting the interrupt pin hi okay
and so after an interrupt happens the handler returns to the next instruction
so an interrupt typically it's the so you're running your program you're running your program and then there's like this little
there's like this little pause while the interrupt handler runs and then your program just continues to run okay
so it's it's usually sort of done behind the scenes and doesn't doesn't affect your execution of your program
now the most common or a common example of a interrupt is the timer interrupts
so you're all systems have a a built-in timer that goes off every few milliseconds
and when it when the timer goes off it sets the interrupts in high
and there's a special exception number four for timer interrupts
and this is we need this in order for the
this allows we need this to allow the kernel to get control of the system again otherwise
a user program could just run forever in an infinite loop
and no one would be no way for the operating system to get to get control
so every few milliseconds this timer goes off that causes a transient exception into the into the kernel
and then the kernel can as we see the kernel can decide what to do
maybe maybe schedule a new process or let the current process run
and then and then this an i/o interrupt from an external devices is also a common example
now the other class of exceptions are synchronous exceptions
and there are three classes of those
one is that one class is called the trap a trap is a intentional exception
so this is an  exception that's caused intentionally by the program
and the most the most common form of a trap is a system call
so you know the operating system kernel provides all kinds of services to to a program
but your program doesn't have direct access your program can't call functions in the kernel
it can't access data directly in the kernel
because that memory is protected and and unavailable to user programs
so what the kernel does is they provide a interface
that allows programs to make requests to effectively call functions within the kernel  and to make requests for various services
and this this interface is called a system call
ok so a program makes a system call
and and and requests various functions from the kernel
the kernel provides those sort of reacts to that request
and then returns control back to the the function there the calling program
so you can think of a system call as kind of it's a
it looks like a function call but it's really transferring control into the kernel
okay then there's some so traps are intentional faults are unintentional but but may be recoverable
okay so things like page faults which
when we will learn more about these when we study virtual memory
but something like a page fault it's actually recoverable
it just that the kernel has to it means that the the data the portion of the address space that your program referenced isn't actually in memory
it needs to be copied from disk where it's stored into memory
and then the instruction that that that caused a fault needs is just restarted and then it works
that the the memory is is there and then the instruction works properly
but other faults are unintentional unrecoverable like protection fault
so if you try to access a portion of memory that's that's not allocated
or floating-point exceptions often times those those can be recoverable
so eat in either case when there's a fault it either re-execute the current instruction or to boat or or the boards
and then there's unintentional and unrecoverable exceptions which are called the boards and those  those always abort
so if you execute an illegal instruction if there's a problem with your memory memory and it's it's corrupted
there's some problem with the machine those creative warts that that always
that are unrecoverable and never return back to the to the program
now system calls there's many different kinds of system calls and they all have their own unique number
which is assigned by by Linux
so in a for example to read a file there's a system call called read
which is number zero opening a file a system call number two  and so on
and there's a there's an instruction called syscall
which actually performs the the system call
now you usually don't use this system call and strike the syscall instruction directly in your program the
Linux wraps those in system level functions which actually call it for you
but it it's interesting to see how it actually works
so opposed you want to open a file you call the system level function called open
with a file name and some options say read only write only
and so in at the syscall instruction takes the first the syscall number is %rax
and then other other arguments are %rdi,%rsi,%rdx, %r10, %r9, %r8
so you can see if we look in the the open function calls the underscore underscore open function which actually invokes
the syscall so if you look at that code you see it moves the two which is the syscall number for read
into %eax and then it does the syscall
and then the the syscall returns its status in %rax
if it's a negative number then that means something some error occurred
if it's a positive number then that means something that no error occurred
so in this case and I in it the open it's returning a file descriptor
a small integer called the file descriptor which then you you can use in subsequent calls to read and write
and then you can see the code is checking for this negative return value
too and there's a whole series of these compares
so let's look at an example of a fault
so here suppose we have this program that we're writing into a valid region of memory
but it's it's not actually stored on it's not actually in the memory it needs to be loaded from disk into into memory
so this is a so-called page fault
so this this instruction this movl
because this because the memory at this address isn't isn't available triggers a page fault
so that that creates an exception a transfer of control into the the page fault handler in the kernel
which copies that page from disk to memory
and then it returns and when it returns it reacts Acutes the movl instruction
so that's kind of cool
so now the memory is available
and now that the movl this movl instruction when it's reacts acute 'add completes
and then we continue
now another type of fault is an invalid memory reference
so here we have a we're accessing an element of a
which doesn't exist and it's an illegal it's an invalid reference
so in this case the movl instruction
it looks like a it looks like a page fault
but the kernel detects that it's an invalid address that there isn't anything that can be loaded from disk
this is an invalid region of the the virtual address space
so it it sends a signal to the to the process and then never never returns
yet so the the signal that sends is the infamous segmentation
the signal that causes the infamous sauce segmentation fault message to print out
and we'll see you next lecture we'll see we'll see how these signals actually actually work
okay so I said we've seen exceptions or very low-level transfers of control
that are implemented by both hardware and the operating system software it could sue
at the higher level is another form of exceptional control flow called
and we see it in the in the context of a process context switch
so let's look at and let's look at what what a process is
so a process the idea of a process is one of the most fundamental and important ideas in computer science
and this classical definition of is that a process is an instance of a running program
okay it's different from a program
a program exists can exist in many different places right
a program exists in yourseif as text in a C file
it can exist as the dot text section of a binary
it can exist as bytes that have been loaded into memory
a process is an instance of a program that's that's running that's in execution
and a process provides two key abstractions
okay it's the first abstraction is that it gives it gives you the illusion that you have
exclusive access to the CPU and thus and the registers
okay so when you're running when you're running your program in a process
you never have to worry about any other any other programs modifying your registers
and and you can't even tell that there's even other processes running on the system
right it looks except for occasional delays like an instruction that just takes a little longer to run
except for that it looks like you have unique exclusive exclusive use of the of the processor  and it's and it's registers
the the other abstraction that it provides is the illusion that you have your own address space
okay so you have and this is provided by a mechanism called virtual memory
so each each running program has its own code data heap stack
and you never see that the code
and you never see the memory that's being used by other processes
okay so it looks for all intents and purposes process gives you this illusion that
you have access to the exclusive access to all the the memory and the and the processor
now that the system runs many of these processes simultaneously
even even on a system with a single core many of these
multiple processes are actually running at the same time concurrently
and you can see this if you look at this here I ran top on on my Mac
and you can see it's running 123 123 total processes  five of which are actually running
and each one of these processes has its own unique process ID this is integer
now the way so it looks it looks like you have unique access or exclusive access to the to the system
but in reality on a suppose we have a single core on a you're actually sharing the system
and the the operating the operating system is is sort of managing that sharing
so what it does is it
we have a process that's running
and it has its own it has its own address space
and and it has it sits and it has its own registers and at some point either
because be cut at some point an exception occurs either because of a timer interrupt
or a fault of some kind or a trap
at some point the the operating system gets control of the system
and and in this case let's say it decides that it wants to run another process
so it copies the the registers the current the current register values into memory and saves them
and then it schedules the next process for execution
and it loads the the registers that were saved from the last time that process was was running
it loads those into the CPU registers
and then it switches the address space to the address space for for this process
so this this the address space and the register values are the context
and so the context switch is is what is the change in the in the address space and the registers
ok so then at that point the that process is running
now in reality on modern systems with multiple cores
the operating system will schedule processes on those multiple cores
and then if there's no if there's not enough course to handle the processes then it will do the context switching
just like we showed before
now each process represents a what we call a logical control flow
so if you were to you know there's a physical control flow
which if we just looked at all the PC values
we'd be executing instructions from one process
and then all of a sudden we'd be executing from another process
but within a single process there's a logical control flow which are all the instructions for that process
now we say that two processes run concurrently
if their flows overlap in time otherwise they're sequential
so let's look at let's look an example we have three processes
process a runs for a while and then it's it's interrupted by process B and process C
and then eventually it it continues running and then it terminates
process B interrupts process a and then it runs for a while and then it terminates
process C once when process B finishes then process C gets to run for a while
then process a runs for a while and then process C terminates
okay so given given this definition of concurrency
which which of these processes are running concurrently
what about a a and B yes
so so a and B's flows B B's flow overlaps with A's flow right
so B
B finishes starts and finish
some portion this portion of Bees flow overlaps with A's flow right
because b is still running hasn't finished
ok so so a and B are concurrent as and similarly C and a overlap
so they're concurrent
but B and C are not concurrent right B finishes before C starts
now this idea of concurrency it doesn't
this this definition of concurrency holds regardless of the number of cores
right if even if you have one core this example that I showed you was on one core
but even if you have multiple cores as long as the flows overlap in time
they're concurrent
but we can think of these no matter what we can we can think of these as running in parallel with each other
at least from the point of view of these individual processes
now this this notion of a context which
is it's managed by its managed by the kernel
okay and it's important to realize that the kernel is not like a separate process that's running
it always runs in the context of some existing process
and it's it's it's it's just code that's in the upper portion of the address space
that gets executed as a result of an exception
so what what happens the way to think about this is that you have this process a that runs
and then an exception occurs which transfers control to the kernel
the kernel invokes its scheduler which decides whether to let a continue to run
or to to do a context switch and run a new process another process
so in this example the scheduler is decided to to run process B
so it executes code and then sort of changes sort of once it repoint s' the address space
then it's running in the context of process B
and it finishes loading the registers for for process B general-purpose registers
and then transfers control to b and b picks up where it left off
okay
and that at some point another exception occurs
and in the kernel decides to transfer control back to process a which picks up where it left off right here
so whatever instruction it finishes executing
whatever instruction instruction was executing at the time of the exception execute the next instruction here
now Linux provides a number of functions
that you can you can call from a user program to manipulate processes
and this this this process this act of manipulating processes  we refer to as process control
now all of these functions most are I should say most of these functions
call invoke system make system calls
but they're they're they're wrapped in higher levels what we call system level functions that
that are the things you actually call from your user program
now system level the Linux system level functions that will typically return a -1 if there's an error
and then they'll set a global variable called error no to indicate the reason
so there's a hard and fast rule when you're doing
when you're invoking system level functions
you must check the return values from those functions you should
and this you never you'll get it you'll get into huge trouble
if you if you neglect to check the return values
okay so you should never make a system a system level function call without checking the return value
the and the only exception there's some functions that return void
such as exit or free don't return anything
so the way the typical way you would do this is like the fork call
which we use to create processes returns the process idea of the of the the process that it created
which is always positive if there's an error returns -1
so we check for the return value to be less than 0 and then we we deal with that error somehow
ok in this case we're just printing a message and exiting
now this gets although it's essential to do this it gets
sort of forked from from my point of view we're trying to present code to you
it gets really messy it takes up a lot of space
yes
I'm checking that it's less than zero
oh yeah that probably that should be normally the convention is to return non zero so you're right that
it's it's not a hard and fast rule but that's that's typically the convention so I guess it should be  exit one
so what we'll do to simplify this
in the code that we present to you and in the code that we present you in the book
well we'll define error reporting functions
so unix-style errors where the function returns -1 and then sets there are no will
well if we get that kind of if we get that kind of error will
will print the will print a message and we'll report what that error was  before we exit
and so then in the code we can replace that
that that body of that if statement with just a single line
okay so that that makes the code a little tighter
but we'll go even further than that and we'll define these wrappers
which were pioneered by a great technical writer named w richards of stevens
and what we do here is we we replace each function with a an error at a wrapper
that has the identical interface as the function the original function
and it has the first the first letter uppercase
and then what this wrapper does is it calls it calls the original function checks for the errors
and then and then if there's no error returns what the original function would have returned
so the behavior of this wrapper is identical to the wrapped
if there's not an error
okay and if there is an error then it deals with it somehow and prints a message
and so then this allows us to make our code really compact without violating this
hard and fast rule that  we have to we have to check for errors
okay the simplest function process control functions are
functions that allow you to get the pig for the current process which is getpid
or the the processor idea of you if the parent process that created the current process
okay so this these take no arguments and they return an integer which is a process ID
now linux provides ways to create and terminate processes
and from a programmers perspective we can think of a process as being in one of three states running
so in this case the process is actually running and executes instructions
or its it can be scheduled
maybe it's not running but it can be scheduled at a later time
right and it's waiting is waiting to be scheduled
it can be stopped which means that execution is suspended
and won't be scheduled until further notice
so we'll see how this works when we study signals in the next lecture
but usually a process is stopped because it receives a certain kind of signal
and then that the process becomes stopped in ways it won't be executed
it won't be scheduled until you explicitly tell it to be scheduled
or process can be terminated which means it stopped permanently
okay so it'll never be scheduled again it's done
now a process can be terminated for one of three reasons
so one it receives a signal whose default action is to terminate it
or your your program returns from the main routine
so you know you can if you know the definition for main is int
see main routines always return an int
so you can return from main and that will terminate your
event it will terminate the process or you can explicitly call the exit function
the exit function exits the program with an exit status of the of its argument
so as as you pointed out that the convention is that for normal return is to return zero
and then non zero on error
or you can another way to do this is just return an integer value from the main routine
and that will that will set the exit status
now exit is kind of unusual
and you'll see this is typical of all these process control functions
that they normally functions you call them once and then they return once
okay but exit you call once and then it never returns
okay so that's so that's a little unusual
now a parent process can create a child process by calling the fork function
so fork takes no arguments
and it returns an integer it it creates a new child process
and then it returns in both the parent and the child
so this is a little hard to wrap your head around at first
it's called once by the parent
but it then it returns in both it creates a new process and then it returns in both the parent and the child
and to the child it returns zero
to the parent return it returns to the child's process ID
okay the child gets an identical copy of the parents virtual address space
but separate right there they're distinct
but immediately after the fork returns the the addresses the address space is identical
so that means that all the variables all the global variables the stack  the code
everything is identical and the child it has the exact same values as it as it does in the parent
the the child gets identical copies of the parents open open file descriptors
so the child has access to any open files including like standard in and standard out  that the parent had
and the only difference is that the child gets a different process ID than the parent
so fork is really strange
because it's called once but returns twice once in the parent and once in the child
so here's an example of this
here's a this is an example program that has a it has a local variable called X  on the stack initialized to 1
and then it calls fork and fork creates the child and returns the it
returns a value to that both the parent and the child
we the only way we can distinguish whether we're executing in the parent or the child is to check that return value
okay so here if the process ID if pid = 0
then we're executing in the child
now remember the child got exactly the same has exactly the same memory and encode is the parent
so X in the child is is one
so when we print we print this message from the child we increment X and then print this this message
so the child will print 1+1 2
and then exit
in the parent when we check that this process ID
it's going to be non zero because it's the process idea of that of the child
so in this case so so the parent won't execute this the body of this conditional
so the parent will execute this printf
and in the parent we decrement X before we print it
so the parent prints out 1-1 is 0
now there's no guarantee we have no guarantee whether the child or the parent executes first
it could at with the fork
when the fork returns the the kernel may decide to schedule the child first
okay in which in which case this code in the body of the conditional would run
or it may it may decide to run the parent first okay
and and there's no way to predict and you it's is wrong it's an error to make any assumption
like that about what's going to run first the parent of the child
and you can see that they share the same open files because
both the parent and the child print to standard out and it prints on the terminal okay
yes
Oh what if the question is what if you call fork multiple times I'll show you some examples of those
it gets a little hairy will have a will use a model called the process graph to sort sort of understand what happens
okay so like just like you said forks forks are kind of can be kind of complex
and time to sin especially if they're nested or you call them multiple times
so we use a tool called the process graph to
to capture sort of what what could happen
when we call Forks
right we can we can't we can't make any assumption about the ordering of of different processes
but we can capture the partial ordering of events using this this tool called a process graph
so what we'll do is we'll let each vertex correspond to the execution of a statement
and then an edge is that happens before relation so a happens before B
and we will label edges with current values of variables
if we have a printf vertices
a printed X that corresponds to a printf we can label that with the output
and then the every graph starts with a vertex with no edges
so given this graph then any topological sort of the graph represents
some feasible some feasible total ordering of events
and by topological sort we mean a total ordering of the vertices
where all the edges go from left to right
okay so let's look at how this would work for our example program
here we have the parent initially X is equal to 1
and then the parent calls fork
the fork returns in both the parent and the child
the child prints and both the parent and the child print the value of x  after incrementing or decrementing
and then they both exit
ok so you can think of these as as happening
so these happen concurrently right which means they can be interleaved in in in any way the
so the topological sort of this graph will tell us a feasible
what's a feasible water feasible interleavings
okay so we can so if we if we real able the graph just to keep it simple
so if we if we real able these edges with just single letters
then this total ordering ABEC FD
represent is represents it's a topological sort and thus a feasible total ordering
so here we have a executing
then B then I execute CIN the child
and then at this point the the kernel decides to swap out
swap out e swap out the child and now let the parent run
so the parent picks up and executes C
and then and then it gets rescheduled to chat then the child gets scheduled and executes F
and then the parent the parent runs and finally finishes
right so this is this is very unlikely that
it you only execute one instruction and then and then B
and then have a context switch but it's it's feasible
right because it represents
because the the total ordering is a is a is a topological ordering
on the other hand this is this is infeasible because F
here in this total ordering we're executing F before E
and you can see that this that just can't happen right
so the the edges on these the logical flow represented by this child
have to occur in this order first E and then F right
by the just because F follows E in the code right that the compilers not
going to it's not going to alter those
okay so what happens if now if we have two consecutive Forks
well let's draw the the process graph will help us understand this
so in the parent we print l0  and then fork
and that creates a child and both
and so the fork returns to this printf in both the parent and the child
so they both the parent and the child print l1
and then both parent and child execute a fork
so that creates that creates another child that creates two more now two two children
and then and so that returns to the printf which says bye
so the result of this of calling Fork twice like this is that it creates four processes
okay and you can and if it's confusing you can always work it out with the the process graph like this
okay so we can weaken us we can see feasible and infeasible orderings
so this one's feasible take my word for
it this one is infeasible
and let's see why so L 0
and there's no way to to print by before the first fork
all right so that's infeasible
if we if we drew out this process graph we'd have a backward  a backward edge
okay now what happens if we nest Forks in the parent
okay I'm not sure why you'd want to do this except maybe to torture to 13 students
but
so we can just work this out by drawing the process graph
so here we have the parent it prints L0
and then it does a fork so that creates a child
so the child if fork is not equal to 0
then we're in the parent right so this code executes sin the parent
if fork is 0
then we're executing the child and the child just prints by and then
and then terminate it eventually terminates I didn't show it here but  calls exit
think the function that called this function calls exit
so the parent so fork not equal to 0  indicates that this is the parent
so the parent prints l1 and then it does another fork
that fork creates a child
so if if fork is not equal to 0
then we're in the parent so the parent prints l2 and then exits this conditional and prints by
if if fork returns 0 then that means we're executing the child
so we don't execute this code we jump out of this conditional
and then the child just prints by
okay
and we can
represents an infeasible output from this program
l0 Fork week so L 0 followed by by that's feasible
and then followed by L 1 that's okay
and then the next by is okay but it since
we can't have this we can't have this by proceeding this L2
because L2 will this printf will execute before this printf
okay and I'll let you work out this one as a as an exercise
all right now when up when a process terminates  for whatever reason
the system actually keeps it around for until it's reaped
and the reason until it's reaped by its parent
and the reason it does this is that the parent may want to know about the exit status of the child
so but if a parent creates a child
it may want to wait for that child to finish and and check its exit status
so when when any process terminates
the system leaves that it doesn't it doesn't remove it entirely from the system
it it keeps it a little bit of state associated with that child
in the form of a the exit status of the child
and the in some other tables some other OS tables
so because this child that's terminated but it's not gone
it they're called zombies so there's sort of half half-living half-dead
and so a process a zombie
remains a zombie until it's it's it's reaped by its parent
using a function called weight or weight pit
and as a result of as a result of doing weight or weight pit
the parent is given the exit status information
and then the kernel deletes the zombie process
now what if the parent doesn't reap it's one of its child zombies
so it if any parent if the parent terminates
then the system arranges for the very first process that existed in the system
called the init process which has a process ID of one
it arranges for the anit process to reap that that child
so there's so orphaned orphaned children will always be reaped by by the anit process
so we only really have to worry about about reaping zombies
in in the case where we have long-running parents like shells or servers
because in that case a server may create millions of child processes
each one of those each one of those does each one of those child processes when they terminate
become zombies and they they have state
that takes up room in the kernel so
you can get this it's a form of memory leak
if you don't if you don't reap these zombie children that can eventually fill up the memory space and crash the kernel
so for for cases where you have long-running programs
then we have to we have to use wait or wait pit to reap the children
so let's look at an example first let's let's look at an example of  this zombie phenomenon
so here we have a function we call fork
and then within the child we print a message of the process idea of that child  and then we exit the child
within the parent we print a message and then we go into an infinite loop
okay so this is a parent that's that never never reaps the child that it created
so if we run this program called Forks
you can see it prints these two messages
the parent prints a message and the child prints a message and then
and we're running it in the background with this ampersand
okay because we're going to otherwise it would it would it's it's it's still v
and we wouldn't be able to inspect it
so after we run this program in the background
then we use PS to print the current processes
and we can see that there's two we can see here at the parent which is process ID 6639
and then the child which is 66410 and
that the defunct indicates that it's a zombie
okay now if we kill six 6639 that's the parent
and then do another PS you see that the zombies gone that the child is gone
because it's been reaped by the init process one
now what happens if the child doesn't terminate you might wonder like if if a parent creates a child
and then the parent and then the chattin the the child never terminates
and and the parent terminates then what would happen right mark
so let's just let's look at an example of those in C
so here we're we're calling Fork we're creating a child
within the child we'd print a message and then the child goes into an infinite loop
and the parent prints a message and then exits
so if we run this program
you can see that the two messages from parent and child
and then if we look at the if we look at the processes
we can see we can see that the child is still running
okay so the channel process is still running even though the parents's has terminated
and now if we kill this child 6676
and then if we kill it then we can see that it's it's gone it's no longer in the system okay so
that child when we when we killed it that terminated
it it had no parents so the unit process reaped it and it it's no longer a zombie
so the the the function that we use to to synchronize with children and reap them
the simplest one is called wait
and wait it takes an optional status
where you can get the exit status of the inspect the exit status of the child
basically wait suspends the execution of the process that calls it
until one or one of its children terminates
and it doesn't specify which one it just waits until one of the children that it created terminates
and then if this child status is is not null
then the integer that it returns or the integer that it points to this is a pointer
the integer that it points to will be set to some value that indicated the reason the child terminated and its exit status
and you can you can check that using these macros
which your your textbook describes in more detail and let you
so let's look at how how this works in a simple example
so here we're calling fork and creating a child which prints a message and then exits
the parent prints a message and then it waits for the child to terminate
and when the child terminates it prints a message
and indicating that the child terminated and then prints by
so if we were to look at the the process graph for this
you would see that we would have the fork creates the parent and the child
both the parent and the child do they're they're print outs
and then the parent waits it suspends until that the child terminates in this case by calling exit
okay so what that means is it's it's infeasible
so you can say hello from the parent
it's infeasible though for this
this child terminated message CT to occur before the bye
because
because the the child hasn't yet terminated so
it's these two these two messages will never be printed
until the child is terminated by calling exit
so is that clear yes
so the question is can you have an output HP
HP HC CT bye yes
yes because the parent ex-prince HP there's a context switch the child prints HC
and then exits and now the parent will the wait will return
and then it prints CT bye
okay here's this is a and this is a little more a little more involved example
so here what we want to do we're going to create a bunch of children
and then we're going to wait for them all to terminate
and we're going to wait but we won't be able to wait in any specific order right we're just
so here we have a loop 0 through n
and in each loop body we're going to we're going to fork a child and exit with a return status
that that's going to tell us which child it was
was ok so in the parent so we do this we do this a n times
and then and then afterward the parent inside inside a similar loop 0 to n
add waits for a child to terminate
so it'll it'll work it will wait for M children to terminate
wait returns a way returns the the process ID
and then a status which is in in this child status variable
and so we take that variable now and we can use this w if exited macro to determine
if it terminated normally with an exit by calling exit
and if so then we can check its exit status using the W exit status macro
otherwise if it if W if exited it
is false then that means some something the child terminated
for some other reason not not because it called exit
okay there's a
weekend we can actually use wait pit which is similar to wait
but it allows us to wait for a specific process a specific child
a specific process a specific child with a specific process ID to terminate
and I'll I'll let you you can wait pit is really involved and
it's described in detail in the in your textbook
and so you'll need to look you'll need to look there for the details on how that works
now another important so we've learned how to create new processes
the but we haven't learned how to when we when we call fork
we just create an exact copy of the the child is just an exact copy of the parrot
running the same code same program same variables
okay to run a different program inside of a process we use a function called execve
and exit loads and runs
within the current process it loads and runs
the executable file name which is its first argument
and file name can be either a binary executable binary
okay or it can be a script it can be a text file
a so-called script file that starts
whose first line starts with a pound bang and then and then that the path of some interpreter
so for example if you if you want to write a shell script
you the first line of your shell script is is a pound bang and then
the path name of the bash
and then that will that will execute bash
and then bash will will read in that the lines following and interpret them
as just as though you'd type them in at the at the command line
so in either case it executes either an interpreter or it executes a binary
with who's argued with the argument list ArgV
and a list of environment very in envp
okay now by default are the first argument
in RV is the name of the file that that's being executed  so it it's it's this file name
so what that allows you to do is
in your code you can check our v-0 if you want to print out the name of the file the name of the program that's executing
you just print out our v-0
okay now and exits all of the code and the data and the stack
it overwrites the completely overrides the virtual address space
so once you call eggs AK within a within a process
it blows away the current program that's it
okay however it retains that it's still the same process it's just running now a different program
and so it retains the process ID and any open files that you have
so x''k is really is really mind-blowing because it's called once
but it never returns
except if there's an error
so if this file doesn't exist for example then then exec will return on -1
but otherwise in normal operation it never returns
all right so let's look at the structure of the stack
when this new program starts so after
app after exit after the eggs egg ve finishes its work it creates
a new stack it loads in new code and data creates a new empty heap
ok everything's new
and the stack that it creates has the following form
ok at the bottom here's the bottom of the stack and our stack is growing this way
so the first function that executes
is is a function called Lipsy underscore start underscore main
so that has it that has a stack frame
so let's look this is what I'm showing here is the situation right before the startup code calls main
so there's there's the future stack frame for main will be here at the top of this
following the top of the stack
there's some padding and then the argument list in RV  is contained on the on the stack
so that the RV is a list of pointers terminated by the null pointer
and each one of these pointers points up into a string that corresponds to an argument
okay so when you run a program you specify the program name
and then arguments separated by spaces
okay and so these these arguments this arc V is a list of pointers to those arguments strings
and it's pointed to right right as main is called
it's it's it's it's the second argument to main
so it's contained in %rsi the address of this argument lists
the number of arguments is contained is the first argument argc
and that's contained in %rdi by the x86-64  parameter passing convention
now the environment list is also contained on the stack
and it too consists of a list of pointers each of which points into a environment  string
which is a set of key equal value pairs okay
and it's pointed to by the global environment variable environ
and if it's passed in it's pointed at an envp it which is contained in %rdx
which is the always holds the third argument
okay so let's look now how how we would use this
so we want to within our current program we want to execute the LS command
with two arguments - LT and /usr/include
so what this is saying is list list the files in /usr/include
show the long form of the listing and sort them in time order
from most recently used to at least recently used
so so the way we do this
if we just called execve it blow away our program
so assuming we want to continue to do work after we execute LS
the the standard way to do this is to to create a child using Fork
and then X act within the child
right have the child do the work
and then the child terminates and the parent maybe will wait for the child maybe not right just
usually it will wait for the child
so within the parent we we we fork a child  check that it's 0
and so if it's 0 then we're executing that this code executes within the child
so the child does the exact
it it passes the name of the function since the
the name of the function that we want to the the program that we want to execute
is always contained in the first element of vard V
we call exit with a parameter of myargv[0]
and we've set up the argument list in myargv
and we pass the global environment variable environment
we're just going to use the current list of environment variables that we have in the parent
okay and these environment variables are things of the form user=droh current working directory
and so the the
if there's if this program in myargv[0] doesn't exist then exact will return -0
so we check for that that condition and then exit
otherwise it never returns right it executes ls
LS the code for LS
this is the name of a binary this is a /bin/ls is a binary file
that binary file gets loaded into memory
that code gets executed and it terminates
okay so the child at this point after the exit
the child is running that the LS code
and it's no longer running any of this code
now this seems the first time you see this this combination of fork and exec it seems
it seems a little odd doesn't it why not just
why not just have one command that creates a new process and runs
and runs a program in that process why
why separate why have these these two separate fork and exec
I mean in fact Windows does this Windows has like one command that creates a process and executes
sit but it turns out that having having a separate function like fork
just to create processes is actually really useful
I mean sometimes you just want to create replicas of your current process for example
let's say you have a server
and you want to create a concurrent server you want to create multiple copies of that server then you just fork
a bunch you have the main the parent server can fork a bunch of of children
so that's useful they're just all running the same code
but what's all what this also allows you to do
is it allows you to execute code in the child
before you call x'q
so you may want to set some you may want to set some
like some signal with is especially useful when you're dealing with
with things like signals if you want to block certain signals or unblock certain signals
you can do it right here in this this gap between the fork and the exact
okay so so that's it so just to summarize what we've we've talked about today
exceptions are in response to events that require some kind of non-standard or exceptional call exceptional control flow
they can be generated internally in the form of interrupts or internally in the form of traps and faults
so it at any point in time a process has multiple a system as multiple processes
only one of which can execute on a single core
so the process execution is interleaved by the kernel
and each process thinks that it has total total control of the processor in its address space
there's only one mechanism to spawn processes that's fork
and it's called once and returns twice
we can terminate our process by calling X exit which is called once and never returns
we reap and wait for processes using wait or wait pit
and we load and run programs using execve
or one of its one of its variants
and this one is called once and and normally never returns
okay so that's that's it for today and
we'll see you have a good weekend and we'll see you on Tuesday