good afternoon everyone
so today we're going to transition into a topic that
to me is sort of the reward for having slugged through all the low-level stuff
you've done up to this point
to be able to really understand and become adept at programming network software
not there's a lot to networking that we're not going to cover
but at least to have some familiarity with it
so I know that a lot of you are sort of in the midst of trying to figure out
how to make Melek run and make it run fast
and so this this uh topic is really more pointing toward the future
but it's very relevant to the final web you'll do for the course
and so we're starting to to get ready for that
so like I said this course is not really a full course in networking
there's many other courses at the university that are
and so what we're going to try and do is give you just a little flavor of it
and particularly as everything in the course of programmers perspective
so how you as a software developer would make use of the c-level api's that are relevant to network programming
and why isn't this working
okay so
the idea behind most networking systems  is what's called  the client-server model
and the idea is that there's a service out there that you want access to
and you as a customer or a client are making a request to that server
so an example would be when you order something on Amazon
Amazon has a bunch of servers
and you go to your web browser and canta it contacts the Amazon a web server
and you make transactions you request something you provide information
and it gives you back pretty pictures of things you might want to buy
it acknowledges your credit card transactions
those are all very classic client-server types of interactions
you as the client,Amazon is the server
another interesting example is a telephone
so if you think about it a telephone is both a client and a server in that
when I'm making a placing a call to somebody else
I'm the client and that person's phone is the server right
it's sitting there waiting for calls to come in
and when that call comes in it makes a connection
we talk over the phone and then I hang up  either side hangs up
so there's a lot of instances out there of of some variation of client and server
and it's a much richer idea in that you can often switch back and forth  the roles of those two parties
but it's a pretty universal and a ubiquitous way of thinking about how to set up a network system
so in general then the idea is that there's a system working
the client is making some requests to the server
the server does something locally to deal with it
it receive it gets information that retrieves from its database  the things you might want to buy
and then it sends back information say a nicely formatted a web page with all kinds of shopping suggestions
and then the client decides what to do next
so from a hardware perspective the
interface to a between the network and
your computer is called the NIC or network interface card even though it's not always on a card
and we really won't talk about hardware at all
but what's most interesting from it is that
it looks to your computer like an i/o device
and in fact the UNIX of API for dealing with networks
makes it look like a file
so in particular just as a disk sits off of a bus
and you write data to a disk
or you read it from a disk
similarly the network sits off of a similar bus
and when you want to send a message you actually do it by writing
to a sort of virtual  file that's called the network
and if you want when you're receiving data you do it by reading
so just as several weeks ago I gave the lecture on Io
it turns out that it's extremely relevant to network programming
that's the basic model that that was created by the early developers of the sort of standard UNIX
and now that's carried over not just to UNIX but it's the same model for Windows and other operating systems
so
and now let's just talk a little about what computer networking means
the idea of a network is it's a collection of systems  that are referred to as hosts
that are able to communicate with each other over some kind of communication fabric let's call
it communications system
and they're sort of partitioned into
mostly referred to as lands or local area networks
that you establish within a small region
and then a wide area network which would be over
or something the size of a city or perhaps more
and over a enterprise such as CMU it's a very complex
set of for example there's wireless base stations
that right in this room that you're interacting with when you're using a wireless system or your your phone
and then there's a whole networking infrastructure within the university
the then goes to some commercial providers
AT&T in particular that give it access to the the commercial Internet
and then there's another set of network connections hosted by the supercomputing Center
that give you access to what's called Internet 2 which is the resource that's used for communicating among universities
so underneath you know when you're doing your networking stuff
there's this amazingly complex combination of things going on
the idea of an internet is supposed is refers to the idea
the general idea of a network of networks
taking for example the local area network that this base station provides
and connecting it up to other networks on campus and across the world
and when we refer to the capital I internet
that refers to the one instance the the most significant instance of an Internet
so lowercase I means the sort of general idea of creating a network of networks
uppercase I is the specific example that we all know and use all the time
that's organized by a certain set of principles that uses a particular set of protocols and so forth
and of course we tend to just talk the internet
and most people know that what that really implies is the sort of existing network structure that there is
and that's good enough for the purpose of this course
we're not going to talk much about other possible designs one might have for a network
so most of the low level networking is supported by something called Ethernet
and the term Ethernet actually has evolved tremendously over time
so that it's almost more like a brand name that it is in specific technology
and the version you're familiar with the wired version of it
you have a wire to some sort of a box
like that you plug the your ethernet jacks into
and historically those were called hubs
and the idea of a hub was it was just a repeater that whatever came into it from one computer
it would broadcast to all the connected machines
and so you only want to do this for maybe a a dozen or
so machines that it's like a party-line they're all hearing what everybody else is saying
and in fact the original first version the ethernet did that by everyone interacting over a single cable
carrying essentially radio signals and
and  similarly when you're in this room using a wireless internet
a wireless internet is sort of like a hub and that
all the packets that you're sending all across the room
they're all sort of making use of the same radio frequencies the same communication channel
and there's a protocol for how they detect when two messages get set at the same time and therefore interfere with each other
so that can only sort of scale up to maybe at most a hundred different
hosts communicating because they're all sharing a single communication channel
now in the wired world what's evolved is usually when you buy a box
or you get one from your cable company
with all those ports in it it's actually called a router
or sometimes a switch  in that
it it doesn't broadcast to everyone
it it selectively tries to guess
is this particular message bound for this particular host
and only send to that one
and as you know you can take these and wire up
I think about up to six levels deep in and hops
and basically create a network of wired connections
and they'll all get from one to the other somehow
and then after that it gets more complicated you can add more sophisticated types of switching on top of it
but so the general idea of even an Ethernet is actually a fairly complex thing
but it's some sort of conceptual level we can just think of it as a bunch of hosts
that can talk directly to one another
and then an internet then refers to the idea of taking those local area networks and connecting them together
via routers and routers obey a particular protocol based on the address
that you're trying to send data to
and
and so what you end up with conceptually is a whole bunch of hosts spread potentially all across the world
and then some magical system of routers
that will get a message from one place to the other
based on a mode of addressing where there's some known address of the hosts
that you're trying to send to
and it will hop through multiple routers to get from one place to the other
and that's true whether it's on campus
or whether it's hopping all the way around the world
and so again there's this huge body of information and knowledge about how that routing works
and how its reliable and all that
but we're going to just assume that somebody else has figured that out
and our job as programmers is just to be able to communicate from one host to another
and so how could you design a system where all these diverse systems
made by computers made by different manufacturers operating under different countries with different telecommunications bodies governing bodies and so forth
how can they all work with each other
and the requirement is you have to have a protocol you have to have some common set of conventions
for what messages look like how they get sent
what happens if one of them doesn't make it how do you recover from that and so forth
and so what does a protocol include well it has to include some way of naming things so that
if I want to send to some host I have some way of designating
who that host is
and then there's the routing system has to have some reliable way of getting my data to that named host
and that's the delivery mechanism
and that's usually done and one of the things that we now accept  as universal
but it really wasn't when it first came out was idea of you take all your data and you divide it into packets
and packets are typically about a thousand to two thousand bytes
and so if you have a longer message it chops it up into individual packets and sends it across `
and all the communication occurs at the packet level
that's different than the historic phone system
I was a connection based system meaning that
if I was calling somebody there is a dedicated wire set of wires maintained by the phone company
that would be reserved and locked down for our own use
during the entire duration of that phone call
so
to get them from one host say a to B
what happens is we want to send a packet
and that packet will contain some amount of data
and the idea of a packet communication then is you put little headers on
that contain certain routing information  see on the front of an envelope of a letter perhaps
and so and at different points in the way
they'll have different numbers of headers and different protocols or formats for what those headers look like
so in particular within
I want to send a message and I'll
I'll do that and then the software that runs on my machine that handles this
will put a header in front of that that describes the internet routing
and then it will tack a header in front of that that talks about the local area network routing that gets used
and that's what's referred to as the a P hat H the packet header for the Internet Protocol
and f h1 the frame header for this particular message being sent within this local network
and then the network interface card or the adapter here
is then responsible for putting that out over this local communication of capability
and then that gets received at the other end by the network adapter at the receivers direction
it will put up its own frame header on it to pass it in
and that then gets tripped off
so that all hosts be set sees is the the data that gets sent
but this idea of putting headers in front and at times sort of what they call encapsulation that
I'll take this big packet and I'll just tack some more information on top to the front of it header information
and I'll send through the rest of it just as a set of bytes
so the internet that we know and love the capital I internet
then has a particular set of protocols that are you've probably heard the terms
one is called the IP the Internet Protocol
which is the one that defines
ideas about how do you get how do you name hosts on the Internet
and how do you send packets
and they're referred to sometimes is datagrams
meaning that a packet is just a single entity that gets sent from point A to point B
and the underlying IP doesn't guarantee delivery so
so it's based on what they call best
effort communication meaning that at each step along the way
if for example things are good then it will just send this packet along
if there's too much congestion
there's been a you know somebody's turned on their microwave oven and
it's set up some radiofrequency interface interference
then at the IP level it just drops that packet and says whoops
I screwed up sorry it doesn't even say sorry it just does it silently
and then you can as a programmer make use of that very global level
so normally as a programmer you don't really want to program at that level
because you'll send packets and they will get there
but you can if you want to and it's called UDP  a protocol
it's just a small software layer over IP
and there's some applications
that you'll see for example in the computer game world where you want to send
information really fast and if some information gets dropped it's not a big deal
that people actually program at that level
we won't really talk about that
the more common protocol that gets used and carries 99% of Internet traffic is what's called TCP
or transmission control protocol
and that provides a reliable the equivalent of telephone connection
that I can reliably send data from point A to point B
as many bytes as I like
it's a guaranteed
every it's sometimes fast and sometimes not but it's there
and it's built on top of the IPO of this datagram
meaning that it has to take whatever you're sending and slice it up into these single packets
if one of them doesn't get sent it will resend it  until it gets there
they have to deal with the fact that packets can
travel different paths and one can get ahead of the other in transmission
and so it has to reorder them in the correct sequence
and so there's a lot of stuff under it but
we'll just assume that it kind of works
and so you can just rely think about it is I have a stream connection
I can send from A to B and B can send a stream of data back to me
and we're all happy
and so that's the version that looks like file IO
I just keep writing to a file and it's sending packets over the network to the other end
and then the other side can be sending stuff to me
and I'm just reading it and I'm just reading bytes of data
not worrying about how that got broken up into individual packets
and so that's referred to as the sockets interface
and you'll hear the term socket programming and that's exactly what we're talking about
and so from a sort of software system
than software hardware system then
the client and the server are both implemented as application programs
at the respective endpoints on their hosts
and they make use of of software and libraries that run at some combination of the user level and at the kernel level
and therefore I have access to direct resources
and so
I is a program or an application programmer then make use of this software API
that lets me do socket programming
and it's based on gives directly supports tcp/ip
so first of all we're going to talk most of the time about what's called ipv4
a version 4 which is the one that's been running for since the 1980s I think early 1980s
and is this the standard and we'll talk very only mentioned very briefly the idea of what's called ipv6
which is sort of a next-generation version
so the idea of a ipv4 and this is now we're talking about IP
and and this is true of TCP as well is that an address is actually just 32 bits
but it's usually expressed in what they call dotted decimal form
and you've seen these addresses before
that it's four decimal numbers
and they can only range between 0 and 255
because each one of them is a single bytes worth of information
so we're used to writing things in hex now in this course
but we're going to write it as each byte is written as a decimal digit
and they're actually passed and stored in
what's called network byte order which is big endian byte order
and so we have to worry about the whole big endian vs. Goodell Indian thing
when we're doing network programming
and you can actually learn a lot there's a whole levels of how the different bytes mean
but for example any IP address it starts with 128.2  is at CMU
I think and then
and so essentially CMU owns that part of the IP address space
which if you think about that's approximately 2^64
2 to the no not to the 64th - to the sixteenth
different IP addresses available for use by campus
alma and as i mentioned there's a newer version called ipv6
that gives you a 128-bit addresses
you can imagine actually that if you think about how many nodes are there in the Internet
if a four byte address is only to the 32 so that's four billion
and I don't know about you but I have a lot of different things that use IP
I have a phone I have two laptops I have a couple desktops
so if all if every one of us used multiple IP addresses then actually the world would be out of them right
there's seven billion people in the world not all of whom have access to the Internet
but a large fraction of them do
and so there's a whole kind of crazy way of dealing with the the multitude of possible IP addresses
so the obvious thing would be well let's just allocate a lot more addresses
and jump let's just skip 64 bits and go right to 128 and that's the idea behind ipv6
but quite honestly this has been one of those technologies that's been out there for over 15 years
and still has a very low level of adoption so
it's it's still a future technology
people have basically figured out all these crazy schemes to make use of of just stick within the four byte limit
okay so let's start talking the program the sort of programmer perspective on this
and this is one area where you'll wish you weren't programming in C
but you are
so there's a lot of really crufty stuff
and it was all developed most of the software protocols were conceived before C even was what it is today
so like the Kernighan and Ritchie book you have is called the second edition
and it's based on what was called ANSI C or ISO C
but these all date before that they date back to the original Kernighan and Ritchie
so for example void star did not exist in that era
and so you use care star as a generic pointer
and so there's just a lot of stuff in this programming
interface where you go wow that is really crufty and that that truth is yes you're right
so in particular there's a lot of different structures that are defined and
one of them is called an in adder which means internet address
and it's just defined to be a 32-bit unsigned number
and in general as I mentioned there
the so called network byte order whoever designed the original protocols was a fan of big endian addressing
and so that's what it is even though actually most of the machines that are out there in this world are little endian
and so there's a set of standard library functions
that you use to convert between network order and host order
and the idea of it is now if I run my software on a little Indian or a big endian machine
these functions will do the right thing
so if I just use these standard libraries
then I don't have to worry about porting it every time I change the word ordering of a machine
one of the things you'll notice here is
there is no function to convert 64-bit data  between a network order and host order so
I don't know what people do when I do it I just write my own saw my own to do  it
or I don't because I know my other end is a little endian machine
so anyways these are already some functions you'll start seeing for that look like network conversion software
and as I mentioned the addresses are written in a dotted decimal form
and it's also big endian
so if I were to write in hex 128 is of course 80
so that's the most significant byte of the IP address
and then there is a set of functions API calls you can use to convert between this dotted decimal format
and the actual just a 32-bit unsigned int
and actually it used to be there is
you might see some older presentations where they use different names for this
but  the most recent version API calls this
the the presentation version the dotted decimal they referred to it as a presentation
then you can look up the and it's in the book to what the the calls to these look like
but you probably don't or very seldom
when you're thinking about I want to go to Google
you don't think about what its IP address is you just go to www.google.com
and for everything you do you refer to it by this
I it would have referred called Internet domain names which is a hierarchical naming system
whereas you know there's .edu is for educational institutions
.com is for commercial
.net is general networking of many countries have their own suffix
so you know .de is for Germany and so forth
and so those are called the first level domain names
and then there's a hierarchical naming structure under that
and
there's actually an interesting question of okay
how do I then map from those hierarchical names those domain names into this dotted decimal or the 32 bit IP address
and the job of that is by a very large distributed system called the DNS the domain name system
where the only sort of centrally managed part of it is at the top level
so for each of these first level domain names
there's there's a collection a very large collection of machines that keep track of all the all the IP addresses
that map to one of those first level domain names
and then for example CMU maintains its own naming Authority
so anything that says something .cmu.edu
there's local DNS servers within CMU
that are picking apart ok where should you know
if I say cs.cum.edu what would be the the IP address for that
well and it's actually pretty interesting how this is managed because it's all it's totally decentralized
there's a whole set of protocols that govern how naming is done
but conceptually we can think of it as just this big database
that gives me a mapping
where I can give a domain name and it will get back to me a one or more IP addresses
I can give an IP address and it will come back with one or more domain names
oh and so there's actually an application you can run
on most machines called nslookup and there's another one called dig
that you can use to find basically probe the DNS
and find in either direction you can look at the given a domain name you can find its IP address
given an IP address you can find its domain name
and we also I'll show you some code that
just as an example of how you do the programming
I'll just show that momentarily called hostname
so just some examples
you know if I look up some address like the the website for the computer science school computer science
using nslookup
it comes back can people see this okay
doing it bigger it's okay
so this is what NSF looks like and this stuff here just tells you
you know who where was the actual directory entry in the which DNS  server actually gave this information back
and it says that
www.cs.cum is actually a synonym for a weirder one called w web - l-bfgs .cum.edu
and its IP address is 128.2 like you'd expect
217.13
and of course that works not just at CMU but I can
you know go ask about what Stanford is up to
and it will come back and its IP addresses of something 171.64
and that's been managed by that and you'll see again it's
I asked for www.cs.stanford.edu it said well the real name of that is cs.stanford.edu
and this actually is a point that the
the mapping between domain names
and internet addresses is not one-to-one
you can have multiple domain names that refer to the same Internet address
but you can also have multiple internet addresses
excuse me
that's weird
so like twitter.com when I ask for it it comes back with four different addresses
and if I do the exact same thing again
mmm Kim but yeah
you see it came back with
the same no not even the same addresses
it came back for example here the one that ends with dot six that wasn't in that first was
so it came back with a slightly different set of addresses and a somewhat different order
and the idea of that is that actually has multiple servers
so when I send to twitter.com or Google or any of these major servers
there's not just one place in the internet that's handling everybody's Google traffic
through thousands of places spread around the world
and the way they get you there is by playing tricks with the DNS
that Google is constantly sending updates to the it maintains its own DNS servers
so it's constantly changing them
and it will actually give you different addresses depending on where in the world you're located as well
to try and provide a server that's sort of reasonably close to you geographically so
there's all just all kinds of tricks that happen through DNS
that is part of the way they can sort of manage this huge set of addresses
and then there's some other domain names that don't have any IP address
that they're somewhere in the hierarchy that hierarchical naming system
but they're not actually referring to a particular host
so it's a Multi multi mapping
in the the API city reflects
it so this is just going what I told you they sometimes one-to-one
sometimes many domain names refer to the same address
sometimes of one name maps to multiple addresses that change over time
and then there's some where it's a valid name
but it doesn't have an IP address it doesn't have a host associated with a  question
for example let's say I create my own servers how does that generate it oh
how do I get how do you get your own IP address
well all you have to beg borrow or you have to either borrow or buy them
so for example at CMU there is some number of what they call statically allocated IP addresses
where it's just fixed assigned to that machine and you can register form and request them through computing services
but most you don't have that most you get one that's I signed dynamically
so there's a pool of addresses that you basically they call them leasing
that you are assigned with for a while
and then but it could possibly be reassigned to someone else
and that's part of the way it can manage
you know somewhat limited set of IP addresses
so the idea of like I said that the main
a way we'll think about it is in terms of what's called TCP
and it says connection oriented protocol
where I establish a connection from one one host establishes a connection to another host
and they they can communicate to each other sending arbitrarily long streams of bytes to each other
and so the connection is then two hosts that can talk to each other
and each of those endpoints is referred to as a socket
and so I can and a socket is both an IP address
and what's called a port number
so there's a 16 by 16 bit number for every connection
that's referred to as its port
and the reason for that is just because I'm talking to a particular machine
that that machine can support different services
it can provide SSH connections it can provide FTP connections
it can host a mail server it can host a web server
so a particular machine might have a multitude of different services
and so those are differentiated from each other with what are called port numbers
and similarly Isaac client might have connections to dozens of hosts going at any given time
I'm cruising the web I'm you know doing all that different stuff
and that's all differentiated the client end that there's different ports
associated with your different programs that are running
and so a port then is a 16-bit integer
that identifies  which particular endpoint is
being communicated with it either the client side of the server side
and typically at the client side these are assigned dynamically
and the referred to as ephemeral ports meaning
they only are assigned for the limited duration that you have a connection with that
that you're maintaining that connection
and then there has to be some way if I'm going to contact
and I want to know the DNS will tell me what the IP address is of say google.com
but I have to know that
am i communicating with its web service which is port 80  or HTTP secure socket is a different report number
so which service I'm asking for
and there's a standard list what are called well-known ports
that are that I can contact at the server end to get the particular service I'm looking for
and those are assigned there's a big waste of port assignments
and so the again that's part of the sort
of a whole set of internet standards is the the identifiers for the different ports
what services those are and how those particular protocols work
so when I have a connection then
as I mentioned I'll think of it as a connection then is as
a link between two machines based on some known port typically at the server end
and a dynamically assigned or ephemeral port assigned at the client in
and I can refer to then that connection then is identified by the combination of the hosts at the two ends
and the ports that they're using
and in general then it's the job of the kernel
to differentiate the different connections that are coming into a machine
and figure out  which software which process to wake up
when a data you know when some data arrives from another machine
in which actual program running on that machine will make use of that data
and that's done by associating for each of the ports   a particular process executing program
that's going to handle those particular requests
and it's totally possible for a client to be interacting with a single server over different ports
but those are considered to be different connections and
and so they don't really interfere with each other
so that's what I mentioned is this is what we refer to as sockets programming or the sockets interface
it was developed sort of as the internet was evolving in the late 70s and early 80s
so socket then as I said is certain logically one end
one of the two ends of a connection
and from an application point of view you'll see it as a file descriptor
just the low-level file stuff that you've already seen that you can do reading and writing from
um
and and so that that's the sort of mental model that is provided by the socket interface
but it's a very different you know the actual implementation of network
when you write to a socket
it's firing up all kinds of network stuff whereas you write to a disk
it's operating a disk controller
so at the hardware level and even at the lower levels of software they're very different beasts
but you as an application programmer see some commonality there
okay so let's jump right into the API
and again this is a place where you you'll wish you were programming in a language
that had a type hierarchy
but you aren't you're programming in C
there's a type there's a zillion Struck's that you kind of have to get familiar with
but one's called a sock adder and basically it's just a 16 bytes worth of stuff
where the the only thing that's special here is that the leading two bytes
a designate what type of socket this is
and particularly be different whether it's a TCP socket
an ipv6 socket a UDP socket
and all those will have different numbers
a different constant in there that tells you which type of socket it is
and then the high level the sockets in a lot of the programs don't need to know
you know which type of connection this is
they can just deal with they basically call other software to deal with that
so that's why it's referred to as being families specific
and then the socket stuff isn't even necessarily referred to the internet the capital I internet
and so there's a more specific one called a socket or underscore in
that is used for ipv4 sockets
well not ipv6
and so in particular it fills in fields one is called the port which as I mentioned is 16 bits
and then the IP address
the four byte IP address both of which are in
even if you're running the software on a x86 machine
these should be in big endian order
and you'll see that this is what I mean that this is sort of a
C's version of subtyping if you know something like C++ or Java
or you know a language with type inheritance
that you can think of it as a sock adder in a sort of a subclass of a sock adder
right it has more information it's compatible with
but has more information than a socket
and then there's another type of for ipv6 has a different kind of
struck that they fill in for its information
and then they they Pat it out with eight bytes of zeros
just because this particular protocol doesn't require the full 16 bytes
okay so this is sort of what it looks like to operate a full-blown
client-server system from a programmers perspective
and we're going to for the rest of today and all of Thursday  go through all these steps
and you as a programmer are actually going to have to understand each of these steps
what they do what they mean and how to use them
the good news is there's some pretty standard patterns here
and so you can often grab some existing code say out of the book
to use that will make this not as painful  as it might look
so but the overall idea of this this picture then is
sorry kick it used to fit my remote doesn't work
on the the right hand side refers to the steps that the server has to go through
and the left hand side is what the client does
so the upper right is what it takes to set up a server
that is then a program that's running there
ready to receive connections  from a client and perform various services
and so obviously before the client can do anything the server has to exist
so that has to be the first step in setting things up
and then we have to we'll fire up a cert a client that will make use of this service
and then there'll be what's referred to as a session
meaning a kind of back and forth communication between the client and server
doing whatever they're going to do this is not specific to any particular application
and like I said it will involve you'll see Rio underscore remember those who are reliable i/o
functions we talked about as part of the UNIX i/o
so it's a way to read and write in a room and and handle some of the quirks of low-level i/o
but basically this is sending and receiving messages over the Internet
and then once that's done
typically then the client will close its connection sort of equivalent of hanging up its phone
and say ok I'm done
and then sometime later or maybe never depending on what kind of web you know service this is
if the the server wants to shut down
it has its own a collection of calls that it makes to stop that service
so anyways just to kind of give you the landscape of what this picture means
so we're going to sort of jump into
the middle this the top level up and we'll focus
actually which will we focus on
well we'll talk to some level in parallel
because there's a lot of commonality as you can see between what goes on with the server and what goes on with the client
yeah and so actually the top level call this one called get adder info is the way that
it sort of
initiate things and actually does the the lookup to map from a domain name to a IP address
so we'll cover that later
so the first step in on either side then and creating a connection is a call to a function called socket
and the reason I wanted to Blackboard was to help you keep track of this
so the first call is a doesn't do much
oh and that's why the the function call is socket
but the
it only happens within the application
it doesn't make a use of any part of the operating system doesn't send anything over the network
and the idea is to basically say hey I want to create a socket
and it's given three arguments
the first two which is AF underscore I net
all these upper case on names are constants that are built in or included in the various
uh .h files that you include in writing this code
and AF underscore I nut just means it's a I P V four so 32-bit addresses
and then the second parameter is says you want a sock stream
and that refers to a TCP connection
it's referred to as a stream connection because like I said you get to send as many bytes as you like a stream of bytes
to in either direction
and then
zero protocol
well I guess it must not be very interesting because I set it to zero
so we don't need to do anything in this particular case
there are man pages on this by the way which
if you just tried to learn all sockets programming by reading men pages you'd go crazy
but once you kind of have the idea of it the man pages are pretty useful
and then the next part
you'll see we're looking only now on the server side is called bind
and
what bind does then is that specific then to a server
and now this is a make this interfaces to the kernel
it says I want to
designate which IP address
and let me just so I'm going to cheat a little bit
and let me by making sure I don't say anything that's not true
yeah I'm right sorry
I just want to make sure
bind actually
tells you
oh excuse me
you'll see that a socket the call to socket returns an int
but it's what it's returning is a file descriptor remember we said that
if you refer to a file a low-level file just by an integer ID typically a small integer value
there's some standard ones for standard in standard out standard error
and then beyond that they're just assigned incrementally
so socket will return a number
that you then refer used to refer to this as a file
so bind then you've pass in that the name of  your socket file descriptor
and you provide a whether is a socket adder ends
ah and si I'm using the the notation
si as a shortcut for sock adder struct sock header
and then you have to also say what the length of the address is
so in the case of ipv4 that would be four
but you don't usually use that number directly there's a
we'll talk about it but that top-level call called gedit or adder info
as a relatively new API that was created and is
in this addition to the book but not in previous ones
is that become the now the standard way that you get all the
parameters that you're supposed to pass into all these different calls
and the idea of it then is it's a pretty small adjustment to then write code that's good for either ipv4 or ipv6
so you don't normally give the actual number  from that you get it from another place and passage it
so binding then
is it's a kernel call
that designates which particular service
this program is going to be hosting
but which will be the server for and that's given by its port number
and then the next step is to
to listen and that's just a call that says
ah that will now convert this socket to a listening socket which you need as a server
so it's a way of telling the kernel that this will be
it will be a server SAR
so obviously bind and listen are related ideas
but you have to do both steps and in that particular order to create a listening socket or one for a server
and then the final part of that to operate us is to say except
and
oh that means okay now we've established this now I'm actually ready to receive phone calls
is essentially what it says is this is the final step to say
okay this one's ready to accept connection requests
it has a similar
set of arguments to sock it is sock it
but slight difference
and now the interesting thing is acceptable return
yet another file descriptor
I'll so the first file descriptor is the sort of generic
accept and base basically except we'll
just hang there and wait until some client makes a connection
and when it does then it will set up a new socket
and a new with a new file descriptor that then the server communicates to the client  via that one
and I'll talk about why it's a different file descriptor in just a second
okay over on the client side goes through  similar steps of socket
but it doesn't have to bind or listen or accept because this is a client
and instead what it does is it it makes a call to connect
so let me finish this off
so these are all on this the server side
and on the client side
it will make a call to connect
from a client side is to set up a connection to server
and so
it's arguments it's a little easier to understand how kynect works
so in particular
the call to socket that was made beforehand returns a file descriptor
and what this says is I want to on that particular using that particular socket
connect to this gives a combination of an address and a port number
and it has to give this address length which I said like I said as before
it's usually that number is filled in using the return value of of get adder info
but that's sort of the equivalent of poisoning the Coleman
and it returns just a code which is
whether the connection was successful or not
so let me just talk about these different ports and
what it all means when you setup a connection
so when the
the server went through bind and listen
it created a listening port from that
which is the one that it's listening for connection requests on
and then the client when it called socket it was given a particular file descriptor for that that socket
and it sends out a connection request
that goes out over the network
and lands at the server and then the kernel hands that off to the
the the program that's running on that particular port
and hands it off to the that call will be handled by the accept
call to accept by the server
and then as I mentioned except actually returns a new file descriptor
which the server will then use as its connection point to this particular client
and the theory of that is you want to be able to in general
as a server be handling multiple clients at the same time
but if I'm communicating with  with Google or Amazon
you should be able to do so at the same time
so you want a possibility of from a single host to be able to serve multiple clients
and that's why they're all assigned different file descriptors at the server end for that particular connection
so you can think of it as the listening file descriptor is just listening for incoming requests for connections
but once it sets up a session and communicates back and forth
those are going through different ports on the server side of things or different file descriptors I'm sorry
same port different file descriptors
from the software that's running on the server
okay and then during the actual communication then as I mentioned it uses reads and writes
as a way to send and receive messages
and that goes on for as long as
you know and according to whatever lo-ove particular protocol is being supported by this application
and then
in the end then when the client the
client is done it causes a request
and what that looks like from the server end is it tries to read from a file
and it receives an end of file a signal instead
and that tells the server okay this particular connection is is gone
and so
now it will close that particular one as this picture shows here
potentially the server could loop back around
and accept a connection from another program and in fact
this can be done this is what we call a serial or a knitter aware
it can only manage one connection request at a time
and when we get later in the course and we stock talk about multi-threading
we'll be able to set it up so this thing can start accepting requests for another connection
even while it's handling one particular client
but anyways what it will look like is the server will read
the attempt to read that we'll get an end of file it will close that particular connection
and it will go back and it will accept a new connection from a new client
okay I'm going to jump ahead and actually start talking about some slides from
that we're if you look online they're actually from a Thursday's lecture  because
there's a lot of ground to cover in that lecture and I'd like to get a little head start
so I mentioned this
up this function called get a door info which is sort of the modern
way in C at least to find information about
that deals with all the funkiness of host names host addresses
all the conventions about ports and some of these various structures and things like that
and the advantage of doing it this way instead of the old way
is first of all now it sort of unifies ipv4 and ipv6 have very similar looking interfaces
and it's fairly easy to write code that can handle either
and the other was there is problems with these old ones that they were designed in an era before multi-threading
and so they have various statically allocated buffers
which gave a lot of bad conditions that you had to watch out for in writing code
and we're prone to errors of various sorts
and so this new new format it's actually harder to use in many levels
because it can't hide away as many details as it used to
but it has the advantage it works better in a multi-threaded environment
the other thing that makes it hard is it's trying to be sort of the kitchen sink of of protocol managers
and that makes it a little bit nasty and messy
and so we're only going to sort of focus in on the parts that we really need to make use of for this course
so in particular there's this function called get adder info
where the information you're passing is a host
which can be either a it's a string as it shows most these are care stars are actual real strings not fake strings
it used to be back in the old days
you use care stars of generic pointer because there weren't void stars
but these are actual strings
so you give the name like the the domain name of a host or you can give the dotted decimal name
but written as you know sequence of characters one to eight dot so forth
a service for example that this is ipv4 T TCP service
some other information that that's associated with this particular connection they refer to as hints
because again this is trying to be a very generic looking call
and then you pass it in a pointer and it will fill in and return back a pointer to a data structure
which is essentially the way it's returning results back to you
and then associated with that is a call called free adder info that will then deallocate this space
that's used by this data structure from the result
and then there's one called get adder info string error
which lets you interpret the various error codes that get created by this
routine of the value that it returns
so
let's just look a little about this and
so the result that's returned by get a door info is a link twist
oh that is null terminated just like most wink lists are
where it gives some combination of the name
of this particular
some naming information for the the first top-level one is the
what I showed you the canonical name for this particular IP address
and then it gives some address information which is
you know an ipv4 them that will encode the IP address
and as a next pointer to change this link voice together
and so this is actually one interesting thing about this is it sort of x
this link voice together  many too many mapping potentially of of names
so if I give for example google.com
it will return a link twist of all
however many or you saw with Twitter it was returning about four different addresses
so this will return actually five missed entries the first will be the canonical name
and then it will give each of the four IP addresses
that's relevant at this particular time
and then you as a programmer
then sort of walk this list you step down this list and typically
try to use each address one after the other
and if you fail on one then you try the next and try the next until you hit the end of the list and then you say whoops
can't do it
and that goes whether you're writing a client or a server
so that adder info
let's look back at what that is
oh so
a door info then is what gets returned is a list of a door info strokes
and so the adder info struck contains various fields
which talks about what type of data is here
what type of socket is it
what its canonical name is how long are its addresses you saw that it's an argument to some of the calls
a pointer to a sock adder struct
that's the way that is encoded for IPV
what we've already seen sock adders is a sort of low-level data structure that gets used
and then an X pointer to chain the link twist together
and so you'll see some of these are the arguments
that then you will use to pass into the other functions like bind and with Simmons and connect
and then there's another version called get name info
which you use when you've got an IP address
and you want to find what is its domain name
and because you remember that mapping is also potentially a one-to-many
there can be multiple domain names associated with it
and so it has a similar  general thing
we'll just look right now it get added info
so just as an example of how you'd write code to make use of this
essentially just as a way of probing the DNS server
is I want to set up an argument a call to get adder info
where the string I'm going to pass the name is
whatever I type in at the to this application to main
and it just for hints just passes a a bunch of zeros
and lists P again these are this will just be a pointers
that I haven't actually
oh okay so you'll notice hints is actually a struct itself
whereas list P and star P are just lists P and P are just pointers to structs
they don't have any allocated data
so the hints I'm just going to fill in that struct with all zeros
because I don't really need to provide any hints
I am telling it that I want a an ipv6 TCP connection here
and then
so what it will do is it will return back
what returns an error code
but it will fill in returned to me a pointer
to a this link twist data structure I showed before
and now I can step through that list
using standard linked list code and make calls to the get name info
function which will return back domain names
and then when it's all done I have to free up that whisk that got returned otherwise  all great memory stuff
so just as a demo
what I'm
on Oh host info sorry
ah so you can think of it this is like
a not very fancy implementation of nslookup
so the kind of stuff we already saw before but let's
all it's returning are the different addresses and one of the things that I found curious is
it returns them in the same order all the time
instead of within a slow cup it kept changing it
and I think that has to do with caching
no that changed
I know it's kind of interesting if it's
it you might want to play with this code it's kind of you can see what's going on in different places
and so you can see though that it's
basically getting the same kind of information
that you would from nslookup it's really just creating the DNS server to do this
but that's the start of what some of this code looks like
one of the things you
by the way when you're writing your own code you often make use of what's called localhost
and that always just refers to the machine that you're running on it
always has this particular IP address
so that address just refers to the machine and as a programmer
you do all your testing on one machine
you just set up both the client and the server on the same machine and play with it so
localhost is a very useful way of doing code development
and if this shows you can request host info for others
thanksgivin and you can also by the way
always give a dotted decimal address
and I'm just making it up here
what and it's not very interesting because it returns back the same address
it's more interesting to run nslookup on that
so
that just gives you a sense
and as you've seen this code is pretty messy stuff to work with there's a lot of
struck so you have to initialize you don't initialize you pass pointers
and so the code always looks a bit crufty
but that sort of the the interfaces it exists
and you'll just have to get somewhat comfortable with it
so that will do us for today then thanks