we're still slogging through the material on machine level programming
which is I talked to you earlier
I think is in some ways the core of this course that much of the rest of material builds upon
and hopefully you've all had a chance to check out lab2 and
your bomb lab and you've gotten started on that
and certainly by the time you're finished with the material from today
you will be well on the way to solving all but the last one or two stages of the bomb lab
so I highly recommend you get going on that not put it off to the last minute
so and what we're talking about today is
is how procedures I'm going to use the same terminology here
whether it's a function a procedure or an object-oriented programming a method
those are all roughly the same thing and what we'll talk about covers them overall
I'll also mention at the outset that the way this is handled in the procedures
that we'll be talking about today is a combination of the actual x86 hardware and how it supports it
but also in some ways more importantly a set of conventions that were developed that
basically everyone agreed to and it's known as an ABI
but I want...who stands for application binary interface
so the idea is a document you can get it online
it's and it's cited in the book
it's a document that people put together the initial version
when the first x86-64 machines were first being developed
and specifically for Linux
they said okay all Linux programs, all compilers,all the operating system,all the different parts of a system
that need to have some common understanding of how to manage the resources on the machine
will agree to adhere to this set of rules
and so it's a it goes beyond the actual what the hardware does to a set of software standards
and it's called application binary interface
because it's particularly the interface at the machine program level
and so that's what we'll be covering today
so people asked sort of well you know who makes up these rules and things
and the point was there was a working group that did this
and there's a separate ABI for Windows
it's similar but not quite the same there's a separate ABI for OSX for Apple
and even FreeBSD a different variant of a unix-like operating system
has its own ABI that they all share a lot in common but some of the details differ
um so if you think about what goes on in a procedure even in C
which is a relatively unsophisticated language in many ways
there's a lot going on and so it's worth breaking down those and thinking about it
one is there's a notion of control
so in my example I show a procedure P calling a procedure Q
and so when P calls Q then somehow the program has to
jump down and begin executing the the lines of code for Q
and then when Q hits its exit point its return point  somehow is to get back to P
and not just to any old place in P but specifically to whatever comes in P right after the call to Q
so somehow we have to record the information about where the return should be to return to the correct place
so that's first of all - for passing control to a function and having that function return back to where it should get back to
our second lose data how do we get operands to it so in this particular case
Q is a function that takes a single argument that it calls internally it calls i
and up here where P is calling it.it's passing some value within P called X
so hum somehow that data value of X has to be recorded in a form
that within Q it will have access to that information
and similarly when Q wants to return a value back
and then P will make use of that value
there has to be some convention of how that data gets communicated back
and then finally in a function might have some local data
that requires allocation of some amount of space
and so where does that space get allocated.how do we make sure it gets allocated properly?
in particular in C as you know when a function returns
any local data that it allocated should get Deallocated should be freed up
so that we don't sort of start consuming an unbounded amount of storage
so how do we do that
those are all the sort of different aspects that a procedure call in return
I have to deal with somehow
and part of the reason for breaking it down into those little segments is
in x86-64 one of the clever things they did was to try and reduce the overhead of procedure calls as much as possible
because as you know in good programming style
you often write these functions that do a fairly small amount of actual useful stuff
and it's sort of good programming style to do that
especially in a more object-oriented programming style
and so you don't want the overhead the extra number of steps taken to
invoke a procedure and deal with all those aspects to take any more time
than it needs to because it's a fairly critical overhead
so one of the things they do in in this is they only do whatever is absolutely needed
so hurt in particular if no local storage is needed on this for data
then don't allocate it therefore don't free it
if you're not passing any values don't pass them
and in general sort of how little can you get away with
and that makes it a little bit confusing from a teaching point of view
and that there is no set template that it follows every time
it sort of you have to each case is a special case for how a particular procedure gets implemented
so we'll go through all these parts and see how they happen
and you've already seen little glimpses of them
we'll hit the little fragments of code that we've shown already
so the first one and sort of the most critical is how do we pass control to a function
but before we can even talk about that we have to talk about the stack
so and you've heard that term the stack in various ways
the stack is really not a special memory
it's just a region of the normal memory remember to the programmers perspective
assembly level programmers perspective is memory is just a big array of bytes
and somewhere within that bunch of bytes,we're going to call it the stack
and the stack is used by the program to manage
the state associated with the procedures that it calls and as they return so it's where it passes
all these potential information the the control information data and allocates local data
and the reason why it can be managed is a stack
because of the nature of the whole idea of procedure calls and returns
that you make a call and you might need some information
but when you return from a call,all that information can be discarded
and so it makes use of that sort of last in first out allocation principle
meshes very well with this idea of procedure call and return
so in x86 stacks
actually start with a very high numbered address
and when they grow when more data are allocated for the stack
it's done by decrementing the stack pointer
so the stack pointer as you know is just a regular register %rsp
and its value is the address of the current top of the stack
and every time you allocate more space on the stack.it does it by decrementing that pointer
now just for convention
and I'm not sure why this happens but this is the way we do it
is we draw stacks upside down
so that the term the top of the stack is actually shown at the bottom
and just to add to that confusion
and also remember that the addresses go from bottom to top not from top to bottom
so when you add to the stack you decrement the stack pointer
neither of those kind of meshes with your intuition perhaps
but you just have to get used to it,because we're not going to redraw out all the slides
so anyway sets just remember that over and over again
that's why this arrow show that
if we were to enumerate the addresses of these different bytes in the data
they'd be increasing in this direction and when we add to the stack
the stack top is at the bottom of the picture and we do it by decrementing the stack pointer
so in particular there is explicit instructions push and pop that make use of the stack
and it's often written pushq and popq
but that q is actually a an optional suffix on the instruction
so the idea of pushing something onto the stack
then is,there is some source operand it could be from register or from memory or an immediate
so this is sort of like a move instruction
but the destination of the move will be toward memory
and that address of the memory is determined by first decrementing the stack pointer  and then doing a write
and similarly the pop instruction takes reads data from the stack
and stores it in the destination which must be a register for this particular instruction
I think push must be a register too
now that I think of it or immediate you can't push from memory to
so pop reads from memory
the address it reads from is given by the current stack pointer
it and then it increments the stack pointer by 8
these both work only on 8 byte operands I'll get to you in a second and
then the result of that is stored in a register
question
...pop and push or just like doing the the three things like is there a difference between like using the like the top
Oh could you write it as a set of instructions
yeah you could actually except for some weird corner cases write it out as a set of separate instructions
but it's a common enough thing that it's sort of built in as a as an operation
where as call and returner are special they can't be simulated
so one thing do you remember too,it's important that
in one case you decrement you do the arithmetic on the stack pointer before you write
because when you first start it out
the stack pointer is pointing to whatever was the top element of the stack
we want to create a new top element so we're going to decrement first  and then do the right
whereas going the other direction you want to read off the current top of stack element
and then you want to increment the stack pointer to sort of deallocate it
and one thing you'll notice here is when I say deallocate
it's not like I magically erase this or...
or something all I'm doing is just moving a stack pointer
whatever it was there at the top of the stack is still in memory
it's just no longer considered part of this deck
okay so that's the idea of the stack
and the instructions push and pop are our two a put data on the stack or take it off
but we use the same basic idea for a call and return
so let's look at some examples and there's a lot of stuff up here
but this is a C function called multstore
and then this is the output slightly cleaned up output from the disassembler of that exact function
and similarly this is a function called mult2
and this is it's disassembled version
and the reason I'm showing this is,because I want to make use of the addresses
that these instructions are app that you don't see when you write it in assembly code
so I'm showing it the disassembled version
and the reason all this is up here is because you'll see the function multstore calls mult2
so I want to show how that works
so and there's two instructions and you've seen these in some form
to call a function you just call it where you give a label
but keep in mind that this these two instructions
and the other is when you're ready to return you just execute the RET instruction
and keep in mind though that these functions don't do the whole business of procedure call and return
they just do the control part of it which as we saw is
only one of three aspects of a procedure
also mention you'll see especially in sometimes
it will say rap semicolon rat q
and you can pretty much just ignore that
and it's a bit obscure why it's even there
so it's really the same idea
okay so what's so to break this down into its simplest part
so let's imagine a scenario
in which the top of stack is at 0x120
which is not realistic by the way
and the program counter which is called %rip which is not anything to do with death
is is indicating that the current instruction is this at (0x)544
which is this call instruction
and so what would happen with the call instruction is it would do two things
it would actually three things
it would decrement the stack pointer and so
so subtracting 8 from (0x)120 and hex gives you (0x)118
and it would write the address of the instruction following the call  onto the top of the stack
and it's important that it does it the one following the call to fit
that's instruction I'm going to return a use for my return address
and I want to resume execution in this function
at the instruction after the call not the call itself otherwise you'd have an infinite loop
and it also this call instruction also embedded in the encoding of the instruction
is the destination address of it
and which happens to be the of it  starting address of this particular function
so the program counter will be set to that value
and now the processor starts just executing along these instructions
so it did a combination of a jump and a push and that's why the question was raised earlier
is a push instruction could you assemble that out of existing instructions
the answer is yes for push but not for call
question back there
- before you actually go to the function in like bolt store you would let me address some multi it alright
no no it did that %rip you never explicitly
there aren't instructions that manipulate that directly
it's implicitly part of the call instruction
the call instruction will take
I don't have the actual encoding
but embedded in this call instruction you see that it's five bytes long.
I don't show you the byte coding.
but embedded in it is the target address
and so it will take that address and use it for the new value of the program counter
so the call does both the pushing of the old the return pointer
and setting the program counter to the new the new target for it
so it does both of those things
question
I don't think so
with either call or return
if so it would be really obscure,no I don't think so
no so call and return are the there might be some weird system instructions that
let you do that but not in you'd see in any normal program
other questions you're good questions
so
okay so that shows you the control how the call works
and then so now imagine this mult2 chugs along
and it hits its return point and it hits this ret instruction
by the way again ret q and red are the same instruction
and ret will
its purpose is to sort of reverse the effect of a call
it assumes that the top of the stack has an address
that you want to jump to
so it will pop that address off the stack
meaning it will increment the stack pointer
like I said the value doesn't really disappear from the memory
just is no consider part of the stack
and then it will set the program counter to what it just popped off the stack
and that will cause the program to resume back to where it came from
so you see that sort of clever idea of pushing the address of the next instruction
so when the return comes it will get it to the point where it should resume execution
okay so that's passing control
it's pretty simple all these things by the way is just the nature machine code
every single part of it is pretty simple
because it's designed to be executed by the original hardware is fairly simple
it's not any more but it's really the basic ideas are
and that we use kind of combinations of instructions to build up all the layers
associated with operations like procedure call and return
ok so passing data
now we've already seen a few small examples of passing data
we've seen a couple registers that get used when you're passing arguments to a function
and we've seen the register %rax getting used to return values from a function
and so those that's the basic idea
and again this is all built into this ABI
you know defined as the set of conventions not particularly part of the hardware
so in particular the rule is that the first six arguments get passed
within these particular registers
and you just have to memorize  the order of them or have a table handy to look at
or something like that because there's no particular logic to it
and the return value is returned in register %rax
and by the way this is all four arguments that are either integers or pointers
well I think I've got a little bit unfolding point those are passed in a separate set of registers
so these are just for assumed now we just are dealing with integer data pointer data
and then you ask well what happens if you have more than 6 arguments to a function
which isn't very common but it happens
well the rule on that is those get put in memory on the stack
and I'll show straight what I mean by that
so they're passed to the function
and then the function has to retrieve those values off the stack
back in the bad old days of IA-32 by the way all arguments got passed on the stack
but now for the most part you pass arguments and registers
and the reason for that is register access is way faster than memory access
okay so here is a kind of a messy bunch of code
but just to show you how they show up all the time
in the function multstore as three arguments X,Y and dest
and you can just see within this code
that it's making use of of registers like %rdi
and doesn't show where
and in other places like mult2 as two arguments
and you can see how it's making use of %rdi and %rsi and the code
so basically the code is generated under the assumptions that whatever arguments is being passed to
it will be passed in that particular set of registers in the particular order they're listed
and the code is sort of makes those assumptions
and then similarly when you have a return value from the function
let's see multstore does not have a return value
but of mult2 does
and the way it does is it deposits the value into %rax
and then when the return from %rax occurs a multstore
you see that it assumes
now that the multstore code can assume that register %rax holds the value of the return value
and it can store it in its destination register
and we'll look in a minute why %rbx gets used here
we'll cover that in just a little waiter
but up that's the point that as long as everyone sticks to this common interface standard
then you can even use different compilers to compile code
and have them be able to cooperate with each other in terms of passing arguments returning data
and that's the reason why you want that convention
yes
8 bytes because the well first of all for call and return
it's a 64-bit machine so all addresses are 64 bits or 8 bytes
but also even the push in the pop instruction only work on 8 byte values
if you said push L ,if you tried to write that in X in 64-bit code
it would come back with a syntax error
if you add it in this somewhere
so oh that and that's different IA-32 there'd be four byte values
okay so like I said you've sort of seen that implicitly in some of the code you've already been looking at
and it's pretty straightforward
to get an example that shows passing arguments
you have to have a function with at least 7 arguments which is pretty messy to do
so I won't do it but there's examples in the book
but now and we'll sort of pick it up
I'll show you,also in this later part
um and now the third part of it is again
what if there's some local data that we need to make use of
and so to get that idea across I have two illest in another
concept which is called the stack frame
and so this is a particularly pattern that's used in memory and as I mentioned
earlier one of the features of calling and returning
is you can imagine when you have a nested series of calls to a function
when a particular function is executing
it only needs to reference the data within that function or values that have been passed to it
some which might be pointers and therefore pointing to other locations in memory
but the point is sort of the rest of the functions
in your code over many they are
are sort of frozen at that moment really there's only one function executing at any given time
I'm assuming a sort of what you'd call single threaded model here
and so we can just allocate on this stack
whatever space is required for this particular function
and then when we return from that function
we shouldn't if it's correctly written need any of the information associated with that function
it can just sort of disappear forever
and that's why this idea of a stack
you allocate something if you make more calls you keep allocating more stuff
but as they return you kind of back out of the stack and and free things up
so the stack discipline is is exactly the right
a matches well this whole idea of procedure call and return
so each block we use for a particular call then is called the stack frame
and to be sort of more technical we'll say
that it's a frame for a particular instance of a procedure a particular call to a procedure
so just imagine we had a set of functions one called yoo
which calls a function called who
and who has multiple calls to another function called amI
and amI is itself is recursive it calls itself
and so an imagine we had a chain of calls
where yoo calls who calls amI
which calls itself recursively twice
and then we'll exit out of amI and get back to who
and then who will hit it second call to amI`
which won't go any further and that will be it
so this picture here shows this whole history of all these calls that get made
but in terms of the stack
all we need what will keep a frame for every sort of procedure
that has been called but not yet returned on the stack
and in general this stack of is delimited by delimited by two pointers
one is the stack pointer which we're familiar with
and then there's another called the base pointer which register %rbp indicates
but one a feature of actually it's now become a feature of IA32 as well
is that this is an optional pointer
and in particular the code that we'll see does not use a base pointer
except in some very special cases
so this register doesn't really won't show up in your programs
being used in a special way as a frame pointer
it will be used instead just as a regular register
so typically then the only thing you'll know about the stack pointer
you won't even be able to figure out where the frame is exactly
you'll just know that the top part of the stack  is the top frame for the topmost function
and this is all managed by the code itself
and this is the same stack by the way in which you're pushing and popping addresses -
and they all kind of get mixed together
so we haven't actually seen any code up til now that makes you ask to do any explicit management of the stack
because all our examples were very simple
and just did a made use of the stack only for return addresses
but we'll see some that uses more
but so in general then imagine that each time you begin a function some space gets allocated potentially on the stack  for its frame
and then and that frame is indicated by either one pointer only or two pointers
and so now as yoo calls who then that will create a new stack frame for who
in some way when mi gets called that creates a new stack frame
and as we continue with these recursive calls
we're just adding more stuff to the stack getting deeper and deeper
and that will keep happening that's one of the reasons why recursion is a little bit of a risky thing
is that it compared to iteration
it keeps requiring more space as you go deeper in the recursion
and in particular most systems limit the total depth of the stack
and you can have what
because they're afraid of the sort of infinite loop version of recursion is
runaway recursion where it just keeps trying to push more and more stuff onto the stack
that's an aside
and then as these begin to return they those frames get de-allocated removed from the stack
so part of it the nice thing about this is it means that
every time I if I have multiple calls to amI
because I've gone deep recursively each one of them will have its own local state  that it needs to manage
and again the whole stack dissapoint is what makes it work
and what we'll find out in particular is because of the way this is set up
recursive calls are handled the same way that regular calls are
there's nothing special about them
all the sort of infrastructure required to support recursion is built into this whole stack discipline
so anyways imagine that all these calls are returned back to who
and then who would call amI again
and then again as we exit we were sort of deallocating these stack frames
and getting back to the the starting point
yes question
[student question]
Oh so the question was if %rbp is optional
then how does the program know how to do the D allocation
how can it reset the stack back to the right place
and the answer is and we'll see examples that the code is compiled
so it knows for example when it does the allocation it's going to allocate 16 bytes
and then it knows at the end that it can D allocated 16 bytes
and it actually brings up a good point
there is sort of an obscure part of the book that goes over this
there's a few special cases where it can't know in advance
how much space will be allocated
when it has to allocate a an array or a memory buffer of variable size
and then it will actually use the the %rbp in those cases for exactly that purpose
okay and so in general that what the stack frame will look like in one of these machines
will be something like this that
the and you'll see this is the caller
and then this is the the stack frame of the the function that got called
so working our way back
if we have to pass more than six arguments
the caller will actually use its own stack frame to store those arguments
and so that they'd be available
and we already saw when you do a call
it will push the return address onto the stack
so before our function even starts all this information would be on the stack
now if there's a if this particular if we're making use of a base pointer
then we have to have some way where to store the old value of the base pointer
so that we could fix it back when we return
we won't show any code doing that here so this is optional
but in general if there's some local state
like some registers that need to be saved and we'll see examples of that
or an array that needs to be allocated locally
that will be stored within the stack frame
and there might be some requirement for some extra space in the stack frame for other stuff
in particular if it we're going to pass more than seven arguments it needs space
somewhere in the stack frame to do it
and what we'll see in typical a code is
this stack pointer gets decremented pretty soon after the procedure begins
and it gets incremented back just before it returns
that's how it manages this deck
so let's do some examples
um let's see look at this before
but this is a function
oh I think the interesting thing about this function is that it has a pointer being passed to it
so this function takes an argument
one argument is a point or another is a an integer value
and you can see what it does is
it dereferences that pointer to get a value code X
it computes a value Y by summing X and the value passed to it
it stores Y back at P
but it returns X the original value of the pointer not the updated version of the pointer
and you can see that in the code here
its codes pretty short remember that in general %rdi will hold the first argument in this case it's a pointer
so we'll do a read from that pointer
and it will put the value in our a X which is where the return value should be  anyhow
and then it will increment %rsi which has the value called Val here
initially and now it has the value of x + Val
and then it will store that in the value pointed to by P
and it will do a return so you see these three instructions do all the different parts of this
and as this shows in general also you know register usage it's handy
by the way to document this when you're looking at code
%rdi is the first argument %rsi gets used initially it's Val
but now it will be set to Y during the call
and similarly %rax is initially the value
well it's it's both what X is here and it's used as the return value
okay so what's up the reason to go through all that is to actually show you examples of calling this
and how arguments get passed to the function and how it makes use of the stack frame
so now there's a function called call incr
and it's going to create a value called vet v1
and have to generate a pointer to that
so what that means is v1 can't just stay in a register
because you can't create an address of a register it has to be stored in memory somewhere
so that you can create a pointer an address of it
and where does it store it well it puts it in the stack
so how does it find space on the stack while allocates it
so the function call_incr then and we'll go through all the different parts of it
but you see that this red code here is generated generates
these two instructions one is to allocate 16 bytes on the stack
and the other is to store $15213
at offset eight from the stack pointer
and as will often see the the program often allocates more space on the stack than it really needs to
and there's some conventions about trying to keep
addresses on aligned in various ways
that are sort of obscure and we you should just kind of not worry about the fact there's unused space and functions
because they do it the reasons for doing it are are
maybe interesting to some but not really ones you need to understand at this point
so the point being that the way we got space on the stack was to just add to the stack pointer decrement the stack pointer
so now we have a number 15213 that's sitting in memory
and we can create a pointer to it
and so now to set up this call we need to create a pointer v1
to v1 and we have to pass the number 3000
so we'll see that will copy 3000 to register %esi
and let me just double check here
just looking up
so one of the annoying features is
you see all the data type here are long so there's no incr
and yet it's copying 3,000 just to register %esi and not %esi
and it's using a movel and not a moveq
I think we might have covered that last time
but 3,000 is a small enough number it will fit in 32 bits
it's a positive number so we don't have to worry about sign bits
so the thing can sort of get away with a trick here of using just a movel instruction
because when any instruction has a one of the eregistry ziz its destination
it will set the upper 32 bits of that register to zeros
so this will have the effect of copying the number 3000
and during out the upper bytes to register %rsi
and the reason the compiler likes this is it takes one less bite to encode
a movel than it does to encode a moveq
um so just you have to get used to these kind of things
so that's setting up argument the the second argument to the call
but the first argument it's using this instruction lea or leaq
for what it's supposed to be used for which is to create pointers
remember we talked about this instruction often getting used just to add two numbers
but it's actually designed exactly for this purpose
that it looks like a memory reference  8 relative to the stack pointer
but instead of
now reading from that memory reference the instruction will just copy the computed address to %rdi
and so %rdi will now be equal to whatever the stack pointer plus 8 is
okay so that creates the two arguments that I'm passing to this function
and now the call instruction will happen
and you'll recall that the call instruction adds(3000) two numbers and stores the result back in the pointer
so its effect will be to set the of this memory location to 18 to 13
you'll notice the clever trick here
and also return a particular value
which we won't make use of the return value
no we do make use of the return value
and now the...
now when we return back
what we want to do is add the value in v1
to the value we just computed the value we just computed is in v2
and we know that the v1 is designated by this memory location that %rsp+8
and so we'll just read from memory to include that to %rax
and then the final step is to deallocate so you see the match here
and this was to answer the question earlier how does it know
how to restore the the stack back to its original place
well the compiler you know built into it figured out how much space it would need for this particular function
and it allocates that when it comes in and it D allocates it when it goes out
so and this you know this is a very simple example
but even more elaborate examples are still based on that same set of ideas
so that shows you in 1 then the data management the stack management
the idea of using a stack frame
and now the return by this point the
the only thing that's left is
after I increment the stack pointer it will be pointing back to this return address
whoops wrong direction here
so now if I do a rep the RET instruction will always take
whatever is pointed to by the stack pointer and use that as the return address
so it's very important that %rsp get set back to where it should be before you it does a rep
okay so that's sort of the the basic principles
now now let's get a little bit more refined
an important idea is well what about these registers
what can be assumed about particularly jesters and how they get changed  and so forth
and so again it's built into this idea of an ABI  is a set of conventions about the register
obviously %rsp is a very important register
and you don't want programs just to randomly change its value without them knowing what to do
but it turns out we'll also be careful with some of the other registers too
and so here's sort of a thought experiment imagine we had a function
called yoo that's going to call who
and it has some data
that it it wants to put somewhere
and then when who's going to get called
and then the question is can I rely on the fact that register %rdx will still hold the number 15213
and the answer is not in general
because who might have overwritten %rdx and put something else there
so in particular if who did some operation involving register %rdx
it could have messed up the value that was there before
so the obvious answer is while you should not have used %rdx for that purpose right
and that's why we will come up with a set of conventions
so just some terminology
when we're talking about one function calling another
it's useful to have used the following words will call  the calling function the caller
and the function that gets called the Kaali
and now there's basically two ways we can manage register it can be what's called caller saved
which means if the caller really cares
if you really want to value that will be there when it returns
when control returns back to it
then it should store it away first it shouldn't assume that the register will be....
it should assume that the register might get altered by it
but there's another class we can define it called collie save
which is sort of a contract between all the functions and it's built into the ABI that says
if a particular function wants to alter date alter this register
what it needs to do is first store it away and it will do it by putting the value in the stack
and then before we return from that procedure
we should restore it back to whatever it was before
so that's a convention called call me save
and it's a little less intuitive and it takes a while to get the hang of this
but you'll begin to see its value
so in particular with this ABI
we've already seen %rax used for the return value
and we've seen these six registers that get used for passing arguments
and will also designate registers %r10 in %r11
to be just temporary values that can be altered by any function
that's meaning of color saved
we've already seen actually within code  often them overriding these registers
because whatever gets passed to a function
the function can do whatever it wants to that data
as long as it's not somehow corrupting other data
so those often get used as temporary storage as well
and %rax gets often overwritten multiple times before it gets set to a final return value
but we're going to say that these four registers and most commonly %rbx
are our what are called callee-save registers
meaning they'll only get used in this special way that if a function wants to alter it
one of these registers has to push it will push the value on the stack
and then just before returning it will pop that value back off the stack
so register %rbp as I told you about is special  if you're using frame pointers
if you're not using frame pointers
then it can be treated as a Callee-save register
so I'll get back to that in a minute
the fact you can combine those two and it works fine is actually a little bit subtle
and then as I mentioned %rsp is special you don't mess with that unless you know what you're doing
so let's look at an example of this use of callee-save registers and why how it works
and I'll do it by a version of this similar function to what we did before
but now what I'm going to do is my return value
is to add X which is an argument of being passed to this function
there were no arguments in the earlier version
so somehow I have to have X it gets passed originally in register %rdi as you know
but %rdi might
well I'm going to have to reuse register %rdi to pass value to incr
so somehow I have to do something with X
because I'm going to need X when I return back to here after the call
so where am I going to put it well that's why I have callee-save registers
and so you see that the code here
at the outset of this function
then it will store away whatever is in %rbx currently it will put it on the stack
and so now the the stack frame for this function looks like there's a return address
from before but I'm going to save the value of %rbx
and then I'm going to decrement the stack pointer by 16 as I did before
but that will be on top of the eight bytes I've already allocated to store %rbx
and then you'll see within the code
for example when it wants to compute this return value
it can assume that %rbx when whatever this call does  inker
we assume inker is well behaved that if it makes use of register %rbx
it will fix it up before it returns
and then this function well in its exit code will not only increment the stack pointer
but it will then pop the value of %rbx back
and so again you see this sort of bracketing push/pop a sub tract
ad and you'll notice that things
on the clean-up part of it the end you sort of do things in the reverse order that they were done
coming in again because of the stack discipline
so that's sort of a demonstration of this eight idea of an ABI that
everyone will treat %rbx this way it will save it on the stack
if it's going to alter it if it's not going to alter it it doesn't have to save anything
whose question I saw No
so we haven't seen that in other code
because we didn't typically need it that's again an example in  this particular machine code
we only do what we have to do
okay
okay so now we can kind of put this all together
and look at some examples of recursion and the important thing to keep in mind is
you know recursion is one of those sort of magical parts of computer science it seems like some black art
that it actually works
but when you look at these low-level mechanisms it all works out
and the C compiler doesn't have to make any special consideration for
a recursive function versus a normal function
because this whole stack discipline makes it work
so I'm going to illustrate that then with a version of this function I called pcount
I've had various instance of it
where you remember it's the the role of this is to count the number of ones
in an initial word
so the recursive version of this says
if the argument is zero then it has no ones in it
otherwise I take the leading bit  the least significant bit
and I'll which is either going to be a one or a zero of course
and add that to what you get by shifting right X right by one position
and recursively counting the number of one bits in that
so pretty natural kind of recursion and
and keep in mind these are all unsigned numbers  the argument is
so the right shifts are logical
this would really be a bad idea with arithmetic right
and this is a code generated in general recursive code
it's going to always generate a bigger blob of code than the iterative version
because it has to do all the stack stuff
so this is about as simple as it gets in recursive calls
so let's just sort of pick it apart
well if easy case is if X is zero you'll see what happens is
it first of all assumes X is going to be zero in fact
and sets up the return value of zero  to the register
and then it will test now while is X zero
you remember the test instruction has two operands that get ended
so when they're the same it just is testing the value of x here
and if that's equal je is means jump equal to 0 in this case
or might say jz is the same instruction
so if the value equals zero we'll jump to the end of the function and hit the return instruction
like I said before the %rap semicolon you can ignore that
so that handles that one
and now the rest of the code is to handle this lower part
where I have to set up the arguments to recursive call I have to keep track of
what at least the least significant bit of X is and handle all that stuff
so here's the code and it doesn't need any other thing anything on the stack
other than a space to store %rbx which is whatever again
whatever was in %rbx when you enter
I'm just going to put it on the stack I won't look at it I won't make use of it
but I'll I'll have it there so I can restore the register when I return
so it will push the value under the stack
and now the real meat of the the body of it is it will copy X into %rbx
which we've just put on the stack so we can safely do it
and we'll just set only will clear out at all but the least significant bit of that particular register
and again this is one of these weird ones where I can use EBX as a destination
knowing that all 0 all the high order bits
and then I'm going to take X and I'm just going to shift it right by one position
which sets me up for this recursive call so
so this red code does both of these parts of it here
and now I'm ready to call P count recursively
because I have the shifted value in %rdi
and I know because this is a well behaved function
that when P count returns it can assume that %rax holds  the recursive result
and I also know even though P count actually does modify %rbx
but I know because I the code is well behaved
the %rbx will get restored to whatever was there before
and %rbx in this case just before making the call i set it to the value of this we significant bit right
so when I return back I can assume that %rbx holds the least significant bit of x  my original argument
and %rax call holds the recursive result
so I can just add those two numbers together
call that the return value and I've correctly computed the result
and then the final queen up is to pop %rbx to restore whatever was in there
and then to do the return
so again you see that the piece is all kind of it's a puzzle that all fits together
because all the functions are using this common set of conventions about
where arguments get past
what registers can be used how registers
if some registers have to be restored back if they get used and all that stuff works together
which gets me back to just the point I was making before
if you're using register %rbp for a frame pointer
so typically point to the beginning of a frame like that
so imagine you have a function that needs a base pointer
because as I mentioned the  case is that if it has to within that function allocate some amount of space
it's unknown at compile time
well imagine now that some other code gets called deep recursive calls
or whatever that might do other things
well if you treat %rbp as a Kali save register
then when these other functions return
if they've altered if they made use of rbp for one reason or another
it's guaranteed that they will restore it back to
whatever condition it was in originally before
so now this function will have a reliable value of %rbp
so again it shows as long as all the code obeys these conventions on
how it they use registers then sort of life is good
you can make use of these...
so to have a trust that the things will be the way they are
and so again that's why there's this sort of very careful process for creating an ABI
of early on in the life time of a new processor
so that all the compiler writers operating systems people
and the ones who implement tools like gdb debugging tools
kind of all I have the right set of standards by which they can work from
okay so just to sort of wrap things up
and I would say by the way this is the kind of thing you can
I could lecture to you for weeks but to really get it in your mind
the best way is to almost to hand execute some very simple examples
or use a debugging tool and and run through them yourself
just to make sure you really are convinced that this is all going to work
because all these pieces just fit together and the way they fit together is what makes it work
so as I mentioned before and I'll say it again
that this this discipline is what makes recursion work
so the idea of having a stack frame for every call to a function means that
I can call a function call a function call a function call function
when I'm deep in that recursion I still have data associated with the other outstanding calls to that function
but each of them will have their own stack frames
and so it has a place to store that sort of
information that's associated with one particular instantiation of a function
the register saving conventions we saw
a way that functions avoid sort of trashing each other's data
if I'm using a call we save register
it's my obligation to save it and restore it properly
it's the obligation of any function that gets called further down to also do that save and restore
and then this sort of...
notion of a stack being the right match of how procedure call and return works
it if P calls Q
then before I go back to P
Q of returned and so I won't need that storage for Q anymore
those you've taken 150 or other wet
places where you look at fancier languages
don't have that status can trust that stack discipline
and they have to use some other mechanism though actually
if required use heap allocation of
of the stack of the frames than all your stack frames
to keep data around after a function returns
but for C and instead of all the standard commonplace languages
the stacked is what is exactly what's needed
and that's not next the designers of C knew this well
this matching of a stack to their language
and I'll mention also this we I was talking about simple recursion before
but there's also mutual recursion where
a function say P calls Q and then Q might call P
and it looks very exotic and  it's a quite clever
but again how it's implemented is exactly what we've seen here
doesn't take any special special kind of code
so
then to finish up this is sort of what you need to remember about  procedure calls
that it's all about the stack discipline
and you'll get as you're working throughyour lab
you'll just get much more ingrained to this idea of of the stack
and what's on there and be able to examine
it okay so that's all I've got for today
so give you a little extra time in your calendar