good afternoon everyone
so now we're going to jump into the part of the course
that I'd call the real core of course
where we go into machine level programming
and by the term machine level programming I mean
when you're actually considering the
the individual instructions to get executed by the machine in response to your program
and there's really two forms of machine programs
one is the actual object code that runs on the computer
and as we'll see that's a series of bytes
that encode instructions  that the prostitute executes
but well because it's hard to look at bytes
and understand them there's various text forms to make it more clear
and one of  those is assembly code
that it used to be that's how people program machines
and nowadays it's what the target of a compiler is to generate assembly code
and I'll use those terms
when I say machine code I sort of interchangeably mean
object code the binary form or assembly code the text version of it
interchangeably because it really is a one-to-one mapping between them
but in case I sort of use a term like assembly code
when I instead of consistently saying machine code
it's because they're really the same general idea
so this is sort of one place where
this course 213/513 takes a particular perspective
that's very different from done ever elsewhere
in the bad old days of computing
you would be required to take a course it was typically called assembly level programming
the way you actually learn to write programs in assembler
and your assignments would be to do things like to  sort a array of numbers
who set up some kind of linked list data structure  just sort of low-level programming
that nowadays you wouldn't even think of wanting to write an assembly code
and so people didn't really enjoy those courses very well
and so they got sort of our we cut out of the curriculum
but what our version of it is is
this is pretty important stuff to know
as the sort of gateway between what's how you write your programs
say and C or any other
and how those programs actually execute on a machine
so machine code is sort of the intermediate form there
the intermediate language and you need to understand that to understand better
what your programs are trying to do
and what the machine is trying to do
so as a result of that our perspective will be
we won't actually write except in very very small amounts
we're not going to actually sit down and write assembly programs in this course
but what you'll do is you're going to look at a lot of code
that was generated by a C compiler GCC
and try to see how does that what came out of that compiler relate to what went into it
how does this low-level code implement the higher level constructs
that I was trying to express my program in
how our procedures functions implemented in machine language
how our data structures such as arrays and struts
how are those implemented in machine codes
so we're going to learn all of that stuff
and it takes a significant chunk of this course
and a fair number of lectures to get through all that material
because it's really quite a bit
but I think it's like I said I think this is sort of the core of where this course is
and as you know in this course we only look at one particular class of machines
even though there's many more different machine level programming possibilities out there
and we've chosen the Intel the 64-bit version of the Intel instruction set
so I'll go through a little bit of the history behind Intel
and how it got to where it is
we'll look at through this idea of how does C code relate to assembly code machine code and so forth
we'll go through set of low-level basics
that you need to understand the of what assembly cup machine code looks like
and then we'll actually take on and look at some real code
focusing specifically on arithmetic operations
so x86 is insert a colloquial term for Intel processors
and the reason is that the first one was called the 8086
and then they kind of skipped a t1 but then they went to 80 to 86
and so forth 8386
so the one thing in common was 86  and so people just call it x86
and one thing that's important to this
and it will have influence on what the programs look like is
x86 is a language like English
that it's been an accrual and evolution of different features layered on top of each other
and not always the most elegant way
so just like English there's all these sort of quirky things
that how you write it is very different from how you pronounce it
then there's all these irregular cases
it doesn't make sense it's not sort of a purpose-designed language
it's the same with x86
it's a language that just got there
because of a bunch of decisions that locally were probably the right thing to do
but globally were not
there's other instruction sets that are much cleaner and easier to understand
but we figure it's just the same reason that you learn English
instead of learning Esperanto or something like that
that it's a much more useful language
x86 is what sometimes was called a CISC
there's a big thing in the early 80s  80s in general called RISC vs. CISC
CISC a well risk was a new relatively new idea
what they called a reduced instruction set computer  and it was all the rage
and nobody had a name for what came before
but the RSIC people named what came before a CISC
for complex instruction set computer with the obvious sort of pejorative nature to that title
and so Intel to the the classic CISC architecture
meaning it has a ton of features we're not going to even scratch the surface if you want it
the manual for it is two big fat books
which nowadays you do with PDF documents but it's still a huge amount of stuff
some 500 or more instructions everything
from doing decimal arithmetic to even decimal floating point
and all kinds of goofy stuff in there
but it turns out that you can kind of get a pretty good handle on it
by focusing more on just what does the code look like that
GCC is generating for the kind of programs that you typically write
and it should also realize it
it many levels of this should not have been the six the the successful design
because as I said it's just got lots of stuff on there
but Intel has been such a powerful company and had so much market
and such better technology
as far as semiconductors than its competitors
that's been able to kind of keep this thing alive for almost 40 years
it's pretty admirable
so just to give you a sort of timescale
as I mentioned the 8086 was the first
one of the first single chip 16-bit microprocessors  came out in 78
and it a slight variation on it was a very basis for the original IBM PC
which I know predates most of you your lives
but it was sort of a the the big breakthrough that put computers on the desktops of many people
and there's been many many generations I'm just giving you the highlights
from that are relevant to this particular class
the 386 which dates back to 1985
was the one that really made the transition from these being personal computers
that could run not very interesting applications
to ones that could actually run something like a UNIX or Linux machine
and the reason is they extended it to 32 bit
and they removed some of the weird addressing stuff that used to be in there
so that these look like sort of a generic a processor
and that was clear back in 85 and that was what sometimes called IA32 intel architecture 32
which was the dominant way of code up told just even a few years ago
so even up as recently as this past summer
this course was teaching IA32
and then there and i'll talk about it more later
there was a reason in a strange story behind the extension from 32 to 64 bits
which kind of was sneaked in by intel
uh and an odd model the pentium 4E
but you see it was only about 10 years ago
and one of the smart things they did with that is
is that the machines that can run the 64-bit code can also run 32-bit code
so they were able to sort of bring out all these machines
without everybody having to change over their software
and it's taken about that amount of time
for the software to largely transition away from 32-bit code to 64-bit code
and then for actually fairly interesting reasons
it you could map how fast a single processor would run
and it was climbing up at a pretty steady pace until around 2004
and then Intel got and all the companies got into serious trouble with the power consumption of their chips
they're approaching a hundred watts
so imagine a hundred watt light bulb
and how much heat that generates inside of a box
that you try to blow a fan on really hard to keep it from getting too hot
and they were reaching the point where they really couldn't go much beyond a hundred watts
and so they sort of got into a power budget problem
and as a result they haven't been a to scale up the frequency
how fast the inner clock that drives this thing is beyond just a few GHz
since 2004 so what's happened was
they said well we can't make any single processor faster
but we can put a bunch of processors on a single chip
and those are referred to cores or multi-core
so most of you with laptops probably have two cores on those
and a laptop processor and a server might have up to 16 cores
so those are independent processors that are all reside on a single chip
the shark machines date back to 2008
and they are each have four cores on them
the shark machines the one thing about
computers haven't really gotten that much faster of in the meantime
so there's still fairways and they were in their day a very high-performance machine
so they're still pretty decent
this shows a picture of the chip that makes up a
I think the the shark machines or approximately that same area
and you'll see that as the picture shows these four cores are integrated onto one chip
and then down at the bottom is what they call a cache
and we'll learn a lot about cache memory but it's
it's basically a temporary memory
used to hold the most recently accessed data
so that you can get to it more quickly
and you'll see that that shared across the four cores
so if you look at the latest if you were to go off shopping on in the catalog the latest instance
and I don't have any chip pictures
it is a model they called a Broadwell model
and you'll see that on a single chip they have multiple cores
4 cores a serious standard desktop model eight first a server class machine
and then built around the perimeter there are various connections to the rest of the world
so DDR is the way you connect to the main memory what's called DRAM dynamic ram
PCI is the connection to peripheral devices
SATA is a connection to different types of discs
and USB well you know USB is
and then the ethernet is the connection also to a network connection
so that's all integrated onto a single chip is not just the processor itself
but a lot of logic that glues that processor into a larger system
and one interesting thing you'll notice is that the desktop model is a higher power 65 Watts
versus the server is 45 watts
when you put a lot of computers in a room
turns out power is the biggest issue you have to deal with
so Intel isn't the only company in this game
they're sort of historic competitors a company called AMD
and AMD was always sort of NO.2 behind Intel
in all the just so I gave is his NO.2 behind Hertz
but they are
but they had a little burst in time when they kind of got out ahead of Intel
because Intel had wasted their time on some bad ideas
and they actually were the one that came up with the 64-bit extension to Intel that we use
right now though AMD is not doing very well
Intel sort of realized that it had to get its act together and it did
and is more or less crushed AMD
but and I should mention that they had these ferocious patent suits
many years ago and the result of that was a cross licensing deal that allows AMD to produce x86 processors
- now it's interesting story behind Intel in 64 bit
they decided to make this radical shift to an architecture that they called the
they called IA-64 at the time
and it was based on a whole new concept
that looked really good on paper and initial results look promising
they invested a lot of money in this stuff
they formed a joint operation with Hewlett Packard on this and it turned out not to work
it was much too aggressive it assumed miraculous optimization capabilities by the compiler
and so it was a from a technical idea it was very interesting technology
but in the marketplace it didn't work
and this was sort of a branch off
the Intel pursued and felt obligated to keep it up because they'd invested so much in it
and Along Came AMD and they said well we don't have to do this radical shift
we'll just sort of do the obvious thing of adding
making the registers bigger making things go from 32 to 64 bits
and they came along with that and gotta and were successful
and so Intel kind of had to just sheepishly follow behind AMD on this
but they could because of their cross licensing deal
so nowadays as I mentioned hardware wise just about every processor that
is in a laptop,in a desktop  even your cell phones of recent generation are all 64-bit processors
so what we'll talk about then we used to teach IA32
but that's gone this is the first term where we're skipping it all together
so we're using what we'll call x86 - 64
there's various ways this is named but this is sort of the Linux way of naming it
if you're interested in IA32 there's a document on the web associated with the book
called a web aside that goes through at least some of the basics of
but to really read that you need to learn the 64 bit
because it assumes you kind of already know that
okay so let's go in and I should mention - if just for general interest
the other major class of processor and common use today are called arm
so arm actually is an acronym for acorn RISC machine
I just told you at-risk means it means risk reduced instruction set computer
an acorn means like you know the seed of an oak tree it was a British company
that decided to make its own personal computers in the early days of it and they said
we're not going to buy those chips from Intel
we're going to make them ourselves so they designed and manufactured their own chips
well as a company a computer manufacturer it was a complete bus
but it turned out that they'd come up with a fairly good instruction set
that was sufficiently simple that it could be put on chips and better yet
it could be customized
so arm is now a company of its own headquartered in Cambridge England
and the reason why part of the reason they're successful therefore is
because it tends to be a lower power Pross than an x86 machine because it's simpler
but the other is that they don't actually sell processors
they sell companies the rights the licensing rights to use their designs
and so if you look at like a a cell phone processor
the actual ARM processor is a little tiny part of it on the chip
and then they'll have other stuff to make the graphics go better to improve your phone calls and so forth
and so they're really selling what intellectual property is opposed to chips
and so people we've gotten various enquiries
when are you going to start talking about ARM in your book or your course or something and we go
it would be another book to write to do justice to ARM
it would be like a whole redo of the thing
and we were not inclined to do that right now
but just so you know there's sort of a two worlds out there x86
ARM are the dominant players right now
so let's talk some terminology
and you've probably heard some of these terms before but let's make it clear
so when we talk about the instructions the instruction set
that's the the target of a compiler to give you a series of instructions
that tell the Machine exactly what to do
but it turns out that the hardware people have figured out
all kinds of clever ways to implement instructions
some of them are really fast but take a lot of hardware
some are pretty slow but don't take much hardware at all
and so they managed to create this
this abstraction that's called the instruction set architecture
which is what the target of a compiler should be
and then let the hardware people figure out how best to implement it
and then the low so that that's a concept actually it came along in the 1960s
so that's even before my time as far as a computer person
but it's a very important concept in the world of computers
and then what they call the lower level stuff
how it actually gets implement is called the microarchitecture
and we will talk very very little about microarchitecture in this course
and as I mentioned machine code is sort of a generic term that incorporates both
the actual (bit)bytes that are operated executing as well as the assembly level version of it
and as I mentioned you can think of from instruction set point of view
so IA32,x86-64 and what's called Itanium
this not very successful Intel thing
those are all in some ways different instruction set architectures
ARM actually similar to Intel has gone through various different generations
so there's various different generations of its instruction set
so from a programmer machine level programmers perspective
things are a bit different than you see when you write C code
first of all there is some very visible parts of the instruction the Machine state
that you can examine and test and operate on  and you must in fact
that you would never understand what those are if you're just thinking in terms of C
so in particular there's some sort of a program counter to tells you what
what address is the instruction that you're going to execute next
where is that located in memory
and then there's a set of registers which are part of the
that the programmer actually makes use of
you can think of them as as a very small number of memory locations
but rather than giving an address from 0 up to n-1 or something
you actually give them by name as specifically
and then there's another sort of state
that's just a few bits worth of state that talked about
what what are the results of some recent instructions
where they did it produce a value of 0 did it produce a negative or a positive value
and those are used to implement conditional branching
which we'll look at later as we go
and then the other part of it
so that's sort of the processor and then the other part of is the memory
and as I mentioned in the one of the first lectures
the memory is you can think of logically as just an array of bytes
and that's what the Machine level programmer sees
and it's actually kind of a fiction in different ways as I mentioned before
there's sort of a collaboration between the operating system and the hardware
what they call virtual memory to make it look like each program running on the processor
has its own independent array of bytes that it can access
even though they actually share values within the the physical memory itself
and furthermore you heard the term cache
the idea of a cache is not visible here at all
because it just is automatically loaded with recent stuff
and the only thing that will look different is if you re access that memory it will go faster
than it would if it hadn't been cached
but it's not visible in terms of
there's no instructions to manipulate the cache
there's no way you can directly access the cache
so you already see that it's already abstract it's got some more details of real Hardware
but underneath it the sort of micro architecture level has some features built into it
that you're not operating on you're not making use of directly
yeah when you write machine level programs
so if you have a program then say and C
it would typically on a larger program that will include multiple files
and it will make use of some library code
and so the process of compilation is actually a series of steps
that will take what you've written for code
turn it into machine code combine it with the compiled
compiler generated code for the libraries and produce finally a in a file
that's your actual executable program
and there's shown here in this picture that the first step is to
take C and actually generate assembly code from it
and then the next is to run that through an assembler
which takes the text representation of instructions and turns it into the actual byte level representation
we'll look at all this shortly
and then there's a program called a linker
which merges together all the different files for both your individual file
their compiled versions and for the library code
and then finally there's a even once you run a program
there's actually some libraries that get imported dynamically
when the program first begins
so it's a sort of many layered set of activities
and I'll go through some of these one-by-one for you
so for example here's a not very interesting function in terms of doing anything useful
but it sort of demonstrates the basic ideas of compilation
and if I run this through a C compiler
I get something that looks like what's shown on the right and that's assembly code
and just to give you an idea of what it is
it looks like a sort of strange language the first time you see it
but you'll see those percent are
something those are the actual names of registers
remember I told you there's registers that you give by name
and then those instructions are telling it to do something
pushq means push something onto a stack
move means move copy it from one place to another
call means to call some procedure
pop is the counterpart to push
and then rep is exit return out of this particular function
so you see each of those is an instruction  and it's written in text
but each of those will turn into one actual instruction  in the object code representation
so I should tell you that this is actually a slightly cleaned up version of what really happens
so let me show you the reality because you'll be experiencing that a bit more too
they had this bigger before let me make it bigger
and blow this up so that you can see it that
that can you see it in the back there?
bigger better
and let me get the other one
it's not anyone
and they've already logged into a fish machine to get here
so this is a file then you see it's called some dot C
and I'll mention that all of these programs are available you can see the whole
well slash AFS is my own personal and all that first stuff is my own personal links
but once you get to the class webpage
or www/code/slash and then it's all given by which particular lecture it
I think these are linked on the home page too
and you can see various files there
that are used for the demonstration the C files are obviously the programs that we typed in
and then once it have an S at the end that's assembly code disassembly
one that end of d what's called
so anyways if I say GCC -O2 ,I'm sorry. -Og -S sum.c
that what I did was just tell the compiler to take the C code and turn it into assembly code
so when you invoke GCC you're actually invoking it's not just one program
but a whole sequence of programs
that do various stages of the compilation
and by giving it this -S which I'm saying stop
I'll just do the first part C to assembly code
and the -Og is a specification of what kind of optimization I want the compiler to do
so if you don't say anything
if you just again it will generate completely unoptimized code and it's actually very hard to read that code
it's very tedious the way it works if
you say -01
which is what you used to do to turn on the optimizer
it turns out that as GCC as they've gotten more advanced
it does a lot of up Touma's ations now
that for the purpose of this course make the code pretty hard to understand
so just with one of the most recent generations of GCC came out with this level called G for debugging
that's a nice for this course purpose of this course a nice level that
it sort of does the obvious kind of optimizations to make the code readable
without being sort of extravagant and trying to
rewrite your whole program in a way that would make it a lot different  and hopefully more efficient
so that's what we'll use in this course
it's only exists in the recent versions of GCC it's non-standard across other compilers
question
no it's an O capital o.it stands for optimized
so what that command just did was produce a file called sum.s
so let me show you
what sum.s is and let me show you the function some store
Can you see that then? okay
so this is the code it says some store
and then you'll see you'll recognize those instructions I mentioned before
the push,the move, the call, the move, the pop and the ret
but you also see other junk there
that that we edited out for the presentation and even in the book it got edited out
and the reason is these are various directives that aren't really directly part of the code itself
the fact they start with a period is an indication that
these aren't actually instructions they're something else
and they all are related to what the information that needs to be fed
to a debugger for it to be able to locate various parts of the program
and some information for the linker to tell it that this is a globally defined function
and various other things that you don't really need to at least think about initially
so we sort of take those out of the program just to make them more readable
but if you ever do this yourself you'll find this crud in there
and we don't want you to get like oh my gosh this wasn't in the book I don't know what to do with it
so let's go back
the other thing is people are learning on data lab is shark versus non shark it makes a difference
and even like this is a Mac computer and I can run got GCC installed
and it generates its Intel processor in there
but it's not directly compatible with Linux code so
it's pretty important for this course
we're saying just stick with the shark machines for everything you do
so what are some characteristics that have assembly code
especially how do they differ from C
well first of all there is a number of different sort of integer data types
of size 1 2 4 and 8 bytes
in integer data types they don't distinguish sign versus unsigned in how in how it gets stored
and even at an address or a pointer is just stored as a number in a computer
and doesn't have any special significance to it
a floating-point is handled in a very different way
on the other hand with a different set of registers
that I think Oh talked about very briefly in one of the later lectures
the program itself is in x86 it's just a series of bytes
and I'll show you some examples of those
and things like arrays and structs
and things that you think of as fundamental datatypes
don't exist at the machine level
they're sort of constructed artificially by the compiler
and later in the course in these lectures we'll cross over into how that's actually done as well
so some of the things you know about and see exist here
and some of them are sort of have to be built up in layers on top of the assembly level program
so the other thing about assembly level programming is
each instruction is very very limited in what it can do
it can move data from a register to memory, from...
or it can do an addition or a multiplication
or something like that but it can really basically only do one thing
and so you have to write a whole  if you were writing it by hand
you'd have to write a whole series of instructions to get anything done
and that's part of the reason why it's really much better to what the compiler do that
and we'll also see they're sort of how things like do loops,while loops ,conditionals,switch statements
those are all built up on top of some other on lower level features in the instructions
so for this function of some store actually it gets encoded by a total of fourteen bytes
and so one thing about x86 is some instructions are as short as one byte
but others can be as long as 15 bytes  thought in the encoding and
like I said each each instruction really typically only does one thing
so for example and see if you say *dest equals t
what that will typically and not always but this sort of way to
think about that at the machine level is its
t or some local value would be typically stored in a register
and as you know and see if you put star in front of it you want it referenced as a pointer
and if that reference is on the left
you want to store a number of value at that place where you're pointing to
so what would typically happen is
dest the the actual pointer value would also be stored in a register here it's in register rbx
and I use a move instruction to say take the value from one register which is called rax here
and store it in the memory location
that's specified by another register
so you see the idea we'll go into more detail about
all these register names and what the parentheses mean
but you get the rough idea that a move instruction is saying
can refer to either a register or a memory location
um and the actual object code representation of this is just a three bytes
where the first byte tells it that it
and we would even talk much in this course about
how the instructions are encoded won't generally let programs do that for us
but in this case it only takes three bytes to write that particular instruction
so how can we know that kind of stuff how can we figure out that level of detail
well there's some really useful tools that let you examine machine code
even if you don't have a copy of the original C file or even the assembly code file ahead of time
and there's one called a disassembler
so an assembler goes from this text version of instructions to a byte level representation
and the disassembler just reverses that it says here is a series of bytes
and I the disassembler know that this particular byte sequence refers is a move instruction
and so it will now print out on the screen to say oh that was a move instruction
and so it basically reverse engineers from the object code back to the assembly code
or something sort of like the assembly code
you'll see it lost ,what it's very slightly different
one thing also to notice I should mention about assembly code is
all those you know all the names I used
all the names of variables are completely lost at the assembly code level,at the machine code level
things are just during registers they're somewhere in memory
the program has no understanding of your original source code at that level
and so the disassembled is just a way to go backward
and you can do that yourself
and you'll find that useful in various contexts and to do that yourself
thanks kind of monkeying around me
so if I compile the sum program
so if I do the more standard thing you doing
using  a compiler you say run the compiler give it some optimization
tell it what the source files are until it where to put the final executable code
and I'm terribly clever I call the function sum
and so sum is a binary file
of 8663 bytes, you see off on the left its mark is executable
and it actually works
I can add numbers together with it
so that's the year two standard executable program
excuse me
and if I run a program called object dump
and ask it to disassemble it can do various things
it will spit out a disassembled version of the program it will fly by on the screen
but if I redirect that to some a file
which I already did I'll remove the old one
and now I look at that
you'll see that it has what I described as is the disassembled representation of the program
including some files that you didn't some functions that you didn't write
has ones that are sort of the low-level functions that are used in the initial startup of a program called in it
but here somewhere in the middle of it  you'll see go and behold is
that program,that function some store that got compiled
and you can see that what it did was it took this 14 bytes from the original that the object code
and it picked those apart and came back with what instructions those bytes in code
so for example the push instruction only takes a single byte
the move as you saw before takes three bytes
this call because it has to give the location of where to call is a five byte instruction and so forth
but again the disassembler didn't have access to the source code
it didn't have access even to the assembly code
it figured this out just by the bytes in the actual object code file
so this is the way if you ever want to know actually the byte level encoding
this is how you figure it out
is to run a program  run it through an assembler get object code  and then come back out with
it there's another way you can do it
using the debugging program which
you'll get to know very well in the next web you're going to do
and it's called gdb
and gdb is a very powerful debugging program that
you can examine step through and operate on programs in
and again you can if you,if the source code for it's available it will make use of it
but it also can be used on programs for which there's no source available
but one of the features is the ability to disassemble functions in there
so if I say disassemble sumstore
it'll come back with something that looks a lot like what you saw from the from object dump
a listing of the instructions and here it just shows in hex
what the addresses of those different instructions are it doesn't show the byte level encoding
so there's my point here is there's various tools
that let you look at a program
even if it's actual representation is a binary file that you don't want to examine directly
I just put this in
so what this slide shows is what I just showed you on the screen
which is what the object dump program produces for this function
and this is a version showing what gdb would show you for it
and with gdb if you want to actually get the bytes out
you can do that you can basically for any address
you can just give an address and tell it to display some number of bytes
and so this rather cryptic command to gdb says examine 14 bytes in hex format
starting at the address of the function sumstore
and it produced something that looks like what you see on the left
in fact disassembly is a tool that can be used as part of any reverse engineering tools
and I used to demo this by showing a disassembly of the windows of Microsoft Word
I had a PC back then not a Mac
but um some people and you know our slides are online
and so we got some nasty grams from people saying
you know you're violating the Microsoft end-user license agreement when you do that
because you're supposed to you don't know this
but remember all those click through I agree things
but you never read
one of them is very not to try to reverse engineer any Microsoft product so
so this is would technically so I've served just for modesty I blanked this out
but you can actually do it
if you can find where the file is it's sort of
obscure where the actual executable files of an application are
my point is that word like any other
application you run is just a executable file
and that executable file is just a bunch of bytes that encode instructions
okay so let's go a little bit further into this assembly level programming business
so I keep talking about registers
and x86-64 has this totally quirky set of registers
and it's a reflection again of this sort of evolutionary history to it
but you'll see that there's sixteen registers that
you can use to hold integers and pointers
and some of them have these sort of alphabetic names and some of them have numeric names
I'll show you why in a minute
and also for each register if you use the sort of %r name of it
you'll get 64 bits
but if you use the %e version of it.you'll get 32 bits
and what you'll find in programs that manipulate long int.you'll see the use of R
and if they're just in 32-bit things you'll see code saying %e
so you'll see both of these show up
but and it's fairly important to remember
that the %e version is just the low-order 32 bits of a larger %r entity
and in fact it goes beyond that you can also reference the lower order 16 bits
and the low order 2 bit,I'm sorry, 1 byte
16 one 2 bytes and 1 byte within each of these registers as well
but again think of these as like named
locations where you can store values and you can retrieve values from them
and you have to you the I'm I'm sort of personifying machine level programming here not
you personally will actually have to explicitly name those registers for the most part
to say where things should go where they should come out of
it's not like a memory where you just give a number to tell where to look for
you could compute a number there actually each one is identified separately
so just as a little bit of history with IA32  so back
we just talked about other being 8 registers all the %e versions
and one of the changes that went from IA32 to x86-64 was to double the number of registers
and by the way this is a really helpful thing because
it was very frustrating how few registers there were in the old IA32 machines
and then the as I mentioned
you could actually in the old machine refer to the Lord or 16 bytes of these registers
and that was a legacy from the 8086 days
and within the first four you could even refer to the individual to Lord or bytes in those
so nowadays you can actually get to the low order byte of all of them
and we just sort of got that's covered in the book actually
we don't talk about how you can get to these bytes because  that's really a legacy from back
before the 8086 was one called the 8080 which was a an 8 byte machine
so anyways you can see then how you got from this kind of weird state of affairs to the even weirder state
that we are in today
where some of them have names and some of them have numbers
and those names by the way had a reason back in ancient days
they had very specific purposes and so they were given names that sort of reflected those purposes
but that that all went away years and years ago
and so now these names are just legacy names have nothing to do with their purpose
now I should mention these only there are some special there's one special register nowadays
as shown in pink here and that's called the stack pointer
and that register you don't just use any old way you please it has a very specific purpose
and all the other registers there's some that are slightly different than the other
but for the most part they're all usable for holding program data
back in the IA32 days there was a register called the base pointer
that also got used for procedures
but that no longer gets used anymore either at least not usually
so anyways I didn't want to I don't want to spend a lot of time on historic legacy stuff
and have you memorized you know what feature was added and what model of processor
but just in case you're wondering why there's these weird names for these things
just so you appreciate the fact that this is a legacy thing
okay so now we can think of it then that there's eight registers with names
and there's eight registers that are indicated by some number
and let's look at some of the instructions that operate on those registers
and there's sort of three different some move
the move instruction in x86 is actually can do a lot of things
oh because it can take different types of information or what they call operands
so the source is some where you're you're copying from the source to the destination
the source can be some what's called a mediate.
it's actually a number that's baked into the program.
that you want to copy into some other location
a register we've talked about is one a specially named memory of locations
and memory is the array of bytes that you typically you have to specify what's the address
that you're either reading from if if it's the source are you writing to if it's the destination
and so the move instruction gives you all these possibilities
an immediate value can be written to a register or directly to memory
a register value can be copied to another register or written to memory
or you can take a value from memory read it from memory and copy it to a register
so if you think of wait shouldn't there be nine different combinations here well
no
because it doesn't make sense to have an immediate value as a destination right it's a constant
and also just for sort of the sake of convenience for the hardware designers
it doesn't let you directly copy from one memory location to another
what you have to do is use two instructions
one to copy from memory to read it from memory copy it to a register
in a second to take that value in the register and write it to memory
so that's why there's this only five possibilities
and so each of these actual five combinations  you'll see in some form or another
so for example if I take a constant value and copy it to a register
it's a little like you can think of register as a sort of the temporary data that
you're operating on right now
so it's a way of sort of of assigning a constant value to a temporary
similarly if you're have a memory as your destination
it's like storing a constant value  in memory somewhere
if you're copying from one register to another
it's sort of like copying one temporary value to another one  register to memory
it's as if you it's sort of like storing to an address
so a pointer dereference where the pointer is on the left side the dereference
and memory to register is the opposite
it's your you're reading from some location into a temporary position
so these you see all five versions get used in some form or another
so now let's talk about how we write these up pointers
how we specify either a source or a destination for a memory reference
and you already saw one version of this in fact in some of the code
when you put the name of a register in parentheses
that's just saying use this register whatever is in that that's an address
and use that address to reference some memory location
and so you'll see something like this is equivalent of dereferencing a pointer
and putting it in a temporary
you're also allowed to do a little bit of arithmetic
to derive an address from some collection of registers and other constant values
so if you see a number it's called the displacement D
in front of this parenthesis it means to offset not use the address that's in the register
but add or subtract some number from it
to get an address that's just slightly off of it by some fixed amount
and that we'll see is fairly useful for accessing different data structures
so here's an example of a very simple function that
we can understand everything about it already
because we know what the move instruction does
and that's the sort of classic swapping of two values that are stored in memory
so my point my arguments are two pointers called xp and yp
and I'm going to dereference those pointers I'm going to read from memory into registers
and then I'm going to copy back to to memory
but reversing the the two destinations
and so as you can imagine it it lines up to be for move instructions
that correspond to these four references
and the final one ret just won't learn more about functions  and how they're called
but just think of the read is it gets you it returns from wherever the calling position was
and so let's look at at more detail at the actual code then
and so it turns out with the 64,x86-64 the arguments always come in some specific registers
and the ones to remember for today is
rdi will be the first argument register and rsi will be the second argument register
there can be up to six of these and we'll go into more of that later
so those two registers represent the values of xp and yp
those are set before when this before the function is actually begins executing
that's set by the part of the code that calls this function
and those will be pointers so what they are is they contain addresses that specifying locations in memory
and then within the code the compiler just came up with its own ideas of
how to use different registers for temporary data buy whatever
what's known as the register allocation algorithm it uses
and we don't really care we just want to what we'll want to do is figure out what it's doing
and we'll see that a register is %rax is being used to hold the value t0 and %rax the value t1
now so let's get actually concrete here and this is very detailed
but I think it's important that you understand
sort of you can almost simulate the execution of some instructions by yourself
you're going to really have to know this stuff
so what each of these instructions is doing
and how it works and really have that wired into you pretty well
so let's make up an example let's imagine that the two addresses that are used for
these two pointers are in 0x120 & 100
by the way those would not be typical addresses
they're way too small a number but it's much easier to use them as an illustration
and let's suppose that one of them held the value 1 2 3 and the other 4 5 6
so the first instruction says use %rdi as an address
copy from that memory location and store the result in register rax
so %rdi is 120
I'll read from that address I'll read the value 1 2 3 and store it and register rax
these are all by the way 8 byte values
and I'm just sort of glossing over that part of it
but the Q refers to what in Intel terminology is a quad word
a word because it goes back to the 8086 is 16 bits 2 bytes
a long word is 32 bits and a quad word is 64 bits
that's just their terminology and we're stuck with it
ok so that one instruction had that effect
the second instruction does the same thing but using rsi which holds 1 0 0 as an address
and so it copies for 456 into rdx
and then the third instruction is writing back to memory
so its source is register rdx
the destination has the address of rdi which is 120
it's storing that back in memory
and finally the this fourth instruction does the other part of the right
so you see these four instructions to read from memory into registers
two of them wrote from registers back to memory and that's the whole function
and you can see it this move instruction is doing all the work here
so we've shown that example just showed this very simple memory referencing
that's designated by the parentheses
and as I mentioned you can do a version where you put a displacement there too
and in fact there's a much more elaborate form and
we'll see that this is useful for implementing array references
where there can be actually two registers involved
and there can be a displacement which is a constant offset
and a scale factor which will be 1,2,4,8
and the general idea  of it is to take our register
that I'm referring to as R sub I that's known as an index register
you multiply it by the scale factor
I'll you add the value of Rb register Rb
and you also add the constant displacement
and these have a Rb refers to base our eyes index and S is scale
and it turns out this will be the sort of natural way to implement array referencing
it will make a lot more sense when we talk about arrays
but basically you can think of is if this is an array index
I have to typically scale it by however many bytes my data type is
so if it's an int I have to scale it by four if it's a long I have to scale it by eight
so that's where these scale factors will come in
and basically the the format in the assembly code
lets you eliminate some of these fields if they're not being used
so you'll and we already saw the single parenthesis a sort of a reduced version of this form
so let's just do some examples of these address computations
and let's imagine that register rdx hold text f with three zeros
and rcx holds a one with two zeros
so if I rather than doing one at a time
you can see each of these I'm taking RDX which is 0xf000 + 0x8
and so that's 0xf008
here I'm adding together registers %rdx and %rcx
and that gives me 0xf100
I'm doing the same here except that I'm scaling %rcx by 4
so 4*0x100 is 0x400 and I'm adding that to f
and here I'm taking %rdx which is 0xf000
if I double that I get 0x1e000
if you think about shifting an F to the left 1 you get a 1
and then it goes 1 1 1 0 and
and that's an e
ok and then I'm adding this displacement of 80 to it
so the point of this is all of this is arithmetic it's all using whatever is in the register
and there's some rules for how you combine this and get an address
and then that's being used to either read or write some memory location
okay so now what is a final part of that today
I'll go through some arithmetic
and one of the things that will be sure to confuse you and drive you crazy and
make you be sending email to the staff  for explanation
is an instruction called load effective address
and the reason is its purpose in life is to do
basically the ampersand operation of C to compute an address
based on some whatever you want to compute an address from
but it also turns out to be a pretty handy way to do arithmetic and the C compiler likes to use it
so in particular it looks the the format of it looks like a move instruction there's a source and a destination
but the destination has to be a register
and the source will be one of these memory references
so it looks like a move instruction
it looks like you're doing some address computation
then you're reading from memory and storing it to a register
but what it actually does is it does that address computation
and then it actually writes that address not the memory value
but the value of got that got computed directly to the register
which is what you want to do here remember the ampersand operation is
give me the address of some place give me a pointer
that designates some location
so for example this is fairly typical in C code if you say multiply X by 12
it will turn it into a address computation
and this is just a clever way to compute three times %rdi
it adds are %rdi + 2*%rdi
so that's three times %rdi and stores it in %rax
and then salq means shift left by two
and so you remember shifting left by two is like multiplying by four
so the first value computed 3*x. I shift that left four by two positions and I have 12*x
so that's a very special the lea but you'll see it all over the place so you need to be ready for it
these other ones look more like what you'd expect for arithmetic instructions
they have names like add and subtract and multiply and so forth
and they all have the same general format that they have two arguments
and what's called the destination is actually also a source
it's a little like in C if you say X plus equals Y
it's saying take the value of x add the value of Y and then store the result in X
and now the destination is like that
the other thing that's weird is that the operands are in the inverse order from where you'd expect them to be
so the source comes first in the destination comes last and that's important to remember
and other thing you'll see that there's nothing special here whether it's a
except that this is a arithmetic shift and this is a logical shift
of whether it's a signed or unsigned value
because you remember the bit level behavior of these two instructions is the same
and then there's a series of instructions that are used
that are just take one operand increment decrement a negate and not
not is not is like the tilde operation and see not the exclamation mark
so those are the basic instructions
and again now we can actually look at some programs and understand them
and here's one that just does a bunch of junk of arithmetic instructions
and it converts into the following assembly code
and you see it's using this lea instruction multiple times to do addition in various forms
and it also has shifting  and it has multiplication
you saw in the original code I just have addition and multiplication
here I have various instructions I only have one multiply here whereas I had two there
so the compiler is sort of scrambling things around trying to find clever ways to implement
what you're asking for using less complex expensive less time-consuming instructions
and if you sort of go through this code carefully what you'll find is
that this instruction here corresponds to this computation of t1
it's adding two values and giving it a new name it's putting in %rax
similarly this one is adding Z to t1 and storing it back in %rax
the x+4 doesn't show up directly here
it turns out what it does is it jumps right at head to here
and multiply Y by 48
it does it by first computing 3y like we saw
and computing shifting that left by 4
because 3 *16=48
and then the 4 here that sin x plus 4 actually shows up here
it just uses the displacement field of this computation to add 4 to some other values
and so this is label then these comments show
how these correspond to the program and these registers show it
so the important thing to get from here
you will want to actually go back through this and make sure you believe
that the comments are correct
but it's very important for you to figure out this lea instruction
otherwise you're just going to be hopelessly confused
and it's also important to understand that the the code
that gets generated will correctly implement your function
but it might not exactly replicate at a low level the the exact sequence of operations
you specified at a high level
so that will just to summarize then you've already gotten a glimpse then of what this very odd a world of machine programming is
and how different it is from C code already
it's all so you've already seen that x86 is weird like I said it's English
it's not a Latin it's not well designed and but you just got to deal with that
so that's your beginning to machine level programming.thanks a lot.