okay so continuing on with the saga of machine level programming
when number four of our series of this
and I think that the total will be five
so we're almost through and I've always it this is a lot of material for the course
it's essentially a third of the course
if you think about well no not that much but it's a lot of the course
and a part that we consider very central to it
so a lot of this involves since we're talking about a particular machine the Intel x86-64 machines
a lot of its kind of low-level nitty-gritty stuff
but part of what we hope you also are understanding some of the general principles involved too
and you'll find if you move from this machine to another machine
sort of learning your first assembly language is your hardest one learning successive ones a lot easier
so today we're going to talk about data representations
so far all the programs we've looked at
have been either just manipulating integers or long integers and pointers
so that's all what we'd call scaler data.data that's not in any aggregated form.
today we'll look at places where data gets collected into you put together multiple data elements
and then see there's really two ways to do that
one is with arrays where you can create many copies
or many copies of an identical data type you can have an array of intz and array of pointers
a second is where you have Struck's
so you create a small collection of values that can be of different data types
and each one you access by its name or a tag
and it turns out those definitions can be recursive
so you can have arrays of structs and structs with arrays and nest it to an arbitrary degree
and what we'll see is both how it's represented in the machine memory
and also then what the code looks like that will manipulate these different data structures
and the main thing to see is
that there's no the at the machine code level
there is no notion of an array
that you'd have at a high level except to think of it as a collection of bytes
that you can are in contiguous part of storage
and same with a struct is just allocated as a collection of bytes
and it's the job of the C compiler then to generate the appropriate code to allocate that memory
to get the right value when you refer to some element of a struct or an array
but the good news is this is such a commonplace type of requirement for a programming language
that the Machine gives you sort of instructions that
you'll see now they make perfect sense.they're exactly designed for this particular class of applications
so we'll talk about structure...array first and then structures or struck
and I'll also mention we'll do a little bit I'll give you a glimpse of floating point today too
because it's worth knowing how floating point arithmetic is implemented as well on a machine
so the basic idea of array allocation is fairly straightforward
if you have n an array with n elements
then that's represented by enough bytes in memory all in one span to hold that much data
so if the underlying data types a it's an int  or a care is a single byte data type
so to have a array of 12 cares takes 12 bytes
and int takes four bytes so to have an array of five ints takes 20 bytes
you get the idea you just multiply the size of the underlying data type by the number of elements
and that's how big the array has to be in terms of bytes
and we've already seen that in the care is one byte
and it is for a double or a long would be eight bytes
and so would be a pointer those are all different amounts of storage
and you see in this diagram we use the X
denotes the starting address of the beginning of this region of memory
and so we can use address computation to compute offsets by adding numbers to X
to get the address of particular elements of this array
and that's exactly what the code does
oh so in general then if you imagine array A has some underlying type T
what the elements of the array are and
some number of elements in that array in the declaration L
then we will that declaration actually does two things
one is it allocates enough bytes of storage to hold the entire array
and the second from a programming language perspective
it is the identifier of the array A can in some ways be treated like a pointer
that you can do pointer arithmetic off of it
and that's one of the features of C that is was a fairly unique to see
when it was created and is still unique to this day
this idea of the sort of interchangeability of pointers and arrays  array identifiers
so for example I can use an array notation to say val[4] is element four of this array
and it's a five element array so that would just be this final element
but I can also just refer to val
and its underlying data type is as an int *, it's a pointer to int
and its value would be X it's just a pointer a pointer is remember an address
and it's just the address at the beginning of the array
and I can do pointer arithmetic on val
which as you know in in C and this is a little confusing we'll have to we'll go back and forth
because in C when you do pointer arithmetic
like you say you know p++ for a pointer
we just give you an example
so if you had something like care * P  as a declaration
and you said P is equal to some string s
and then you say p++
so you're incrementing that pointer 1 in this case you're incrementing it by 1
because the underlying data type is a care
but if you said something like int *
I'll call it IP and I different pen
and I said you know ip++
then ip would get ip+. what does anyone know?
4! yes!
so it's a confusion in see this remember is the same as saying IP plus equals one
but what you're actually doing is incrementing that the number of the value of P by four
because you want a pointer when you jump from one place to another
you want it to increment by enough bytes to point to the next integer in this case  for IP
and so similarly val+1
denotes this value x+4
because it's a the address of the next integer in the array
by the way the one thing different between an array and a pointer is I can't say val++ right
I can't change the value of val.it's fixed
by the Declaration whereas a pointer I can increment it I can change it in various ways
and similarly ampersand val of 2
says give me the address of the second element of the array so that would be at x+8
and this is again one of the fundamental properties of see
that basically in NC if you take a pointer
that's weird
this is an eye not very well written
these are equivalent statements
right there just two notations for the same thing
so on the upper part it says IP plus two meaning
actually add 8 to ip
and then dereference that
it's the same as finding the second element of a array an imaginary array
where IP is indicates the beginning of the array
so that's a very fundamental principle of see that
again this whole idea of pointer arithmetic is fairly unique to see
question
[student question]
pardon?yes!
the compiler will happily let you use negative values for array indices
and it will give you a potentially undefined value
but there's nothing in C that prevents you from giving out of bounds either
numbers that are too big for an array or too small for an array
there's no bounds checking it
yes if we have to
yes so the question is becoming what about negative indices
and the answer is very simple
because in other words in general something like IP plus X
maybe can you see this
should I turn it kind of bright
is really equivalent to IP plus 4x
so this is the notation
and it's really hard to read isn't it
and the right-hand side is the computation
so you and see you write it using you don't have to give scaling factors for your data types
otherwise would drive you out of your mind
but you secretly underneath when the compiler generates the code we'll see examples of this
it's scaling everything
so now the question that is being asked is what if X is a negative number
well the rule still applies
it's just that the final result will be less than IP instead of greater than IP
but it's totally valid see
and there's actually times you will use it in this term I can promise you
yes question
how did you
No! you can't write 2 plus IP
try it I'm pretty sure you can't do that and with pointer arithmetic
try if somebody wants to type in some code and do it.I don't think you can do that.
but if you did it would have to figure it out that
you know the parser knows the data types of it's two arguments
so yeah you could probably do it I've never seen this
you could do it but the compiler would know that one of the arguments is a pointer and
therefore scale the other what you can't do is add two pointers
you can take the difference of two pointers
this is obscure I'm not even taking about this
woke it up in knr but you can do arithmetic
but you can only for addition it can only be one pointer in one and then the other has to be a regular integer value
and it will scale it appropriately
so I believe you can do it
it's just somebody will smack you on the back of the hand if you actually write coded up
but not the compiler
so in particular you know you can...
if you go beyond the bounds of an array of this you'll get whatever is beyond the bounds of that array
and it might be an invalid or it might not even be a valid address
and you get a segmentation fault but more typically you'll get some whatever it happens to be there
and that's not so bad when you read it but you can also potentially write it as we saw before
and corrupt data that's already in memory
so here's again the same statement I was making before that
IP val + i just get scaled the value computed would be the starting address plus four times whatever i is
so let's look at...
so that's sort of that's all see everything I said before is just basic C of stuff
now let's start looking at the actual machine code involved
and so I made up this example here
where I declare a three arrays each with five ends
and I go through what is considered sort of good form
when you're building up data that instead of having arbitrary constants sprinkled
through your program often called magic numbers
that you instead use a pound define and you give it some meaningful name and some documentation
usually at the top of a file or a dot H file
and then the type def is a very handy way if you're going to create complex data structures
I highly recommend you sort of break that into type deaths
because the declaration notation in C gets fairly obscure fairly quickly
but all this is saying is the the data type I'm going to call a zip_dig
is defined to be five an array of five int
and now whenever I say zip_dig something
I'm just popping down I'm saying this is an array of five events
and so I created three of them with the appropriate support us Kools represented here
and now I'm just making up for sake of presentation  actual addresses for these
in general you don't have any control over that
and I made it up so that they all happen to be in contiguous part of memory
and again there's no fundamental reason that should be true
so you can never trust what particular I dress anything is ever going to be allocated at
but you are certain that each of these blocks will be a contiguous collection of 20 bytes
so here's some example code then to say
I want to retrieve for one of these arrays I want to retrieve a element whose index is digit
and this gets turned into the following code
so remember the first argument which will be a pointer now
will be passed in register %rdi
and the second will it will be an INT will be passed in register %rsi
and what I want to get out of this is an int
and so you see that it here's where that scaled addressing
this is exactly what it was designed for and why
why they went to the trouble of adding this sort of fancy address modes to x86
because this is such a common thing
so remember what this says is take %rdi
and add to it what you get by multiplying %rsi by four so you scale that
and of course that's exactly the computation we want to do
if we compare it to you know this is what we're trying to get computed
it's exactly this computation here
and that gives us an address and then we're reading from that address
and we're going to copy it in %eax
remember this is an int so it will be in the erosion the lower four bytes of register %rax
and that's all the code it takes to implement this particular operation
yes
so %rdi is the base address of the array yeah ah si on the right side yeah
this is a typo thank you thanks for pointing it out I'll make a note of that
right so this slide is incorrect and I'll fix that
so this should be %rdi+%rsi right thanks for
noting that let me make it
okay
and so now let's just look at a another just some code
in particular what if I wanted to go through one of these arrays
and for every element of the array add one to it so increment every single element by one
well first of all you can see that we're setting up a loop
and it uses the jump to middle of business with where  the initial part is to jump to the test
and all the testing involves we're increment we're using our a X's 4i here
and we're incrementing it and comparing it at various places
but um here's the line of code that does all the real work
again it's taking up the ithe element which is in our a X scale 8x4
adding it to the base of the array and that gives us an address
and now remember you can have an arithmetic instruction
where the second operand the destination is a memory reference
and what this actually requires is to first read  the original value from the memory
do the addition and then store the result back in memory
so this one instruction is exactly Inc doing this plus plus operation on this stored data in the array
by the way I should mention the whole idea pointer arithmetic  and and C
C was really people who had programmed an assembly code for most of their lives
thinking about how could I make this look like a high-level language
but keep all the flexibility all the tricks I learned to play  at assembly code in a programming language
because it was designed it was originally designed to implement an operating system
the UNIX operating system
and historically operating systems were written directly in assembly code
and these people Kernighan Ritchie Dennis Ritchie
and realized that the way to do this is to sort of build point arithmetic into a programming language
so anyways the reason I'm saying this is
you see a pretty close correspondence here between instructions and machine code
and constructs in a program in the C programming language
and that whole ++ operator and += is sort of something you see a variations of in suggests and way code
okay so that's a sort of single dimension array
and I'd like to just change things up a little bit  by having us look at
what the real difference is between a arrays and pointers in a programming language in C
and so I have a couple of these examples
that I'll bring out one by one
but the idea of this is you see the declaration on the Left
there's something called a1 and something called a2
so call those a sub N
and now what I want to know for each of these
is doesn't compile is this a valid statement in C
second with this potentially give me a null pointer reference because i'm referencing a pointer
for which the I haven't actually allocated space for them that pointer is indicating
I haven't initialized the pointer to a valid memory reference
and then finally if I were to use the sizeof operator on that particular  value with that
and including for the case where there's a star in front of it
and part of this is to understand the difference then between an array and a pointer
and the main reason this the main factor is an array
when you declare an array in C you're both you're actually allocating space
space is being allocated somewhere for it
and you're creating a using allowed to now use the array name of in pointer arithmetic
whereas when you just declare it a ret a pointer
all you're allocating is the space for the pointer itself
and not for anything that it's you're pointing to
so
just to you probably figured out that these both compile
let me get my cheat sheet Andy
well but what would be the size of a1 here
if I ran the size of operator on
let's do the easier one what's the size of a2
hmm 8
because it's a pointer
what's the size of a1? a1 is an array of 3 ints
12 right
oh and those those aren't no oops
and now if I said * a1 or * a2
those would both compile
could either of them possibly give you a null dereference
[student speak]
yeah oh yes the pointer itself is no but that the
I haven't dereferenced it yet it's a null pointer
but I haven't...it's not a bad potentially bad reference
right it's not a runtime I won't create a runtime error
if I just say a to in my code okay
so you're a step ahead of me basically
so in it you kind of answered the second question though
this one could give you a null pointer error
if you try to dereference a pointer that hasn't been initialized
it doesn't point to anything
whereas this one is fine
and now what's the size of a1 of of * a1
4 and what about * a2
4 yeah
because they're both pointers to ends
so one way to think about that is as a picture
a1  is like we've been showing here
it's an array of for ints
and when I declare a1 I'm allocating all so the program is allocating
12 bytes of storage that's able to hold that
a2 on the other hand is just a pointer
which I'll show there
until it's 8 bytes long
but it doesn't point to anything
so that's what I meant that if you tried to say * a2
you'd potentially have a null pointer reference dereference out there
and so that's why this is 8 and this is 12
so those who are the warm-up 1 so let's make it a little more interesting
these aren't in the slides you'll notice but I'm going to I'll update the slides to include these later
I'll but I think the point that if you find this confusing
it's a sign that you really really really need to understand
what a pointer is and what an array is
and how they're the same and how they're different
because it's a core part of programming in C that will lead to endless hours of confusion
if you don't really have this wired down pretty strongly
so let me just give you a preview of what's so interesting about this
is I'm going to give you some numbers
and then we're going to have to explain how those numbers come around
okay
so let's try and understand what's happening here
and you see that all of these declarations involve some combination of pointer and array
and the question is is it a pointer to an array is it an array of pointers
and the answer to those will depend on the particular syntax
so of course the first one is one you've already seen before
and so you know that compiles and it's not null and you can dereference it and it's not null
but if you tried to say **a1
that's not valid it won't even compile
because you're trying to here take the data type of *a is int
and then you're trying to take a dereference an int
so that will compile and therefore you can't even test it
okay the question is for these other three you can see that
somehow one is a well let's look at the bottom two first
so the one on the bottom says that
and this is part of and there's actually a really great section in Kernighan Ritchie that I highly encourage you
which is how to read pointers how to read declarations in C
and the basic rule is you start from the inside
and you work your way outward
so that declaration of of a3 says that
with that parentheses says a3 is a
what is a3
a3 is a pointer
that to parentheses around it
what does it point to
it points to an array of three-inch
so we can diagram a3 then
to be something like this
a3 is a pointer like I said read it from the inside out a3 is a pointer
and what does it point to it points to an array of three elements
and what type of elements are they there in
so you're sort of reading outward and picking up pizzas from the right and from the left as you do this
and so when you know that this all makes sense
that these numbers the size of a3 itself is eight
but since it points to an array of three ints the size of *a3 is twelve
and then a **a3 would indicate this particular element of the array
and so it sizes four
so these all compile but which of them could cause a null pointer dereferences  which of the less two
guess you can flip coins
yes
well I'm only looking at it I'm trying to fill in a3 right now
so a3 is fine
but if I said *a3 could that have a null pointer
problem yes
why because when I declare a3 here all I'm declaring is this particular
I'm only allocating enough storage for that pointer
I have an initial I I haven't allocated the space for an array I haven't initialized a3 to actually point to an array
so it could be a null pointer it could be arbitrary junk
but it the chances of it actually pointing to an array of three ends is highly unlikely
so this would be a potentially bad in there for double stars doubly bad right
okay so now let's look at a4
so a4 to understand that you actually have to look at the charts in C
the precedent chart
which if you're like me your book falls open to that
precedence chart the different operators and what levels they are
and one thing you'll see is that
a level one of precedence the highest precedence includes square brackets
and level2 include star
in other words bracket is higher precedence and star
so this particular statement here
the binding is actually like this
it says that a4 is an array of three elements
and those elements are pointers and they point to int
so a4 is an array
can you see this
but each of those elements is pointing to an int  somewhere  hopefully
and so let's see if that matches the numbers we got
so the size of a4 is 24 because it's 8 times 3
if I were to dereference a4
it would just indicate this particular pointer
right a4 is an array of pointers
so when I get an element out of that array what I'll get is a pointer
and so a4 is a pointer and so it's also 8
but if I now do a second dereference
then I'll get an int and it's size is 4
okay
these all compile
so could I have a it could start a for them cause problems
as far as a null pointer or bed pointer
no that's right
no is the correct answer no is yes
because you've a4 this you're a four is an array you've you've defined an array
and it arrays get allocated by their declaration
as a4m of three element array
on the other hand this could give you a null pointer
because I haven't initialized the array to anything
so for example if it were initialized all zeros it would just be three not null pointers in that array
so this is sort of the stuff the nitty gritties of C. question yes!
how does it know that the size 12 like I thought see they don't really know how many things are in an array
the compiler question is how the compiler
that what I'm...I'll answer your question by saying remember the compiler knows a lot
so that in particularly I've declared this to be an array of three pointers
I'm compiling for a machine where pointers are eight bytes
and so the compiler knows that SP 24 bytes
in general when you're referencing in C
there's no you know the machine doesn't have built into it any bounds
and doesn't do bounds checking for you
but that's in the runtime execution
if but in C if I...
when I declare something it's known it has to be known at that point when the declaration occurs
question
go back there
so instead of doing three I just need a one that just...empty bracket?
yeah I think empty bracket is it just another name for a pointer
usually it's just given as argument some restrictions on it
but when you use the empty bracket notation in C
it's equivalent to doing a pointer declaration you're not allocating any space for
it by saying one graphically necessary...
and you give a number the size of that array it really allocates that memories
question
yes oh yes and that's the final one
you'll notice that the numbers for a2 and a4 the same and the reason is it's the same thing
and that again goes by the precedence rules of C
that a2 first binds this way  and then this way
and so a 2 and a 4 are synonymous just with west parentheses
okay so that was a bit of an aside
but as you can see I think this is the kind of thing that will really probe your
your understanding
and now you know as a beginning C programmer
where you don't have a very good sense the underlying representation of a program
it's really hard to figure these things out but now that you know
what it means to compile code and you can actually look at compiled code
that will sort of clear up a lot of the what's really going on in a program
so let's now generalize from one dimension to two just to make life a little more interesting
and again that's an important principle to understand that
in a when you want to declare a multi-dimensional array and see
you do it by a sequence of brackets with the bounds for each one
and the reason for that is actually there
it will see that it has to do with
this notation that we just went through so if I say int
it turns out that I can read it like
this that A is an array of three elements
and each of those elements is in itself an array of five elements of type int
and we'll get back to that but that kind of explains everything I'm about to tell you  in this picture
so in particular if I declare an array with our rows and C columns
and you think of it mathematically as sort of a matrix two-dimensional matrix
what it really does is it says we'll see eyes on the
yeah I'm sorry
C a actually ends up being the inner element it says first ofC all I want
row 0 will be an array of C intz
C being the number of columns
I'll put so all the elements of row 0 will come first
all the elements of row 1 come next
and so forth up to the end
of it all and so the total allocation will be
4 times the data size times the number of rows times the number of columns bytes
but the reason why they're in that order
which is called row major order
because if we thought of it these terms we go through the first row and then the second row and the third row
is precisely because of this notation
let me write it down like this
int of a of well
let me just use the the one I said
we can write this out as a is a array
a free element
it's over half it's one two three I'll just put it over here
okay so a is a three element array and
and or generalizing to this picture a is an array of our elements
this is the first element this is the second element and this is the earth element
but what kind of elements are those
each is an array of five minutes
alright so within array a here each subpart of a then
is an array of C int
and so that's why logically the way these are organized
actually comes from this declaration notation directly
and what's the examples of that
so for example if I wanted to
extend my zip_dig idea and introduce an array of four of these
I could declare it this way and again with remember I used a type def to declare zip_dig
but if I were to expand this out
it was would be as if I was declaring this array PGH to be a four rows and five columns
but what it really is is array of four elements
one two three four each of which is an array of five ints
okay so think of that nesting
when you read declarations you start from the name of the element
and you work your way outward through these brackets and stars in some order
and so in particular if I want to reference a particular element of an array
uh the general rule is wrong here
oh uh the general rule is this one
if I want to reference literally oh I'm building up to it
uh so yes this shows that a[i]
I can actually just do the reference a[i]n't have to give a[i][j] in C
and what that denotes is one of these are rows of the array
and each of which is an array of C elements of type int
and so imagine that in general we have K bytes for data type T
the underlying data type in this case of T is an int and K equals four
but in general the starting address then of row I
would be gotten by multiplying the number of columns by K
and then multiplying that by the row number
and now if within the array I want to reference a ray element a sub IJ
then it comes out to this computation you take the starting address
you scale the row number by the number of columns
add to it which column you want
and then multiply that all by k
so the way to see that is here I can get to row number I
by just scaling a I by the number of columns times the size of the elements are four
and now I want to get to the Jeth element of this sub array here
and I can do that by scaling J by four
and adding it to the beginning of this sub array
and now I can just collect the force together
and that's what and pull it outside here that's what gives you this formula
so again the the point of this is that
this all kind of is a natural outcome of the declaration
and it's easy to think of it in terms of this storage model here
of how the actual array is allocated
okay now a different style of declaration
is imagine I create three of these arrays
and now I want to create an array
that contains that appoints to these
so this is a different data structure you'll observe from before
what Univ now is an array of three pointers
and each of those pointers points to a one of these arrays of five ends
and their underlying data type by the way of these elements are in stars right
and C does not differentiate
when you want to declare a ring like this you just say it's an int star
you don't say how many elements are the underlying array is
so you'll see by these picture that these are different data structures
so now let's go through the what the assembly code looks like to reference these two data structures
we didn't did we do the I'm sorry up I would have thought I'd have assembly code
Victor might be a missing slide you
so we'll see...so imagine I wanted to reference
I'm sorry I'm confused why there is no
ah the shipping I'm sorry this is uh I'm pausing here because I think
I meant to have a slide that would show
what the code looks like and I don't
okay well we're going to have to wing  it
so if you wanted to in assembly code then reference an element of an array
like this a multi-dimensional array
what you'll see is that the code kind of builds up  a computation like this
and typically in the compiled code
the value of K is a kind of a constant value
and if it's a array that's been declared with a constant bounds
then the value of C will also be a constant
and so a piece of code for this and that's why it got omitted by accident
will basically take this value and use some combination of the memory referencing
and shifting and lea instructions and so forth
to implement this computation and then do a dereference
so let's look at this second example and
there is code for this and it's actually a little bit more complex
because this is going through two levels of indirection
so you'll see that to get the digit
a a particular digit from a particular one of these of universities then
it has to first of all figure out i
do this dereference is get the a pointer to the beginning of the array
and that's what this reference is doing here
oh okay but first of all what it's doing is shifting %rsi
I left by two which is equivalent to scaling the the digit by four
because it's getting ready to take that digit of parameter and scale it appropriately
and then it takes that number and it adds to it
the value I get by reading from there the array univ
but using a the index scaling it by eight  to actually do a memory reference
so remember this instruction then
and it looks a little weird is actually doing a memory reference here
of this three element array of called univ
so it's reading from memory and doing an array index directly here by scaling
and now getting from that a pointer
adding to that the the scaled value of of the digit
and so that gives me a pointer now as this notation shows
to to the particular element i want and now it does a dereference
so that's a pretty tough example to get as you're one of your first array ones
and as I said I apologize for missing the  reference to a particular element of this array
is done entirely by computing scaling indices in appropriate ways
you want to take the array and scale the first index by 20
because each row is 20 elements it's 5 times 4
and you want to scale the digit by 4 to select the particular element within that array
and so you all this address computation takes place and then there's a single memory reference
whereas in this data structure you have to go through to memory references
first of all to you have to index and get the appropriate element here
but that's just a pointer
now and then we add an offset to that pointer to get the appropriate element in this array here  and then we read from that
so that's what this notation means is that I'm doing two memory references here  and just one there
and it's a little bit curious because if you look at the C code  it looks the same
but the underlying data types are different and so the references are different
okay so let's look at some other variations on this code
and these are all will sort of fall out from these general principles I've described
so first of all let's introduce an array a two by two
I'm sorry sixteen by sixteen array of intz
and it used to be and see if you wanted to do multi-dimensional arrays
where the size of the array was not fixed at compile time
you basically had to implement your own version of that computation
I showed before of scaling the the row number by the number of columns  and adding to it J
so this is sort of classic C I've written it as a macro here but you can see it
it's just doing the row major scaling directly here is address arithmetic
now since a more recent generation of the C compiler
what they call c99 it was introduced in 1999
um you can actually pass as a parameter an array
where the number of elements in the array  is also a parameter
that's being passed to the the function
and similarly you can declare an array to be of n elements
as long as n has been computed before it hit set array declaration
and the compiler will do the right thing it will allocate the proper number of elements
um so let's just look at some of this code examples
and again what we'll see here and
this will show you an example of the tutor the the kind of address computation that takes place with a two-dimensional array
in this case I know C is 16 and K is 4
so if I want to get element I sub j IJ out of this array
then first of all scale I by 64
because that's and I'll add that to the base
and then I'll scale our DX by 4 that's J and and add it to this array
and so and then do a memory reference there
so in the end I'm doing you see these two instructions have done the appropriate
the three instructions have done the appropriate scaling of I and J
added them to the beginning address of a and done the computation
on the other hand if it's a
1 the third example I showed where N is a parameter
that's passed to the function so it's not known at compile time
how big a scaling factor to use
you'll see that it has to use a multiply instruction to do that
which is a relatively expensive instruction in terms of performance
well and then once it has that that's just n times I
and then it uses various combinations of LeA's
and the scaling notation from before
to compute an appropriate offset into the array to do the reference
so here I could do it with a shift
I'll and here I had to introduce a multiply because I don't know in advance how big it is
if you want to torture yourself
here's an example I was going to go over of triply nested possibilities and dereferencing of the same idea
but let's move on to pointers oh it just drugs
so the idea of a struct is actually quite simple
oh well the base idea is simple and it gets more complicated
oh the idea of it is I want to I declare a struct to have some number of fields
each of which can be an int or it could be in this case a pointer  or it could be an array itself
but the rule is basically what I'll do is allocate enough space
if I introduce one of these trucks for all the different array elements fields and that our struct
and then I'll basically keep track the compiler will keep track of where each of these fields starts
and generate the appropriate code to offset from the beginning
so the structure itself the reference to it will be the beginning address of the struct
and then I'll use appropriate offsets to get to the different fields
so here's an example of some code
imagine I have a struct a pointer to one of these structures
and I have an index and what I want to do is get to the that
appropriate part of array a  within this struct
well array a is right at the beginning of the structure
so I can treat this just like I would any array reference
of scaling ID X by 4 and adding it to the base  to get the appropriate element
so I don't really have to do anything special for this one
let's look at some other code that you'll typically see  actually this example is pretty involved
so I'm actually doing a whole bunch of stuff here with this one struct
first of all I'm trying to retrieve element I from the structure
then I'm using that to index into array a
and and insert a value into there
and then I'm updating this pointer to point to the next
I'm I'm I'm if this were a link twist what I want to do is step to the next over the list
so I need to retrieve the next field from here
and so these in so I'm actually making three references to this structure
in this one rather small function so let's try and figure it all out
so first of all I have to retrieve element I from it
and here you see that we know that element I is it offset 16
and so if and here's where you see that displacement field being used in the memory reference
exactly for this purpose I want to take R but add 16 to it to get a memory address
that I can use for for I
and you see it actually uses move
because i itself is an INT
but I'm going to use it as an array index
in which case I have to scale it
I have to do a just arithmetic using 8 byte quantities
so this actually retrieves the four byte value and does a sign extension on it
and now what I want to do is store at a val at a element i
and so here you'll see that it's using %rax is the value of just computed for  I scaling by 4
and using the starting address of the R which happens to be the starting address of a as well  and doing a store
so that's sort of an array operation there
and then the next part is I'm going to offset 24  which is the position of next
read from that location and store that in %rdi which is a R
so this is the operation argit's our arrow next
and then the loop is I'm testing until R is null so that's going on here
so you see that those three references to the struct were implemented using three instructions here
so it's a very direct mapping between the the code here and the x86 instructions
and part of the x86 instructions because this kind of stuff is so commonplace in programs
they kind of made the instructions map very directly toward these operations
and now you should probably see why all the bells and whistles are there for these address references
question
what if I was three
I'm sorry
Oh a had a eyes three elements
yes it will access...
make sure I think that's a typo hey is supposed to be for
its it with
them so if I is for it would access itself yeah  and it would mess things up
question this is a typo by the way it should be air for
yes a null pointer I
know is a zero
um so that's sort of the easy version of structs now let's make them a little harder
one is for reasons that are a bit obscure
the machine generally prefers that if you have a data type and underlying data type of K bytes
that the address that that starts at be a multiple of K
and so that introduces a property we call alignment
which well actually when a structure gets allocated
well the the compiler will actually insert some blank unused bytes in the data structure
in its allocation just so that it can maintain this alignment
so for example here I is a as an int
and I want its address to be a multiple of four
I'll give you a minute why that's true
I just so trust me for a minute
and so it will actually had three unused bytes here
because the first byte is being used by C
and in general we'll see in the allocation we're going to make sure that
the pointer to this data structure is itself a multiple of eight
and the reason for that is because there's a double here
and it should reside on a boundary that its starting address should be a multiple of eight
and you'll see as long as this is eight a multiple of 8
and this offset here is a multiple of 8
then this address will be a multiple of eight
so that's an idea of alignment
and so why is that true well it's really a hardware issue that
the memory system instead of the actual hardware memory does not reference
one byte at a time it references actually in most machines nowadays about 64 bytes at a time
or depending on various widths within the the hardware
and in general with if a particular piece of data across
--is the boundaries between two blocks that are
because of a misaligned address that will take X your steps by the hardware
and potentially even the operating system
to deal with so just for efficiency reason they say  do this alignment trust me
in x86 machines if you have unaligned data it will execute just fine
it just might run a little bit more slowly
on some other machines if you try to do an unwind access it will actually cause a memory fault
question yes the
cecum the question was how could you force it to generate unaligned data
I don't know if you could
and we'll talk about ways you can sort of be more clever in how you do your allocation to avoid wasting space
so in general then we have
we're mostly looking here at data types that are either 1 2 or 4 8 bytes long
there are some 16 byte data types
but we won't be looking at those
and in general with the address then you can tell the alignment of an address by how many zeros
if it's a power of 2 alignment how many zeros are at the end of a bit level representation of that address
and so as we showed in general the C compiler when it's creating the layout for a structure  a struct
will put in padding bytes in there to make the alignment work
oh the other thing it will do is if it need be
it will add bytes to the end to make sure that the overall size of the data structure meets
whatever underlying alignment requirement there is and this one because it contains a double
the overall data structure has to be aligned on an 8 byte boundary
and the reasoning for that is imagine I had an array of structs of these structs in particular
then if I can assume that if I can ensure that this array is a month address as a multiple of eight
then you can see that each successive element of this array of these trucks  is a multiple of eight
and then within that struct I've ensured that each field that requires an alignment by eight
is a positioned with an offset that's a multiple of eight
and so it all works out but if you try to tinker with this  by making this too short
then you start getting misaligned references
and so one thing you'll see is for every struck the actual alignment requirement depends on
what's the sort of worst-case alignment the the maximum alignment of any element
so this particular structure for example
contains a float V which has a size of four  and so this would be an alignment of four
and you'll see in the code
in general when it has two this all this address arithmetic
we've seen gets used in various different ways to scale values compute offsets and so forth to get the appropriate elements
so your question before is could I tell the compiler not to do alignment
and the better way is to declare your fields
in a way that minimizes the amount of wasted space
so for example here
I wasted three bytes here and three bytes here to meet the alignment requirements
but if I just put I at the beginning and then C and D
I would have only wasted two bytes total
and in general because all the alignment requirements are powers of two
the sort of greedy algorithm works it says if I just take put the biggest stuff at the beginning
and then successfully smaller elements
I will be able to minimize any wasted space
and that's a general property but
this is a case where you is the writer of C code  have that effect
if the compiler will not do this for you automatically
-question -what about the case of having in under ray -what's that
oh but remember an array I don't care about the array I care about the elements of the array
because this is only down at the lowest level where I'm accessing either a single int a single double or a pointer
and not all the rest of this stuff remember I never read an entire array from memory
so alignment only refers down to the most the primitive types not the aggregate types
if this is confusing the book covers this fairly carefully
so let me just finish up with a little glimpse of floating point
a floating point is a complicated history in x86 how back in the really ancient days
there was a chip that went with the 8086 processor called the 8087
and at the time it was a masterpiece of engineering to be able to complete all the hardware necessary to implement
for IEEE floating point on a single chip
and it was the first one of its type
in fact it was a sort of co-developed with the IEEE floating point standard itself
but the programming model for it is horrendously awful and ugly
I used to in older editions of the book there were
it was in the first edition it was in a web aside in the second edition
and now it's been expunged completely because it's so awful
but more recently in the world of x86
they realized that to support things like video and all the stuff people actually do with their machines
they needed some more horsepower in numeric processing
and they implemented a class of instructions called SSE
which stands for sim D something Cindy execution
anyways and I'll show you in a minute what that means
and that's now in the more recent versions of x86
has been juiced up to something called a VX
which but the shark machines support this version of what's called SSE so let me just give you a feeling for that
and in particularly the shark machine support what's called SOC version 3
and what it is is that there are 16 special registers
distinct from the other registries we've talked about before
each of which has 16 bytes
and then there's operations that can operate on those and treat them in different ways
so one is to treat this such an a register as an array of 16 cares
or as a short or for its or and also to support a double floating-point arithmetic
so this stuff was certainly going on
and somebody had the observation that said well I could just then
sort of subset all this and implement the floating-point operations
directly using this SSE stuff and skip the old x87 stuff
and so that's the way floating point is now generated
on say the sharp machines and most recent machines
this is a this is again an example of where the world is more complicated than it should have to be
so for example there is an instruction that says add SS
so add a single scalar is what that notation add a single precision scalar
add a scaler single-precision
and it looks a little like the ad instructions the ad cute instructions you've seen that
it it increments it adds the source to the destination
there's ways I can do for ads and at the same time
using this is what they call sim D execution
which stands for single instruction multiple data
one instruction the ad PSP stands for pact
will do well will perform that one instruction will do ad with four different numbers
and similar you can do it with double precision you can do one of them you can do pet
and so actually the underlying and we'll see this when we look at code optimization
if you write code to make use of these instructions you can really boost the performance of the computer
but this just gives you a flavor for what floating-point code looks like
and the rules are pretty simple that just as we saw before that
that arguments get passed in in registers
while 14-point arguments get passed in these xmm registers
xmm zero you don't have to memorize RDI RSI RDX
there in Ex mmm zero one two it's all very logical
and the return value is in Ex mmm zero
and all the registers are called color safe there's no Kali safe
so something like adding two floating point numbers will just look like a single floating point addition instruction
same with double
and if you mix together code that has a pointer and a floating point operator
the pointer will be passed in a regular register RDI
and this double will be passed in xmm zero
so it's sort of as it goes through the argument list you sort of
in the particular order if it's an integer or a pointer it's in one of the our registers
and if it's a floating point value it's in one of the xmm registers and potentially interleaved
almost done oh and so this is a code that
does this particular operation and it's interesting because it's returning a
it's doing memory referencing so
again there's instructions that will read from memory and copy into an X mm register
you can add registers you can make a copy of from one X mm register to another  and you can store results
so this code looks a lot like what you do in integer arithmetic except it's using X mm and special floating-point instructions
rather than the ones you've seen before
so the basic idea of it is fairly simple
it gets way more complicated because there are lots of instructions
double float but on and on and on there's a special instruction to do square root and all this stuff
and the comparison stuff is really nasty and messy and hard to understand
and then uh you'll see various tricks to use constant values to
so that's covered in the book we're not going to really talk about it much in this course
but the underlying the the basic principle of zovut are fairly straightforward
ok that'll do us for today