Good afternoon everyone welcome to 213 it's good to see you
Just a reminder that your attack lab is due tonight at 11:59 p.m.
You have one grace day for this lab
And cache lab we'll go out it right about the same time
Now it's going to be a little tight for cache labs it'll be due next Thursday
So you might want to you might want to get started on that soon
Last lecture we learned about the memory hierarchy and the idea of caching
Today we're going to look at a very important kind of cache
Which are called cache memories
And they're very important to you as a programmer
Because they can have such a big impact on the performance of your program
So if you know about these the existence of these cache memories and you know how they work
As a programmer you'll be able to take advantage of that in your programs
So last time we looked at the memory hierarchy is a collection of storage devices
With smaller,costlier and faster devices at the top and slower cheaper and much larger devices at the at the bottom
And then at each level in this hierarchy
The device at level k serves as a cache holds a subset of the blocks of
That are contained in the device at the lower level at level k+1
Now recall the general idea of caching so we have a memory
It's an array of bytes and we break it up arbitrarily into a collection of blocks
And these this memory is larger slower and cheaper
And so it's,and it's much larger than than a cache which is smaller faster and more expensive
And which holds a subset of the blocks that are contained in the main memory
And then blocks are copied back and forth between the cache in the memory in these block size transfer units
So for example if our program requests a word that's in contained in block number 4
It asks the cache to return the word that's contained in block 4
The cache looks and it's at the blocks that it's the subset of the blocks
That it's stored discovers that block 4 is not there
So it asks the main memory to send it block 4
Which it does and when that block arrives at the cache
The cache stores it but potentially overwriting some existing block
Similarly if our program asks for a data word
If that's contained within block 10
The cache looks sees that it doesn't have that block
So it requests that block for memory which copies it into the cache
Which overwrites an existing block
Now subsequently if our program asks for a request
If our program references a word that's contained in block 10
For example then the cache then we have a hit and the cache can return that block immediately
Without going through the expensive operation of contacting memory and fetching that block from memory
Now there's a very important class of caches these so called cache memories
Which are contained in the CPU chip itself
And are managed completely by hardware
And they're implemented using fast SRAM memories
And the idea for this cache which write next to the register file
Is to hold frequently access blocks or blocks from main memory that are accessed frequently
Okay so hopefully because of the principle of locality
Most of our requests for data will actually be served out of this cache memory and a few cycles
Rather than from this slow main memory
Now cache memories are managed completely in hardware
So this means that the heart there's ,here has to be hardware logic that knows
How to look for blocks in the cache and determine whether or not a particular block is contained there
So cache memories are have to be organized in a very kind of strict simple way
So that the logic the lookup logic can be pretty simple
So this is very all cache memories are organized in the following way
You can think of the cache as an array of S=2^s sets
Ok each set consists of E=2^e lines
Where each line consists of a block of B=2^b bytes of data
A valid bit which indicates whether these data bits are actually that the bits and the data block are actually meaningful right
It's possible they could just be random bits like you know when you first turn on the machine
There's nothing in the cache
But those bits will have values right that they'll lead to be ones or zeros
But they won't actually correspond to data
Okay so the valid bit tells us if these B bytes actually mean anything
And then there's some additional bits called the tag bits
Which will help us search for blocks which I'll show you in a minute
Now when we talk about our cache size
We're referring to the number of data bytes that are contained in blocks
And so each cache has there's S sets
There's E blocks per set
And there's B bytes per block
Ok so the total cache size C=S*E*B
Ok now so there's a lot of terms to sort of keep straight and it's very easy to get
To confuse the difference between lines and blocks and lines and sets
Okay so we'll go through some examples and hopefully these will see these will start to make more sense
Now let's look at in general how the cache hardware implements a read
So when our program accesses, when our program executes an instruction
That references some word in memory
The CPU sends that address to the cache
And asks and it asks the cache to return the word the word at that address
So the cache takes that address
This would be a 64-bit address in case of x86-64
And it divides the address into a number of regions
Which are determined by the organization of the cache
Okay they're determined by those parameters S sets
The s the number of sets a the number of lines per set and b the size of each data block
So the low order bits there are b low order bits which determine the offset in the block
That that word starts at
Okay the next s bits are treated as an unsigned integer
Which serves as an index into the array of sets
Okay remember we just think of these as think of this cache as an array of set
The set index bits provide the index into this array of sets
And then all of the remaining bits
All of the remaining t bits constitute what we call tag
Which will help us when we do our search
So the cache logic takes this address
And it first extracts the the set index
And uses that to,as an index into this array to identify the set that
If this block is in the set,I'm sorry,if the data word
If the block that contains the data word at this address is in the cache
It's going to be in the set denoted by the the set index
So first it identifies which index to look in
And then it checks the tag,it checks all of the lines in that set
To see if there's any of those lines have a matching tag
That a tag that matches the the t the tag bits and the address
And it checks to see if the valid bit is turned on
So if those two conditions holds if there's a line anywhere in the set
As of where the valid bit is one and there's a matching tag
Then we have a hit okay then the block that we're looking for is contained in this set
Okay if we...once we determine that with that we've identified the block
Then the cache uses that the low-order b bits to determine where that
Where the data we're interested in begins okay within that block
All right let's look at a more specific example for a the simplest kind of cache
Which is when E=1 when there's only one line per set
Okay so E=1 one line per set
This kind of cache is called a direct mapped cache
So here we have S sets each set consists of a single line
And now suppose our program references the data item
And a particular address the CPU sense that address to the cache
The cache takes that address breaks it up into these into these three fields
For this particular address the block offset is four
And the set index is one and then there's some tag bits which we'll just denote with is a color pink
So the cache extracts the set index which is one
And then it uses that as the index into the set
And then it just ignores all the other the sets
If the block we're looking for is...is in the cache it's going to be in this inset number one
Then it does the comparison of the tag bits and the valid bits
And assume that they assume that valid bits on and that it matches
Then it looks at the block offset which is four
And which tells it that the four bit in suppose that that's what the instruction was referencing
The four byte in begins that offset for
So now the cache takes this int and it sends it back to the to the CPU which puts it in the register
Okay if the tag doesn't match then the old-line, if the tag doesn't match then there's a miss
And in that case the cache has to fetch the block the corresponding block from memory
And then overwrite this block in the line
And then it can serve,then it can fetch,it can get the word out of the block and send it back to the processor
Okay now let me ask you a question just to see you kind of check to see you're following along with this
So if there's a miss
And the cache has two requests the block for memory
Fetch it from memory and then overwrite the the block in the current line
Does it also have to change the tag bits or do those stay the same?
So does the do the tag bits that were in this line get overwritten with a different value
Or is it the same? same? different? same? different?
Now why would it be different ?
-we haven't changed yes-[student speaking]-I'm sorry oh-[student speaking]
Oh it almost certainly has different data
But just have a different address
Exactly it missed because the tag
It missed because the tag didn't match
If the valid bit was false and the tag match then that would also be a miss
Oh then you wouldn't...okay that's right,that's...okay good good good,okay,great
All right let me do a little, let me do a really simple specific example of a how direct map cache works
I want you to understand in real detail how this would work
But I also want to make a point for about the weakness of direct mapped cache is and why
Why you would want to have more than one line per set
Okay this is a really simple we have our memory system consists of 16 bytes
Ok so it's not a very useful system with 4 bit addresses
And it's broken up into blocks of 2 bytes each
Our cache consists of 4 sets with one block per set
Now 4 bytes,4 bit addresses
Because B=2, that's 2^1 we only need 1 block offset bit
Right there's only 2 bytes in a block so the byte we're looking for is either at 0 or 1
Okay because we have 4 sets we need set index bits
And then the remaining bits are always tag bits in this case there's just one tag bit
All right now let's suppose that our program executes instructions
That reference the following memory address is 0,1,7,8 and 0
And these references are reads that they're reading one byte per read
Okay like I said this is a really simple system
So let's look at what happens now
We start tag,initially,cache is empty valid bits are all set to zero
And now the cache receives the request for the byte that's at address 0
So it extracts the set index bits which in this case are 00
So these so it's going to look in set 0
For and in this case since valid is 0 it's just a miss ok
So it fetches that block from memory sticks the block
So this memory this is the...this is using array notation for memory
So this is like the the bytes that extend from offset 0 to offset 1 inclusive in memory
The tag bit is 0 and the valid bit is 1
Ok now the next address that comes by is for address 1
Well that's a hit right...because we...that block the block that contains the byte at address 1 is already in the cache
The tag and the tags match okay so we're good that's a hit
You now we get address 7
So the cache extracts the set index bits,which in this case are 11 or 4 or 3 rather
Looks in set 3 there's no valid bit,so that's a miss and it loads the the data from memory
That spans bytes 6~7
In this case the the tag bit is 0
Okay so we record that in our metadata
Okay the next reference that comes by is 8
Now 8 has a set index of 0,00
But that's currently occupied by block zero one
And we can tell that because address eight has a tag of one
And the existing block,the block at the earlier address at address zero has a tag of zero so that's a miss so
So now we have to go fetch the block containing byte number eight into memory
So now we have bytes 8-9 and we in our new tag bit
Okay now the next instruction is for byte 0
And we just replaced,we had that it,we had that in our cache and we just replaced it
So it's another miss so that's unfortunate
And it's the only reason we missed it is because we've got just one line per set
Right so we were forced to overwrite
That that block containing bytes,the block zero one when we missed on block eight nine
Okay and you see there's plenty of room in our cache we've still got,we've got two lines
That we haven't even access right so we've our cache is plenty big
But just because of the low associativity of our cache
And the the sort of the pattern the access pattern that we were presented with
We've got a miss that really was kind of unnecessary
So oh yeah sorry
[student speaking]
Six,so when we referenced a seven
It's actually the it's at offset one in that block 6-7
Okay since blocks are two bytes they'll always start on an even multiple
Any other questions
Okay so this sort of is the reason why you have caches have higher associativity,higher values of E
So let's look at...and so for values of E greater...for values of E greater than greater than 1
We refer to them as E way set associative caches
So here E=2 so it's a 2-way it's 2-way associative
Let's suppose we have a 2-way associative cache
So here we have an array of sets and now each set contains two lines ok instead of one line
And suppose we're presented with an address with the following form
We're looking for the word that begins at an off set of four inside our block
At within set number one
Okay so the cache expects tracts that set index
So this is set 0,this is set 1,this is set 2,throws away all the other sets
And now in parallel it searches,it searches the tags,it searches for a matching tag in both of these lines
And a valid bit so if we get a matching tag and a valid bit true
Then we've got a hit
Now that yes yes
[student speaking]
Oh it's a very good question,so there's hardware logic that does that compare
And that's the reason that as the number of...as the associativity goes up that logic gets more and more expensive
Okay it's like something...like you're kind of doing some kind of tree search
And so that actually is the limit that's why..
I mean because in general right that if you take this to the limit there's just one set
With there's just...we call that a fully associative cache so there's just one set
And now any block...a block can go anywhere
Right there's no constraints now where you place a block
But because of the complexity of that fully associative search
Those are very rare in fact we do see we'll see fully associative caches but their software caches
Okay so in software,so the complexity the hardware
And sort of doesn't
Doesn't it's not worth the complexity of the hardware for the penalty of having a lower associativity
Okay but there are some systems later on when we study virtual memory
In a virtual memory system the DRAM serves as a cache for data stored on the disk
And as we saw last time the penalty for a miss
If you have a cache on DRAM and you miss and you have to go to disk
The penalty is huge for that
And so because of that it's worth while having very complex search algorithms
In particular in a virtual memory system that the DRAM is implements a fully associative cache where blocks from disk can go anywhere
We'll get into that later when we look in virtual memory
But you're right you'll see in real systems
Nowadays that the number goes up right because feature sizes are going down and
Designers can afford to implement more expensive hardware
But the largest associativity are Intel systems that I know of is 16-way associative L3 caches
And then the others are 8-ways associative
So that's sort of the order of magnitude that's state of the art right now
Okay so then once we've identified a match we use the set offset bits
In this case we're accessing a short int, so four is the offset within the block of this
The two byte short int which then we can return to the processor
Alright so let's do that same simulation that we did before
But this time with a 2-way associative cache
Now memory system is the same
But now instead of one set we have two sets
And I mean I'm sorry instead of four sets we have two sets
So the cache,this is the same sized cache
But we're just going to organize it differently, instead of 1-way instead of a direct mapped cache
With four lines containing four lines,one line per set
We're going to implement a 2-way associative cache where we have two sets with two lines per set
Okay so each case there's four total lines
Question
[student speaking]
Oh so that that comes in with the request somehow
And I actually don't know the details of that
It may...I guess there...it could ask for just...
there could just be a default sighs maybe it's always a 64-byte word and then the processor extracts that the current bits
I actually don't know the details of that
But it either comes in on the request or there's a standard size that the processor then parses out
We'll just assume that the cache knows the what size to return yes
[student speaking]
How do you decide which block to replace?that's a really good question
So there's a lot of different algorithms
The most common algorithm or a common algorithm is least recently used
So by locality you want to keep blocks in the cache that are being used a lot
And so if a block isn't referenced for a long time by the principle of locality by sort of the inverse locality principle
It's likely not to be addressed referenced in the near future
So that's one algorithm
That you just keep track of and I'm not showing there needs to be additional bits
In the line to sort of keep like sort of virtual timestamps that
But that's sort of the general way you do it
Just try to keep the things that are the blocks being accessed the most frequently,most recently yes
[student speaking]
Okay the question is what determines the block size
That's determined by the design of the memory system
So that's a fixed parameter of the memory system
So when the intel designers decided to put cache memories on their processors
They decided that the block size would be 64 bytes
Sorry
So the block size comes the block size comes first
Then you determine how big you want your cache to be
Okay and you determine the associativity
And then once you've determined the associativity and you know how big your cache is
Then that determines the number of sets
Okay so basically all of those the
The the number of lines and the cat and the capacity
The number of lines per set is sort of a fixed high-level parameter design parameter
The size of the cache is a high-level design parameter
And then the number of sets then is induced from that
Okay yes
[student speaking]
Ah that's yeah how does...so that's the replacement policy
So the question is how does it when there's multiple lines in a set how does it determine which to over overwrite
And that was the previous question probably maybe I should have repeated it
So you try to pick a line that was least recently used
So lines that haven't been accessed
Recently are good candidates for replacement because
Because of the sort of inverse locality principle right that
They haven't been inverse referenced recently chances are they won't be referenced
Again it
Oh yeah there's additional bits that I'm not showing here that you have to
So when you replace a line in the set
If that data is has changed then it has to be written back to memory
And that's another bit I haven't shown
Yes
[student speaking]
Ah so yeah,so this is a really this is really tricky parameter writing
It's a high level system parameter that it goes on for years
So the idea you want to have blocks in order to exploit spatial locality
Right think about if you're going to go to the trouble of if you have a miss in cache
And you're going to go to the trouble of going all the way to memory to get some data
You want to amortize the cost of fetching that data by fetching more than one byte
That's the motivation for blocks
Because by the principle of locality in spatial locality in particular
If you reference a word inside of a block
Chances are you're going to reference a nearby word which will also be an epilogue
Okay so blocks the whole purpose of blocks is to exploit spatial locality
Now if you make your block too small then you don't amortize
You don't get the same amortization right you maybe get one
You bring the block in
So there's a reference you get a miss you bring the block in
There's another reference nearby you get a hit because the blocks in memory
But then the next reference is in a different block
Because your block sizes are too small
Right so you kind of want to make blocks big as big as possible
But without slowing the system down
So if you made your block size too big it would just take too long to bring that block in
Plus now your blocks,that your blocks are taking up bits in your cache memory
So now there's no room for other blocks
Right so it's a really tricky design problem right and
If we're doing it taking an architecture class then we would sort of dive into the
You know how how architects make those design decisions
But in general that's what it's kind of a balancing act right
Were there any other questions? yes
[student speaking]
Oh the question is every time there's a miss
Do you have to select a victim line and override it
Yeah I don't know of any caches that don't do that
Now we'll see when we look at rights
We'll see there's an option of whether we're only looking at reads right now
But with rights that question does come up
If you wait in a couple of slides we'll go over that
Any other questions
Okay so let's look at this two-way associative cache now
There's one block offset bit
We only have two sets so that we only need one set index
And then the remaining two bits are tagged
So let's go through our trace so address zero has a set is in set zero right here that's a miss
so we load that into memory
With the reference to address one
That's in set zero and that's a hit because that byte is in a block
The reference to seven is a miss that's in set one so we load that
And we were just picking randomly pick one of these two over right
Because the cache is empty
The next reference is to address number eight which is in set zero
Now here's the difference between the direct mapped cache and this 2-way set associative cache
When we reference address 8
That block has to the corresponding block has to go into set 0
Because of this zero set index bit
But we've got room now because we are set to have room for two lines instead of one
So when we load that in well if we have an available empty slot
We'll put it there we won't overwrite anything right so if possible always try to overwrite empty lines
So now we've got in this set...we've got block 0-1 and block 8-9
So when we get our reference to address zero
Whereas before with the when we had a conflict miss in the direct map cache
Now we can satisfy that that request
It hits in memory and the cache can satisfy it from the cache instead of going to memory
Okay so that makes sense
Okay now what about rights?
So there's multiple copies of the data
Right we're sub setting as we move up the hierarchy we're creating subsets of the data in the caches
So what we do a write to a word within a block that's currently in the cache
Okay we have two options
We can write that block immediately to memory right
We're got a block that's like this big and we're updating a little chunk of it
So we can either do the update and then flush it to memory immediately
So that memory always mirrors the contents of memory always mirror the contents of the cache
Okay but that's expensive right
I mean you know memory accesses are expensive
The other so the other option is what what's called write back
So in this case when we write to a block in the cache
We don't flush it to memory
Until we elect that particular line as a victim that's going to be overwritten
And only then when we're just we sort of defer
The writing to memory until the last possible minute
We defer it until just before the cache would overwrite that  that data block
Okay so that's called right back
And for right back you need to have some an extra bit in the line that indicates whether that blocks been written to
So the algorithm is when the cache identifies a particular line to overwrite
It checks the dirty bit on that line if it's set then it writes that data to back to disk
Okay if the data hasn't...if that block hasn't been written there's no point there's no need to write it back
Because it has the same value as the copy of the block on disk
Okay now so what about...so that's a right here now what happens if we have a right miss
So we're doing a write to memory
And the word that we're writing is not contained in any block that's in our cache
So we have two options we can do what's called write allocate so we can treat it if there's a miss
We can do sort of the symmetric thing that we did with a hit which was create a new
A newline possibly overwriting an existing line
And then write in so we could create that cache enter that cache line
Fetch it from memory and then do the right
Okay so this is sort of symmetric to reads right then
So every right if it misses when the write finishes the that block will be in the cache
And if we do a subsequent read we get a hit
Okay so that's the reason you might want to do that
The the other option is just to
Don't allocate an entry in the cache don't allocate a new line just write write the data directly to memory
You don't really need to understand the distinction between these two things
Different caches use different policies
For your own mental model a good model to use is just to assume write back write allocate
So just assume that we won't copy the data to disk
If there's a hit we won't write it back to disk until the last possible minute
And every time there's a write miss what will create a new entry in the cache
Okay so that's...that I think that's sort of the simplest model that
And it's a reason it's a reasonable model that you can use regardless of the particular cache implementation
Now in a real system so far we've only looked at we've only assumed that there's a single cache
But in a in real systems there's multiple caches
So modern core i7 has well architecture from intel
Contains multiple processor cores
So 4 is a typical number for like desktop systems
8~12 is typical for server class systems
These processor cores can each execute their own independent instruction stream in parallel
And each processor core can contains general-purpose registers which that's level 0 in the cache
And then two different kinds of L1 caches
The data cache the L1 d-cache
And the i-cache is the...which is the instruction cache
And these are fairly small 32 k bytes they're eight-way associative
And they can be accessed in a very small number of cycles
The next level of the hierarchy is L2 cache
Which is still fairly small 256 k bytes same associativity
And it has a slightly longer access time
And it's unified in the sense that the L2 cache contains both data and instructions
Ok so that's all within a single core on the chip
And then also on the chip but external to all the cores and shared by all the cores
Is at L3 unified cache which is 8 megabytes and 16 way associative
With an access time that's like 40 to 75 cycles
So if there's a miss in L1,then the L1 sense or tries to sends a request to L2 to try to find the data in L2
Since L2 is a little bigger maybe maybe the data hasn't been flushed out of L2 yet
If L2 can't find it,it sends a request to L3 to see if they can find the data in L3
If L3 can't find it then it gives up and it goes off chip to memory
Yes question
Yes name memory is this that's it's the DRAM built of DRAM chips
It's separate,it's in a separate separate set of chips on the motherboard
Connected by those that I/O bridge
That we and the bus various buses then that we talked about last time
And for all different for all of these different caches that block size is 64 bytes
Now there's a number of different ways to I think about the performance of caches
My most common way is using a metric called the miss rate
So what this is the fraction of references that miss
So we're very so I thought and it's 1- hit rate
So typical for caches to work that miss rate has to be pretty low
And fortunately because of locality these miss rates are low
Another metric is the hit time
So if we do have a hit in the cache how long does it actually take to...
Sort of look up the you know do the lookup to determine that there was a hit and then return the value
So for L1 and in an intel system this is 4 clock cycles,10 clock cycles for L2
And then there's an additional cost if
So you always have to pay the hit time right the hit time is the best you can do
But if you have a miss then it's you pay the hit time
Because you have to do the search and eventually you're going to have to return the word back to the requester
But you then you have this additional cost
Which you have to go which is going to the the memory ready to fetch the data
Okay so that miss penalty,that's what called miss penalty
Is on the order of hundreds of cycles for main memory
But at other levels of the hierarchy it can be huge
So the miss penalty if you have a cache in main memory
That's caching blocks that are stored on disk, the miss penalty is enormous
So it's kind of interesting if you think about it
The performance of these systems is very sensitive to the miss rate much more sensitive than you would think
And in fact 99% hit rate is twice as good as a 97% hit rate
Yes
[student speaking]
Yeah they hit,so the question is does the hit time include the time to access the tag and yes
So the hit time is the time it takes to just to search
To determine if that item is in the cache and then return it
[student speaking]
Yeah so the yeah so the the miss the miss penalty is the time it takes for the cash to fetch the data from memory
So that's all the latency you know going across the buses
The time it takes the memory to respond to the requests
The time it takes the data to flow back over the buses back to the the cache
So the time for a miss is going to be the hit time plus the miss penalty that clear
So I mean imagine suppose there's a hit time of one cycle and a miss penalty of 100 cycles that those are reasonable numbers
So the the average access time if you have 97% hits
It's the hit time plus the percentage of misses times the miss penalty
So that's four cycles for the average access time
But if we just increase the hit rate by two percent
The average access time drops by 50% a factor of two
All right so why is this stuff important why should you care about it
So cash is that as we've seen are these these they're automatic they're all built in hardware
There's no part of the sort of the visible instruction set that
Lets you manipulate caches and your assembly machine code programs
So that it all happens behind the scenes automatically in hardware
But if you know how kit...if you know about the existence of caches
And you have this general idea of how you can work how they work
Then you can write code that's cache friendly
In the sense that your code will have a higher higher miss rate than code that that isn't cache friendly
So the idea is to...you want to focus on making the common case go fast
Don't spend your time on code  that sort of code that doesn't get execute very much
So look at the most commonly called functions
And then within those functions look at the inner loops of those functions
Because it's the inner loops that are executing the most
Right so you can as a first approximation you can just ignore sort of stuff
If you have nested loops you can ignore stuff that's going on in the outer loops
And just focus on the code in the inner loop
Now what you want to do is try to minimize the misses in the inner loop
Okay so repeated references to a variable is variables are good
Especially if those are local variables
Right so remember if you declare a local variable and see
The compiler can put that in a register
Right if you're referencing global variables
Maybe not,the compiler doesn't know what's going on
So it can't put the reference to that variable to see in a register
Okay so repeated references to local variables stored on the stack are good
Because those will get turned into register accesses
You'll never go to memory
Okay also stride one accesses two arrays are good
And they're good because of the existence of these blocks
Right so the only way you'd know that stride one references our good is if you knew that
Caches have the 64-byte blocks
Okay so the and stride one reference will have half the miss rate as a stride to reference
Because if you're doing stride one references the first reference to a word and a block will miss
But then subsequent references will hit
Right and you'll hit if you're doing a stride one reference you're going to hit every word in that block
If your drive if you're doing stride two references you're only going to hit every other word
Right so you'll only get,you'll get sort of half the so you'll missed at twice the rate
So
So basically the point I want to make to you is that our understanding of caches
Allow us to sort of quantify this qualitative notion of locality that we developed the last time
Right the last time we looked at we said if it's doing stride one references that's good if
If we're doing if we're accessing the same variable over and over that's good
But if we understand caches now we can quantify it in terms of miss rate
All right so let's finish up the rest of the class
We're going to look at the performance impact of caches on your code
Okay and why you need to why you need to know about these things
And that the impact that they can have
So there's a very interesting function
This actually plotted on the cover of your text book
That we call the memory mountain
I learned about this from a graduate student here at Carnegie Mellon back in the 90s who developed this notion made Tom Stricker
And what it's a the memory mountain plots a measure called read through put or read bandwidth
Which is the number of bytes read from memory
So if you have a loop and you're scanning over a vector
So you have a vector of say double words
And you're reading those elements from a vector one after the other
The read throughput is the number of megabytes per second that you can perform that task
At and the memory mountain plots read throughput
As a function of the temporal and spatial locality in that loop
Okay so in a sense it's looking at a wide range of locality options or characteristics in a program
And it's plotting the performance of that memory system on that across that range as a two-dimensional function
So in some ways the memory mountain is a
Kind of a fingerprint right every system has its own unique memory mountain
That we can measure right by writing a simple program
And so the idea here is that to construct the memory mountain
We write a program called test
Oh shoot
For some reason it's not
Okay right
So when we build a memory mountain
We're given a vector that consists of a collection of double words
And then we write a loop that reads those words that read some number of words in this case
Hmm
There we go
So it reads it reads elems number of elements right
So we've got each of these double word elements with a stride of stride
Okay so if we have a stride of one
I know that was kind of redundant huh
So if we have a stride of one
Then we'll have our loop wills was sort of looped through
And read these elements until we've read elems number of those elements
Okay and then we'll do it again and then that warms up the cache
Then we do it again and do exactly the same thing
So if we're doing this with a stride of two then we would be reading
We would read this word zero or elem 2 elem 4 and so on
Okay so well then what all we're doing we're just for wide range of strides
And a wide range of sizes
We're scanning over this vector and just recording how long it takes to do that read
And then convert we convert that into megabytes per second
And in order to I just wanted to show you this is we don't need,we're not going to go into detail about this but
This is actually how I generated the the cover on the book and
In order to use to exploit the parallelism inside the intel processor
Like you learned about last week there's a lot of parallel functional units
In order to exploit those I did 4x4 loop unrolling
So I'm actually doing sort of four scans in parallel
But the general idea is just what I've showed you here
And this this 4x4 loop unrolling is just an optimization
But I wanted to show it to you because it actually it's the exact same principles
You learned about last week professor Bryant talked about code optimization
So what we do is,we call this test function with these various ranges of elems and stride
And then we measure the performance and we get this beautiful picture
This beautiful function ,to me it's beautiful I don't know does it look beautiful to you
So on the z
On the z axis is plotting read throughput in megabytes per second
Ranging from 2000 megabytes per second up to 16,000 megabytes per second
This this axis is measuring is stride
So going from stride 1 up to stride 12
And this axis is...so as we as we increase stride we're decreasing the spatial locality
Alright
And this axis is the size axis so we're going from I think 16k up to 128 megabytes
So this is the number of elements we're going to read each pass through
So as we as we increase the size
We're sort of decreasing the impact of temporal locality because word
As we increase the size there's fewer and fewer caches in our hierarchy can hold all that data
And so this so we've got spatial locality decreasing in this direction
And temporal locality decreasing in this direction
So as a programmer what you want to do you want to be up here
Right good spatial locality good temporal locality
Because you can get like 14 gigabytes per second measure agreed throughput
You don't want to be down here
Which is only about 100 megabytes per second where you're reading out of memory
Right so the difference between reading all of your data from memory
And reading it from some part of the the caches is huge it's enormous
Ok so because you're 213 students you'll be up here
And all the students that didn't take 213 they'll be down here
And I've actually had I've actually had people several people write back
To tell me about their experiences you know in internships and jobs after they left CMU
Where they were given some code that that was down here
And they recognized the locality issues and they got it you know better up here or close at least better
So this picture this so-called memory mountain has all kinds of interesting features
First of all there's these what I call ridges of temporal locality
Where these ridges see these ridge lines if you think of this is like a mountain
You see this ridge line and you see this ridge line
And here's another ridge line and then here's a here's another one
These correspond to different levels in the hierarchy
So this this top ridge line is where you're reading directly out of L1
And it should be perfectly flat and
It's so fast that we're getting like measurement jitter performance jitter right
But it's and this little drop off here is a measurement artifact it it should it shouldn't be there
It should be flat and go all the way to the wall back here
And then here this ridge line is where we're accessing L2
This is where we're accessing L3
And here's what we're accessing mostly from memory
So you have these ridges of temporal locality
And then you have these slopes of decreasing spatial locality
So you see the slope here
As work so as we're moving from the top of the slope down to the bottom
We're decreasing our spatial locality so we're getting less benefit for these blocks that we're bringing in
So you can see the we're getting less benefit out of the cost
That we went through of importing of fetching these blocks
And once the stride hits the block size
Now every reference is hitting a different block
And so and then it flattens out then you get you're getting noes benefit from spatial locality
And similarly here is where this this slope is where we're reading from L3
And it flattens out always they always flatten out at the block size which is a stride these are double words right
So it's stride of eight is 64 bytes
So once you exceed a stride of eight then you're no longer
You're missing every time in a different block
There's this interesting this one puzzled me for a while
You might be wondering like how come like over here is we increase the size
We can sort of getting the...we're sort of as we increase the size
We're doing most of our references out of caches that are lower in the cache hierarchy
Okay but except when we're doing stride one references
You can see all the way up to right at the end
Right before it exceeds the size of L3
It's flat
And it's running at the L2 rate
Alright so here's the L1 rate and then it drops off and then it's running at a constant L2 rate
Until the data no longer fits in L3
So I think what's going on here is that the the hardware
The cache L2 cache hardware is recognizing or maybe it's an L1 but
Some logic in the cache system is recognizing the stride one reference pattern
Right because it sees all the addresses
It's recognizing that stride one pattern
And then it's aggressively prefetching from L3 into L2
So that those so it's fetching ahead of time it's anticipating
It's saying look I've gotten five stride one references in a row
I'm going to go grab a whole bunch of blocks and load them all up
Because by the principle of spatial locality those blocks
Those blocks are going to be referenced in the near future
So this was really neat and this only happened within the last couple years
So the intel engineers are always hard at work
And maybe by the time the time we do the next the next edition of the memory mountain
Those systems will recognize stride 2 and you know other stride pattarns two
But from this data it appears that it's only recognizing stride one
Ok so you can real...you we can improve the spatial and temporal locality of our programs
In several different ways that one way to improve the spatial locality is to rearrange loops
And I'll use matrix multiplication as an example
So here's a sort of a simple matrix multiplication in code
Where we're multiplying a times b and adding it
We're taking what's in of the c[i][j]
And then to that we're adding the sum the inner product of row i of a and the row j column j of b
Okay and then so we're going through and for each i,j in this matrix c
We're computing an inner product and then creating that sum
So we can actually turns out there's a lot of different ways to do matrix multiply
And this is we can permute these these loops
In any of six different possible permutations
So this is a permutation where it's i followed by j followed by k
But five other possibilities are feasible
And so we can actually analyze those those different permutations
And predict which one will have the best performance
Okay so what we'll do is we'll look at the inner loop
And we'll look at the access pattern of the inner loops
And it's in the access pattern on arrays c,a and b
Okay so let's look at the i,j,k implementation that I just showed you
So as always we focus on the inner loop
And if you notice this inner loop is doing a row wise access of column a
And a column wise access,I'm sorry, a row wise access of array a
And column wise access of row b
So row wise of a,column wise of b,we don't really care about c
Because it's not in the inner loop okay so just ignore that
So given our assumption that we can hold in this case we're assuming that
We can hold for of these integer elements in a in one block
So the row wise access which has good spatial locality will miss one every four accesses
Okay the very first reference will miss and then the next three will hit
And then the next reference after that will hit a new block
Okay so one out of four references to a will miss
But because the access pattern for b is column wise every reference to b will miss
Okay so the average number of misses per loop iteration is 1.25
Okay the j,i,k version is exactly the same pattern
K,i,j is a little different here
We're doing row wise access of b
And a row wise access of c, so that's good right
So now we've got stride one accesses on both b and c
And the reference to a is outside of the loop,so we don't care about it
So so both b and c will miss one quarter of the time
Okay so the total average number of misses per loop iteration will be 0.5
That's pretty good and i,k,j has the same similar behavior
Now j,k,i is sort of the exact opposite
j,k,i does column wise access of a
And column-wise access of c so right we know that's a stinker right
And we qualitative well you know it's bad and we can compute that it will miss a one time per loop iteration
So that will be two total of two misses per iteration
And k,j,i has the same bad pattern
Okay so if we look at all these permutations
You can see that i,j,k and j,i,k miss 1.25 have 1.25 misses
k,i,j has 0.5 misses and j,k,i has 2 misses
So clearly it looks like k,i,j and its brethren are the best option
The only difference is that k,i,j has this additional store
So there might be a question that is that going to create is that going to slow things down
Well it turns out in systems in any kind storage systems rights
Are much easier to deal with them reads
Can you think about why that might be true
So writes you have a lot more flexibility than you do with reads
I mean yes
That's exactly so you can you have options you can do you can write back defer you can defer writing
Until the value that you're written is actually used
But when you read an item you're stuck
You can't do anything until you get that data
So it turns out that rights don't really that this additional store doesn't really hurt us
And so when we measure these on a modern system
You can see that that the k,i,j which has the the fewest number of misses
Has you see we're getting like one miss what we're plotting here is cycles per inter loop iteration
So each iteration is taking about one cycle which is really good
This i,j,k pattern which is kind of the intermediate 1.2 misses
That's sort of in between and the j,k,i which has two misses per iteration is the worst
Ok so what's interesting is we could actually just by doing a little bit of analysis
Simple analysis we could actually predict what this graph would look like
Okay in the last ten minutes of the class
We're going to look at how to improve temporal locality
Now so what we did with... when we rearranged our loops
With in the matrix multiplication what we were doing was in improving our spatial locality right
But we didn't really do anything to improve the temporal locality
To improve temporal locality you have to use a technique called blocking
And this is important to understand because you're going to need it in your cache lab for one thing
But it's also a very general technique
Anytime you need,any time you're having issues with temporal locality
Okay so
We're not going to go into too much detail this code but what I did I rewrote the matrix multiply
So that it operates you know a two-dimensional matrix that you can really just think of it as a contiguous array of bytes
So I just rewrote this code to operate on a contiguous array one-dimensional array
And then I'm doing the indexing explicitly here
So here at c[i*n+j] this is n matrix
So what I'm doing is...I'm accessing the I'm computing where the I throw starts
And then I'm going to the j column of that row and then accessing that element
All right so let's...but it's the same idea as before
So let's look at the miss rate for this, this is just an original this is an original unblocked matrix multiplied
So what we're doing is we're computing c[0][0]
And we're doing that by taking an inner product of row 0 and column 0
So if you look at the we're assuming that the cache blocks holds eight doubles
And that the matrix elements are doubles then we're going to miss one eight of the time
Okay so in the first iteration
We're going to miss the first iteration does n of these things
And since we're missing n over eight of the time
We're missing one block for every eight references
For each for the first iteration we're going to miss n over eight
And since there's n for each element for each block I'm sorry
And then oh so this is the number of blocks and the number of misses and then we have n elements
So that the total number of misses is 9n/8 misses for the first iteration
Okay the second iteration will have the same number of misses
Because of our assumptions about the the size of this array
So this these rows are way too big to fit in the cache
So we never get any we don't get any temporal locality
Okay so the total number of misses is 9n/8 times the number of elements that we're updating which is n squared
Okay so our total misses is 9n/8*n^3
Now let's rewrite the code to use blocking and so
You can look at this code later
But it's much simpler just to look at it pictorially
So what we're doing instead of updating one element at a time
We're updating a sub block a b by b sub block
And we're doing that just totally analogously to when an original case where b=1
This b by b sub block and c is computed by taking an inner product of the sub blocks
Of a set of sub blocks in an a with a set of sub blocks in b
And for each one of those we're doing a little mini matrix multiplication
So we're taking this sub block times this sub block
Plus the second sub block of a times the second sub block of of b
Plus the third sub block of a times the third sub block of b and so on
Okay so we're doing the same inner product  operation
But instead of scalars we're doing it with these little sub these little tiny matrices
Ok all right so let's look at,let's look at what happens to the miss rate when we do this
So there's there's n over b blocks in any row or column
And since there's b squared items in each block b*b
There's B^2/8 misses for each block
Okay and so then and then since there's there's n over b blocks in each matrix and there's two matrices
There's 2n/B*B^2/8 misses for this first iteration
So that works out to be an nB/4 and
And the second iteration has the same miss rate
So the total number of misses is the number of misses for each iteration
Times the number of elements in C that we're updating
Okay which is (n/B)^2
So that all works out too it's still in n^3*(1/4B)
So in our first case with no blocking although that the number of misses is asymptotically the same
But there's this pretty, this big difference in the constant factor so for no blocking it's 9/8
For blocking it's 1/4b we're now we can we can just sort of drive that down
By by increasing the block size so this gives us some control
But we still we have...we can't make the block the blocks too big because we need to fit three blocks
In cache at any one point in time
Ok so the reason this is a dramatic difference right
And the reason for this is that by doing the blocking we're sort of exploiting
Once we load a block into memory we're sort of reusing its items over and over again
So we're exploiting more temporal locality
And matrix multiplication has this into this implicit locality
Because the computation is order n cubed but the size of the data is n squared
Right so we must be reusing some data items
Right the problem with our scalar approach is that we were when we were reusing them they weren't in the cache
Ok
All right so the point that I wanted to make with you is that
Cache memories although they're sort of built-in automatic hardware storage devices
And you can't really control them
If you know about them you can take advantage of your knowledge
And exploit them and make your code run faster
Okay and the way you do this is like I said focus on the inner loops
Do is try to do try to do accesses that a stride one
And try to maximize to to maximize spatial locality
And try to maximize temporal locality by reusing local variables
Which can then be put into registers
Okay so that's it for today good luck with your attack lab if you haven't finished it and
Don't forget to get started on cache lab this weekend