This come this will be the last lecture on machine level programming
We call it advanced topics but think of it more as miscellaneous topics
And I think most to you of course you know that your bomb lab due tonight
So you most year probably well into that or hopefully through it
And then at midnight tonight the next web will come out which is called a tack lab
And there is a recitation about that yesterday
But this is a lab that's  a new to the course
It's a similar to one that we used to use at this point in the course
But it's been updated and changed in significant ways
So we're actually when you have labs like we do in this course with this many students
There's a lot of things that go can go wrong
So we're going to keep a close eye on on how things are going
But I'd encourage you you only have a week and a half to do this next lab
To get started soon and partly by having some people start sooner
You'll start breaking things for us that we can track down
So today what we'll talk about is a couple like I said it's miscellaneous topics but important topics
One is just sort of where what does the memory look like ah
When you're running x86-64 programs
The other is a very important topic on security vulnerability called buffer overflows
And in fact at a collab will be precisely exploiting those security vulnerabilities
And then we'll look at unions so far you've booked it arrays and structs and how they're organized
And I want to compare that to unions
So let's talk about memory  then as I said at the beginning early in the course
Conceptually a memory is just a big array of bytes
And that's the view of this the machine level programmer
Even though it's not the actual implementation
There's a whole part that we'll talk about later in the course
Of this is called virtual memory
This organization is very simple organization
But the underlying implementation is this complex management of
Various different memory types from disk memories to solid state disks
And to what's called dram which stands for dynamic ram the
When you buy memory for your processor its dram
Um so as you know in x86-64 we're working with machines that nominally are
Have addresses can be up to 64 bits long
And if you work out the numbers remember I told you at the beginning of the course
You can estimate how big a number like to the 64 is  by remembering that 1024
And a thousand are very close to each other
So 2^10 is roughly the same as 10^3
So you take 64 and you.thank 60
So how big is two to the sixty well that's six times ten
And therefore it's six times three it's like ten to the eighteenth
And then you add the four to that that's two to the fourth and 16
So it's around 16 times 10 to the 18th fights
So if you were to go off and look online on amazon for dram chips
And try to buy that much memory you'd find you're spending a lot of money
More than you I don't know the numbers but it would be a lot of memory money
And so you basically can't do it nowadays
Tend to the and so
Right now the machines limit you to actually only 47 bits worth of address  in the address space
I'll and so 2 to the 47th again work that out that's like 10 to the 12th times 256 times 10 to the 12th
So it's 256 terabytes
And as you know you can buy a disk drive now that has 8 air bites
So it doesn't seem like that much
But if you tried to buy that much dram again you'd have to have a pretty big credit-card limit
And so even that's a huge number and modern super computer installations actually will have  almost that much memory
But the point is that the hardware of today limits you to 47 bits worth of address
But that's not really a real limitation in terms of of of actual machines
And what will happen is memory prices get cheaper and the technology gets better
They'll slowly start adding as succeeding generations of processors come along
Let you have bigger and bigger range of addresses
So all that is to say that's why
This number shows up which is a seven	 followed by eleven fs
I can tell I need to scribble some numbers you guys
Aren't just saying numbers in the air is not working here
So let's try
Ok
Okay so remember I said before to 264 is about equal to 16 times 10 to the 18th
And 2 to the 47th is 128 times 10 to the 12th
So it's 128 terabytes
So what's the number after a terabyte you know 10 to the 15th
How many but yes petabytes right
And you know what 10v 18th is exha
So just as a reference a company like google roughly
It's probably it's total storage across the whole
Enterprise is measured in some small number of x bytes
And it every day is getting several petabytes I don't know the numbers are of course secret
But maybe 10 petabytes or more per day of new data that it's ingesting into its system so
These numbers are pretty huge but not just totally off the charts
Do you know what 10 to the 21st is it's called a zettabyte  with two t's
And it's estimated if you add up all the digital content in the world
That gets created everybody's cell phone camera every video
Taken by anyone anywhere  all year long is a couple of zettabytes a year
So it'll be a while before we're really having to deal with that kind of memory
So just just to give you an idea so 128 terabytes is the address limit on these systems
And so that's why you have to have seven because you remember that's one two three
And then there's f but there's 11 of them and this is one one one times 11
So that's 44 ones and this is three ones
And that's where you get 47
And that's the address of the in Linux
That's where they put the stack  is up at the very top of the address space
And I should tell you this picture is not at all to scale it would be impossible to draw this picture to scale
For example it shows that the stack starts way up at the top
And remember stacks grow to smaller addresses when you're pushing and also we show the
Them upside down just to make everything confusing
So the the stack starts there and it grows towards lower addresses
And on a typical system it will be limited to 8 megabytes
And you can tell that on a Linux system at least
With the the limit command
Which used to be more interesting than it was is now because a lot of things are unlimited
But you see it says the stack size is limited to 8192 k bytes or kilobytes
So it's 8 megabytes
And what that means is if you tried to access any memory  via the stack pointer
That was outside of the range of this 8 megabyte range you'd get a segmentation fault
And then down at the lower addresses what comes in what gets put into your program are the parts of the code
That that come out of the executable file
And so there's a section and we'll talk more when we talk about linking actually
About the way out of the memory and the different regions of it
But for some obscure reason they they call where the code is sitting the executable program  the text segment
I don't know why that's true but it's the way it is and that's across many machines
And then the data is first of all there'll be a section for the data that's allocated at the program begins
So any global variables that you've declared will be in that section
And then the heap is the part of memory that is x is allocated via call to malloc
Or one of its related functions
And so that varies dynamically as the program runs
It starts off with a very small allocation and every time you call malloc
If you're not freeing memory and so your memory requirements keep growing
It will crease keep up moving up larger and larger addresses
And then somewhere in the code - and this can vary by system is
The code that gets brought in that represents the library functions things like printf and malloc itself
Our own library code they're stored off on disk
And they get brought in they get linked into your program
When it first starts executing by a process known as dynamic linking
Which we'll talk about later in the course too with the linking
And what you'll find in general is that
Allocations will tend to be either at these very low addresses
Or these very high addresses as your program is running
So just as an example here is some code
Um that it's only value is to show you different  where things get located
And so you'll see I allocated some a fairly large arrays here
This one is there all cares but this is 2 to the 24th so it's 16
A megabyte array and this one is 2<<31
So it's 2 gigabytes worth of array
I found that if I tried to allocate larger ones it the program wouldn't run
And I also do some here's just a sort of global variable and here's a function
And then there's a single function here with some local variable
And that will be allocated somewhere on the stack
And then there's several calls to milk some of which are for some very small chunks of memory
And somewhere for some very large chunks of memory
And so we can run this program and see what addresses pop out of it
And what you'll see is the stack
This local variable is somewhere up with an address in the range of the stack
And you see the 7 and a couple fs and then it goes to something else
And you'll see also interestingly enough that the code and then looking down at the bottom
Of this yellow color is things get relegated to the text segment the main function
And this function I called I declared called useless
And then the predefined arrays
That were in other words globally declared not declared by malloc
They're declared as part of the program itself are down here in this data section
And because it's a very large array, the huge array you actually get some fairly large addresses
And then interestingly enough
Or I don't know why it's interesting but for one reason or another
It happen that the smaller chunks of memory allocations
Are down here at addresses that are actually just a little bit above  the the pink section right
And similarly the really big chunks of memory I a located
Are way up here near the stack limit
And they are
And so they're there and in general what's happening is if I were to try and reference
A memory address in this empty range I'd get a segmentation fault
It's a valid address in terms of its bit of properties
But it hasn't actually been set up and allocated by the memory the virtual memory allocator
So at any given time the valid addresses
Are just those in the lower portion or the upper portion of this address ranges
And the middle is sort of no-man's land
And then what happens is you keep allocating more with malloc
And it will push the limits of what's addressable in toward it
And in principle if you ever got too much of a memory request
If these two would hit each other and you and malik would return zero at that point
But it's highly unlikely given that you have 128 terabytes of memory address range here
So that just and you've probably seen this when you're running
You're looking at disassembled code with gdb
You're seeing some addresses that are way up here with the 7 and some f so they're stack addresses
And you see these fours
You know a lot of zeros and some fours those tend to be where the code is going
To question
Why doesn't the heat proceed in one direction I actually don't know
I'll just observe that it was had a strategy of putting big things here in small things here
And it probably uses different slightly different management strategies for those two
Okay so that I think you'll find that kind of useful to have some sense when you're looking at
When you're running gdb it helps to just have some idea of
What's going on when you're looking at these different addresses
Okay now let's talk about buffer overflow
And we'll start this you remember on the very first class
And I think we might have reviewed this part way along
We showed this example of some programs where if you do an out-of-bounds
Reference and write a value that's out of bounds in particular
I only have a array of two elements here
But this function will take an arbitrary value of i
And assign some magic number to ailment I of the array
And it has the possibility of
And we saw that when you do that
If I gets too big it will first
Corrupt the the double that stored is part of the struct
And then when it gets bigger it seems to
Not have any effect until it gets too big and then you start corrupting memory
So the basic point is that it's very easy in a program  a C program in particular
To a reference memory that's not part of the sort of intent of the program
And this can happen in programs that aren't properly written that
And it becomes a security vulnerability if there's some way for an outsider to overflow a buffer
For example if there is some way for an outsider to give a larger value of I and ask that
That value be stored there it could crash the program
And so in general when you write in code you try to think about  can I trust this value
This a value that's been computed by my program and I'm sure that it's within bounds
Or is it something that's come from an external source
And there is potentially that risk of being a vulnerability
And so in particular there's a lot a huge class of errors
That have to do with overflowing buffers where
Where they're trying to store a string of some type that's been read from a message
And without knowing in advance how big that string is
It's possible that it will be too big for the buffer that's been allocated
And so one of the culprits is there's a whole class of library functions that
Let you store something a string somewhere without any kind of bounds checking even being possible
So the sort of worst one is one called gets
And the purpose of gets is normally it's used to read a string from
An input from a terminal input something that somebody's typed into a terminal
And so what it's doing is it's scanning this input string
And looking for a character that represents the end of the line
Which we write in of cea's is backslash n
And it has a character code at hex of 0 a
And so gets this is sort of an approximate version of what the code for gets looks like
That and it's as an argument it's just given a destination of where to store the result
And all it does is it reads one character at a time
Looks for an end-of-file meaning that the input stream is closed  or an end-of-line
But as long as it until it sees that it just keeps adding more things to the end of this buffer
And so typically
When somebody calls gets they'll pass it a pointer to some buffer that they've allocated
But the function and it will just get us we'll just fill that buffer up
But it can potentially just keep going there's nothing in the function
There's not even an argument to the function
That tells the function when when it has to stop
When it's reached the limit of it
So it was written it actually get us is
If you try to compile code would get us it will flash up a big warning that says
This is really an unsafe function you probably shouldn't even be using it
Because it it has it was written in an era in the 1970s 
Even be using it  the early unix distributions were coming out
Where people just weren't worried about security vulnerabilities
And they just assumed that if you allocated a big enough buffer
That there's no reason why a string should be bigger than what you've allocated
And that's actually true with other functions like strcpy
You recall strcpy has two arguments
Excuse me a destination and a source
And its purpose is to copy the string at the source into the destination
And the way it determines the end of the string and the source is when it hits a null character
That just keeps copying one by one well until it hits it
But it has no way of knowing there's nothing no information there about how much
How big is the the buffer allocated at the destination
And so it can easily overrun that
That a similar one called stir cat which is used to concatenate two strings  copy amasian
And the scanf functions also have possible in the format string
You can give the %s
A directive to the format string which says read in a string  and store it someplace
And it doesn't say how long the string is limited to be
And it doesn't say how much memory is available at the destination
So again it can easily just write over that a buffer
So these are real vulnerabilities and they we'll talk in a minute a little later about
How you as a programmer can be a little smarter than this
But in their suit of raw form as presented they have this vulnerability to them
So let's look at an example of what this can what can happen there
So imagine for example we want a to implement echo function
So an echo function is one that you just type something in and it prints it back out
It's very uninteresting function except it's very useful to demonstrate things
So the idea is it has this little buffer it's only enough to hold four characters
Because get us to read a string from the input and then it calls puts
Which simply writes back out the output
And
And so let me just demo this not very interesting function
So I call here buff demo-nsp
Meaning as no stack protector we'll see in a minute what a stack protector is
But you see if you type a reasonably strong small string
Let's see what remember it can handle more than four
Actually as written it can't handle more than three right
Because there should be room for the null character - on terminator
So it turns out with this particular one if I type in a string of 24 characters
It'll be okay
But if I type in a string of 24 characters
It will hit a segmentation fault
So where do those numbers 23 and 24 come in
Well that's something we can learn by looking at the assembly code
So here's and we'll go through this code
So first of all this is the code for echo then
And you see the echo calls gets and it calls puts
And here's the part of the code where you can tell how much memory got allocated for the buffer
And x18 is what in decimal and you
24 right
And just saw that the thing actually segfaults with a input string of 24
So we'll see that in a minute
But anyways you can see here that it's allocating on the stack a region of 24 bytes
And it's copying that into rdi which is of course the argument forget us
So get us is being called with a pointer to a buffer of size 24
Of maximum 24 even though you saw the original declaration was just four four
Um and then it calls gets and then get us does it thing i
And just one last little bit to keep in mind is
We'll get back to them
Oh yes and remember echo
I there's a function called call echo which is the thing that calls echo
And just to keep in mind this red is the return address  for call echo
And that's going to be important
So what we see then is the memory way out is
The buff is normally big enough for four characters
There's a sort of 20 bytes of unused or wasted space here
And then the actual return address which is the return address for back to call echo is stored on the stack
So when this program int begins running when echo starts to run
We'll find that this is the value on the stack for the return pointer
And if we type in a string of up here of 23 characters
You'll see that it uses up this entire buffer and remember a string is terminated with a 0 0
But it still hasn't it's still within the region that was allocated on the stack for that
So it just barely fits into the the stack
And that's why we technically we overflowed the buffer
But we didn't really cause any harm because there was this extra space available
And so that's why I could type in that string of 23 characters and  and it worked fine
But now if I type in this is an example showing actually 25 characters
So once I go beyond the 23 characters plus the null character
You'll see what I'm slowly starting to do is
Is corrupt the the the byte representation of the return address
And so what happens for example here
Is that rather than trying to return back to the where call echo
Was supposed to where it was supposed to go back to
It goes back to some other part of your code
That may or may not be a valid address or
Might not have anything to do with the program you're trying to run
So this example shows it and if I typed in the 24
Let's see.before I got it to run
Like this you know this thing depends on the what happens
How the code happens to get compiled
Oh yeah so okay so actually you see here
This first string I typed is actually 24 characters long plus the null pointer
So uh and we'll see why it didn't it should have crashed
Because we actually overwrite wrote the low order byte of the return address
Here we typed in this is 25 characters
And so that's the one I just showed where it really whacked the two bytes of the return address
So here we actually did overflow the buffer
And let's try and figure out why that didn't harm the the program execution
I see a question
Yes it could have been various other things could have there's nothing
It hit a segmentation fault
Because it probably went to some weird part of the code and just started executing some random stuff
And just got itself into trouble
But that's the point is it's not predictable exactly what will happen when you do this
So this is that the example of what actually happened the first time
When I typed in a string that had 24 characters
And so this null byte at the end actually corrupted the return address
And so it was supposed to return back to this address 4006f6
And instead it will return back to the address 400600
Which happens to be in some other weird function that's there
And it just sort of landed at some place here
And it's doing various things but somehow it didn't really didn't crash the program
And that's one of the frustrating things about this is that  things can go wrong in a program
And they don't always cause a crash
And so often a bug that's working there might be doing some weird stuff that you don't even know about
So that's all a fine if it's just a way of crashing programs and
I mean that's not great if it's controlling your pacemaker or something like that
But if it's just a homework assignment it's like not a big deal so
I'll but what actually and this is sort of only happened since
Attacking became a normal activity which has only been the last 30 years
Is that it gives an opportunity for a hacker or a attacker
To inject code into the program and execute it
And that's what's called a code injection attack
And so that the general scheme of it is I have this buffer that I can fill up with whatever bytes I want
By feeding them to get s or whatever function is doing this copying
And what I can do then is set up and pass to it
Some bytes of actually that encode an executable a little bit of executable code
You've seen an object dump it's printing out these byte code representations of instructions
So imagine you fed some of those bites into your string
You encoded them in the string that you pass to get us
And then you might have to add some more sort of padding characters
That characters whose value doesn't matter
In order to then get a number back into the position where the return pointer is supposed to be
And so what's call that number b  it's going to be an address
One of these ones with the you know that represents a stack location
And that value b that is the the starting address of the buffer
Which happens to be where your exploit code remember this is just executable instructions
Of words stored here
So now what will happen is when the program does its return here
It was supposed to return back to wherever it got called from p
This is a typo p calls q not the bar
So it's supposed to return back to p
And we're and the address the return address was stored here
But now I've overwritten that return address  with this buffer position
So what will happen is the the program counter will happily jump to this spot
And see start executing whatever it encounters which are the instructions that you've inserted
And by that means  then you can inject code into a machine potentially
Somewhere else in the internet if you could set up a scheme like this
That would feed these bytes into that machine
And it would read it in with a function like gets
And then it would try to do its return but it would start executing your code
So that's a classic code injection attack
And in fact in this lab that you're going to start to comes out at midnight
It's called the attack lab because you're going to do this yourself
For part of the lab and I think you'll find it pretty interesting
So this used to be a huge problem  on programs
-yes
-so when you're trying to replace read how do you make sure that your new submitted read provides that exact line
Well that's part of the cleverness of being a hacker
You have to make sure it's in the right spot
But it's that's actually one of the easier parts
Because for example we did you know you have to know the binary code
To be able to do this or be able to guess
So for example in that previous one I could tell that it was allocating 24 bytes for that buffer
And so if I just made sure that the length of my exploit code plus the padding is 24 bytes
Then right after that comes the return address
So that's actually pretty easy to do
There was certainly how much memory program is that no you have to have access
You have to what the reason why this works is
It works if you have enough knowledge about the operating system that's running at the other end
For example you know it's Linux
You know that you can look at you know what gcc tends to allocate for
It you somehow have access to information about the code itself
Let's you do this
Oh so anyways this used to be a huge problem
And it started way back in 1988 the first internet attack with called the morris worm
And it at the time the internet was not a very big place
And it basically brought down a huge fraction of the machines
That were on the internet at the time
Interestingly enough cmu did not fall victim to this attack
Because we'd patched already the vulnerabilities that this particular program exploited
And that was the cause that the software engineering institute runs an organization called cert the
Computer emergency response team
And that team was set up in response to this attack the morris worm attack
Will also see an interesting example  between two companies in in messaging services
And many others it's been the sort of standard attack mechanism for many years
And fortunately nowadays there's a few things that make the attacking a less likely to be successful
And so it's not as huge a problem as it used to be
But still it's a source of many vulnerabilities in programs
So let's see I won't talk too much about this
But it used to be in the original implementation of
There's a command that most systems have now disabled that
You could finger you could across to information about
Somebody in some remote location it would send a message to that location
And then it would reply back
And it used get us the honor the actual original implementation called geddes
To read the input string from that was being sent to it
And then there is an interesting one
You guys don't remember messaging instant messaging
But before it used to be that people would talk to each other on their computers  by sending messages
Sort of like you send text messages today
But there is an interesting thing that
There's a company still exists
But it's a shadow of its former self called aol
Which ran the most popular internet services and had the most popular instant messaging program
And microsoft came out with its own client
Its own program that you could run on your machine
And communicate to other people on this a messaging system
So the microsoft code was running on your machine
But it would use the servers that were being run by aol  to manage this messaging traffic
And the funny story was over the
The this microsoft program would work fine
You can communicate with your friends who had different messaging clients  and it all seemed compatible
But then suddenly the people that were running the microsoft version of the software
It wouldn't work and then microsoft people figured out how to patch it
And then it would work for a while and then it wouldn't work
And the way what was happening was aol was using a bug in its own code
To be able to determine who's basically peek into the the machines on the client side
And do a buffer overflow attack on your code that you're running on your machine
And then basically peek around and see does this look like aol code
Or is it something or is it some foreign code
And so is basic be able to use its own security weakness to figure out this information
And that got disclosed by a sort of funny message
From somebody who called himself phil bucking
And it was determined that this email originated from somewhere within microsoft
So anyways that and you can read more about it in the book around the slide fun choice
So in general in the security world you're supposed to distinguish between the idea of a worm and a virus
Although people aren't very good at doing that
So worm is a program that can run on its own and propagate itself from one place to the other replicated
A virus is like a biological virus it doesn't live on its own
It works by attacking a program and basically modifying that program's behavior
So that gives you the basic idea of buffer overflows and you'll see it more first hand
So let's look at it techniques that machines can use to avoid
To make themself less vulnerable to these attacks
Well first of all you the application or the cert the writer on the server-side
Can write code that's more secure
So for example what you're supposed to do instead of gets
Is use a function called fgets
And fgets has a property that it it passes a parameter
Which is the maximum number of bytes that the program should read
And if there's more bytes than that in the input it will just truncate the input
So you're really supposed to use fgets and give a limit
Similarly a strncpy there is a version of it called strncopy  where you can give a limit
And with a scanf you're supposed to be careful about using the percent s
There's even a terminology you can say percent give a number
That's the maximum length of the string it should read
So these various places you can protect your code  to make sure it won't overflow buffers
Unfortunately a lot of code has been you'd call it hardening
It's been people have gone through it and it's a lot of work
Because there's a lot of places in programs where you're copying strings from one place to another
And there are a lot of real subtleties like when you're converting from unicode to bytes and so forth
That you're going back and forth between different character encodings
But for the large part and there's tools that the code developers have created to help  track down these bugs
So it's become a little bit safer out there but there's still vulnerabilities
So then there's other parts where you just try to build in safeguards into the system
That would make it much harder to do a buffer overflow exploit like I showed you
And so one of them is called stack randomization
Where it goes by a more general term
That's abbreviated a slr
Which stands for address space layout randomization
And the idea of it is to make it so every time a program runs
The addresses change  a little bit or a lot
So that you can't reliably know where things are going to be in the code
So imagine for example the and the way it's implemented is before
In the sort of run-up of your program when it first starts up
But before your main routine gets called
It will just do a allocation on the stack of some random number of bytes of storage
A fair amount like maybe a megabyte roughly of storage where the exact number is randomly chosen
And what that means is that the the dress of the stack
Of all the different positions of your ear
All the local storage on the stack will shift up and down from one run to another
And we can actually see that
In this example I showed
So I have a program here it's not a very interesting program I'll show you
Except to demonstrate these ideas
All it's doing is there's some code it's based on that one
I already showed called locate
But this one there's a global variable
There's some functions there's something that gets allocated by malloc
And there's something that is a local variable stored on the stack
And so what I'll do is show addresses that are chosen
The address of this variable then will be  a stack address a local of a local variable
Global will be this one that gets allocated globally
The heap is something allocated with malloc
And then the this function useless will count as a code address
And now when I run it
You'll see from one run to another that if some of these stay the same and some of them change
So in particular the global variable  is the same 60102c
And the code is the same 0x400590 is the same every execution
But you'll see this local variable it's on its a stack address
But you see that the lower half dozen or so bytes are actually changing from one run to another
1 2 3 4 5 so 5 bytes so that's
What 5 hex digits I'm sorry
So that's 2 to the 20th
So roughly a megabyte of variation is going on in stack addresses there
And similarly you'll see that the heap addresses are also varying from one to another
From one execution to the other
So malloc has built into it some amount of randomness to in its allocation
So why is that ik you know what's the purpose of that well
As I told you this code injection vulnerability
Relies on the fact that you can you can load up this buffer with some executable code
But somehow you have to know how to get to the start of that code
And so this is relying the attack is relying on the fact
That it can somehow predict what the this address of the buffer is
And so that it can store it in the right part of the string
Put it encode it in the right part of the string so it will show up where the return pointer is supposed to be
And and have it jump to that location
But now with this randomization
This number is varying by quite a bit
Sort of million over a range of a million or so values
So there's no way in advance
Even if I have an exact copy of the code not even had access to the system itself
And could run it
I can't predict from one run to the next where it's going to be
So that gives it sort of thoughts this particular attack
To to make it using this randomization
Another idea that's fairly straightforward
But it took a long time for the hardware people to implement this
Is well why why is there supposed to be code on the stack
In the first place isn't the code supposed to be located down in the text segment
Where it can be sort of specially identified as being executable
So in the original x86
There's a one bit flag for each region of memory
Saying is it actually - one bit flags
One is can this be written to
So that you can prevent over writes of things like string constants
And so and then the other is am I can I read it
And read means access those bytes and
It was interpreted that readable and executable were the same thing
I can read it I can execute it and that was the rules
In a sort of last 10 years or so starting first with amd and then intel
Have added a third bit that says is this executable or not
Similarly to the permissions you have on a file on unix is it readable writable executable
Those are three separate permission bits that are alone
So by simply marking the stack is not executable
It'll also fort this particular attack
Because I have to be able to execute these bytes that I've injected into the system
And then there's the final idea which is actually fairly effective -
Which they call a canary  that they built into the stack
And some of you actually encountered this code already and looking at your bombs
Because we've been getting some questions about it
So let me just give you an example here
And this one's called buffdemo-sp
Because it's been compiled with what they call stack protector
And this one on now it's the same code as before it's dis compiled a little bit differently
What you'll find is I can give a string of length eight
And not have a problem
But if I now have nine characters
It will dump out with this very strange exit error message
That is an indication
That it's detected I attempt to smash the stack
So buffer overflow is sometimes called stack smashing
So it detected somehow that even though my code was still the same old crappy code from before
Of a very small buffer allocation and no protection
Somehow the the system protected me from myself
And that's a by a relatively simple trick that's a fairly clever though
What they call stack canary
So that the term canary comes back from a back in the coal mining days of old
Before they had very good ways of measuring things they take a bird down with them in a cage
And a canary is a property that's very susceptible to dying
If there's nothing if there's methane gas present
So these miners would be down there working and they'd see their bird
Keel over and say oh we got a problem here let's get out fast
So that's why they call it a canary in a coal mine sometimes
Some kind of warning signal that that something's not not right here
And in general we see a gcc if you invoke it with a stack protector
Nowadays that's the default
So even without you saying anything this code will get built into it
And so let's look at at what that canary code looks like
And how it does its thing it's really pretty clever as I said
And some of you have already observed this strange kind of memory reference
In a register reference in the code and your boom labs
Because it was compiled with this deck protecting enabled  because that's the default
And so in particular what this code shows is it's allocating as before 24 bytes on the stack
But now it's getting some number and we'll talk in a second what that means
And storing it at position 8 offset from the stack pointer
And then the rest of the code and then it zeros it out  that's not to worry
And then it looks like the your previous code that it's passing a pointer to the stack
Top of the stack as the argument to get us
And get us it gets called and then put s gets called
But now there's some more code here that is it involves this strange-looking register
And then there's some kind of test and then if that test fails
It will call this a code that you just saw printed out this error message
So let's see what that all means
What that means is that at offset 8 from the stack pointer
It's putting in 8 bytes a value
That it's retrieving from a special register
So fs is a reference to a type of register that was created for the original 8086
And is now completely obsolete but it's still there for backward compatibility mode
But what it is it and I actually I looked and I've never fully been able to find the documentation on it
It's able to read from a part of memory
A set of values that you can't otherwise get to
And so that's the khmer canary it's getting a somehow it's grabbing eight bytes from somewhere
Storing it as this canary value
And then if you give like a seven character input
So you would affect the canary and so what happens when it returns from
The two calls from gets and puts  before it exits
What it's trying to detect is has anything as this buffer somehow overflowed
And potentially at risk of of corrupting some other part of the stack
So basically what it does is it retrieves back from the stack
What is the current value of this canary
And it's comparing it to what it should be  by retrieving that back from this special region
And if they're equal it says fine
But if they're not equal it's detecting this got corrupted so just like the canary in the coalmine
If these bytes get corrupted in any form it's an indication that something went wrong
Now that example shows that if I have a seven characters string
Then I'm not going to corrupt the canary
But you notice I just got away with an eight character string
So let me just see what's going on here
Okay I want a character e-string right
Oh wait wait wait
Ah sorry I have to look I don't have the code in front of me so I have to look at
So anyways here's where it's subtracting 24 from the stack pointer
And then the next instruction is retrieving this canary value
So let's figure out what the canary is right now we are at
72f so we're at the first instruction here
Let's do another step
So this is the canary
And it's you'll see actually when from one run to another you get a different value of it
So it's purposely put in there in a way that it's unpredictable
The one thing you'll notice is that the lower bite is zeroes
And so apparently they knew that it's so common to have suta off-by-one bugs with strings
Where you don't allocate enough space for the null terminator
That they said well rather
Than having a canary that will detect that bite being corrupted we'll just sort of give that bite away
And so that's why it's letting me type in eight characters
And it's overriding this low order byte of the canary later on
But that's not going to affect anything
Strategic but let's give it a 9 characters 10 character string  a 9 character string
All right charts mark
Oh well I'm not finding it where I thought it would be
Anyways oh this will crop this deck
But what I showing you the main idea is the canaries some value
That gets pulled out and it will vary from one time to the next
And it's letting you get away with eight characters plus the null terminator
But anything more and it will detect that corruption
Okay so now we've seen three different protection well for one is write better code
But there's three protections that are done by the system that have nothing to do with your code
Right one is to randomize the stack position
So it's harder to figure out where the start addresses are
The second is to make the stack so it's not executable so you can't put code on that
And then the third is to use a stack canary or other mechanisms to detect
A potential buffer overflow at the source
So now there's another attack that was developed in response to some of these
That is still often successful it's called return I did programming
And for your attack lab you're going to be doing these attacks too
That's why the attack lab is different than the old lab
Way of the old web justed code injection exploits now you're doing both code injection
And return oriented programming
So the idea this is if you are a hacker you're frustrated
Because of these these three techniques stack randomization non-executable stack and canaries
Well I can't fix the canary problem that actually the canary is a pretty secure technique
There's very I've never seen anyone able to bypass a stet canary
But the other two you can do it using this technique
And the strategy is so we don't know where the stack is
But we could still
But we know where the code is because you saw in that example the code
My layout randomization was shifting the stack positions in the heap positions
But it wasn't changing either global variables or or the code itself
So what if I can find some code that sort of already there in the existing part of the program
And I'll use that instead of my own code that I've injected
And of course in general you're not going to find exactly lying there the exact program
You want to execute that will cause whatever harm you intend to do
Because that's not usually compiled into most programs
But if I could set a string together little segments of code
And somehow put together a series of little sequences of code
Maybe I can get something useful done
And so that's the idea of this return oriented programming
And the idea of it is to find what are known as gadgets
And a gadget is a sequence of bytes  that are represent part of the executable program
Where the last byte this is x86 talking here  has a hex value c3
Which is how the ret instruction the return instruction is encoded  in x86 both ia-32 and x64
And so as an example
On the easy case is where there's some function
And it implements some operation that I might find useful as an attacker to be able to do
So for example this function is computing a times b plus C
And if I look at just the last two instructions from there one of them is a la which is performing addition
And the other is doing a return
So I can think of this this good old five bunk byte chunk
Is a way if I could get some data in registers r di and rdx
Then I could compute their sum and stick it in %rax
So imagine taking your program you're trying to execute
And breaking it up into these good old fragments
And you want to somehow find little block of code somewhere to implement each of these fragments
And then the interesting part is because they each end in C 3 this return
It has is it well let me get to that in it
So that's sort of the obvious way that you pull out this is an addition which you'd expect
Because that was in the original C code
But here's an example of a gadget that has nothing to do with the original C code
It just happens to match the bite pattern of of some existing code
So this function seems to not do anything too terribly useful  from a hackers point of view
But if you look at this particular byte sequence
That happens to encode the instruction move q are %rax to %rdi
And C 3 encodes repped
So and you can see if this is at address for d9
That's for da for db for dc
So at address 4004dc
If you could start executing here it would first do a move and then it would do a return
So I'm sort of taking advantage of the fact in x86 it's this buy donated instruction sequence
And if I sort of go off the aligned instructions I can often find useful things to do
So that's what's called a gadget
And you might ask well what's so special about having them end in a return
Well imagine I could fill up my buffer instead of with executable code
I could fill it up with a series of gadget addresses
So each gadget then is some series of bytes where the final byte is c3
And I'll actually position this
And not the oppositionists at some place
Where you're actually going to do the initial return instruction of from before
So if I can somehow get the program to return execute a rest
Right now what it will do is return will pick an address off of the stack
Pop an address and begin executing
So that will start this code executing
And it will hit the c3 the ret instruction at the end
Which will again take a address pop it off the stack and begin executing
So we'll start executing the second gadget
And so you'll see what will happen is we're effectively concatenating these pieces of code together
Where it's using a rep to get from one part the end of one gadget to the start of the next
And so that's why it's called return oriented programming
It's a way to instead of sequencing programs using a program counter like you normally do
Your sequencing programs using the sort of peculiar behavior of this particular x86
How returns work and in that program
And remember there's enough x86 out there that if I can find a way to attack them
I'm in pretty I'm in a pretty good place
It's also possible to attack other processors this way -
It's just particularly nice on x86
So that's the idea of return oriented programming
And you'll do this yourself you'll find gadgets string them together to do different things in the attack way
But I'll point out that this still doesn't so that
This stack canary idea is still successful detecting a buffer overflows  fairly effectively
So in your attack lab for example
We've carefully compiled the code to make it vulnerable to these attacks
Otherwise it would be a lot harder web
Like if you could do this you could probably go into the dark world and be very successful
So we're actually sort of exposing the vulnerability
But in the the first part of the lab you're using code injection attacks
So we've had to disable stack randomization and also make the stack x cutable
So we had to sort of button the return rated programming  we reenable that
So that the stack is not executable it keeps jumping around randomly
But we've turned off the stack canary
So you'll be able to overflow the buffer
And put in your gadget addresses and build up attacks that way
So I think you'll find by actually doing it you'll earn a lot more than you can by just hearing about it
Oh you might ask why do we teach you this stuff right
And if we supposed to teach you to be good and not evil
Well there's a couple reasons one is you're going to learn a lot about machine program execution
And how stacks work and how byte instructions are encoded and stuff like that
You'll use the tools gdb object dump and all those even more than you did with the bomb lab
So you'll learn a lot the other is we assume that you will work for forces of
But to be a good person you also know what the bet have to know what the bad people do
So part of it is to become more effective as a force for good
Okay so the final thing to talk about today is unions
And the observation about a union nc is the declaration of it looks a lot like a struct
Where there's these different fields and they're named and they can have different types
And there can be pointers to unions and all that stuff
But they're actually totally different what they do
You recall with a struct what happens is it allocates enough memory for all the fields to coexist
And potentially adding padding bytes for what a union does is it
Only k allocates enough storage for the maximum field in it
And it assumes that you're only going to be using one of the possible fields
And it will literally a store on top of it these fields get stored on top of each other
So that if you try to use multiple fields you can mess things up
And it's not for that purpose of doing multiple values
It's for the purpose of for example if I know I'm only going to use one of these
Or it's another also a way to create essentially an alias that will let you reference memory in different ways
So for example in your data lab you are using
You were manipulating the bit level representations of floating point numbers
And in our code that would then convert that to an actual float
We used a union
Where the union is either to view this field of four bytes is an unsigned or is a float
And so I can convert from unsigned to its float representation by just storing the unsigned value  in this union
And retrieving it as if it were float
And this is a fundamentally different operation than casting
Because you recall when you take a unsigned value and you cast it to a float
You actually change the bits
You change it into the floating point number that's the closest a match to this particular number
It would be the equivalent of the function you implemented float underscore u2f
But this one actually doesn't change bits it just changes the numeric value changes quite a bit
So it's a useful technique to do that to be able to override the the type system and get two bit representations
And this actually turns out to be one of the places to where byte ordering
Will show up in programs if you're not careful
So in particular with this union I can view a block of eight bytes
As either eight characters for shorts two ents or one long
And on a 64-bit machine like is shown here where along is 64 bits
You'll see that you're you're able to look at things as either as a the individual bites making it up
Or some longer aggregation of those bites
And you'll actually find that depending on what machine you run it on
You'll get a different result because of the byte ordering of the different machines
So this goes through it what happens when you run on different machines
But you'll you'll notice in particular that
On an i-32 machine a 32-bit machine
It's coming off in in this byte pattern f3f2f1f0
And on a sun back when they existed you'd get the opposite because of the byte ordering
And now on an x86 64 where a
Along is 64 bits you get eight bytes
And you can also determine from this if you look carefully that it's in
It's a little endian order because this is the we significant byte is f 0
Which is the first byte f 0
So it's also way to to get to the low level bytes
But when you use this kind of thing you're sort of intentionally telling the  the C compiler
Trust me I know what I'm doing you don't have to protect me from myself
And so if you're not careful you can write code where
Because of a byte ordering problem or something like that
Won't run properly on some machines
So just to summarize then we looked on it
We've looked then at the three compound types in c
The ways you can aggregate smaller types into larger ones
You can make an array of identical elements indexed by a number the position
And that usually turns into some kind of scaled computation to get to the particular place
We've seen structures where it's a fixed number of fields
But the fields can be of different type and the reference by their names
And that usually turns into some type of displacement off of the original position
And then a union is just a way of sort of piling up in one place
Of what a number of different fields
And so all it does is ellicott the maximum number of bytes
For that and doesn't create enough space for them all to be there at the same time
Okay that's it for today then [applause]