So today we're going to continue our study of virtual memory
By looking at more detail at how how address translation works
And then we'll learn about how virtual memory works on real systems on Linux and x86-64 systems
And that the payoff for that is that you'll really be able to now understand how fork and exec really work
And how how vital the virtual memory system is due to these sort of the entire working of the system
So let's look at some specific examples of how we do address translation
And here's that reference slide
So let's suppose we have this simple memory system with 14-bit virtual addresses
12-bit physical addresses
Page size of 64 bytes
So in our we have so we need six vpo bits offset bits
And then the remaining bits are the virtual page number
And similarly for our physical addresses we need
We need six offset bits and the remaining bits form the physical page number
Okay now our that the TLB in this in this system has 16 entries
And it's 4-way set associative
So remember that the TLB caches page table entries
Okay and those page table entries are uniquely identified by the virtual page number
So we only need to use the vpn to to access entries in the in the TLB
We have 16 entries 4-way set associative so there's a total of four sets
And so we use the low order the two low order bits and the vpn as the index
And then the remaining bits just like any other cache or the tag bits
Okay and then this we've initialized this with some some various values
Notice that the actual contents of the the TLB are in this read in this region here right
So the the set this is just to help identify what set there there is no entry called  set with a value of zero
Right we just will just we're just identifying that as it and
Say yeah just--we're just explicitly listening the index
And so each of our entries in the TLB consists of this tag
And if that if the TLB entry is valid a physical page number
Okay now
We also need a page table so we'll have
We'll assume that we have this page table with them we're just showing the first 16 entries
And the each page table entry consists of a physical page number
And a valid did
If valid bit is on then then that indicates that the page is in memory and
And the ppn field gives the physical page number
Okay and again there's there's no actual this vpn column doesn't actually exist in the page table
Okay and now we have a simple simple direct mac direct mapped cache
It's addressed with physical addresses
Like and it contains 16 sets each with one line
And we'll assume a four byte block size
So we have
So we have a four byte block size so we need to offset bits  for the cache
16 sets we means we need for cache index bits
And then the remaining bits are for the tags
Now just it's just an accident in the way that I define this the system that
The cash tags are exactly the same as the physical page number so this
This this is just the coincidence and it doesn't isn't necessarily that way
Okay now with the magic of av audio-visual systems
Switch good
Okay so let's we're going to look at this a couple examples using this this little system
Okay now so let's suppose the cpu executes is an instruction that generates an effective address
It's a virtual address of 0x03d4 and then
It passes that to the MMU
Which is needs to figure out the the
Corresponding physical address and then it needs to fetch the data  from cache or memory
Ok so let's the first thing we do
Is we just write out the bits for this virtual address
Okay and then we identify the different fields ok so we have the offset virtual page offset bits
And then the remaining bits or the virtual page number
Okay the offset in this case is
2,4 0x24
The vpn is f
And then we have that the two TLB I bits
Which are 11 so 3
And then we have the tag bits which are also equal to 3
So the first thing that the MMU does given this address is it checks the TLB
On hoping that the page table entry that it needs is cached in the in the TLB
So it goes extracts the index bits 3 and that that gives us
So now that
That says that if if this page table entry is in the TLB it's going to be in set 3
Ok so so we go to set 3
And now we're looking for an entry in set 3 with a with a tag of 3
Okay so we go across this one there's 4 entries in this
Here's a entry with the tag of seven so that's not ed and plus the valid bit zero
Oh here's a here's an entry with a tag of three and  a in a valid bit of one
So we're luck we lucked out the page table entries in the TLB
And so the the TLB returns the value
The the physical page number which is zero d back to the MMU
Which can now construct the the physical address
So it constructs that physical address pa
By copying directly copying the vpo bits
To the ppo bits okay
Right as we discuss the last time that the virtual page offs that's always identical to the physical page offset
Because the block sizes in the virtual address space and the physical address space are the same size
Okay so here so we get the low order ppo bits and then
The physical page number which came which comes from the PTE that's cached in the TLB is 0xd
And so that forms the ppn bits of the physical address
So they cut these these now constitute our our physical address
So now the next step once we have the physical address is to look
To send that to the cache and ask the cache to return the value at that address
And in this case we're just doing one byte accesses okay
So we're asking the cache to return the byte that's in this at this physical address
Okay so the the cache
Of course it first checks to see
If that if the the byte that's requested is contained in some block in the cache
Okay so we so it it takes in it extracts the cache index bits
Which is 0 0 1 0 1 so 5
And so if this if this byte that's being requested is in the cache.it's going to be in set 5.so we go to set 5
And then we're looking for a tag of 0xd
And lo and behold here's we have a matching tag and about matching valid bit
So the good the line that we're that we request that is is in the cash
And the word that the word that we requested is at offset 2
Okay so we go to
So this is offset one
This is offset 2
Oh no I'm sorry
Let's see what
Oh I'm sorry it's
It I was getting confused the into these are the index bits so the offset is actually 0
Here's the this is the this is our physical address
Okay and the and the the value of that offset is zero
So we're asking for the in the fifth set we're asking for the the byte at offset zero
And that's 0x36
So we have a hit the cache returns that byte back to the MMU which which passes it back to the processor
Which stores it in a register most likely
Ok so let's look at another example
And I've recorded these here for you if you want to go back in and look at them
Let's look at another example this would
So this time the cpu sends a virtual address of 0x0020 to the MMU
Ok and so if we if we write out the bits for for that virtual address
We get we get we get this result and then we mark off the virtual page offset the virtual page number
And the TLB index low-order bits of the virtual page number and the and then the tag for the the TLB t
So as step 1 same as before check with the TLB let's see if that  page table entries in the TLB t
In the in the in the TLB
So we're asking in this case
This set if this if this page table entries in the in the TLB it will be in edit it will be in set 0
And it will have a tag of 0
So we look we look in set 0 for a tag of 0
Now this doesn't match o3
Here's oh nine that doesn't match
Zero zero matches but the valid bits 0
So this isn't a valid entry it's just a coincidence that this tag was was 0
So this is a TLB miss
Ok so that's a bummer because now we have to go off the chip
And make an expensive memory access to read that page table entry from the the page table
So now we have to so now we have to check with the the page table
And we're looking for virtual page virtual page zero
So we check the entry at virtual page zero to see if that page
If that page is in memory
And if so if it has a valid and if it is in memory because the valid bits one
So this so we have a valid physical page number so
The memory returns the page table entry or the the ppn back to the the back to the MMU
Which is a it's a 0x28
And now the mm you can use that
That physical page number to construct the the physical address
So as before we copy the virtual page offset  directly into the physical page offset
And then our ppn is is to 8  so we have 1 0 its to 1000 8
So now concatenated that those form the the physical address
And now the MMU has a physical address that it can hand off to the cache
And request that the cache return that value at that at that physical address
So now the the cache gets that physical address
And it it extracts the cache index bits
Which in this case are 8 okay 0x8
So if this the block if the word that we're looking for is contained in the cache
I'm sorry if the byte that we're looking for is contained in the cache it'll be in set 8
Ok so we go so the cache goes to set 8
And it looks for a matching tag which in this case is
It turns out that it's 28 just like the ppn just by coincidence
So in in set eight we have a tag of we have an entry the block has a tag of twenty four so there's a miss
Okay so this is a cache miss and now the cache has two requests past that physical address to the memory to fetch that byte
Yes
How do ya the question is how do you know how do you determine the size of the virtual page offset
And yes it's based on the page size
[student speaking]
It was 64 bytes
So 64 bytes so that that's why we have six 6vp  oh and ppo bits
Okay so is that clear to everybody that
That's a kind of thing that sometimes turns up on exams  you know just
Yes any relationship between the length on physical page number and the cashback
That one okay so the question is is there any relationship between the length of the physical page number  and the cash tag
This was just a complete coincidence
Okay it just happened it was just a coincidence they normally they don't necessarily have to line up like that
Any other questions
Yes yes um so
For instance if I'd had more sets in my cache then I need more bits and they'd spill over right
If if my it was just a coincidence because I had six ppo bits
And just a block size of four and four sets
So if I if my cache had more sets the cache index would spill over and then the cache tag
Wouldn't match up with the physical page number okay
So were like in this case
That's that's right it's similar to the question before and it just happened to be a coincidence
Maybe I should have chosen a different example but they're completely independent
Everybody else good okay
Okay so now I want to I want to talk to you about how
How this stuff all works in a real system in this case it's a core i7 system from intel thin x86-64
It's a family of high-end desktop systems x86-64
If you are similar to the the shark machines that you use  to do your labs
So here's the here's the way the memory system looks and none in the core i7
The processor package is the chip
Okay so that's like a single and then and then there's four cores  in this package
Each core is a separate as a separate cpu and canary executes instructions separately
Okay so each call each each of these cores has a register file
And then a some hardware that fetches instructions
It has two l1 caches there's a data cache called the d cache
Which is used to fetch data
And which holds data fetched from memory and then there's an instruction cache called an ai cache
Which holds instructions fetched from the code the code region
So data this the d cache has data only the ai cache has  instructions only
There each 32 k bytes 8 way set associative so they're very small
But they have fairly high associativity
And then the next level in the hierarchy is a an l2
So called unified cache because they can  hold both instructions and data
Okay it's a little bit bigger 256 k bytes and also eight-way associative
And so both of these caches are on the on the core itself
Ok
And then outside and enters an l3 cache which is shared by all cores
Which is 8 megabytes and 16 way associative
Okay so the access is because the l1 cache is closest to the processor
This is this is fast this is like four cycles to access l1
L2 is bigger and a little further away so it
The it's about 10 10 cycles to access this
And l3 is off the core right so it has to go over a connection
Some connection off the off the chip into this into this cache
And so the the access time for this l3 cache is like 50 30 to 50 cycles
Now the the MMU has it also has a hierarchy of TLBs
And I was talking with a student after class the last lecture night
I mistakenly said that the the system didn't have a hierarchy of TLBs
But it does there's a a small l1 data TLB and  a and a separate instruction TLB
So the this has 16 64 total entries and it's 4-way set associative
So how many sets are there then in this
How many sets in the l1 data TLB
16 right good
And then the an inch the instruction TLB has more entries interestingly so
So it's it's an interesting decision I guess the I guess the thinking
I don't I don't really know I'm just trying to conjecturing that the reason
They would make the instruction TLB bigger is that the the penalty for missing on instructions would be much larger
But yeah I'm not sure it's an interesting decision and then there's a there's a unified TLB below that
Which is a larger larger still
So the I think if you're wondering I mean it's interesting to think like why do they have these
Like like these second-level caches why didn't they just make these out the l1 cache is bigger right
And in the case of the in the case of the d cache and the I cache
Over here I'll show you in
It just a little bit if you hang on there's a really interesting reason why
They can't make these things bigger or much bigger right there
There's a so there's there's a there's a property of the
They're sort of they're constrained in the in the size of the offset and index bits  in these these caches
And it's interesting I'll show you in a second
For that for the TLB
I mean one reason that comes to mind for why they didn't why they have the second level is that
If they decided just to make the l1 data d TLB
And itl b's bigger you know take the take the transistors that they used for this l2
And and just give them to the the level one TLB s
It you're kind of by partitioning those by partitioning those those
That storage ahead of time you're kind of locking yourself in
So if if you didn't have this level two TLB and and
You just increase say you gave half and so it made l 1 and l the data TLB an instruction TLB twice as big
Then you're sort of locking yourself in right if if
If you run you might run out of you still might run out of instructions and
And have capacity misses in that in that l1 cache
I'm saying similarly for data right so you're not sure
You may in a particular program there mate there may be a lot more data
Page table entries than instruction page table entries in or vice versa
So by by creating the second level of a cache
You're kind of hedging your bets right so you may the miss penalty
When you have this l2 cache the miss penalty in l1
Isn't nearly as big as it would be if because if you didn't
Okay so that
That that's sort of the thinking that goes on
Now there's a there's a memory controller which count which fetches data from memory
And then there's links to other cores into the i/o bridge
Now m2n so it's really interesting so
It's interesting to see how this all fits together end to end
So let's let's let's look at it so the cpu generates a virtual address
In intel systems the virtual addresses are 48 bits
We have 4 k sized blocks so 12 offset bits
And then 36 vpn bits
So first we look in the in the cache I mean in the TLB and
There's as we said before there's 16 TLB sets
This is the l1 I'm showing the l1 data TLB
So we break it up into 4 TLB I index bits and 32 tag bits
So we do a lookup on the in the TLB to see if we can find that
The PTE that contains that the corresponding physical page number for this virtual address
If we have a hit then the MMU can just construct
The physical address directly by copying as we saw before copying
The gpo to the ppo and then using the ppm that was returned from the TLB
How's that for an out acronym
So if there's a TLB miss
Then the system has to fetch the the corresponding ptn from the page table
Using that multi way lookup we looked multi level lookup we looked at before out
And I'll show you how this works in a little more detail coming up
But the end result is that a page table entry is located and
The ppn is extracted from that and concatenated with the ppo to form the physical address
Then the MMU passes that physical address to the cache
The l1 data cache has 64 sets
So we need six cache index bits
Now here's what I was alluding to before notice that the number of cache index and cache offset bits
Is exactly identical to the vpo in the virtual address
Okay so the the cache offset and index bits in the physical address
Are identical to the the dpo the offset bits in the virtual address
Ok and this is not a coincidence ok unlike that other example I showed you this is not a coincidence
And this is sort this is at the root
This is at the root of why the l1 cache is so small
Is that the way the way intel implements their cache lookups
Which we'll see in a second depends on the cache index and cache offset bits and the physical address
Being identical to the offset bits and the virtual address
Anyway so then we do our cache
We do our cache look up using the the cache doesn't look up using the using this physical address
Takes the index bits to identify asset
Uses the tag to see if there's a match
If there is then we have a hit which returns the resulting word back to the cpu
Otherwise there's a miss so then the cash has to request the data from l2 l3 and main memory eventually
Worst case that that data comes from main memory
So I guess worst case it comes from disk right if you have page miss page hope
So eventually though the data the data comes back and is returned back to the cpu
Now that the page table entries on in intel systems have the following structure
You can see that the the level the level one page
Which levels the level 1 through 3 pages
Remember that that page table entry points to the address of the next level page table ok
So it contains the level 1
The level 1 PTE contains the base address the physical address of the level 2 table and so on
There's a there's a bit this is the valid bit they call it the pvp for present
So this identifies whether that the page is in memory or not if it's not then it's
Then there's a the location of it of that page table on disk
There's bits that control whether the that page table can be
Read as it is read-only or it can be written
This corresponds to all reachable pages
So you know you can so all reachable pages so all all of the portion of the address space
That's covered by this particular page table entry
There's also a bit that indicates whether users can can access that or if they need to be running in kernel mode
So this this is how the kernel protects its code and data from from user programs
There's a there's a bit here to indicate whether we should be using write back or write through for this
For these page tables and all the systems I know of use use right back just because of the miss penalty
The enormous miss penalty
Forget what cd does
There's a there's a reference bit  which is set when the MMU reads or writes
Reads or writes that pit the the page table at this points to
And there's and then there's a there's a bit that indicates whether that the page size is either four k bytes or four megabytes
Okay and then there's this there's this new disabled
It's the xd bit which which disables allows you to disable or enable execution
From all the pages reachable from that page table entry
So this is how the stack modern systems protect the stack from code injection attacks
Ok the last level page table entry points to a four it points to not another page table
But actually a page in memory ok
And so the same we have the same bits here the same 40 bits that
That give the physical address of that page in memory
And then we have the indication of whether that page is is present in memory or not
And the rewrite and x and permission execute permission bits
Right through a write back
There's a reference there's this reference bit and then there's a dirty bit which the MMU sets
When it writes to that page ok
So this is how this is how the os knows that it needs to
When it selects this if it selects this page as a victim it
It looks at the dirty bit to see if it needs to write that page back
Did you have a question
Have the protection that are being provided by the new sarcastic versus jax oh excuse me net
You can't execute any instructions
You can't load any instructions from that page okay
The this user or supervisor mode it determines
Whether you can access that page so if it's set to supervisor mode only the kernel
Can can access that page anything on that page
If it's set to you then anybody user code and kernel code can access that page
Any other questions
Okay so then the the way it does address translation then is
The physical for this process so the kernel for each process maintains
The you know set of page tables of course
And then it in it maintains the address of the first 11 one table
In a register called cr 3
Ok and this is a physical address
Points to the base of the level 1 page table
The the vpn is broken up into 36 divided by 4  equals 9 bits
That give offsets into each page table entry absolutely
Okay so so there's two to the ninth potential page table entries in each in each pay in each of these different page tables
So the this vpn one is used the high order nine bits are used to compute an offset into the into that table
And you can see each each level one PTE covers a swath of memory that's 512 gigabytes in size
So you can see for most most programs that exist today
You only need one level one page table entry that to be initialized that would cover
You know the vast majority of your programs
The the next nine bits it
So the page table entry in the level 1 the page table points to the it gives the physical address  of the level 2 page table
And then the vpn bits in the the virtual address are used to compute an offset into that table and so on
It just cascades and then finally the last the low-order bits of the nine bits of the vpn
Are used to form an offset into the level 4 page table
Which in which each each PTE points to an actual page
It gives a physical page number
So then that that physical page number then is extracted
And concatenated with the vpo which we copied down to form a physical address
Okay so that everybody good
Okay now there's this there's this cool trick which
I was alluding to earlier that limits the size of l1 cache
Now to this point we've been we've
Been using a model where that the MMU takes the verge does address translation and
Creates a complete virtual address a physical address
And then it sends that physical address to the cache
Okay but in reality intel does this cute trick to speed up l1 cache accesses
So what in reality what happens so we're given a virtual address
Okay and in this virtual address the index and offs the physical
The index and offset bits in the physical address  are identical exactly correspond to the ppo in the physical address
Which is exactly identical to the dpo and the virtual address
So that means is that when the the MMU is given a virtual address
It can send the vpo off to the l1 cache
Even though it's of even though l1 is is phys is it is physically addressed
We can send the the vpo in the virtual address to the l1 cache because of this
Because of this phenomenon that the the ppo is identical to the vpo
So even before the MMU is doing any address translation
It can send this these these vpo bits to the cache
And then the the cache can get busy extracting the index the cache index bits
Looking up you know looking up all of the the lines
In that in that set
And then have everything ready for the tag check
Which can only occur after the address translation happens
So it can only occur once there's a physical address with a
From which we can extract the the cash tag
So this so there's a little bit of parallelism now in the l1 cache accesses
So we can be the MMU you can be doing address translation while
The the l1 cache gets going on it's it's lookup
Okay so now let's look at how Linux implements virtual virtual memory
And in doing so will now get a clearer understanding of how fork and exec and loading really work
Okay so we've seen this pictures of picture like this several times before
This is the virtual address space of the Linux process
Because we have because of the way the virtual memory system works every process has a very similar-looking
Address space that program text the code is always loaded at the same  0x400000 address
And that's followed by initialized data which comes from the .data  section of the the executable binary
And then there's a bss section which contains uninitialized data
That was that was defined in the binary and
Then the heap then the heap grows up from from the initialized data
There it's pointed to by a global variable called in a global variable in this process context called break
So the kernel keeps track of  where the top of the heap is for this this process
There's a memory mapped region for shared libraries
And then at the top of the users the user level user user-accessible memory
There's this user stack which grows down and which is pointed to by rsp
And then the that the kernel code and data live up in the upper portion of the address space
Now this picture isn't completely accurate there's actually like a big gap
Between the top of the stack and the beginning of the the colonel code and data
I'm the reason for that is that the intel architecture says that that
So there's 48 virtual address bits right
So if so that's it's the high-order bit of that 48 bit address  is 0 then
All the all the remaining bits have to be 0
All of the all of the height the remaining 6 the remainder of the 64 high order bits need to be 0
So it's kind of like sign extension right and if that if that high order bit and the 48 bit address  is 1
Then you extend the the 1 all the way up to the remaining high order bits
Okay so those are the only feasible bits so what that does is it creates a
That the colonel's living the colonel's living in in a portion of the virtual address space where that the 12
The 12 high order bits are all ones okay
So that creates so you can think of it this is the colonel lives in the very top of the 64-bit address space
Okay another way to think of it in colonel addresses always start with one
The most significant bit is 1 and user addresses always have a most significant bit of zero
Key that's just the detail doesn't doesn't really affect things
But with him what is important is that
This this is the process virtual address space of a process right and so
The kernel exists in the virtual address space of each process in it
So there's there's kernel code and data
And then it also maps it has a region of its virtual address space that map's
Each element of this of this region with an address in physical memory
Ok so that this this mapping this region is is  corresponds to the amount of DRAM on the chip
And so it's a mechanism that the kernel uses to get access to physical addresses
Ok and this is important because remember the kernel there you can never you can't turn off address translation
Right it's always happening
Ok even even when the kernel runs the address translation is happening the kernel is generating virtual addresses
So this this this this this region this is map to a region of physical memory
So that if if the kernel accesses bytes 0 of this of this block
It will it will actually be the the the the address that the corresponding physical address will be 0
And if it accesses a byte at an offset of 1 in this region
The physical address the corresponding physical address from the address translation process will be 1
Ok so basically by reading and writing into this region the kernel is reading and writing into physical memory
And this so there's portions of the kernel
That are identical for every process right
The codes the same it's not in
But then there's there's process specific data structures that
That the kernel maintains for each process that the context for that process
So we refer to these refer to all these with all these data structures as the the context
And these of course have to be these would be different for each process
Now Linux or organizes this this virtual address region
As a collection of what it calls areas
An area is like a segment think of it as just a chunk of a contiguous chunk of related memory items
So the there's a there's an area for code there's an area for data
Shared libraries have areas there's an area for the stack
And it it contains there's a structure for each process called the task task struct and
This contains a pointer to the mm struct which has a bunch of stuff in it but the
It contains the the address of the level one page table
Okay so that's part of the context when this process runs
When this process is scheduled the kernel will take this entry this pgd entry and he'll copy it into cr3
Okay so that's how it switches just by changing the cr3 register the kernel changes the address space
So that's how and once once that once that cr3 value is changed then
The process no longer has access to the previous processes page tables right so
And then there's a and then there's a pointer to a list of these these so-called area structs
The area struct identifies the start at the beginning and end of the region
Any protections like is this read-only region
For example so the code the code section would be set as read-only or is it read right
And enter some other some other flags we'll see
Which we'll see later
In particular when we when we look at sharing and mapping for our purposes
These these flag bits tell us whether the page is shared with other processes or whether it's private to this this process
So normally the default is that pages are all private
But you have the option if you do if you do a fair amount of work you can get processes to share memory
Okay so let's look at what happens when we have a page fault
So let's say so there's you know the processor issues and instruction the address translation process determines that the corresponding page
Isn't contained in memory
So it triggers a page fault
And so the fault handler there's several up there are several things that might have happened
One maybe we were reading memory it faulted because that that memory that area doesn't even exist
We haven't even created the kernel hasn't even created allocated that that page in virtual memory yet
Okay so that's an error so that's accessing a non-existing page elicits a seg fault
So the kernel figures that out because it runs down this list of various trucks
And it it doesn't find this address anywhere within the ranges of those areas
So that's that's a segfault caused by accessing a non-existing page
Another possibility is that the instruction is attempting to write into a read-only section segment of the virtual address space
Well they this that there's nothing in the page table the MMU typically would check the  the permission bits
In the in the page table entry and throw an exception if the write is trying to to write  to a read-only page
But in this case that there was no page table entry
Right at the trick that's why I triggered a page fault
So the MMU doesn't know that this is an illegal right
The colonel can check the protection for this area
And if if in the kit in the case of text that will be set to read only
So that triggers a protection exception
Which actually Linux reports as a segfault
And then then the other option is that maybe we're trying to read data from a valid from a valid area
So then the kernel faults that the requested page in
And and returns the requested data back to the back to the cpu
Okay the last thing I want to look at today is is it yes
[student speaking]
Okay s-sorry
Yeah so all of the segments are contained in the executable file
Okay there's a at the at the beginning of the elf binary
There's a list of all the all the different segments
Okay so when it went it when eggs act loads the binary creates it creates areas for each of those each of those segments
Good yes
So like you so easily it is still first checks like you just have you it gets but it's just like once it
This is after the page fault
Yes
The MMU doesn't know about these
Okay so yeah the question is exactly how are these areas structs use
And they're used they're used in this in this content in this example anyway they're used during the page faults
Okay and also just as a an aside
I've shown these actually are implemented as list
But in the real system they use some kind of tree red black tree or something like that
Okay so I want to talk about the last thing we're going to look at today is
This is this this interesting idea called mapping and
It will help us understand a lot about what's going on in the system when it executes fork and exec
So vm areas are initialized by associating them with disk objects
Okay and so this this process in a using a process known as memory mapping right
So the every every area and thus every page within that area is associated with some portion of a file
And it's that and that's the initial contents of the pages in that area come from that file
Okay so the the an area can be backed by what we call or get its initial values from either a regular file on disk
So this we saw this so in the case of pages that are containing code
That that area that has a code is mapped to a portion of the executable binary
Okay and then the initial values of that area come from that executable binary file
Okay so that's how that's how we get that's how we get data copied
Back and forth from or from executables into into memory
The file can also be an anonymous file meaning
It's a file it's an it's some anonymous file that consists of all zeros
It's an anonymous file of arbitrary size that consists of all zeros
And so of course it doesn't exist this is just a trick
So this allows us to create pages that are initialized to all zeros
Okay and then so the if a page is associated with the anonymous file
Then the first fault will alec a physical page of all zeroes
So this is called the demand zero page
Okay so it's brought in on demand and it's initialized to zero
Once now once an anonymous once a file wants a page that's backed by an anonymous file
Is written to or dirtied then it's like any other page okay and
Then dirty pages are copied back and forth between memory and a special swap flow
Now you remember in normally processes don't share anything with each other
Okay but it's possible using this idea of mapping for processes to be mapped to the same objects
So suppose that we have we have two processes with their own separate virtual address spaces
And the pages in these two processes are being mapped to portions of physical memory
So let's say there's a an area a segment in process one
That's been mapped to this to this object so to this portion of a file
Okay now process 2 can also map to that same that same object
And notice even at a completely different virtual at virtual address
So there's no there's no relationship between
The region of this virtual address space that's mapped to the shared object in process 1
And the region of the virtual address space in process 2 that's mapped to the same object
And the kernel because these these objects have unique names right their files
The kernel can can check the other processes to see if any other processes are mapping to that object
And if so map this region of the virtual address space to those same physical pages
Ok so now we have a situation
Where each process is accessing some chunk of its virtual address space
And those accesses are actually being done on the same region of physical memory
So this might be useful you might imagine um you know say these processes are servers
You know say you've worked a bunch of copies of apache
You might want to have some kind of shared cache
Maybe a shared memory cache between those all those different copies
So this this would be in this case your cache would be a file
A file on disk and then as you as you access regions of that file
Those pages get copied into physical memory
So that would allow you to have a shared cache in in the in the memory across all those all those processes
Now
Sometimes there's another objects can also be private meaning they shouldn't be shared ok across processes
And there's a special an especially interesting kind of private object called the private copy-on-write object
So the the idea here and you'll see when this will become very important when we look and see how fork actually works
The idea is that we have an object
That's it we have two two processes that are mapping to the same object
But instead of instead of this being a shared object it's what we call this this private copy-on-write object
And just like before these two regions of the virtual address space
Map into the same region of physical memory
But they're tagged using the and this is where those flag bits come in
There they're the pages in this area are flagged as private copy-on-write
Okay now what that means is normally if this was a shared object
Let's say this was a shared object and processed to wrote did a right into this region of the virtual address space
If this was a shared object that right would also be reflected on the disk on the file on disk
But if it's if it's if it's flying this instead of being shared
If that if that area this area is marked as flagged as private copy-on-write
Then if if process to does a write to a page in that area
Then instead of it reflecting that change in physical memory and on the the shared object
It makes a copy of that of that page
A separate copy of that page and maps it to some unused portion of the physical address space
Okay so that's why that's why we have the name copy on right
So if we but if we read if we read values from this area
Nothing happens it just it will just read from the this portion of the physical address space
Okay it's only when we do a write to some page
In an area that's flagged as private copy-on-write
It's only when we do that right that the system first makes a copy of that page
And then does the right
Okay now why on earth would why on earth would anybody want to do this
Actually this this notion of copy-on-write is is another one of these
Kind of fundamental important system concepts that's used a lot
Whenever you want to share things efficiently yes
Right then you don't know love which one two and three ready to thank you can you get some tissue if you didn't do this if you
Well although the rights all go through
Yeah the memory system okay this is a really really good question
And it's it's beyond our scope but the memory system takes care of those
And it provides some guarantees
So it the memory system you're right it's receiving from multiple cores
It's receiving multiple multiple instructions multiple addresses
And the memory system itself takes care of sort of providing some ordering on those
And it provides it provides some sort of non-trivial guarantees on what you can assume the ordering is but
That's a that's a pretty a pretty complicated topic that we'll get into
It's called the consid it's called the consistency model
Right so every every processor provides some kind of consistency model
Any other questions
Okay so why is this copy-on-write technique useful and interesting
Well it turns out I mean if you if you think about fork
It seems like it would be terribly expensive right you have
If you want to fork a process you know the naive way to do it would just be to copy
You'd have you have to somehow get us exact copy of the address space
But a separate a separate copy of the address space that's identical
So if you approach this naively you'd have to make copies of all the page tables
All of the other data structures and you'd also have to copy all the memory
Right so if you're you know if you're forking a process that's created a huge number of virtual pages
And it's address space
Those would all have to be copied to and mapped to different portions of the physical address of the memory
Okay so you'd have it would be very expensive right
Potentially almost unbounded depending on how much memory you are using
Right so unfortunately this this copy-on-write technique provides an efficient solution
And so the idea when we do fork
When we when we when a process executes fork
The kernel has to create exact copies of all those internal data structures
They mmm struck the area structs and the page tables
There's no way to get around that
Okay but those aren't those aren't really huge of
They're not as potentially huge as the the actual data that the program is is accessing and
Then and then it flags each page in both processes as read-only
Okay even though they're not no matter where they are any process
Any page in that process it flags is read only
And then it flags each vm area struct in both processes as private copy-on-write
So on return now each process has the identical address space
Because it they have it has identical page tables
Okay we've made copies of the page tables
And all of the other all of the other structures
And if as those processes just read
Then they're sharing the same physical pages
Right it's only when a process does it right
That the the system will create a new page will create a new page  using this copy-on-write mechanism
So it's only when a process rights to a page will
It tries to do a write the page is flagged as read-only  okay in the pt ii
That triggers a fault
The kernel looks at that looks up the access that looks up the flags for that
For that particular page sees that it's private copy-on-write
And so it makes a copy of the the target page
And maps it to a new region of the physical address space
And then does the allows that and then and then when the right executes again
And then it restarts when that fault handler returns it restarts that instruction
And now the right is writing to the copy
Okay so what what this does a very clever technique it defers the
The copying till as long as till as late as possible
And it only does copying when it's absolutely needed
Okay so in some sense it's the most it provides you with the most efficient way to
A most space efficient way to represent those two
Those two different virtual address spaces
And so what's interesting is that regions of the virtual address space that
That are read from never get copied
So so they it's perfectly fine for those two processes to share
To share that data on physical memory because it's never written to write so
Okay so that's why that's why fork isn't so bad right
Good now execve now that we know about sharing
And now that we know about this this mapping notion
The execve function loads and runs a new program in the current process
And so what it does is it frees all the all the area structs for the current process right
So xx not creating a new process
It's running a new program in a new virtual address space within the current process
Ok so it it so it frees all the arias trucks and page tables  for the current process
Ok and then it creates new area structs and page tables for the new areas
And the programs so the program and initialize data
Those areas are backed by the file in this case the executable binary
And their program is backed by the portion of the executable that contains code data segment
Is is backed by the portion of the executable file that contains initialize data
So these two together are private
What we call their private
Ok these this object it shouldn't isn't being shared with with any anything else
And it's file backed because these this area is backed by portions of a file
The the uninitialized data which was specified in the bss section of the of the binary
That's defined as a private demand 0 area
Ok so this so these these pages will all be remembered by definition bss is uninitialized
Okay and so the system initializes these to zero
So any pages then any pages in the heap are also private demands zero
Now the memory mapped region for shared libraries
Remember every every process share is the same copy of lib C and in memory
So this is a region of the virtual address space that's shared
Okay because it's shared by multiple processes
And it's backed by files of
And the de file in this case is the .so file the shared object file
And the code for this region is backed by text
The the portion of the this object file that contains code and
Data is initialized data is backed by a portion of this file that that contains data
Now there's I haven't shown it here but there's other there's other portions of this
Of this region that need to be a private copy-on-write because different lib C functions
If a lib C function has static variables or can contain state
Like a random number generator typical random number generator
Retains state across each invocation
Okay so that state would be different for each process
So there needs to be a sort of private copy-on-write area for for any data that's that's being written to
And I suppose I suppose the system would just
With just  if you if you made this entire region
Now you'd have to have it you'd have to have second portions of this that would be private copy-on-write
And then the stack is private demand zero
Okay so so what what exact does is it just sets
It creates new areas that are backed backed by a different by the object file that you want to execute
And it creates areas for bss and stack that are backed by anonymous files
And it creates a this memory-mapped region that's that's a shared object  which corresponds to lib c
And then it sets the program counter or ip to the entry point in text
And then once as this program runs now notice we haven't loaded anything
Right all we've done is set mappings
We just we just created data structures in the kernel
And we've we've created mappings between portions of the address space and these objects
But nothing's actually been copied into memory yet
Okay well this is all we've just created we've modified data structures in the kernel
Now but once the once the loader sets%rip to the entry point
The first instruction in in this text segment
Then Linux will fault in all the code and data that's needed on demand
So loading loading hab is deferred until the loading of a page of code or data is deferred
Until that code or data page is actually referenced and accessed
So it's very this is very clever and very interesting I think how
How it's like yet another example of how useful and
How tightly integrated virtual memory is with the operation of the system
Right you wouldn't have to do this
You could just as part of the loading process you could just copy those take those object files
You could just have a loop that would read these object files and just copy them into copy them into memory
And create page table entries for of as as you did it
But even that would be efficient that would be inefficient too right
What if you had a very large array that you'd initialized to some nonzero value
That would require you to copy that that entire array in at load time
Even though you may be only accessing a small portion of that of that data structure
Now the kernel provides a function called m map that allows you to do your memory mapping just like the kernel does
Okay and so it's basically a way it's a system called it that
Allows you to request the kernel to map a region of virtual memory on your on  its behalf
And so this this m map function takes a a virtual pointer
Which is some pointer into the virtual address space
And it maps tries to map length bytes starting at this address
It tries to map that portion of the virtual address space to the object  to an offset
To some objects specified by this file descriptor
Okay so remember we when you open a file you get back a file descriptor
So it's mapping this region of the virtual address space starting at start for length bytes
To a region of the that the file denoted by this integer file descriptor
So it's it's mapping length bytes in that file starting at offset  offset
Now and then there's the user can specify different flags what kind of protection they want for this
This whether its private or whether it's read or whether it can be it's read-only or read/write
And they can also specify by the typeof of object
If you map and anonymous if you use this flag and m map then you get a demand 0 page
Okay that's the anonymous file
In which case you don't need to specify this this file descriptor
And you can map that object as being private or shared
Okay like we talked about before
Now the kernel will will it will return an pointer to the start of this mapped area not necessarily
This this start address is like a hint to the kernel so
So if it can it will will try to map that area
But if that portion of the virtual address space is already contained in some already existing area
Then it'll it will pick an unused portion of the virtual address space to to map
Okay so what what we're doing really is we're we're taking
An offset into some file specified by that fd argument and length number of bytes
And we're associating that or mapping that into us the same sized region of the virtual address space
Okay so now if we do if we read
Now again nothing gets copied
Okay it's just a mapping
So that if we were to read a portion of let's say we mapped an unused portion of the virtual address space
And then at using m map
And then after m map we just started scanning through this this portion of the virtual address space
You know say it's an array we then we've m napped a big array
As we read as we read each non-existing page will be swapped in automatically
Kate will trigger page fault
And it will be swapped in and the value that it has will be will be determined by the the contents of this portion of the file
Okay and then so one here's an example of how you can use em map
To do  and this is kind of an interesting example we're copying a file from standard into standard out
Without ever transferring data to user space
So the normal sort of into naive way to do this would be to read from a file
Read from standard in and then write to standard out so to syscalls one read and one write
We can actually do this using using one 1m map and then a single right
Okay so what we do is we open a file our v1 is is standard in
Or we I'm sorry we open a file that was passed in on the command line
We get its size and then we call em and then we call this m map copy function to say
Copy copy that the copy of the bytes the size bytes
From this file to standard out
So this n map copy function does m map using that file descriptor
Sets that is read only private sets the size
And length means everything
Or at the off at an offset of zero
And then we do one writes this call to standard out passing at the pointer to the buffer that we want to copy
And of size bytes
So as this as we so as we
So this will read this will read bytes 1f the right the right call will read bytes in buff p
One after the other and as that happens they'll be faulted in
And then it will write them
I will write them to the descriptor indicated by a on the one which is standard out
Okay so that's that's it for today
Hope you guys have a good weekend
hope you guys have a good weekend
And see you next week
and see you next week