Well good afternoon everybody welcome
Good to see you
So this week we're going to study how to incorporate concurrency into programs
Now we've seen concurrency before in the form of processes exception handlers
And in the case of processes it was a mac
We use processes as a mechanism to run multiple independent application programs
Now but you could concurrency also exists in application programs
Now we've seen a little bit of this when we studied signal handlers
Okay so a signal handler is a concurrent flow that runs concurrently with your main application program
Okay and we've seen
We've seen how some of the difficulties that can arise
When we introduce concurrency in our programs
So even with something like a signal handler which isn't doing very much
It's very hard for us to reason about this kind of thing we have to two concurrent flows running at the same time
Like there's our brains just tend to be kind of sequential we want to think about things happening one after the other
You know it is and it's much easier for us to reason about that
Reasoning about multiple things happening at the same time really causes problems
And the fundamental reason is that to really reason about say (two independent) two concurrent flows
We have to account for all of the possible inter leavings of those flows
Okay and that's where and that's that grows exponentially with the number of flows
Okay so you had you saw this with your signal handlers when you did shell lab
You had two concurrent flows the main program and your signal handler
Both accessing a shared resource in the form of the jobs list
Right and you had to be very careful to prevent an interleaving where
Where that data structure was being referenced in an inconsistent state
So what we're going to do this week,and into next week is we're going to look at that kind of application level concurrency
But in a more principled in a more principled way than we encountered with signal handlers
So as soon as you have multiple flows accessing shared resources all kinds of bad things can happen in your program
And these have been...these bad things,these problems that occur been objects of study in computer science for decades
But the kinds of things that can happen are our races
Which we've seen in when we did the shell lab
Where the outcome whether good or bad outcome depends on some some arbitrary scheduling decision
Right in the case of you know one of the races we saw
In the case of a shell was the case where that a child just because of a scheduling decision by the kernel
Runs and finishes before the parent has a chance to add that child to the job list
Okay so that's a classic example of a race
And similarly if you have two people that are trying to making accessing a reservation system on a bird for an airline
Who gets the if they both access at the same time,who actually gets a seat
Just depends on those various scheduling decisions that are going on in the reservation system
Another kind of a problem that occurs is deadlock
So a deadlock is a condition
That exists where you have multiple flows waiting for an event that will never occur
Okay so using printf in a signal handler is an example of this kind of problem
Introduces the potential for that kind of problem
Okay so in your main routine you execute a printf
And that printf acquires a lock on some system resource,i think it's a terminal lock
And then after that main printf
Acquires that lock it gets interrupted by a signal handler
And now the signal handler if it does a printf
That printf will try to acquire that lock
But it won't be able to get it because the printf and the main routine has it
So now your signal handler the printf and the signal handler
It's waiting for that lock to be released is waiting for an event that will never occur
And it will never occur because the printf in the main routine can't release the lock
Until the signal handler returns
And the signal handler can't acquire the lock until the printf in the main routine terminates
So that's a classic example of deadlock
Another more from real life imagine that you're all drivers follow the rules very precisely
And the rule for a four-way stop is that whoever gets there first gets to go first okay
So if four cars arrive at the intersection exactly the same time
Then you have a deadlock,you have none of the drivers was first
So none of the drivers goes
And so they're all waiting for a condition that will never occur
And then other classical things that can go wrong or things like liveness  starvation fairness of this
Starvation occurs when you fail
You're trying to do something but you fail to make progress because somebody else keeps getting all the work
Right so if you were...if you had two processes and the kernel always scheduled process a instead of process b
Process b that would be an example of process b being starved out because of a improper scheduling decision
And then we would say that that that scheduling policy always schedule b is unfair
Right so it doesn't have this property of fairness where every entity in the system gets sort of a reasonable chunk of the processor
So like i said i mean this
Concurrency has been studied for years it's a very difficult topic
Because of this because of this sort of exponential explosion in the number of inter leavings
So we can't,we're not going to cover all of them
But we will cover some so as you get a reasonable idea
Of how to incorporate concurrency in your programs
Now for our study of application level concurrency
We're going to use servers as a motivating example
And the reason is that you cannot write a correct server without using concurrency
Okay so it's a good,it's a really good,good motivation
And here's the reason
So far we've looked at servers that are iterative
Okay so the only process requests from one client at a time
And once they finish processing a request from a client then they go on to the next client
So they so like with our iterative echo server
You can see the each of these clients makes a connection request
Then it writes a line of text to the server
And then it waits for the server to echo that back
And in this case this simple case then it just closes
Okay and the server waits for a connection requests and accept
And then waits for...and then once it accepts that connection requests
It reads and when waits for what waits for that client to write something to the connection
And then it echoes it back
And then it waits for the next line
Until the client closes that connection
And then the server closes this connection
And then only them does it does it do another except to wait for the next connection request
Okay so in this example client two is also making a connection request
But it never runs it has to wait until the server actually echoes back the response
Now there's a little subtlety here that  in where exactly that this client waits
So the semantics of connect
You would think that connect would block until the connection was established
But actually if you tried this out
It turns out that connect actually initiates the connection process inside the kernel
But then it returns
Okay before the connection has been established
And then it does a right
And that right also returns immediately
So right it doesn't wait until the server reads that the string that was written
And it doesn't block until it calls the read function waiting for the echoed response from the server
So it actually it doesn't block until it hits this read and then it spends all
It waits waits waits waits
And finally the server accepts the connection requests and then writes echoes the string back to the client
So the call to connect actually returns immediately
And it exploits this feature in the kernel that can queue up these connection requests
Okay so that the kernel now is going through all the process of setting up the connection
But the application program continues
And then the right,the right inside the client doesn't block
Because the kernel can also queue up the data that's written
So it'll little queue it up remember that it was written when the connection actually gets created
Then it'll send that data along
And
But there's no way to avoid the read from blocking,write a read can't return until it gets some data
Okay so read has to block
Okay now here's the fundamental flaw of an iterative server
And the reason why we have to write them with the concurrency
Okay so let's say in a echo server example
We have a client that creates a connection
Or request a connection it's accepted in the server
Does the write
The server echoes back one you know one string
And then the client blocks again or instead of doing the next write or closing the connection
The person
The user goes out to lunch and never types in a string to the the echo client
Okay so at this point the server calls read
And then it blocks waiting for this user to type in something
And so that the client can send it to the server to be echoed
But the user is gone gets hit by a truck
Who knows
Anyway so this never this read then blocks
For an indeterminate amount of time right
And while it's blocking client to which also wants service
It has to block
Okay so now you're in an untenable situation
Where one client has sort of totally affected
All of the other clients in the system and none of the other clients can get service
It's so if this were a web server
If one client for some reason
Blocked
No other users would be able to use that web service or look at pages on that's site
So obviously this we can't have this
Okay so the solution is to use is to write a concurrent server instead of an iterative server
Where we'll have a separate concurrent flow handle each clients request and interact with each client
So now if one client for some reason is slow or misbehaves or blocks the system
Other clients won't be affected because those clients will be handled way by concurrent flows
So there are several ways a number of ways to create these.yes
[student speaking]
It actually could and in fact that's that's a form of concurrency
So the question is the could the server queue up requests from the from clients
It could but it would...
You know i guess actually it would have to queue up it would somehow have to accept those connections right
So that
Now so that wouldn't work so somehow you have
Since the accept calls are iterative sequential
There's no way to get data from those other clients
Okay but actually what you're suggesting is very similar to something called an event-based server
That will which is one of the ways we can create concurrent flows
So there's three ways to create these concurrent flows
One is to use processes okay like we've already seen
Okay so the kernel...so in this case the kernel handles all the scheduling for us and interleaves
It interleaves the process execution automatically for us
And then as we saw before each flow has its own private address space
So that each flow is independent and scheduled by the kernel
Okay now there's a another approach called event based
Where the programmer manually interleaves the flows
Okay so instead of relying on the kernel to interleave these different flows
The user the programmer creates this flows and then manually interleaves them okay
And since it's one program
All of the flows share the same address space right
So they have access to all the same global data structures
And they do they do this inter interleaving using a technique called i/o multiplexing
You know i'll talk briefly about that but
It's addressed much more detail in your book
The third approach which is kind of a hybrid of process based and event based is thread base
So used each of these flows is implemented using something called a thread
The kernel like processes
The kernel automatically interleaves these different threads
But unlike a process each thread shares the same address space
Okay so each thread has access to all the global variables declared in the program
So in so it's like process based and that the kernel automatically schedules it for us
But it's like event based in the sense that
Every flow shares the same address space
Okay so we'll look,let's look at all three of these approaches in more detail
So the first approach is to create these flows using processes
So in this case
This is our echo server example
The the client requests a connection
And then calls fgets to wait for the user to type something at the keyboard
But the user is gone and so fgets this client just blocks in the call to fgets
So the server when it gets a request,it accepts the connection requests and returns from the accept call
And after it returns from the accept call
It forks a child
And then that child interacts
That child process now will be responsible for interacting with client number one
So the child blocks waiting for data from client one
Which is never going to show up because the the user left
Okay but it that's okay because it doesn't stop the server
The server after it forks the child goes right back and calls accept
And now accept can accept the connection request from client 2
And fork off another a different child that can interact with client 2
So that child will read waits for data to show up from the client  and then it echoes it back
And at some point then closes the this connection
Okay so you see that this misbehaving client number one
Now because we have concurrent flows interacting with all the clients
This misbehaving client can't adversely affect other clients
Okay so now that's
And this idea of creating concurrent flows to interact with clients is fundamental
There you have to do this in order to have a sort of a working server implementation
Alright so how would we actually program this process based concurrent server
It's actually surprisingly compact
So
We're going to pass in argv,we're going to pass in a port number that we want this server to listen on
We've got a listening descriptor and a connected descriptor
We've got and then we've got a length and a an address address field
And the address is declared in a protocol independent way using this sockaddr_storage type
Which is guaranteed to be big enough as you saw last time
It's guaranteed to be big enough to handle any type of address either ipv4 or ipv6
Okay so we install a sigchld_handler
And then we use the open_listenfd call from your textbook
To create a listening descriptor on port that we pass in as the as the argument to this program
And then the server goes into an into a loop
And in each iteration
It gets the size of the socketaddr_storage type and puts it into clientlen
And then it calls it except
With pointers to the clients address and clientlen
Using the listening descriptor that was returned by open listenfd
The accept call after it gets a connection request it returns with the address of the client that made the that
At the other end of the connection along with the true length of that  address
So the case of ipv4 before 4 bytes
And then the acceptor turns this this connected file descriptor
That the then that that the the child
That that it can use to to read and write and interact with that client
So it creates say it forks the child
And then the child closes it's listening descriptor
And then it calls the echo routine to interact with the client
And when the echo routine returns the client closes this connected descriptor and then exits
And so this close isn't absolutely necessary but we just did it to be careful
Okay now the parent
And this is important closes the connected descriptor
Because it's not going to use that connected scripture only the child's will use that connected descriptor
So in order to avoid this memory leak it's very important for the child to to close this descriptor
Okay because remember this the server's running in an infinite loop on it
In theory it would never terminate
Okay and then to avoid a memory leak
We have to...in a handler we have to have a sigchld_handler that will reap all of the children that have terminated
Okay so let's look a little more detail how this except works
So you have a client with a client file descriptor
And then you have a server that creates a listening descriptor
So let's say that's you know descriptors are indexed by small integers
So let's say that index is three the description number is three
So the server blocks and accept waiting for this connection request
The client makes a connection request using the connect call
Okay the server accepts the connect call and then it creates a child
And then the child interacts with the client using the connected file descriptor that was returned from the accept
So that would be say descriptive number four just be some different number
Okay so are the execution model we have for these process based servers
Is that we have this the server processor listening for connection requests one after the other from clients
And then we have multiple clients interacting concurrently with multiple children interacting concurrently with multiple clients
Okay since each of these children are processes there's no shared state between them
And both parent and child inherit the have,they inherit the descriptor table
So they have they both have copies of listenfd and listening descriptor in the connected descriptor
Okay and as we saw before the parent must close
It's copy of the connected file descriptor,the child should close the listening descriptor but
It's you know just to be just because it's not needed
All right when you,so these are actually pretty simple to create and there's just a couple of things you have to keep in mind
When you build a process based server
So firstly as we...as with any process that creates children
It has to reap these children that have terminated to avoid this memory leak
The parent process has to close its copy of the connected file descriptor
And there's a couple reasons
It fact if it doesn't it will not only create a memory leak but that
The state associated with that descriptor will actually stay around forever
Because the kernel won't close that connection
So it as we saw when we looked at file i/o
This is just enough,this is the same kind of file i/o we looked at before
So the kernel keeps a reference count for each socket that's open
So after the fork now there's two,there's a parent and the child which are accessing
The file table associated with the connected file descriptor
Okay so that
And the connection won't be closed until the reference count for that connected file description is zero right
That file table entry won't be removed from the kernel
Until until there's only there until there's zero references to it
Okay so both the parent and the child have to close that descriptor
Okay now the good thing about process based servers is that they do the job for us that we asked them to do
Right we wanted them to handle to interact with multiple clients concurrently or have that ability
There's a very clean sharing model
Right so there's private address spaces between the all of the children and the parent
They shared,they have separate descriptors,but they share they have separate copies of the descriptor table
But they share the same open file table
Okay
And there's so in some sense this is a simplest possible way to create a concurrent servers
And if you can get
If you can get by with not sharing any global variables or sharing address basis then this is the way to go
The disadvantage is that there's additional overhead for
Even with this processes copy-on-write trick that we saw for sharing the
Sharing the address space between the parent and the child still
It's still non-trivial overhead
And it's you have to actually do a lot of work if you want to share data between processes
So like let's say you want to have some kind of a shared cache between multiple processes
Either have to use files okay on disk
Or if you want to share memory you have to use  some kind of you have to use some kind of memory mapping
Or you have to use what's these inter process communication mechanisms which
We haven't talked about but there's ways pipes are probably the ones you're most familiar with
So a pipe allows one process to send data to another process
And there's ways to share memory between processes
But they're cumbersome and require i have to be implemented with care
Okay now the second approach is we call an event-based server
So the idea here is that the server maintains a set of active connections
So it  has an array of of connected file descriptors from different clients okay
And then it determines which of those and it also has a listening descriptor
And then it determines which of those descriptors have pending input
And it determines this using a system call called select or epoll there's several ways to determine this
But basically using select or a epoll
You can determine which of a set of descriptors has pending input right and
Then this and so the arrival of input at a descriptors is called an event because it changes the state of the descriptor
So an event is always event in general is always some kind of state change
So in this case when data arrives on a socket  that's a change in the state
So there was no data before the event after the event now there's data that the server can read
So if the listening descriptor has input then the server calls except to accept the connection
And for all and then all connected descriptors that have pending inputs
It services those it reads from those in some order
Okay now that the details for how to do this are described in the book
But basically
I mean the conceptually is pretty simple it's actually tricky to implement
But the idea is that there's some set of active descriptors
Right there's some set of descriptors connected descriptors that you're using
That are being used right now to to interact with a client
There's some that are inactive so if descriptors was closed
Then it's no longer active right
And then there's other descriptors that have never been used
So we just have this array of descriptors
And then we record there you know the the descriptor number for each of those connected for each of those descriptors
And then using select or a epoll or some other mechanism
We somehow determine which of those active descriptors have input
And then we service each of those
In the case of listenfd by calling except
In the case of these connected descriptors actually either
This should be connectfd not clientfd
But in the case of these connected descriptors we read the data from them
And the when we read the data from each descriptor we do some work
Okay so data arrives that a descriptor
And then we read that data and then we do some kind of work
Maybe in the case of an echo server we echo it right back okay
In the case of a web server we may
If that data was http request we might go and fetch a file from disk and return it
Okay but in any case we notice that the descriptor has some data
We read that data and then we respond to it in some way
Okay so that response those multiple responses are concurrent flows
Okay the we're interacting with that client
We're interacting we're creating concurrent flows while concurrent flow for each client
And we're servicing those clients concurrently
Okay so even though it's a sequential program right we're not using fork or anything
It's just a c program straightforward c program
We're writing in such a way that we're creating our own concurrent flows
So there's...as with any approach there's advantages and disadvantages
So the a big advantage of event based servers is that it's just
A sequoia it's one process with one address space
Right so it's very easy you can use conventional debugger gdb to step through
You can see everything you have access to everything
So in that sense they're much simpler to debug understand
And then there's no process or thread control overhead
So when we service a particular descriptor it's very...there's very little overhead right
We just the only overhead is sort of determining that descriptor has input available
Okay and so because of that this is the
High performance web servers like nodejs,nginx,tornado they all use this event based approach gates
If you want to get over 10,000 requests per second you have to go with something like this
Okay the disadvantage is it's much harder to more complexed
It to code up then the other processor thread based designs
And it's very difficult
So one of the hardest aspects of the writing and event based server
Is that you have to figure out how much work you're going to do in response to an event
Okay so let me give you...let's say that this server is a web server
And you get input on one of your connected file descriptor
The simplest thing to do would be to then assume to read the entire http request
And not return until you've read the entire request
Okay so in that case the amount of work that you do in response to an event is very coarse-grained
There's a lot of instructions because we're going to read every single line in that http request header
But it's...so that's course that's an example of coarse grain
It's very simple because every time you get a request on a connected descriptor you just read the whole
You just read the whole http request  and then send a response
Okay so there's
On the other hand it's vulnerable
Because what if a client misbehaves and doesn't send the entire http request
What if it sends half of the requests
So if you were doing to design an event based web server you probably wouldn't want to do that
Right because that a single client we would be back in the situation we were before
Where a single misbehaving client could sort of shut down the whole server
So you might say well
I'm going to my unit of work that i do in response to a request will be to read a single line from the request
Okay so i'll read a single line and then i'll return
Okay so every so now we're interleaving reading single lines
And once i've read the entire request then out then i'll send the response
So that's better right so a misbehaving client
If sending like whole text lines at a time
Even if it stops halfway through we'll still be able to make progress in service other other clients
So that's a finer grained approach it's better
It's probably more robust than waiting for the whole request
But it's still vulnerable
Because the client could just send a partial line
So now we're back
So really the only way to write a robust event based web server is to be able to handle partial lines
Just read when there's data available on a descriptor
You just read whatever data is available
You remember how much you read
If it's not a whole line you somehow have to remember that you have to buffer it remember it
So now it's getting really complicated right
But that's what you that's the price you pay for this low overhead sort of easier to debug kind of kind of model
And then another disadvantage is that you can't since it's really a sequential program right it's one c program
You can't take advantage of multiple cores
So the only way to get sort of more performance out of something
An event-based servers just to replicate copies of that server
But you can't make an individual server go faster by using multiple cores
Okay the third approach is to use threads to create these concurrent flows
It's very similar to processes but there are some important differences
So let's look first at what we mean by a thread
So let's go back i'm going to...let's go back in and look at the traditional view of a process
So we think of a process as some context that's data structures in the kernel
Okay data that the kernel keeps about that process
As well as this private address space which contains a stack  code and data and then the stack
Okay and then as part of the and then the
The process context consists of context that's associated with the program like the registers,condition codes,program counter,stack pointer
And then it contains kernel context which is information in the kernel
That the kernel needs to implement this idea of a process
Okay so all of this data is actually stored in the kernel
But some of the data is directly associated with the program and other data is sort of
Support data that the kernel needs to implement processes
Okay so let's just take this picture
And we're just going to just move things around a little bit
So what i've done is i've taken the stack off of the this virtual address space
And sort of pulled it out along with its stack pointer
And the contacts that's associated with the program
So the data registers the condition codes the stack pointer the program counter
Okay and i've just renamed a thread context instead of program context
But it's the same it's the same thing
And then i'm going to call this whole thing the combination of a stack
And this thread context i'm gonna call that a thread
And then everything else remains the same
It's we have...we still have a code and data
And we have the kernel context
Okay now by doing this sort of refactoring and just moving things around
I can now imagine so this stack isn't very much right
It's so there's that,there's this,there's the stack space
And then there's a little bit of data here in the form of some registers and some things to be stored
But in this is a fairly small amount of data
Now when i really like this
Now i can
I can think about there being multiple threads associated with the same process
If i just keep different set of data thread context for each thread
And then a private a separate portion of the stack that's associated with that thread
So now each thread shares the same code and data
Same virtual address space has the same kernel context
Okay the same i/o structures
But now it has its own separate individual stack
Okay so local variables things that you would store on a stack now would be would be private sort of independent
And it has its own set of its own program counter its own stack pointer
Its own set of registers and condition codes
And then the one difference is now is that each thread
Instead of there's still a process id for this process that's pointed part of the kernel context
But each thread now has its own thread id as part of its thread context
Okay so now
The kernel can just treat each of these as separate flows
Right there's a separate so it's just like a process now
The kernel can remember where the each thread has its own program counter
And but they're running code out of the same
That code the same code section in the virtual address space
So the sharing code sharing data
But they have their own program counter
So they can the kernel can provide
Can create each of these threads as a separate flow of control
That it then schedules just like it does of a process
Or in a similar way that does is a process
But the difference is the reason that for threads in the first place is that when the colonel wants to contact switch from one thread to another
There's not that much information that has to be saved and restored
It's just a small amount of data
So the kernel has to save this the data thread one context
In some data structure some way and then restore the context for thread 2
But we're talking about a very low overhead kind of operation
Right it doesn't have to mess around with page tables virtual address space or any other of the process context
So threads are luck kind of like processes
But they're different in the sense that they share the same virtual address space
And unlike processes which are created by fork
Which creates a strict process hierarchy threads are just pools
You can think of threads as pools of concurrent flows that access the same code and data
And then the kernel is responsible for scheduling those flows
And if in a way that so each flow gets time on the processor
So much like processes,much like concurrent processes
We say the two threads are concurrent
If their flows overlap in time otherwise they're sequential so this is the exact same
Example that i showed you when we looked at processes
So here you have instead of three processes we have three threads running it within the same process
Thread a runs for a little bit
And then the kernel just decides to walk it out and run thread b
So then thread b runs for a little bit and then the kernel decides to give thread c some time
So it saves thread b's context restores thread c's context
And sets the pc to...the pc value
And thread c's context and so c runs and then the kernel decides to give a some time again
So then a runs some more
So because thread a and b overlap in time they're running concurrently
B and c don't overlap in time so they're not running concurrently
But a and c are concurrent because they overlap in time
And so you can...you also have the option if there's multiple cores than multiple threat
A thread can run on each core so then you can have true parallelism
Okay
Okay so like i said threads and processes are similar ideas
But in the sense that they each stage kinase and process corresponds to some kind of logical flow
And they can run concurrently with other flows
And each is scheduled and contact switched by the kernel
Okay but they're different because threads share all code and data except their local stacks
And in fact those local stacks although they're each thread has its own it's really just sharing the same stack
And so it's really the same portion of the virtual address space
It's just that each thread is assigned its own part of that stack
Okay so even though threads have their own individual stacks
Since it's all part of the same virtual address space
A thread can access the stack of any other thread
If it's and that's not a good thing to do but it's possible
Okay so processes don't share any of the state
Right they have their own private address spaces
And threads are less expensive than processes
It's cheaper to create them
And the main reason is that there's just less context associated with the thread than there is as a process
And so on our system when we measure
A bunch of we just create in and wait for a bunch of creative process wait for word process over and over again and measure the time
Turns out to be about twenty thousand cycles to create and
Reap a process about ten thousand cycles to create an reapeth thread
So that the kernel provides threads to us using an interface called the pthreads  posix threads
So this is a fairly recent standard that all linux,unix systems and windows macintosh
So every this is a sort of standard posix standard for manipulating threads
And so you can do things like create and reap threads
So there's this is sort of sort of like fork
And this is sort of like weight but not quite because it doesn't create
There's no hierarchy associated with these
You can you could just like get pit you can retain there's a function to get your thread id
You can kill threads so one thread can kill another thread
A thread there's a there's a function to exit a thread
The normal exit system call terminates all the threads
And return is similar to pthread_exit in the sense that just terminates the current thread that calls it
And then there's ways to access synchronize access to shared variables
Which we'll look at on thursday more detail
Okay so here's the pthreads hello world program
You know your k&r book the the c reference manual
The very first thing that it does is it shows you how to write the simplest possible c program called
So the famous hello world program
So that goes all the way back to like 1978 when k&r book was first written
But that's caught on
And whenever we like learn a new language or we learn a new concept
We always write the hello world program for that concept
So the hello world program for threads this is a simplest threads program that i can think of
So i call it the hello world program for threads
So this program defines a function
So court by in posix
A thread is actually executed by executing the the code and a function called the thread routine
Okay and posix imposes
This thread routine takes a generic pointer as an argument optional generic pointer
And it returns a generic pointer
Okay so anytime if you want to pass anything to a thread you somehow got to pack up all that data into a single object
Then you can take an address up
But it's it you can see that this is extremely general-purpose
So our hello world program creates a thread by calling pthread create
And we say instead of a child we call this a peer thread
Okay so that there's no parent-child relationship any threads can threads can reap other threads
Whether they created those threads or not
Okay so you don't have the strict parent-child hierarchy
Pthread_create creates a thread that executes the thread routine in this third argument
And returns the thread id of that thread in the address and the integer pointed at by the first argument
The second argument is set up there's ways to set attributes of threads
That are beyond the scope of this course and will always just have those no
And then that this fourth argument is the optional argument that you want to pass to your thread routine
Okay so in this case we're saying call the thread routine
That's called thread with no arguments
And then our thread routine just prints out hello world
And then it returns in this case it doesn't return anything so it returns no
But if we wanted to return something to the calling program
We could have returned something a pointer to some generic object okay
Okay so the thread id the thread attributes are null that the thread routine the thread arguments are void *p
And the return value is a void double
So it's a pointer to the pointer that you want to return
Okay all right so let's look at what happens when we execute hello world
So the main thread runs for a while
Then it calls pthread_create
Which creates the peer thread which now is a concurrent flow that's running
Once the pthread create returns then we're running two concurrent flows or running the main thread
And we're running the peer thread
And so in this case hello world waits for the peer thread to finish by calling pthread_join
The peer thread after the calls it's printf it returns
No which terminates the thread at that point the pthread_join returns and the main thread continues
Okay so using these create this create function how would we write a thread based concurrent echo server
And again it's very similar to the way we did it with the process based design
So we call we acquire a listening descriptor by calling open_listenfd function just as before
And then inside this infinite server loop
We get the size of the
We get the size of the clientaddr struct so which is going to be a large enough to fit any address
And then we malloc space for the connected file descriptor
So we're making a one integer sized portion of dynamic storage for this connected descriptor
That were that we're going to get back from accept
And we're going to...this is actually really important to avoid a nasty race condition
They'll show you in a second
So now we call except with our listening descriptor and clientaddr and clientlen just like before
And except returns the connected descriptor and then we dereference this connected descriptor pointer
And so and store that the value returned by except in this location in the heap
And then we call pthread_create
By giving it the name of our thread routine
Which in this case is just simply a function we defined in our program called thread
And the pointer to the connected file descriptor
Okay now a client which a client which a thread routine then will use to interact with the client
Okay so the thread routine dereferences the argument a member is a pointer to a connected file descriptor
So it dereferences that pointer to get the to get the actual integer connected descriptor
And then it detaches the thread
So by default threads
Threads run an independent and attached mode
So they can be you know they can be joined by other threads and they can be killed by other threads
But
By default if
It's similar when threads are running in unattached mode or undetected mode
That when they die they have wait by a join function to acquire those resources
But if we detach a thread then it can't be joined by any threads but when it dies the kernel will automatically
Restore the the resources associated with that thread
So in this case we're going to just detach this thread
So we're not to worry about reaping it when it finishes
And then we're going to free this memory that was malloc
So this is important we have to free this memory that was malloc by the main thread in order to avoid a memory leak
And then we call echo function so we interact with the the echo client until the echo clients finished
And then we close this descriptor again to avoid a potentially fatal memory leak
So this thread based education model is very similar to the execution model that we saw with processes
So we have a list of a main thread that's listening for connection requests
They were waiting for connection requests via accept
And then we have for each client we have a peer thread that interacts with that client
Using the connected descriptor that was passed in when we created the thread
And then each thread has its own since it has its own stack it has separate space for its local variables
And this is really the powerful thing about threads
Now we can with these things they by declaring these local variables we can
We can create threads that won't interact with each other
It won't and can run independently yes
[student speaking]
I guess yeah the question is there any time you wouldn't want to run detached
So when you run detached you give up the power to kill other threads so
So i don't know if you it's hard to it's hard to come up with good example right that
But if you wanted the ability to be able to terminate other threads
You know maybe if you had
Maybe if you were running a pool of like worker threads
And at some point
At some point if i mean i guess you can imagine a scenario where suppose you're running a pool of worker threads
You give them all jobs to do the first one that finishes you take the result
And you don't need the results from the other threads
So you might just want to kill those threads
But it's yeah it's hard to come up with a really compelling reason
Okay so there's a few things to think about when you're writing thread based servers
So the first is that yet you need to run detach to avoid potential memory leaks
I'm sorry i forgot this word so it the opposite of detached is joinable
And so joinable threads like i mentioned can be reaped and killed by other threads detached threads cannot
And their resources are automatically claimed on termination
So the default states joinable and you have to use this detach function call to make the thread detached
The biggest issue with threads though
Like the beautiful thing about threads is that you're sharing the same global address space
So it's very easy to share data structures you know if you had multiple threads
If you had a web server a concurrent web server that was built with multiple threads be very easy to implement a cache
All the threads could use right because they're all sharing that same virtual address space
But the thing that makes threads so nice
This ease the ease with which you can share resources  is also the thing that makes them very tricky to deal with
So as soon as just like we saw with our shell lab handlers
You know as soon as you have multiple flows accessing shared resources you have to be very careful
It's very easy to make mistakes
And it's very easy to or it's possible to to share resources in unexpected and unintended ways
For example if one thread passes the address of a local variable on its stack to another thread
Then now that the called thread now has access to the callers thread
And there's nothing to prevent that called thread from manipulating local variables on the caller stack
You know that would be a very bad thing to do
But it's possible you might forget,you know you might forget that the variable you're passing is a local variable, not a global
Okay and a really bad mistake
In our hello...in our echo server example
Notice we were very careful to malloc you space for this
For this connected file descriptor that we passed into that the peer thread that we are creating
Would have been much easier just to pass the address of the connected file descriptor into a peer thread be much easier
But it would also be wrong
Can you say why
Okay let's say right here when we call pthread_create
Instead of passing a pointer to a separately allocated region of the heap
Instead of doing that we just pass the address of the connected file descriptor same thing right
Okay and then in a thread routine we dereference that pointer to to get the connected file descriptor
Okay if we just pass the address of the connected file descriptor
This is real it's really bad,can you say why
Yes
It does, okay that's true, and why is that
[student speaking]
That's yeah that's right so what this is assuming
This entered this bypassing the address of this connected file descriptor
We're introducing a race
Okay in the race what we're assuming
That the peer thread will be able to dereference that pointer
Before
The main thread goes back up and gets a new connected file descriptor
Right so what happens what happens
Right we can't in a concurrent system,we can't make any assumptions about how the kernel is going to schedule things
Right we saw the same thing with processes
So what happens if after pthread_create
The main thread runs instead of the peer thread
Okay so we've passed the
We've passed the address of the connected file descriptor for this client
That we accepted the connection requests from
And then before the peer thread can dereference that argument we get a new connected file descriptor
Okay
And now the child runs
And it dereferences that descriptor
But what it gets now is the descriptor
That's corresponding to the second child not the first child
So now we have two threads talking to the same client using the same descriptor
So do you see them hope
So it's very tricky this is like a real subtle this is an example of sort of subtle errors that you can introduce
Because of this unintended sharing
And it's cause the root cause is as you correctly pointed out is that they're both sharing the same memory on the caller stack
Yes
[student speaking]
In this case of what you could do there's another thing you could do you could just pass the descriptor itself
Okay so you could just cast the descriptor to a generic pointer and just pass that
And that that's just kind of yucky though that that would work
Because instead of dereferencing it the child would just use it directly
Okay so good that's good
Okay the
So the really good things with with threads is ease of sharing
But that sharing also introduces can introduce complications
In fact that's we're going to look at ways to sort of control the the sharing
So that we do...so that we don't get unintended unintended sharing
Okay so to summarize the the approaches to concurrency that
That we've looked at we have process based concurrency
So it's hard to share resources but
It's easy to avoid unintended sharing so in some ways it's safer and easier to program
Event based so it's it's very low-level very tedious
You have to be very careful about how you the granularity of the work that you do in response to events
But you have total control over scheduling so you can decide which
Which descriptors you're going to service and in which order it sits since there's a single flow of control
You can debug it with a debugger
But it doesn't make use of multi-core so there's a handful of trade-offs there
And with thread based systems
It's very easy to share resources but that sharing can create problems of its own
It's fairly efficient compared to two processors
You don't have much control over the scheduling
So just like we saw you're not you can't really control which threads get executed in which order
And it can be difficult to debug
Because there can be races that occur very rarely very infrequently and
So the probability of sort of creating one of those race conditions is difficult
Okay so that's it for today
Tomorrow we'll look at thread based servers in more detail
And how to write thread based systems efficiently and correctly