so today's the second lecture about network programming  we got started last time
and as you probably saw last time there the API is for this are really big and hairy and messy and
it takes just a lot of time in my own personal experience of
rereading we looking at code looking at examples rereading documentation
going back and forth over that a dozen or so times
before it all really sinks in
and it's one where it really helps a lot to look at example code
and there's example code in the book in that CSAPP c file
that you've seen versions of in various forms
so I can lecture for days and weeks
but this really would all settle in until you've spent time studying yourself
anyways I want to repeat  and go back over a little bit of ground before
but last time we talked about the idea of translating from a domain name
which is something like www.cmu.edu to IP address
it's usually written in dotted decimal
form and I showed you a program last
time called host info that you could
that will look actually at the code for
and I just wanted to show you today I just did one very small tweak to that program and I'll describe it today
and the interesting thing is it lets you look at both ipv4 and ipv6
and it's one of the interesting features the code in the book
and it's new to the third edition is it uses a new API
that lets you pretty easily write code that will work under either of these two versions of the Internet Protocol
so for example
with this slightly modified program
if I now look up the IP address for Facebook
you'll see it comes back with two different ones
and the
the first one is the familiar dotted decimal form where each recall that each of these digits
it's a decimal representation of of a single byte
so it's a number between 0 and 255
this is a ipv6 address which is I told you is 128 bits long
so that's to the seventh takeaway 3 to the fifth 32 bytes right
and it's usually written in this hex format
with colons be after every pair of bytes
and I think the colon colon just means that's a zero there
when the cute things Facebook did was embed fac ii as a hex code inside of their ipv6 address
and
that's really different I get very different results
running this at home and then I do here
and as I mentioned you'll get different results running a DNS server depending on where in the country are
uh if you repeat the same thing over and over again
you'll get different results and that's because these very large companies are providing servers  that are stationed all over the world
and as a way to sort of balance out the load of the traffic they also have multiple server addresses
that then they kind of rotate through to give you so that different people will get served by different machines
so you see for example Twitter our Google just gave me two addresses in ipv4 and ipv6 address
Twitter gave me a for different ipv4 addresses
so let's look then at the code
I'll go back through some of what we talked about last time
I quite honestly I spent a fair amount of time looking at it
so I can really understand it better
because it's pretty it's not simple stuff
but as I mentioned that
as we went over last time
this is sort of this giant block diagram that shows
all the activity involved in setting up and running both a server and a client
and just to repeat
the idea is you need to the server needs to fire up
you can't contact a server until that server exists
so it's the server is the thing that has to exist first
and all these steps are what are required for a server to begin on a machine
and then to accept a connection request from a client
similarly once the server is set then the client can begin
and it's like placing a call to the server
and it makes a connection request
and that's accepted by the server
and then what's called a session begins meaning an ability for these two
machines to talk back and for worth over an internet connection
and they'll do it this example I'll show is done by reading and writing
as if they were filed a file each end looks like it's reading and writing a file
and then once the client is done with whatever it it's trying to get
it will disconnect
since we hang up its phone
and then the listening the server will detect this by receiving an end of file
when it attempts to read from the client
and then it will close that connection but and this I didn't have stated quite properly last time
this it's not going to actually shut down at that point it's just going to return back
and accept a new connection request
and this is what's known as an iterative server it can only handle a single client at a time
later in the course we'll talk about how to do a multi-threaded server that can handle multiple connections at one time
so this is a pretty basic version
so the first step on either the client or the server side is this very hairy messy relatively new API  called getaddrinfo
and the idea of getaddrinfo is it's a sort of kitchen sink  our Swiss Army knife for you
all those expressions of it has a zillion features
to that sort of subsume a lot of other sort of individual protocols
so for example it's pretty much the same whether it's ipv4 ipv6
it lets you sort of go forward from and a domain name to an IP address
lets you go backward from an IP address back to a domain name
it supports all of those things it will let you look up what is the port number associated with an HTTP server
so it will let you do all kinds of different things
and as a result it's a big and messy API with a zillion zillions features and parameters and and so forth
so you recall from last time that the
the the data structures we use to refer to a connection
whether it's an ipv4 or an ipv6 connection is called a sock outer
and as I mentioned this is sort of the C version of subtyping
if you know a language with a type inheritance
this is how it's done in C it's done by casting
and so in particular the sort of generic socket address
all it needs to know is a two byte field at the front that specifies what kind of socket is this
and then in particular
we'll be looking at what's called a sockaddr_in
which is an ipv4 version of of a socket
and so what it needs to know is a port number which is a two byte integer and a IP address
which is a four byte address for ipv4
both of those are actually stored in this structure as I mentioned in in
in big-endian order even if you're running it on a little endian machine
and one of the interesting features of that
this API this get adder info is
it's largely removed the need for you as a programmer to worry about byte ordering
and that's a nice feature
so in general for example and getaddrinfo if I want to pass an ax port number
I'll pass it as a character string
a string representation of a decimal number in other words
and then the the code here within this API will automatically turn that into a 16-bit integer and  put it in the proper byte order
and same with how it takes use of this 32 bit  IP address
and you want to get it into dotted decimal form it will do that for you
without you having to worry about byte order so it's kind of a nice thing
so get editor info has a whole bunch of arguments
and some of them are essentially outputs
some of them are inputs  things you're passing into the function
and others are really more like outputs how it gets information back to you
so in particular
the first one is just the name of the host and that can be either a domain name
or a dotted decimal name or one of those funky looking things with the Cohens that you solve for ipv6
the service is usually if you're looking up so if we're using this to look up
that'll actually be a null pointer
and basically what typically you'll have is one of those two will be  a string  and the other will be a null pointer
and the reason for that is the same function can be used either to look up a service like
what is the port number associated with HTTP
or it can be what is the IP address of www.cmu.edu
the hints is something that you're passing in
and it's basically as you fill in a small amount of a fairly large body of information
about what specifically are you looking for in this request are you looking for an ipv6
information are you looking for ipv4  and so forth
and then what it returns back
that's why you pass a star star
is it will return back a linked list that it's generated of results
and the reason for that as I mentioned is
that IP addresses are sort of many to many mapping potentially there as you saw
it's possible for a single domain name to have multiple IP addresses
it's possible for a single IP address to have multiple domain names
and so this is how they handle that sort of fact that they return a whole list of results
and associated with that once that result gets used once you done with it you're supposed to call a function called free adder info
that will basically dispose of all the elements of that linked list you don't have to do it yourself with free
and then there's a another helper function called gai_strerror
that you use if there's an error code to help you interpret that error
and it returns an error code
so as I mentioned it returns up a link twist
that result is a linked list of these a get of adders Struck's header info struck
and the adder info struct has iliyan fields
some of which you'll use and some which you won't
this is for example when you're passing in hints
hints is sort of that what you're passing in the information you know some conditions about
what you're looking for in this request
and then what some of these you pass in and some of it returns
and so some of these fields are ones that then you can use
when you're making calls to other socket functions
functions in the socket library
it'll fill in instead of you having to worry about
what's the structure the format of a sock adder in and how do I convert into network order and stuff
it will do all that for you
so it's a little confusing to use though because sometimes the stuff you're providing
is stuff you're giving it and sometimes it's stuff that it's returning back to you
and then there's an inverse function
that so get editor info is given a
it's actually give me the address information about some name
and get name info is I give you an address
and you give me back some documentation about it including potentially a domain name
so there you pass in as a the first argument is a sock adder struct
remember for this lecture and I think in the book in a few places
we've sort of created a type def to alias
so we don't have to say struct sock adder all over the place but that's what the SA is
and it will provide back information about that that address
so if you passing in a 32 bit IP address
you can get it to return either a dotted decimal version of that or to do the DNS lookup
and have it come back with the domain name for that
so this is that program that I just demoed to you this one called host info
so all it's really going to do is use these features to all on the command line give a domain name you say
and it will just come back with a list of IP addresses
so
and this is pretty much the way you write code for this get adder info API
that you typically so hints is the information I'm passing about what it is I'm looking for here
and so you start typically by zeroing out that entire field
and then setting the particular things you want
so in particular
in this code that's it that's in the slides and the one I demo to you last time
I'm only going to be looking for ipv4 connections
and so I use the constant called AF I net which is defined in the sockets interface
and also I'll say that I want a TCP connection out what's called a socket stream
which if you recall is the sort of protocol that 99% of the the IP traffic in the world is carrying is on TCP
meaning it provides a somewhat higher level abstraction of
of what's going on of sending packets back and forth
so that's as much hint as I'm giving it here
and now I'm I'm making a call to get adder info and this argument is the name
which is I'm getting it right off of the command line here
so in my demo it was always the commit up  a domain name
I'm passing it null for the service as I mentioned this call you typically have one of the two are is null  but not both
hints is what I'm passing in is this is the kind of information I want
and list P is a will now become a pointer to the results that get returned by get adder info
so that's the calling all of its quarry
okay and now I want to go back so I got one of those linked lists
and that will have a whole bunch of IP address of potentially multiple IP addresses in it
maybe just one maybe none
but some number of them in a link twist
and I want to walk through that list and get back the dotted decimal version of all those names
or the colon eyes of those ipv6 addresses I don't know how you refer to those by the way
I know relatively little about IB v6 I have to confess
so then there's a function called get name info which usually you use to take
a socket address IP address and go backward and get a domain name
but if I tell it
by a flag one of the the final argument to it is a flag argument
and say what I want back from this is not a donut main name I wanted in this numeric format
either dotted decimal or the Cohen's between hex digits
so by passing that to get name info
what it's going to return and I'm passing in a buffer meaning of a care star
and some size of that buffer and it's going to fill that in with the string representation of it
so you see this is a way I'm going from the
if you look at this is the actual sock adder of each of the wist elements
I'm giving it it's going from that sock adder which embedded within it
as you know is the four byte IP address
and what it's doing is it's taking that
flipping the bytes well and converting it to the dotted decimal form so
this function can do a lot of different things and I'm using it for that particular feature here
question
if he is no then I will go very far
yes because you know it's a null-terminated whist so
other questions
good questions
but that's exactly the code you saw running
and all I did to generalize it to include ipv6 addresses
was I commented out this one
say I don't I don't demand that it be a IP AFI net is a shorthand for ipv4
so by commenting that out  it said okay I'll get whatever TCP connections this domain will support
and that will include ipv6 addresses
so I thought it's pretty neat
and you have to be a pretty nerdy but I am pretty nerdy  to think this kind of thing is neat
but that you could write code
in this way that whether you're doing your different versions of the Internet Protocol
well it's all one common body of code
so we've seen demo of this
okay so now let's jump into that shows you sort of a little bit of this  get adder info API
now let's jump into the the full-blown web server part
and as I mentioned in chronological order you actually want to set up the server first
but it's easiest to understand the code for the client
because as you see it has a couple fewer calls to make
so let's go for through the client and just imagine
that somewhere out there there's a server that's waiting for us to connect to
so this now doesn't perhaps
when you break it down maybe this picture looks a little less daunting
we already saw get a tour info is the way I'm going to get an IP address  out of whatever I'm where my server is
socket I mentioned this yesterday or last time
it's just a local call that's used to allocate some data structures for this particular connection
and then connect is like placing a call
it's an API it's actually sending over the Internet to the server
some information saying hey I'd like to connect you
and then once the server risk that once that connection is accepted then I can begin my session
so let's look at that
so first of all I have to go through all this rigmarole with get adder info
but it will look pretty similar to what you've seen before
except I'm going to give a little more information because I want this to be
I'm filling in a few more details here
because I want to specify more features of this connection
so I'm saying that it's a TCP connection that's a sock stream
I'm saying that I'm going to give it a port number in a numeric form
you could also say as I mentioned of the certain ports have standard names HTTP SSH and so forth
you can actually pass in the string representation of those
but I'm using this in a sort of idiosyncratic way here
and then this feature get adder config is a parameter that's described in the book
and it they say it's a good idea to use it
and then I'm making a call to my friend get adder info
with these hints and it's going to return back this linked list of representing the the results of this request
so basically a linked list of IP addresses
and now just like you saw before I'm going to walk that list with a
except now what I'm going to try and do is for each of those say
well here's a number let me give that a try and if that fails
here's another address let me give that a try so I'm going to just sequentially try
all the different addresses you saw
for example for potential addresses for Twitter
I'll walk through all of those
and on each one I'm going to call for a socket
and the socket is the one that
as I said it allocates some data structures
I talked about this last time that's why I'm rushing through is pretty fast
but you'll notice that the fields that you're filling in are actually all been generated for us by the
get adder info call
so whereas the East have to remember oh this is a number and it should be a shortened
network order and yada da
pretty much nowadays you can just say here I'm just going to pass you this information that
was returned by a function call
oh and then as I mentioned also last time
I know I went through a pretty fast last time
socket actually returns back to you a file descriptor
and you recall a file descriptor is just a small integer starts with 0 1 & 2
and then it goes up from there
and so I'm going to interface with this network code as if I'm talking through files
but it doesn't socket doesn't actually do anything as far as the internet goes
there's nothing going there's not even
the you know serious effort within the operating system nothing goes over the network here
so the real work here is but it also allocates some some local data structures
and then what I'll do is I'll attempt to connect to the server
and again you'll see the various arguments I have to pass to the connect command
I get provided for me out of this call I made to get a tour info
and that's either going to work  or it's not going to work
similarly the socket call is either going to work or not work
be very unusual for a call to socket to fail
but connect for example will fail if the server's not available  or doesn't like you for some reason
and so if that succeeds I'm going to break out of this loop
I'm going to then free this data structure  and return the client the file descriptor
for the  this particular function its job is to open a connection to a client and return a file descriptor for it
and this is just what happens if you fall out of the loop not having made any connections
ok so I know this is I'm marching this fast
and as I said I know from my own personal experience I can attest this stuff
just takes time to understand because there's so many different features here
ok but that's the idea is we're going to
now on this server side which as I mentioned is that actually what you do beforehand
because you can't really have a client connect to a server that doesn't exist
but it's just a little bit trickier to understand what's going on
but you'll see it the first two steps are the same I need a socket
but then remember what I want to do is essentially set up a server
that's listening on a particular port for clients to request on it
and that's the function of the bind and the listen functions
and then the accept is when I'm saying ok the server is ready
I'm ready to accept requests
and it will fire that up
in particular the accept will just stop and hang up and wait
indefinitely until some connection request comes in
so if the server has no customers if there are no clients
it will just be waiting potentially forever with the call to accept
ok everything else goes through boom boom boom
but that one is where the actual waiting occurs for client connections
some way I should mention the connect
will also hang up and wait until the connection is formed
but typically it's built in with a time out so that it will fail if it takes too long
and there's you can adjust the parameters on both of these how long you wait for whether your weight or not
but I'm talking the typical case
so anyways
that again what will look a little those functions then
okay so this again we have to make a call to get editor info
and this time it's not because I need any IP addresses I already have an IP address
I'm a local server I don't actually need to know the IP addresses of my of the clients
I usually won't know them
but I need to fill in all those nasty little data structures and so
that's what I'm going to use get adder info here for here
so I'm going to say this time again I want a TCP connection a sock stream
I want it to be a listening for any IP address connection coming in
so it's passive meaning it's not actively reaching out
its passively waiting for connection requests
I'll say that I'm going to tell you a port number
that I'm going to actually use as my servers port number
and then I'm going to make a call and this time you see that
I'm not giving any information about the host because I am the host
but I'm giving the information of the port number that I'm using for this server
and the other hints that I've just filled in
and then it will return a wispy yes
[student speaking]
memset is the standard way that you set
all the bytes in in some number of bytes to a fixed value
it's the same as if you've use B 0 before or B
it was is the way you often would zero out a bunch of bytes
and if you look at the web page and I don't know why they say use memset don't use b 0 anymore so
cal equal to 0 it out but I'm not actually
eleking anything see the hints is a struct here
and remember is struct is just a bunch of bytes
and so if I make that particular call to memset it will set every byte in that structure to 0
and this is sort of the official standard way you're supposed to do that kind of
thing it's a good question so question
hey I passive is that it's a
it's a listening connection it's going to be a listening connection
and a I adder config was  some other argument
and quite honestly I don't remember but you saw I gave it before  with the get host name
so I don't remember it's it's a slot somewhat obscure per parameter
that's not even a required parameter
it's in the book I'm sorry
or you could Google it right now
one interesting thing is I didn't say that on this code on either side that it's a Fi net
I didn't force this to be ipv4 code
this will work for ipv4 or six the exact same code
okay so again whispy comes back with a list of stuff typically that list will be of length one
in fact I don't know why it would be anything else
but it has the same general look to it
so again I'm going to make a call to socket
to create a file descriptor that I'm going to use this will be the one that
it's missed the server listens on of your connection requests
and then there's another kind of obscure thing you have to do of setting some options on that socket
that will get it to free it up more quickly if there's a failure
if this is gone this one I dunno and it's kind of obscure and it's in the book
so I won't spend a lot of time talking about it
okay but now what here's the real work is the bind call i s the one that says
I want this file descriptor  to be associated with
this information which in particular specifies the port number
so that's where the binding occurs for this machine remember port numbers are
a resource that all the different applications on a single machine are sort of sharing
where are competing for
and so this is requesting I want to use this particular port number
in doing this in setting up a server
and that may fail if the ports already in use
or if you're trying to set up a service on a port
that you're not allowed to do like you're not allowed to set up a service on port 80 unless you have root access
so and
then again it passes in the information that was filled in by the call to get a tour info
so we're not quite done yet
but we if this succeeds then what we've done is we bound a port number
and a file descriptor together  and a socket
but it all that's done is that's again just within the machine saying okay
I agree you you you particularly this particular process gets to be listening on a particular port
but it's not actually listening yet
and I don't know why they split it into two but they do
and now I actually have to explicitly make a call to listen saying okay
now I really am ready to receive connection requests
and you can give as a parameter of a
number that says how many a request connection requests are you allowed to queue up
before they start getting refused and this is a performance parameter
that if you set it too low then
unless you have a really fast server people will get failures in their connection requests
but if it's too big then you can you're vulnerable to certain types of sort of  denial of service attacks
so again a little bit of an obscure feature
but the result of this is now
I'm returning out of this
a file descriptor that the server can use to listen to pick up connection requests
okay so let's do a little example of how we might actually do something
and I'm going to use as an example a rather mundane application
which is an echo server
an echo server is just one that responds back whatever it just received
and the code for it saw in the book on the slides
we're studying
so let me set up this amazing demonstration
so it's called the echo server I I meaning iterative it can only do one connection request at a time
and I'm going to set it up on my laptop here
and
I'll connect to that
so you'll see that I told the server use port 15 to 13 which is just a random number I picked out
as the port number
in general if you want to do your own stuff
you pick port numbers that are a thousand or greater and they're limited to be unsigned 16-bit n
so 64 or 65 thousand something some maximum
and as long as and by the way
if you're you live in a corporate world your ports will all be locked down and they will not let you do this
but in the CMU environment has a pretty permissive policy
and actually I'm just doing this on localhost but you're allowed to at CMU  open up ports like you want
so anyways I'm going to run this client and
you'll see that
the server just said I've received a connection from the localhost  not very exciting
and I've received it from port 55457
so this is the part that got assigned to the client
in making the connection the server is using port 15 to 13
and you recall we talked about last time that a link   is defined by the host and port names on either end
and that the client side is usually assigned what they call a ephemeral port
it's meaning it's just assigned a trip for this particular session that I'm going to run
and now here's the amazing feature of an echo  server is that you can type in stuff
and it will come back to you
because echoing so what's happening is
I'm sending those meaningful messages to the server
it's reading them
and it's just sending them right back
and then the clients reading that and printing it on the screen
can see that the server is telling you
oh by the way I just received so many bytes so many bytes so many bytes so you can see that it's actually doing something
and then if I send it into file which is just to control D
the client will exit and the server will
drop that connection but doesn't show
you anything and if I wanted to I could start it again and
you see this time it signed a different ephemeral port to the client
but I can only do one at a time if I tried to now do another connection
I will try and do it if I tried to do it
I wouldn't I it would just hang up the the client would hang up it would not be able to get a connection
because the server is only able to handle one client at a time
okay so that's the
what the application does and now let's see how its implemented
it's pretty simple the the nastiness was those functions we've already seen
so here's the client side of it
it calls that function I went through called open the client file descriptor
where you gave the name of the host and the name of the port
that you're the server's operating on
so I said here localhost 15 to 13
and I'm going to initialize a buffer
that will be used for communication back and forth for this network communication
so now echoing means I from a client perspective it will just read in what I've typed
so using gets or F gets to read in what's been typed on the standard input
and as long as that's not null meaning I don't have a end of file
then I will write it to the client file descriptors
so that's how I actually send it over the network
as I do a write to that a socket that that file descriptor represents
and then to get something back from the server its response I'll do a read
and riyo as you call has embedded within it
now what file descriptor that read is using
so I'll say read from that particular file descriptor fill the results back into this buffer
so I'm using buff both as a sending buffer and a receiving buffer
and then just print that out onto the on to the terminal
and this is by the way the new lines being included in this not just the
in all of this and that's how it's working
so that's all that happens
so the main point you see here is that I'm using this a socket like a file to both send and receive
the server code is just a shade more nasty than that to support some of those amazing features it has
so in particular
there's a weird struct called a socket or storage
that is just again part of this generic API
that gives you a buffer of some kind that's big enough to store
a name of a host is what I'm going to use it for you
and so I'm going to accept a connection
so except recall you recall is the way
it it says okay I'm going to wait here until a client contacts this server
so that you make a call to accept and it will just hang until that contact occurs
and then what it will return from you is a new file descriptor  that we call a connection file descriptor here
which is different from the listening file descriptor
and the reason is doesn't really show up in this code  where I'm doing iteratively
but you can imagine if I had a server and I wanted to be able to maintain a thousand connections at once
there'll be one of those file descriptors that I pick up new requests on
and then all the other ones are the various other clients that I'm communicating with right now
oh and then what accept fills in here into this information
it's a sock adder struct is about information about the client the IP address of the client
and
I'll use this call called get name info which is again at one of these kitchen sink features
that I'll pass in this client address
and
it will come back with the I the domain name of the client
and that's what you saw how it printed out when the connection was formed where that connection was coming from
so this all this business here is used to support that feature of being able to print out
what's the host number name and what port am I using
and this thing by the way  client port is
a client host name and client port are both buffers
yes host name and port are both buffers
and I'm passing a pointer those buffers
and I'm passing their length max line
and then the call to get name info is filling those in with a string representations of the host name in the port
and now it just makes a call to the echo function which I'll show you momentarily
and then it closes that connection
and then this continues you see the while one this is in a loop forever
and you actually have to control C on this program to get it to quit
okay
so let me just look one more
so the func this now is the echo function that the server uses and it's pretty straightforward
in fact it looks kind of like what you just saw except it flips around the reading and the writing
it will read some number of bytes over the connection file descriptor
and if that's a nonzero number
then it will echo that back by writing it
if it's a zero that means it's detected and into file
and it will just exit from that little loop
but remember echo is within a bigger loop of accepting new connection requests
okay but again just see that it reads is way of accepting information from the client
and then it writes to send information back to the coin
good
so one interesting feature is if you want to test some programs
you can use a program called telnet which it used to be the old-fashioned way you use before SSH
this is how you communicated with other machines
and it's absolutely completely insecure
so don't ever use it to actually and most most places
you can't even make a connection to another machine using telnet
it's amazing how simple life used to be
but for example
if I tell net to myself on that port
it will begin a session
and it will in fact look a lot like an echo client because
because telnet just sends information to the server
and the server is designed to echo it back and so it will print the response
and so if effectively telnet is behaving like an echo client for me
and I'll demo that because it's useful I mean
this is a pretty trivial program but there's actually times you can use telnet
if there's the server somewhere out there and you want to give it a poke and see what's going on
as a tool you can use telnet
let's see you have to escape with a control right bracket quick
okay
so
now let's move on to http
I try to get rid of all the animations in this
okay so that's sort of the basics of the low-level socket programming that you need to create client-server applications
so the best example out there of a client-server application is the world wide web
and you know the idea web servers  and your browser is a client
so but all of that sits on top of the protocols for that sit on top of the other internet protocols
so we talked about TCP is sort of sits on top of the lowest level the packet protocol
and then HTTP sits on top of that and uses TCP connections to send and receive data over the World Wide Web
and that's all according to a protocol that was developed starting in the early 90s
but and that's what Tim Berners Tim berners-lee did initially
and it's gone through a couple revisions
but the latest one is still dates back to 1999 HTTP version
excuse me 1.1
so just as a some terminology and you've sort of heard this at various different ways is
It’s you can one of the clever things about HTTP is it lets you set set handles different formats
you can send a JPEG image you can send a a text and so forth
and those are all encoded in a format called mime
which is actually just a way to take a binary values and convert them into hex formatted strings
oh and
and then sort of a standard for how you encode it at one end how you decode it the other
and so you get to specify when you're sending stuff you specify what
what type of information it s
and then the other thing you've probably experienced
and now we're talking a little bit ancient history and I'll update  it momentarily
but classically you either use static content meaning a fixed web page
that was written in HTML format and was designed
to just give you information that was the same every time you looked at it
or dynamic content where you will change so
for example a application a server application that's giving you the weather
it's not the same page every time and so it will format it in dynamic content  if you make a request
nowadays it's gotten a lot more complicated
because of JavaScript and all these other sort of client-side programming languages
that actually execute code on your client and communicates back and forth to get results
so I'm a little bit dated here talking about this sort of old-style way of working
but in all cases what actually comes across the wires are some type of a file
and then you've heard the term URL meaning Universal resource locator
is a combination of a couple things one is it tells you
where is that information in terms of a domain name and potentially with a port number
and then also on that particular host
where where within the host is that information to be found
and there's defaults like if you don't give anything it defaults to index.html for example
but a URL in principle gives you
where to locate something on a remote machine
and now we've seen examples of the tricks that DNS plays
so that even though you're giving a hostname a domain name
it could be any of a number of different servers but the the concept still the same
so when I make a request then
when I running my browser and I want to see a webpage
what it does is it sends an HTTP request out to the server to do something and to return back a webpage
and there's a couple of different standard services the most common the one that
it's used ninety 90 some percent of the time is get  get me a page
and there's other stuff too
and and then it will respond back
with what's called the response line and embedded within that response will be the thing you're asking for
but in front of it all is a header
that contains other stuff that is of of some range of interest of whether you really care
not it can also come back with a response that says there's an error code
as you know the infamous 404 error code
so let me give you a demo
of this just so we're talking a little abstract
and this is a little tricky to make it work
and I'll use auto telnet as a way to probe a webserver
so I'll make a telnet connection to the computer science departments a web server
and now I need to make a get request
this remember it all it is is now I'm basically providing the exact bytes
that will be seen by the web server so if I say get
slash tilde bryant
test on HTML see if this really works
hot worked
I'm always surprised when things actually work
ah so anyways let's just look at what happened
so at the top is what I typed in
it's getting and this I'm giving some the name of a particular web page that
I made up just for this purpose a fairly simple web page
and I'm telling it I want the response in the HTTP 1.1 format
and then I have to also give a hostname explicitly and the reason for this is
I given machine can actually be a serve multiple hosts
like if you know I want to pay for a hosting of some domain name  of say 2 godaddy.com
but it's serving hundreds or thousands of different domain names
and so it actually used that host information to figure out oh which particular web
you know customer am i supporting here
ok and now it came back with its response
and it said the code 200 means that was accepted which it tells you ok
and now it comes back with this is the header information that says
here's the date here the server here's some cookie information
it's a the overall content is exactly 479 bytes
and it's a text HTML format
and then it will return back the raw HTML
that this web page had
which is what I actually you know I type that I did this by hand
but you can imagine other types of things
and then it just closes the connection
so you can see that this return both the header information
and the actual content information as well
and so that's the general idea of what an HTTP transaction looks like
and the slides go through a different version of it
but it's the same general idea
so the text has a really interesting code that I
highly recommend you read and study called tiny
which is the world's smallest functioning webserver
and what it's really only a couple pages of code
it serves it says some very basic handling of static and dynamic content
it's something you can sit down and read and study 239 lines of code
now it lacks a lot of features it does very bad job of handling errors
it doesn't have a lot of the functionality you'd come to expect on a server
so it's been stripped down to the sort of Barriss bones to demonstrate the the concepts
but it's pretty cool that it works and I can say this because I didn't write it
so
so the overall idea then is on the cert it's a server
so it's receiving requests from clients from browsers
saying I want this web page or I want to execute this particular dynamic program to get dynamic content
so it comes in with a request get requests like you just saw
and it splits that it picks out  the what's called the URI
the argument to the get request a URI is a universal resource indicator
which is not a complete potential URIs are a super set of URLs
URL has to include the hostname and all the information to get from anywhere to anywhere
but a URI can just be a portion of that information
and then it it will determine is this a request for static or dynamic content
I'll show you both of them hopefully
and if it's a static content all it has to do is retrieve a file on its own machine
send that back in that format that I just showed you
so let's take a look
so this is sort of the guts of the static server
so what it's done is its received a request
this is you know a function a helper function of of this code
so I'm kind of buried down in the middle
but what it's picked out is the server has received a request for a particular file name from the URI
and it's also done a look up through the OS cal
l to figure out how big is that file how many bytes long is that file
and it's also given the file descriptor that
is the connect it the file descriptor for this particular connection
so all it's doing here you'll notice is it's doing a bunch of Spirit ups into a buffer
and what it's doing there is its formatting the header information
as a byte is just a big long string including the returns in it
and one of the features which don't ask me why the great wisdom of of Tim Berners Lee
we did or whoever figured this out but every line has to finish with both a carriage return and a new line
instead of the usual Linux thing of just new lines
so that's what the backslash R backslash n
means but you'll see it's going to respond back  to with an okay
and some of this kind of information that's not very exciting
but the ones that really matter are are the lengths the in bytes that has to be given
and the type ones beginning this file type
oh there's another function oh I remember why
there's a another helper function here that because this supports not just text but also gif and JPEG images
so get file type is another function somewhere else that's telling
which which a mime type is this particular file
and and so it's putting that together
and it's and now write set out
so it writes the header information out to the client
so it's sending back to the client
and then it's going through a few gyrations here to get the file open it up
and then there's a function called MF
if you guys covered them up
yet know which is just a tricky way to avoid having to actually read the file into the machine
but basically be able to pass off a pointer directly to or into the read it
through explicit read commands into yet another buffer just avoids one step of buffering
so all it does is map then of from the operating system where this particular file is located
and then writes that so now it's sending it off to the client
and so this could be done with a regular read in a
but this is a little bit more elegant way to handle it
and you'll notice by the way that the content length here is the length of the file
the and not does not include the the number of bytes in the header so the header comes first
there's no length associated with it that so sent back
but now the only way that the client knows exactly how many bytes
that response is going to be is by picking out this number in the header and reading that many bytes from it
we'll see that in a minute but anyways this is the way a file gets sent
so now let's just real quickly look at dynamic content
so the idea of dynamic content is it lets you pass in parameters to a program
that then gets executed and the purpose that
what that program then has to do is compose a web page  and send that web page back you
so I'm going to demo this with a feature built into here
so in particular
you probably can't you can barely see them I don't have a good way to blow up the thing
but the um you can also see what kind of things I look at but anyways
if I just say local host : 15 to 13 that means port number 15 to 13 on my local machine
which is currently running the tiny web server
and the only webpage available for it is this rather stunning figure here
but it shows that it can handle both gif content and text HTML
but it also supports
another interesting feature which is a program that can add two numbers
called add com
so our idea for a startup company that didn't quite make it so
so in particular
that the idea of this is it's a CGI program it's a dynamic content
so that I passing two numbers
embedded within the URL my request
and it comes back with a web page that is beautifully formatted like this one
so you can't see very well maybe but if you look up there the teeny tiny print at the top
Yosi localhost colon 15-213 that's the web server
and slash cgi - bin that's
what this particular server and what most servers do for interpreting dynamic content
and then a program it's an executable file called adder
and then the argument string that you embed in this kind of curious way the question mark
and then use ampersands to separate out the different fields
so that's all pretty a standard way of handling dynamic content
and as I said nowadays there's a lot fancier ways of doing it
but that's sort of the basic way
and you'll see it's still getting used today
so imagine that this time it's a get request
but instead of the adder function at some other Perl program that is sitting on the server somewhere called Eng
and we won't worry about what that program does we'll just show you the idea behind it
so in particular there's a get request comes in and it says cgi-bin
and then the next argument is interpreted as the name of a file
and what will happen then is that the server will spawn off a process
using our friends fork and exec
which you know so well now
doing the shell web so
and that that program will execute of will execute
and it will its job then is to generate a file in HTML format
and then the server will send the result back to the client
so there's a few details we got to figure out to make this work
one is how will I actually pass arguments how will nvl know what's being passed to it as arguments
how npl get whatever page HTML it creates back to the server
so that the server can send it to the client
those are all the sort of details of the CGI
specification CGI stands for common gateway interface
so you just saw a demo of edcom
and so let's just look at how this works
so as I mentioned the way things get passed is within the URL you include the program name
and then the question mark is what is like the Terminator for the program name
and then all the other arguments with ampersands between them
and you can't have any blanks in here so they put 20%
and as you probably see in various other those are called escape codes
when you can't use a particular character how do you encode it in some other way
so the first thing is how does the server then pass the argument to the program that gets executed
well it's really weird the way it does it is by creating an environment variable for your machine
that's called query string
and so the server defines that environment variable
and then the job on the CGI side of the script
is to then retrieve that environment variable is a way of getting the string
you can already see hey wait a minute what if you were running multiple servers at once
you can see you've got a problem here but
actually no environments are specific to particular processes so this will work
so it's creating for the application program that we'll be able to sort of retrieve from the operating system essentially
what arguments were passed to the are being passed to it
and so this is what the code looks like for the dynamic server
again it's going to write back
some information back to the the client
and let's look at this
and now it's going to set up this CGI a query string environment variable
and then use our friends dupe and exec
basically to redirect the standard output to its client
oh I'm sorry
the file descriptor is the the clients file descriptor
so it will tell it's going to
go and we're enough work I'm sorry
so now we're in the child process okay
let me read all the code and within the child process it's going to rename
the it's standard output so that it's writing directly to the client
and and then call exec
which as you know it's the way you take this program which is just given by a file name
and fire it up and get it going with that defined environment value
and then this is the parent we'll just wait until the child completes
okay so now we're almost done
so the now this is what the actual program the adder program does the one that the CGI program
the one that's been forked off and exempt
so it creates them the HTML
that you want to send back and here it's pretty mundane
the only actual HTML and here are the peas meaning paragraph markers
so this is literally generating HTTP  HTML content  and storing them all in a string called content
and now it wants to send that content back
and you saw before that the server already filled in the top-level stuff
but I have to tell what is the type and how many bytes it is
so I'll use sterling to figure out how many bytes I'm sending back
and the content type
and then I will and I'm pretty effing this
which as you recall ivory mapped a standard output now is talking directly to the client
and just to be sure it all goes out I'll flush that out of there at the end
so what's happening here then is that it's the job of the the CGI program to write the HTML and to send it back to the the client
so again let's just do a real quick demo here got just enough time
Oh
so I've got the tiny web server running down at the bottom and I'm using telnet to reach it
and so now I want to say
I have to take time
slash CGI - bin slash adder quest what numbers do you want to add 17 and 13
so you don't get many shots at it so I like to double check I'm doing
we worked
always amazed so it shouldn't surprise you what comes back because you just saw the code that did it but
what you see then is that this first three lines got generated by the the server code
that comes back with the ok information about the server
and then the content length was generated by the CGI program adder
and the content type and then this is the HTML that you saw being generated
so it's actually what people say about this early world wide web
and it's gotten a lot more complicated
is the best thing Tim berners-lee was to figure out how simple it could be
because other people were working much more exotic ways to get different agents to talk to each other over the Internet
and what berners-lee figured out is we can just kind of cobble together standard ideas of sockets interface
have some protocol pretty straightforward protocol
handle different content type of set up these dynamic things by forking off a process every time
which is extraordinarily inefficient way to do it  like to add two numbers by forking off a whole process
and doing it is totally absurd but then so is addcom
but you know it's not it in some ways it he took a bunch of ideas that existed and figured out how to put it together
and I'll recognize that the value people would obtain from that and it took the internet from being something that
was certainly used by nerdy people to talk to each other
and opened it up to all the things that we know of today
so it was a huge step forward I give them full credit even if from a technical point of view is actually fairly straightforward
ok so that will do us for today