I guess one thing I I and the rest of the staff request is that you
Whenever you have a question you first read the book
Then you reread the assignment and you maybe reread it again and then you ask us
Because a lot of the questions we're getting are ones
Where we just say look at this page of the book,look at this paragraph of the assignment, look at this part of the file that you were given
And so I mean, there's a lot of stuff and I understand how sometimes it's easy to miss things
So not saying don't ever ask questions but just before you ask your questions try and figure out
If I really should have come through the resources I have available to see
If the answer to my question is can be found there
So anyways enjoy the lab
So today is a suit a second part of a two-part lecture on integers and integer arithmetic
Last time we looked at representations about  how bit patterns can be interpreted is either of unsigned numbers meaning
They range between 0 and (2^w)-1
Or as two's complement numbers which is the most compliment usual way to represent what are sometimes called signed numbers
Ones it can be either negative or positive
And by the way there are other ways to represent signed numbers out there but
Two's complement is so overwhelmingly the most used system that that's what we concentrate on
Today what we'll do is that
Now go beyond the representations of these values to talk about arithmetic operations on them and some of their properties
And what we'll do in general is talk about the unsigned case
Which is in some ways easier to understand and more intuitive
And then talk about the two's complement case
So the basic rule on this is
If you take two numbers that range between up to the maximum value of an unsigned number value add them
That in principle you might need to get an extra bit to represent that sum
If you want to represent the true sum the sort of integer sum of those two numbers
Because you've doubling it
And unfortunately we can't just go out and add more bits to your computer indefinitely
So we just stop it at some point and say
Well whatever bit happened to be in that sort of next bit position
We're just going to drop it and pretend it doesn't exist
And say that the result of addition is just whatever the w bit pattern you get
If you only consider the first w bits out of it
With no warning no messages no error or anything
This is just it happens silently
So for, two's complement this is not such a hard thing to understand
It can be thought of as just modular arithmetic computing modulo the two to the word size
I'm going to use some examples and this time I've got them worked out a little more carefully
So I won't get mixed up as much
And we'll use a word size of 4 here
And as I mentioned last time
It really helps with this to work do the examples with small word sizes
To get you intuition for it rather than trying to write out 32-bit numbers or 64-bit numbers is something like that
So if you think about in the unsigned case
A 4-bit number means that it will range between 0 and 2^(4-1) or 15 right
So let's just do a few examples of cases where it overflows
So if you add 13 to 5
First of all you know I assume already that
You just add binary numbers the way you learned in school
Just doing carries and so forth except it's all modulo two
So this is 0 carry 1 1, 0  carry 1,0 carry 1
So in principle to represent the sum which is this is 5, so to represent 18
You need 5 bits, not 4
But we're just going to conveniently drop that number and say that this is actually a 2
Which of course is what 18 modules of 16 is
So the unsigned case is really pretty straightforward
And we can visualize this in this pictures in the book too
By seeing if you are representing on the x and y axis what they call U and V
Values between 0 and 15 the range of possible unsigned numbers
And if we add those we could get a sum that's up to as much as 30
Which would in principle require 5 bits to represent
But what we'll do is we'll just by dropping that most significant bit
What we do is sort of create a cliff
That when you roll over from 15 to 16  instead it drops all the way down to 0
And that's referred to as an overflow
And then from there we'll build up to the maximum value here will be 14,which is 30-16
So what we've done is basically as this picture shows when we overflow
We effectively subtract off 2^w from the sum
And keep it within the representable range of w bit numbers
So that's an unsigned
Two's complement
The first thing I want to convince you of is it two's complement addition looks just like a regular edition
In other words I can perform a subtraction
And addition of subtraction of numbers by using this two's complement representation for negative numbers
So well let me just show you some examples of that
So first of all remember that what range of values
What's the smallest number that could be representatively the 4 bit
The most negative number 4 bit two's complement number
-8
And the largest plus 7 thank you
So let's just do some examples if we took
This number 1101, as a two's complement number is -3
And we add it to 5. We'll get what we got before
And we're not good at we're going to ignore whatever carry bit it is and so the result is 2
I'm going behold that's what 5-3
So it seems like magic because it is
( Two's )And that's why part of the reason why I choose complement is to  the most commonly used way of representing signed numbers
Because the same hardware the same algorithms that are used for doing
Addition in work for either unsigned or two's complement numbers
And this works as well just to show you
If the overflow goes if the resulting thumb is goes the other way
So if I have -3, and -5 + 3
And I add those together
ok,1110 which is -2
So again if you use the same patterns for the same rule for addition
As you do with the unsigned case you'll get two's complement arithmetic
So what smoke in a few cases where the two's complement overflows
So if we take -3 and -6
And we add them together we'll get 1110
We're going to drop off the carry, which is what?
So we've added two negative numbers
And it's become positive and that's referred to as a negative overflow
And the reason of course is the number -9
I can't be represented in a 4-bit two's complement number so
It  overflowed
You'll notice that the +7 of cause differs from -9 by 16 and that's not next
And then going the other direction
If we had two large positive numbers so if we had 7 and 5
We'll get -6
So this was 7 + 5 = -4
And so this is referred to as positive overflow
We've taken two positive numbers and added them together and gotten a negative result
And you could see this  by the way if you think about this addition we took 7 and 5 would be 12
And this is the bit level representation of 12
It's just that because this is now the sign bit
We think of that as -4 not +12
And so that's the the idea of two's complement overflow
And you can see there's two different cases here
One is where the number that the sum was if we looked at the true sum
The number that you'd get for example 12 is too big to represent
So when we think of that as a two's complement number it becomes now a negative number
So that's positive overflow
Similarly if we have two negative numbers and we add them together
So that the sum is too small to negative to represent
Then those become positive numbers that's negative overflow
And you can see that in this picture
The same idea as before except there's three regions
This is the and by the way now you'll see our numbers range between -8 and +7
And the some two's complement also range between -8 and +7
But there's these three regions one is the where everything is fine
It's within the representable range
The other is where the sum was so far toward the negative side that it becomes positive
Or where it's so high on the positive side that it becomes negative
And so part of data lab you'll learn to understand these in quite precisely
But then let's see idea it's a little bit counterintuitive to say
You know somehow I can accept the idea that modular arithmetic for unsigned numbers
There's some sort of mathematical beauty to a modular arithmetic
And this is looks like kind of useless right  from a from operational characteristic
But it's the way it is and we're stuck with it
And multiplication is basically the same idea
In fact all the operations are the basically the same idea that
If you can't represent it within the word size you just take the lower w bits
So all this complicated notation here is just a way of saying
In principle if you take two W bit numbers and multiply them together
You may need a the result may require as much as 2w bits to represent
Before addition its w+1
Multiplication you actually have to double
Because you're potentially squaring the largest number
And so again we don't want to just keep doubling our word size over and over again we'll run out of bits very quickly that way
And so we just truncate it at w bits
For the unsigned case it's again modular arithmetic
It's something that you can kind of understand and believe
But for...
And so again let's just do a few examples and I won't try and work out multiplying in binary is like multiplying in decimal
You do a big table and it takes a long time so I won't try to do that
But let me just show a few examples
So if I multiply 3 * 5 is of cause equal to 15
And in an unsigned number I can represent that right
So that's okay
But if I multiply a 5*5
Then that would have representation
If I were to think about it as possibly as many as 8 bits
It would have a representation with an extra bit
And I'm going to throw this part away
And so I'd call that 9
Which of cause is equal to 25 mod 16
And so that's the general idea of it is regardless of whatever's in this upper part of the word
The product I'm just going to discard that and only look at the lower one
And life gets a little more interesting with the two's complement case
So let's look at what that does
And the answer is
Even a little bit stranger
That you not only trunk throw away whatever high order bits happen to be there
But whatever bit gets left in this position will determine whether it's a positive or a negative result
Even though with completely irrespective of the signs of the original two operands
So that can make you go all over the place
so if we had 5*4 of 20
That would be represented in this 8-bit form like so
And we just call that 4 right
Because we throwing this away
But if we did 5*5 as we saw before that's represented like this
And that's sum...
Now becomes...
So we're throwing away this
And this becomes our sign bit so the result is a -8 + 1= -7
So you see this is a similar to an example we showed at the beginning of the first lecture
You can have two positive numbers and multiply them and get a negative result
Because of the sort of quirks of this overflow
Question that
[student speaking]
Oh I'm just taking 25 and writing it in binary
Yeah if you want to you know you start with the two numbers
I'm not going to do well actually this one's an easy one there's a trick for this
If you want to know multiply a number by a power-of-2
We're going to show that later you just shift it left by two positions
So that one's an easy one
Otherwise you have to write out the table and sum all the results and all that stuff
I prefer to what computers do that
And again this two's complement stuff one interesting feature is that it works for our negative numbers too
If you do this trick of throwing away the high-order bits
And you'll have overflow cases like before because you're throwing away information
But the lower bits if the number is representable you'll get the right result
So let me just demonstrate to that to you
So this is -3
But you remember that this is equivalent to 13 as an unsigned number
And this is -2 which is equivalent to 14 as an unsigned number
So now if we multiply 13*14, you get 182
And that has a hex representation of 0xb6
And so just looking at the low-order for bits are 0110 is 6
And indeed that's -3*-2 is 6
So the point being oh and I'm waving my hands here
Because I don't want to go through all the details
But two's complement multiplication also gives you
If you can do it using the exact same rules
And as you do for unsigned multiplication the exact same hardware
I should mention that and there are instructions in the computer
In ways that you can get the upper word of a multiplication too
And those the bit patterns are different depending on whether
it's treated as a two's complement number versus unsigned
So these typically different instructions for doing that computation
But 99% of the time or more you just are looking at this lower part of the product
And that's the same whether it's a two's complement or an unsigned
And it handles negative numbers positive but it has these overflow characteristics
So as I was talking about there's a trick we can do for multiplying by a power-of-2
Which is just to shift the number to the left
And you'll often see that when you have in your code
I want to multiply some number by 4 you'll write it in your C code
If you look at the assembly code you'll see that what
The compiler generated is just says oh just shift it left by 2
So in general and you could see why this is true
By the way if you think of the number as the sum of the bits
Where X sub I is the if--but and X is the number it represents
If I want to if I shift everything left by 2
What I'm effectively doing is increasing their weight by that number of positions
So let's just shift by one if I shift everything to the left by one
Which we write like this and see two left two less symbols
It's like taking that sum but now weighting the bits by two to the i+1 by one more
And of cause that's equal to twice what the original sum was
And so we double the number
And that works also even if you shift things
So that you lose some bits right they they shift off to the left
All you're doing is the way multiplication works anyhow of truncating to w bit product
So you'll see this as I mentioned quite often in in compiled code machine level code
That they're doing shifts where you might expect them to be doing multiplications
And the reason for that as an optimization is historically the multiplication instruction took a lot longer than a shift instruction
Say one clock cycle to do a shift
And it used to be like 11,12,13 clock cycles to do a multiplication
Nowadays like on computers
We use the shark machines it only takes three clock cycles to do multiplication
Because they added a lot of hardware to do that
But three clock cycles is still more time than one
And so when you can get away with a shift it's generally a better idea
And the compiler has its own kind of judgment calls on
When is it more efficient to substitute one up for another
Did we, did I lose ground here?
Okay so the idea that if we want to multiply something by 2^k
We just shift it left by k bit
It turns out that the same almost works for dividing by 2 as well
That if you want to divide something by a power-of-2 you can shift it right by this in the same general
The only thing that becomes a little bit quirky is
Well what if the number you have is not actually divisible by that power-of-2
So for example if we had the number 01
I want. I'm going to use this
Yeah so that's 6
So if we shift it right by one we'll get 0010
(00)11 thank you
Which is 3 and that's 6/3=2
If we shift that again
We'll get 1.But of cause you know that three-halves or 1.5
The rule on integer division is you round it down round it toward 0
And so that goes to 1 so
This is what the unsigned case works fine
The signed case which I don't have a slide for
Is a little bit less of pretty
Well first of all you notice if it's a positive number the shifting rights going to be the right
Just as is for unsigned
But let's take a number that is negative
So this is -6 right
Now here's where remember I told you in the previous lecture
There's two ways to do shifting there is logical shifting where you fill in with 0
And arithmetic shifting where you fill in with ones
And guess where arithmetic shifting comes in this is it
When you want to preserve the sign of a number
while you're dividing it by power-of-2 you want arithmetic shifts
So if we shift this by one we'll keep that sign bit
And then copy the other ones over right
So we just preserve this bit here and copied the other ones over
And this is -3.And so that's good
But now if we shift again arithmetic
We will get what? -2
I can see you guys need to know how to negate numbers right
You don't know that so I'll show you in a second
So here is a little bit problematic that we shifted
We want to divide by two
But the rule should be the same that you should round toward zero
And what this is doing is it's rounding toward
Minus infinity it's rounding toward a more negative number than the the true thing
And so there's a little cute little trick
That says before you shift before you divide by a power-of-2 before you do the shift
You should add a bias
Which in this case would just be one
You know and I'll tell you where that comes from
And so if we add those numbers together we'll get 1110 right
And now when we do the shift on that we'll get 1111
And that's -1
So there's a trick and you'll again you'll see the compiler doing this where
You have in your code divided by 16 and we'll add a bias
And then it will do a right shift instead of calling division
And by the way division really really is slow even on a modern computer like what you have
The shark machines it takes 30 plus Hawk cycles
So anytime the compiler can avoid figure out a trick
That does it with shifting and tweaking things around it will
Oh so I realize I should tell you
There's a couple ways you can negate a number
That are handy to know if you ever have to do it in your head or on paper
And the standard way is what's called complement and increment
So this is how do I go from X to -X
So if I have a number and I want to negate it
Whether it's currently a negative number or it's a positive number the same trick works
What I'll do is complement it meaning I'll flip all the bits
And then I'll add one to that
And do the regular sum
And so this is 6,this is -6
So if you ever have to do it by hand
That's the way to do it complement and increment  and it goes the other way
You'll see if I compliment this
And I increment it I'll get back to my previous number
So that's a trick
That is pretty much only useful when you do things on the blackboard
Or when you have to solve a problem in data lab
Anyways the this idea of doing a using up shifting to the right to do power-of-2 division
is actually that's the whole justification for arithmetic shifting in the first place
Which by the way in and see there's no fixed requirement
For how shifting works in c for signed numbers
For unsigned it has to be a logical shift
Sign numbers the C standard says there's no fixed definition
The reality is on our machines most machines just about every machine out there
When it's a two's complement number when it's a negative where it's the signed number it's two's complement
And when you do a shift it will be an earth metic shift
So getting back to them summarizing this integer arithmetic
You see that first of all whether it's signed your unsigned
The addition or multiplication operations are the same
Whether it's a unsigned number or two's complement
And it works the negative stuff works out
As long as you don't have an overflow
And you can end up with an overflow
Only one type of overflow for unsigned and two types for signed numbers
But it's not like they just overflow on generate random numbers
There is some a pattern to what result what they are and how they can be interpreted
So we I talked about this a little bit last time and gave this example similar to this
But let me go over it a little bit more
One thing you might think of wow if this unsigned and signed stuff gets so murky
And we saw some funny examples last time
Maybe we should just banished unsigned numbers from the universe
And only allow two's complement
And that's exactly the rule that was adopted for example in Java
They said is too weird
What let's just say every number is two's complement
The only trick they did was they put in a triple right shift
Means logical shift this is Java this is not C
Whereas the double is a arithmetic
So because they realized there's a lot of cute little times
When you want to play tricks with things
And you need that logical right shift
So that's actually one approach or other more modern languages and C are saying
It's okay to have signed and unsigned
But we don't want them sort of mysteriously being cast back and forth
In ways that the programmer might not recognize
And so you have to explicitly do a cast rather than implicitly
And I think that's the better approach
But C as I mentioned does this implicit casting
And so as we saw for last time what happens with this program when you run it
To count down through an array do you remember?
Well as I if it's unsigned what will happen with this test
It always succeeds so the thing will be in an infinite loop
Actually what will happen is it will try to access
I will go down to 0 and then it will wrap around to become
The largest possible unsigned number
Which is probably way out of bounds and it will give a memory error
But it won't do what's supposed to be
And as I mentioned before these things there is a lot of sneaky ways this problem can show up
In ways you might never think of
So for example the operator sizeof is defined to say how big a particular datatype is
It's a very useful operator
But it's its return value is a what's called a size underscore t
Which is defined to be a long unsigned number
And so if we just throw in a constant like this
Then this subtraction we have a sign in is now int
But sizeof is unsigned
And so it will cast that to be unsigned implicitly
And when you compare it to 0 you'll have the same problem as before
So just to show you that these things can sneak in very tricky ways
So one way to do that then is just don't use unsigned like
And make sure if this is a a possible
Unsigned number you cast it to signed
You make sure this is recognized and signed
But there's another way that actually
At least there's a fellow over the software engineering Institute named Robert Seacord
Who has written the books that are suited to considered the  this the gold standard for how to write secure code
He works for this organization called the computer emergency response team
Which is out there tracking down bad things going on in computer security
And one of the things he and others have done is to try and come up with standards
So that people who write programs will you know avoid some of the pitfalls
That make their programs vulnerable to the security of was to attack
And so his recommended technique is when I first saw this
It was so counterintuitive to me
It hardly made sense right
So you start and again this is all unsigned arithmetic
So I'm starting to count down
And my test is when I is less than count
So here's the thing I started off smaller than count
And it's only being decremented so when would this test ever fail
[student question]
When it overflows when it wraps around
Right when I goes from zero and counts down to what would now be UMax
This test will fail which is exactly when you want it to stop
And his observation is and in C with signed numbers there's no guarantee on what happens with overflowing
As I said most people just assume it's going to be two's complement
But if you really want to be careful
You shouldn't assume anything outside of the C standard
And if you're trying to write secure code
It's probably a good idea to be cautious be conservative
On the other hand the C standard guarantees
That unsigned arithmetic will be modular arithmetic so it guarantees
If you subtract one from zero you'll get the largest number that could be represented
So it will be okay
And in fact he recommends instead of using unsigned
Which is on our machines just a 32-bit value
That you call it a size_t which is a 64-bit value
And so and write your code the way that I showed you
So I've actually started doing this
And once you kind of get used to it it it's an OK way to write code
But it's very strange-looking initial
One thing I'll point out is
What would happen if count were a signed number int
And it were you were up and it was less than zero what would happen here
So I less than count what would happen
[student question]
Right and so it become a very large positive number
And this test would almost certainly succeed
So you have the same this code doesn't avoid the pitfall
It just shifts it to saying
You better make sure you don't you know just for this case beforehand before you get into it
So I think part of it is the observation that man if you want to be careful and write code that
That is guaranteed correct no matter what implementation goes on as long as it's within the C standard
It's pretty tricky business.question up there
[student question]
Yes!Which is unfortunate right
So yes that's exactly the rule
That it's implicitly silently the C compiler doesn't give any warnings
You'll never know it cast it to unsigned and
As these examples show when you stare at that code and you think about it
It's really easy to have bugs
That you just you can look at it a thousand times and not realize that it's a bug
It's a very...and there's examples these examples in the book of
Of security flaws in sort of very important library software due to this problem exactly
So part of the reason we teach in the course is just so you appreciate that
This is a quirk in this and see that again
99% of the time you'll never even it won't bother you at all
But there will be some oddball cases that you can get in trouble with
So the other place that you'll find
Unsigned arithmetic unsigned representation use voice first of all
When you're doing modular arithmetic
Which is for example the way most encryption algorithms work
Or when you're using the bits not to represent numbers
But to represent sets the way I described it before
Then you don't want it it's easiest to just think of that as unsigned numbers
Okay so the final thing to talk about today is
Some of the low-level representations of numbers within memory
And the main point is when you are running a program on a computer
From the programming perspective either, even not just as a C programmer
In your mind the memory is just this big array of bytes
That's numbered from 0 up to some maximum number
So for example in the machines we're using the 64-bit machines
I'll an address is represented in 64 bits
But in fact the maximum address
You're allowed to use in current machines is a 47 bits
And 2^47 is still a pretty big number
So that's more memory than anyone's able to buy right now anyhow
And so it's a reasonable restriction
But the point is that logically your program thinks that it has a of that many bytes
Let's try and figure out how big 2^47 is. Anyone know it off the top of their head
So there's a trick if you want to get an approximate idea
Which is to say that 2^10 which is 1024 is approximately equal to 10^3
You say oh well that's really helpful
What it means is that 10 bits worth of number is about the same as three decimal digits all right
So for example 2^20 is around 10^6
2^30 it's around 10^9
2^40 it's around 10^12
And so that would tell you that
2^47 is around 128*10^12. Which is 128 terabytes right  tera 10^12
So if you just want to say you know get a quick figure 4 and of course these are approximations
But if you just want to get a quick handle on
How big a number you know what's range of values can I represent with so many bits of it
This is a really easy trick to do that
So the point is a 128 terabytes is a lot
You can buy disk drives a couple of disk drives will do that for you
But you couldn't buy enough DRAM on a normal budget to get that kind of memory
So that's the the current range of values but logically when you run a program
It thinks that it has that possible range
Now it doesn't really
And in fact what happens is that the operating system only allows certain regions within that memory to be referenced
And other regions if you try to access them it will create a it will signal an error what they call a segmentation fault
But logically at least it's as if you have this big array of bytes
Now in reality and we'll go into this when we talk about
How the memory system is works in virtual memory
There's this very complex combination of hardware and software begins the program this image of a very large
What you call flat space just a big array of bytes
When in reality it's shuffling between different regions of your memory
And even between your memory and your disk drive on your computer  to make it implement this particular
Idea that you have this big array of bytes
And that's all handled as I said by the operating system by the computer hardware
And it's largely invisible even to the machine level programmer even people writing assembly code
You'll often hear the term word size and it can get very confusing confusing nowadays
Because there's no really fixed idea of what a word size is
But roughly speaking the word size should be
Whatever the largest number is that or  the range that sort of signifies how big a pointer is in this language
Or hardware wise the largest sort of chunk of hardware for which
There's standard support for storing it for arithmetic operations and so forth
So when we say it's a 64-bit machine
What we mean is that it it regular and routinely manipulate 64-bit values and arithmetic operations
And also it has a pointers or the values of of addresses are 64-bit
Even if for right now only 47 of those bits are usable it's still considered a 64-bit machine
One thing that strange is in one of the features of of machines such as we have
It is that if I compile a program using GCC is the standard compiler
I can specify either I want it to be 64 bit code or 32 bit code as a flag
And it will actually generate two different kinds of object code as a result
And we'll talk in about these later
But for right now the point is the hardware itself doesn't necessarily define what the word size is
It's a combination of the hardware and the compiler  that determines
What is the word size being used in this particular program
And that code can be run on the point is a 64 bit machine
Such as we have and most machines are nowadays
Can insert of a backward compatibility a style also executes 32-bit code
And as we also saw one of the other features is
Even though it's a 64 bit word size the data type int
Without any other qualifiers to it is just 32 bit
So the sort of this mixture of how big things are
So when people just say word or word size
And let's say give a precise definition that's not a very meaningful term
And we'll sort of throw it around when we mean sort of a generic
Chunk of bits without trying to assume that it has a particular number of bits to it
Yes so one of the things is if we ever get to 64-bit words
It will be 16 petabytes 18 petabytes depending on how you define
When you those numbers get big but the error due to this approximation gets more significant
But something times 10^15 bytes
But right now we can only get to 128*10^12
So anyways the idea that that the memory itself is a series of bytes
But we can group those into blocks of words of different word sizes
And the way we do that is usually by assuming that the address of the word is the lowest value address in it
And we also will generally try to align these
So that for example a 32-bit word would be a line
So its first byte its lowest byte has all zeros in the fruit stuff in the first 5 bit positions right
No 32 4,I'm sorry the low is 2 bytes
Right so as this example shows their address is 0,4,8  and 12
They should have really written this in hex and set at C
I guess these are all in decimal anyhow
So yeah these are decimal numbers so 0,4,8,12
So you see these are on multiples of 4 of bit boundaries
And same way the 64-bit words are on multiples of 8
And those are known as aligned words and will generally will see that the compiler works pretty hard to keep things aligned
Because the hardware runs more efficiently that way
But the main point is that we can just take as many bytes
As we want and collect them together and call it a word for whatever word size we need
And as we think we saw a variant of this table before
But this is machines we'll be working on that  the standard int is still only 32 bits
But if we qualify something as being wrong
Then it will be 64 bits and will tend to do that
There's two different floating-point representations that we'll talk about
And then the main feature of a 64 bit machine  is it has an 8 byte or 64 bit pointer as compared to 32
Now there's one other kind of detail that says ok
So if a word has multiple bytes in it
What order should those bytes be should it be the
And there's two basic ways this could go one
One is that you put the bytes in what's known as little endian order meaning that
The first byte and the word is the least significant byte
Then the next and the final byte in the word is the most significant
Or you can flip that around and
Those are called little-endian and big-endian is the sort of terms for that
Which comes from English book called Gulliver's Travels
Which didn't anticipate computers at all
But it's an interesting story of how that comes about
So in out there in the world you'll find both types of machines big-endian and little-endian machines
It turns out that increasingly it's getting hard to find big-Endian machines
So little-endian all of x86 is little-endian
And it turns out ARM processors like
What you have in almost every cell phone here is an ARM processor
And the hardware those can actually be configured to run either way big-endian or little-endian
But when you're running it on any of the standard operating systems that run on ARM processors then it's running little-endian
So there used to be a brand called Sun Microsystems and they were fairly common on campus
And then back in the Macintosh before they were x86 processors
They ran one called the PowerPC
And that was a big-endian machine
But those are long in the distant past
The internet's about the only place out there
When you send packets over the internet and you want to send it of 32-bit words
They're actually sent in big-endian order and so
At the network interface you have to translate between those two
So again just to illustrate what I mean by this
is think of a byte value 4 byte value like this
And remember that the way we write numbers is we put the most significant to the left
And the least significant to the right
And so now with a big-endian instead of the intuitive one from that perspective in that the bikes
If you write the words in memory from the smallest address up to the highest
The big-endian will sort of map to what you see
Whereas a little-endian will look confusing
that you say 01,23,45,67
Because 67 is actually the least significant byte here
And so that comes first in little-endian order
And so the it used to be people would get in passionate arguments about this
That's sort of in the distant past
But and people saying you know
And the main feature in some sort of argument of big-endian is's this feature here that
When you look at it it's easier to write down
But computers don't really care
They're happy either way and so they just want one convention or another
And like I said some hardware's can actually be a by a sort of flag to flip it from  being big-endian to little-endian
But the reality is most of machines  one counter you'll encounter a little-endian machine days
But just to give you an example
Here some results that I got from actual machines there used to be some machines around
So back in the old days I could run this
I don't even know where to get a big-endian machine anymore
So these are sort of legacy results
But you'll see that the main feature is between a little-endian and a big-endian machine
When you have a integer the bytes get flipped around
So that the least significant byte comes first in a little-endian machine  and last in a big-endian machine
And that's true with negative numbers as well
That you'll get the the sign bits first in a big-endian machine
Along you'll see that the only difference between a 32-bit machine a 64-bit machine
is you have more zeros or more ones depending whether it's a positive or negative number
And again the a Sun and if I had access to a 64 bit machine
Sun is now manufactured by a company called Oracle
So in principle I could go get one of these machines and run this experiment
But it's really not a very interesting experiment so I won't bother
So in principle I could try it on a 64-bit Oracle machine and show you something different
So one thing that it's kind of a useful tool the book goes through some examples of this
is a little program that will take a series of bytes starting at some position start
And do it for however many bytes you request
And just print out in hex format
The two hex digits that represent that byte valve
And here this term pointer I'm using an unsigned char  as a pointer type a sort of generic pointer type
And so again if I run this on a x86 machine
I'll oh and I'm also by the way printing out the actual address
This character is stored it to
And so you'll see that there is these addresses with a lot of 7 Fs
What that means is it's in the upper end of this 47 bit address space
If you work it through
There's seven is three ones and then there's
Enough hex digits here to correspond to
So there's 11 hex digits beyond the seven
And you'll see that these addresses are at successive bytes bc,bd,be,bf
And the values are 0x6d3b0000 this is the least significant byte
And these are the successive bytes
And similarly I can  use this to examine pointers of various sorts
And I can examine different values and just get their low-level byte representations
And so I did this back when I could get to a Sun machine
It had one way of representing a pointer
And the main point is even across machines
Whether it's a byte ordering or whatever
You'll get different values for pointers,there's no guarantee  that when you load imputed a min to one machine and run it
That it will use the same addresses as that same programming running on a different machine
Even if actually they're identical hardware and operating system there can be variation
Because pointers aren't you you can't directly copy a pointer from one machine to another
On one thing about also is regardless of byte ordering  the ordering of of characters is the same
And so a string in C is always represented by a series of bytes
Where the final byte is 0 note called null terminator
And the individual bytes correspond to the character codes for that number
And these character codes are just sometimes called ASCII format
Which is a little bit old-fashioned by the way
There's more modern character codes too that can represent non English alphabets
But the C standard is still back in the days of only supporting the the ASCII format
Question
[student speaking]
Yes!So this should have been...well no this is good so I'm casting
I want to show the 4 bytes size event
Because this is an int I'm representing
The pointer let's see the code where it's printing the pointer
All this notation %p is the directive to say print out a pointer proposed right
And %x is the directive to print out a hex representation
So it's printing out both the address the starting position of that particular byte
And the value of that byte as two different things
Does that answer your question?
[student speaking]
But remember show bytes is being given a pointer and a length
And so what this is and what it's saying is starting at that address print out the next series of bytes for me
How many bytes I asked for
And in this case I'm creating a pointer to this integer
But I want to show the the bytes in that integer the four bytes that make up that integer
And that's why I'm giving it the number four here instead of eight is it
[student speaking]
Yes it will be
And that's fine because in this code
It's I'm using the %p directive to designate how to print out the pointer
And that will print it as many bytes as it takes for that particular machine that it's running on
So %p is actually a very handy directive
If you have to print it addresses like for debugging purposes or something
Because it will automatically adapt to whatever machine it's running on
Question
[student speaking]
Well I've defined it to be an unsigned care here
So type death is a way to introduce a name for some of datatype right
And so I've just declared a pointer quote pointer to refer to an unsigned care
If you did a void * it would not be happy with this reference here right
You can't reference a void * is just a way to pass around a generic pointer
But you can't actually reference that element
So what I'm basically doing is saying this reference is treat it like an array
Treat you treat my series of bytes is an array and print out each of the bytes in that array
And so here where I'm a is a number
And I'm taking the address of that integer
And casting it to be an unsigned char *
So sort of a generic slightly generic pointer but not quite as generic as void *
And then printing it out.It's good question by the way
Okay so the point being that strings are just strings
So that's the same from one machine to the next
Okay what soonish up today with some puzzles
And these have this annoying way of showing up on exams
So it's worth being able to do these kind of things
And you'll also notice I cleverly did not include the answers in the slides
So you can't just peek ahead and figure out what the answers are
So let's just go through them but I actually worked them out to make sure I have the answers
So if x and basically these are sort of statements that you want to say these are either always true
And maybe there's some logic behind why it's always true
Or it's possibly false and you won't have to give some example that would make that false
So let's go through these as many as we have time for  and see where we get to
So if I take x and I double it multiply it by 2
if x who are negative and my guaranteed that 2x will be negative
No so
By the way one general way to find counter examples is to try team in
It's a really good one
And that works here right if I take team n which is one and a bunch of zeros I double it
It's like shifting it but left and it will become what 0 right
And so again assume that x is at any negative number
And ux is any two's complement number
And ux is what happens if I cast it to be unsigned
So as ux always you're greater than or equal to 0
Yeah
This is slightly more obscure if I take x and I mask off 7
you remember is the bit pattern 111
So if I mask off all but the lowest 3 bits
And I find that those are all ones
I'm already giving you the answer here
And then I shift it left by 30 positions
What can I say about the result
So I know the x must finish with three ones right
And I shift that by thirty
And this these will be the only two bits that are left after the shifting
And they will be in the most significant position
So what can I say about that number is negative
So this is a true statement rather obscure,but it is true
Is UX greater than -1?
It's almost true right
The one counterexample would be what zero
Well actually no you're right there's a lot of examples it's hardly ever true
It's almost always false I was wrong
The only thing that would make it true would be...it's never true
[student laugh]
Okay so it's never true
Okay if x is greater than y is -x less than -y
No so by the way one thing we didn't really cover is
What is the negative of Tmin
And to see that we can use our compliment  and income increment trick
So when you compliment and increment G min you get Tmin
And that's a why it's such a great counter example
So in particular if y is tmin and x is something else
Then that left-hand part will be true but the right-hand part will not be true
Okay x*x greater than or equal to zero we've seen examples of that being false
If x is...this is kind of silly. If x is greater than 0 and y is greater than 0. Is x+y > 0.No
If x >= 0. Is -x<= 0
Gotcha, you're right it's true right
Because that...but let's take it counter part.If x <=0. Is -x >= 0
Tmin right so right the point being that the largest any positive number can be represented as negative
But there's one negative number that can't be represented as positive
And so that asymmetry is why you get different answers to these
If I take x and I look at -x and I shift them to the right by 31
Am I going to get all ones
This is a really weird statement
So it actually kind of works right
If I take all zeros
And I subtract one I'll get -1
And I all them, that works
So what's wrong with this?
what's that?
Oh but if I shift this to the right 31 places it's going to shift arithmetic
[student speaking]
What's that?
Oh I see, oh I'm sorry I already jumped ahead to a different puzzle
x and  -x and I'm so you're right actually
If the two numbers are 0 and I or those I get 0
But you'll figure out you'll notice if it's anything non zero
Actually this will be true
And that's an interesting feature
So there's a couple other puzzles and I'll let you solve those on your own
We're all set for today