Good afternoon everybody
Welcome good to see you as always
Today we're going to learn about a important concept in computer science called virtual memory
So consider a system that uses physical addressing
Right we've always idea about memory so far has been that it's a contiguous array of physical bytes
That we can access just by giving some an offset called an address
So in a system that uses physical addressing
The CPU executes like say a move instruction
Which generates an effective address,the physical address
And this address is actually the offset of a byte in main memory so
You know here the CPU has generated a physical address of 4
Since that address to the memory
And then the memory fetches the word from at that address and then sends it back to the CPU
Now this is in fact the way that very simple microcontrollers work
But it's not the way most systems work including your phones, your desktops,your servers
These systems instead virtualize this main memory
Now the idea of virtualization is a very important one in computer science
And it expands a lot of it applies to, a lot of areas of computer systems
Now when you virtualize a resource
You present the user of that resource with some different kind of view of that resource
You present typically some kind of an abstraction or some kind of a different view of the resource
And you do it by interposing on accesses to that resource
So in all cases there's some resource and you want to virtualize it
And you do that by interpting or interposing on the accesses to that resource
Okay and then once you...we saw this when we created wrapper functions for like malloc
I will showing you inter positioning
The same technique is used to virtualize a resource
And once you've intercePTEd that access then you can deal with it any way you want
So that's how you have sort of full power to change a person to change the view of that resource okay
So a good example you saw this when we looked at disks
And you know physically disk consists of cylinders tracks sectors platters surfaces
And to access a particular sector on of those disks
You have to specify the cylinder and the track and the surface
Okay but we saw that the view that disk controller is present is actually different
It's a virtualized view of the disk
And the controller instead presents to the kernel a view of the disk as a series of a sequence of logical blocks
And it presents that view by intercepting the requests from the kernel for I/O
And changing those logical block numbers that the kernel sends into the actual physical address
Ok so that's a very important example of virtualization in a system
Now the memory is that is a very....is a crucial resource in the system
And what we found is that it's useful to virtualize that memory resource
Okay and the way this is done
Remember before we virtually the disk by having the disk controller intercept request
In the case of the main memory resource
The requests are actually intercePTEd by a piece of hardware called the MMU the memory management unit
So the way this works is that the CPU executes an instruction
Say it's a move instruction that generates some effect of address
So this is actually a virtual address
It's the CPU sends that address to the MMU
Which goes through a process called address translation which will study later today
And it converts that virtual address in this case 4100 into a physical address 4
Which actually corresponds to the address of that the data object that we want
Ok so once the MMU translates the virtual address to a physical address
Then the memory will return the word at that address
So this...
My wonder why in the world would you want to do this
Well it turns out there's all kinds of good reasons to virtualize the address space
And so before I can explain those to you
Let me just define a few terms
So an address space is a set of addresses
Ok so an address spaces is a set
Not of data bytes but of the addresses of those bytes
And a linear address space is a content is a contiguous set of contiguous non-negative integers
Okay so just 0,1,2,3,4 and so on
The virtual address space is a set of N=2^n virtual addresses a linear it's a linear address space
And the physical address space is a set of M=2^m physical addresses ok
And so typically the virtual address space is usually much larger than the physical address space
Okay the physical address space corresponds to the amount of DRAM that you actually have in the system
The virtual address space is the same for all processes running on that system
Okay why do we want to implement virtual memory
Why do this,why do this level of indirection with the MMU
Well there's really three big reasons so
The first is that virtual memory uses the DRAM as a cache for the actual data stored on disk
Okay so you can think of virtual memory as it as a DRAM cache for data stored on the disk
And this allows us to use the memory much more efficiently
Because we only need to cache items that are frequently used
Right just the same idea that we learned when we talked about caches and locality
So that's one thing we can use the memory much more efficiently by only using the portions of the virtual address space
By only actually storing the portions of the virtual address space in the physical memory
Okay the second thing is it greatly simplifies memory management
So we saw it every process has the same view right
There's code loaded at code and data are always loaded at the same address
The stack is at the top of the user visible address space
So every process has the same similar-looking virtual address space
But in actual in actuality that the memory that corresponds to those
Those addresses is actually scattered all over main memory
Okay so that's a really important benefit of virtual memory
And then finally it allows us to protect accesses
So remember we had to...
A process we saw that a process provides the separate address space
That's protected from accesses by other processes
Okay so virtual memory allows us to create these separate protected private address spaces
Okay and so what we'll do today we'll look in more detail at these three ideas
And then we'll go into the specifics of address translation
So I'm going to...for the first part of this lecture
We're going to talk about address translation just in kind of high-level terms
But then we'll go into the details at the end you can see how it really works
Okay so let's look at VM as a tool for caching
So conceptually you can think of your virtual memory as a sequence of bytes stored on disk
And then the contents of that virtual memory stored on disk are cached in DRAM
Okay so think of the the DRAM is a cache for this array of contiguous bytes stored on the disk
And just like any cache the data is broken up into blocks
Okay and then we have so... so here we have the...
And those blocks for virtual memory systems are called pages
They're typically larger than much larger than the cache blocks
That we that we study done
So for k bytes typically instead of the 64 bytes
Like that we learned about in when we studied cache memories
So this virtual memory conceptually you can think of it as being a sequence of pages stored on the disk
So called virtual pages
And each of these pages will identify with a number so here's virtual page 0,virtual page 1
And then a subset of those pages are stored in the physical memory, in the physical DRAM memory
And then there's some mapping function
That tells us which pages have been cached
Ok so in this case I've just shown a snapshot
Where we have three virtual pages cached somewhere in DRAM
Okay and there's no relation between the virtual page number and the the physical page number that it's mapped to
Some of these pages are not cached so they're still stored on disk
So in this case VP2 is still stored on disk
And there's some pages which aren't even allocated,so they don't exist on the disk
It's a way to think of that
Right we really wouldn't want to store
Every single page in address space with that's to the size to the 48th
We really wouldn't want to store all those on disk
So most of the address space is unallocated
Ok so we can just think of this,so this DRAM is just a cache
But it has a much different organization
Than the cache memories we studied earlier
And the difference is driven by that the enormous miss penalty when you go from
If you have a cache and DRAM the miss penalty would to fetch a data item from the disk is huge
So the design of this virtual memory cache is totally driven by this enormous miss penalty
And so as a result that blocks are larger
So remember we talked about that the block size is kind of a trade-off
Between sort of useful getting used being able to usefully amortize the cost of fetching that block
Versus sort of consuming too much of this scarce cache space right
So in this case our cache memories were 64 byte blocks
Virtual most virtual memory systems have like 4k byte blocks with an option to increase to 4 megabytes
In the case of x86
And now this cash and other consequence of the enormous missed penalty is that
You really want to have as large associativity as you can
Remember we saw with direct mapped cache is that were subject to these conflict misses
And and if you increase the associativity of the cache
You reduce the probability of those conflict misses
But you never completely eliminate them until you have a fully associative cache with just one set
Okay so in a virtual memory,in a virtual memory cache
It's fully associative there's one set and each virtual page can go anywhere in the cache
Okay so this requires a really complicated mapping function
Somehow we're going to have to keep track of where all these cached pages are
And we can't really do a search that would be way too inexpensive
So you remember when we with a cache memory the hardware actually did a search within the set
A parallel search to find try to find a cache line
But with a software cache like this that that's not feasible
All right so somehow we're going to have to remember where these cached blocks are in this very large set
And again because it's so expensive if you make a mistake
When you're trying to identify a victim page
If you make a mistake and you evict a page that then is referenced again in the near future
You pay a big price for it okay
So virtual memory caches have much more sophisticated replacement algorithms than like simple lru that
That we saw with cache memories
Now they're these replacement algorithms are outside of the scope of this course
You'll learn about them and when you take OS
But because it's in software we can afford to do very expensive replacement algorithms
And we can take a long fairly relatively long time to execute the code for those algorithms
Because any time we spend figuring out a victim block will be much less than the cost of making a mistake
And paying the access time,the miss time,the miss penalty to to disk
And then also as a result of virtual memory systems never use right through  just  it takes to one
Right so they always use right back and they try to defer writing anything back to the disk as long as possible
Alright now how do we keep track
Somehow we have to keep track of this complicated cache and DRAM
And the data structure that keeps track of the location of the virtual pages
In memory is called the page table
Now a page table is just a data structure in memory
That the kernel maintains for as part of each process context
Okay so every process has its own page table
And it's just a...it's an array of so called page table entries or PTEs
Where PTE k contains the physical address of physical page k in DRAM okay
So here's how it works there's this page table in DRAM
There's virtual pages stored on disk
And then there's....and then there's physical
There's virtual pages stored in various physical pages in DRAM
And then the page table keeps track of where those are stored
So here we have a case this PTE 1 corresponds to virtual page 1
And in this case it says that virtual page 1 is mapped into physical page 0
Virtual page 2 is mapped into physical page 1 and so on
Ok now some of these the pages that aren't in memory are stored on disks the allocated pages
And so for those pages the page table entry contains a pointer to the location of that that page on disk
So think of it as a logical block number where that page can be found on the disk
And then some of the pages are
Not allocated so there's a null entry in the page table
Now a page hit
So this is just a cache right,so we have hits and misses
So a page hit occurs when there's a reference to a word in the virtual address space
That's contained in a page that's cached in the DRAM
Okay so let's say that we have you know the CPU execute this and move instruction it generates a virtual address
The MMU
Looks up in the page table and let's say this virtual address is somewhere within virtual page 2
Okay so that the MMU looks up the page table entry number 2
And it extracts the physical address of that of that virtual page 2
Okay so that's a, so in this case
In this case the page is in memory it's cached in memory
And so we have a hit
And now the memory can return that,can return that physical address to the MMU
Now a miss is a reference to a word that's not cashed in physical memory
So in this case virtual page 0,1,2,3 is not cached in DRAM
It's stored on the disk
So now that triggers an exception ok page fault exception
In the hardware the hardware triggers the exception
And that causes the transfer of control to a chunk of code in the kernel called the page fault handler
Which then selects a victim to be evicted,in this case virtual page 4
And it fetches virtual page 3 from the disk
Loads it up into memory
And if and then changes,and then updates this page table entry to reflect the fact that virtual page 4 is now stored on disk
And if virtual page 4 had been modified at any time it would have to write the contents of it that to disk as well
So once the handler is copied virtual page 3 into memory
The instruction that caused the page fault now can be re-executed
Okay so once the...so when the page fault handler in the kernel returns it returns to the faulting instruction
Which then reacts acutes
And now that page is when the MMU checks that the PTE corresponding to that page
It finds that it's indeed cache so
So now the instruction can continue and we can fetch that
Whatever word at that virtual address from the DRAM
Okay now we can allocate a new page of memories
So in this example virtual page 0,1,2,3,4,5 is not allocated
So if you need to let's say you do malloc of a very large chunk of virtual address space
If those pages,if one of those pages hasn't been allocated yet then the kernel actually
Or the malloc function actually has to create allocate that memory by calling a function called s break
Okay and then what s break does is actually allocates
This page and records where it's loaded now would probably actually put it up into
Now I guess it wouldn't actually show up in the DRAM cache until it was that page was touched
Okay so just allocating space just changes this page table entry
And then when that page is actually touched then it'll be brought into the cache
So I don't know about you but the first time I learned about this I was
I was pretty appalled it just seemed like the most inefficient terrible idea right
How in the world can you afford to on every single instruction that uses memory
Do all this copying back and forth and looking up in tables
And it just seems like an awful idea
But once again locality saves us
Okay and it actually works because programs have locality
Okay and it's actually fairly efficient
And the reason is that at any point of time programs tend to access a set of pages called the working set
Okay just by locality right by temporal locality,by the principle of temporal locality and spatial locality
You tend to sort of reuse the same things reuse nearby things okay
And so if that working set is less than the main memory size
Then all of the pages in the current were that will fit in memory and then things will be great
Okay but if the some of the working set sizes for for every process right our systems running multiple processes
If it exceeds the main memory size
Then you have this meltdown where processes are thrashing each other and causing pages to be copied back and forth
So you never ever know process ever gets it's working set fully into memory
Okay and we'll look at a technique when we look at address translation
We'll look at a little hardware cache called a translation look aside buffer
That further exploits the locality property of programs
Okay so that's virtual memory is a tool for caching
It's also a member of tool for memory management
And it greatly simplifies all kinds of aspects of memory management for the kernel
So the key idea is that each process has its own virtual address space
The kernel implements this by giving each process its own separate page table
In the context of that process so it's just a data structure in the kernel
That the process key...that the kernel keeps for that process
And the page table for each process maps the virtual address space for that process
Now what's interesting so you have that these pages contiguous pages in the virtual address space
Can be mapped anywhere in the DRAM,in the physical address space
So and they can be scattered all over the place
And different virtual pages and different processes can be mapped to different physical pages
So here we have virtual page one which is mapped to physical page two
In process 1 but in process 2 virtual page one is mapped to physical page 8
Okay so in this way we can present a view to each,to the programmer and to the tools
That each process has a very similar address space virtual address space
Same size address space code and data start at the same place
But then the actual pages that process used can be scattered in memory
Okay and then it gives us the most efficient way to use the memory
If we didn't have this mechanism think about how would you keep track let's say you had 50 processes running
On the machine at any point in time
How in the world would you keep track of where all of the the data  those processes were using
Well one technique that you could imagine in fact it was used in the in the bad old days but before virtual memory
One thing you can imagine is that just give every process its own chunk of the physical address space
Just take your physical address space partition it
And then each process gets loads and runs and it's own part of the address space
Well this has all kinds of problems right I mean you could
If you what do you do if you add a process
So you really can't partition the address space you really have to sort of say well
Each process gets some little chunk
And I'm going to reserve some of the address space in case there's new processes that need memory
Another problem is that now you have to write your programs
You can't just link your program ahead of time
Because it has to be relocated when it's loaded right
Because you don't...you know a process, you don't know where in the memory it's going to go, it's going to get some chunk
So you have to either relocate all the the references
That the references to global symbols at when it's actually loaded
Or you have to create a system where all of the instructions are relative
So there's no absolute addresses
All addresses are relative to say the start of the program something like that
So anyway all of these things are just terribly complicated
And they're all solved beautifully by virtual memory
So the each virtual page can be mapped to any physical page so that really helps simplify things
And even at different times the same virtual page can be stored in different physical pages at different times
All right so if a page for it,for a while it might be cached in one physical page
Then it gets swapped out and the next time it's referenced
It can get cached in a different physical page that if it's no longer available
Right so it provides so the most flexible scheduling freedom
In the way that we in...the way that we manage the memory
And it also provides this really neat capability
Where you can map virtual pages to the same physical page
So there's this is a very simple straightforward way for multiple processes to share certain code or data
Okay and what you do is you just that the page table entry in these different processes
Just points to the same physical page
So in this case virtual page 2 points to physical page 6
In each of the page tables for process 1 and process 2
So this is how shared libraries are implemented
Right so lib.c is the same code for every process running on the system
So lib.c just needs to be loaded once into physical into physical memory
And then processes that want to access functions and data in lib.c just map
The pages in their virtual address space to the physical pages where lib.c is actually loaded
Ok so now there's only one copy of lib.c everywhere in the system
But every process thinks it's got its own copy
Now this virtual memory for...
Using virtual memory to help simplify memory management greatly simplifies linking and loading
Ok for the reasons I mentioned before
Linkers now can assume that every program is going to be loaded at exactly the same place
So the linker knows ahead of time where everything is going to be
And then it can resolve it can relocate all those references accordingly
Now it really makes loading as simple
So what...so execve the loader
If you want to load a program now execve looks at the elf binary the executable binary
Ok it sees how it identifies how big the code and the data sections in that binary are
It allocates virtual memory starting at a fixed address for the code and data
It creates PTEs for them and marks each of them is invalid
Ok so each PTE contains a valid mapping
So each PTE that's mapped to code and data contains a valid physical page number
But then the it does this trick of setting the valid bit to 0
So when the MMU x encounters a PTE whose valid bit is 0
It triggers a page fault
Right it looks as though that page is not been initialized yet
So it's kind of a trick
Right and then that triggers a page fault to the kernel
And then the kernel will then can then copy that that page into physical memory
Ok so this the loading actually programs and data aren't actually they're not low loaded
You know they're not just like copied into memory
It happens as a result of of page faults,it happens as a result of misses
When and it's deferred to until a byte in that page is accessed
Okay so this is called demand paging okay
But it's really just like any of the other caches we've looked at right
You don't load a block into the cache until a word within that block is accessed okay
So loading actually...so loading is actually this is a very efficient mechanism right because
You may have a program that contains a huge,say a huge array,a large array
But you're only accessing a portion of that array
So that entire array won't actually be be allocated the pages will only come into DRAM
When they're...when a word within that page is touched
So if you're only accessing a portion of this extremely large array
Only the data that you access gets loaded and used
So it's a very very smart mechanism and extremely helpful for
For allowing us to use this precious memory resource
Okay so the third motivation for virtual memory is that it helps us protect portions of memory
So you recall that our processes
You know portions of our virtual address space or read-only like the code section
Okay and there are other portions of the address space that can only be executed by the kernel
So on...
On systems like x86-64
It's a 64-bit system
So the pointers and addresses or 64 bits
But in actuality the real virtual address space is 48 bits
Okay so it's only..it's 2^48
And then the high-order bits after bit 48 are either all zeros or all ones
Okay so
And that's the that sort of intel's rule
And so the addresses where the high order bits are all ones are reserved for the kernel
The kernels code and the kernels data
Okay the addresses were all the bits are zero or reserved for user code
Okay so any reference,any address that contains all ones in those higher order bits
Is by definition either code or data in the kernel
And so you can add bits to the PTE
That specify whether certain virtual pages can be accessed by user code
Or if they have to be accessed by the kernel,so this so-called supervisor mode
And you can also add bits that control whether that page can be read written or executed
Okay so this executes bit is new with x86-64,it didn't exist in 32-bit x86 systems
And this is the technique that's used now to try to prevent against attack lab code injection style attacks
Because it makes it impossible
If this bit is set you can't load instructions from any byte within that page
And so in fact it was this the introduction of this execute bit
That's or led to things like return-oriented programming attacks like you did in your attack lab
Okay so this by just the simple technique of adding bits to the PTE
We provide a way attic way to protect
Different parts of our virtual address space from unauthorized accesses
And then the the MMU actually checks these bits on each access
And if there's a problem you know if you're trying to do a right and the right
The right that's not enabled then it throws an exception which then the kernel the colonel deals with
Ok so so far I've been talking about address translation it kind of high-level terms
So let's get down to details and see how it really works
Okay so we're given a virtual address of N elements physical address of M elements
Like I said before N is usually larger than M but it doesn't have to be
Okay it's perfectly there's no reason M could be much larger than N
And there it's typically not but it could be
And so given these two address spaces we have a map function that takes that maps from V to P
With an optional empty set or with an additional empty set
And so for virtual address a,MAP(a)=a'
If the data at virtual address a is a physical address a'
Okay so I mean that's just what we...it's just a little more formal way to say
What we've been talking about before with our diagrams
And then map a is the empty set if the data at virtual address a is not in physical memory
Okay so just for a summary I'm going to put up a list of all the symbols we're going to be using in address translation
But this is just for summary,this is just for reference if you're using the slides later on
Okay so here's how address translation where the page table works
So we're given some virtual address
That consists of n bits
And we have blocks that consists of whose size can be represented with p bits
Okay so think about this now there
So this is very similar to what we looked at when we did caching you know the address bits for a cache
So these first p bits correspond to the page offset
So this is analogous to the blocks offsets that we saw with caches
And then the remaining bits correspond to the virtual page number
This is so member this is fully associative right so there's only one set
So in a fully associative cache everything after the block offset is tagged
So think of this as like a tag
This is the...this is what uniquely identifies this block
And we in virtual memory parlance we refer to it as a virtual page number
Now the page table the beginning of the page table is pointed to by this page table based register
On intel systems  that's it's called CR3 control register 3
But this register contains the physical address of the page table in memory
The beginning of that...
And so when the when the CPU presents a virtual page,a virtual address to the MMU
It takes the virtual page number
And uses that as an index into the page table
Ok and then it...and that identifies a page table entry which contains if this is mapped into memory
I contains the physical address of the corresponding physical page
Ok so the whole purpose of address translation is to come up you're given a virtual address
And you want to come up with a corresponding physical address
Ok so the physical address,the physical page number portion of the physical address comes out of the page table entry
And this is interesting the the physical page offset portion of the physical address comes out of the virtual page offset
And it those bits are identical
Okay so now you should convince yourself that this is true right
The offset in a virtual block is going to be the same as the offset in a physical block
They're the same size blocks
And you can also see why this virtual page number
It identifies the page number in the page table
So imagine a virtual address that's all zeros
Okay all zeros
So it's virtual address zero
And now that will have a virtual page number of zero
And the byte at that address will be at offset zero
Okay now increment by one virtual address one
So that will be in an offset of 1 and it will be in the same virtual page of zero
Right now keep incrementing until all of the bits in the virtual page offset are ones
And the virtual page numbers is zero
Okay so this is the last byte in that virtual page zero
Now increment one more time
The one bit carries over to the virtual page number so now we go to the next virtual page
And it's at an offset of zero okay so
So can you see it's sort of sort of obvious when you think about it like that
You know why we can just take these bits after the virtual page offset and use them to uniquely identify
What virtual page were we're working with
Okay so let's see how I
Let's see how it works in this system in more detail
So our system our CPU sends a virtual address to the MMU as a result of executing
A move instruction or call or return or any kind of control transfer
The MMU
Looks up the PTE, so it fetches the PTE from the page cable stored in memory
So this is actually going off the chip onto memory into this PTE stored in memory
It gets the it fetches the PTE extracts the and uses that PTE to construct the physical address
Okay and then it sends that physical address to the cache and memory system
Which eventually results in the data being returned back to the CPU
Okay so even for a hit,we still have memory references
Right because we have to fetch that page table entry
Now miss is in this parlance is called a page fault
So in this case the same thing happens as before that the CPU sends the virtual address to the MMU
The MMU fetches that the PTE for memory
But then when it looks then when the MMU looks at the PTE
It sees that there's either an invalid valid bit or a zero valid bit or the
The it's indicated that the data stored on disk
And so in that case it the MMU triggers a page fault exception
Which transfers control to this page fault handler
The handler identifies a victim and
If it's been modified copies it out to disk
Then it fetches the new page from disk into memory and up through the cache hierarchy
OK
And then it did...
And then it causes that the then the handler returns to the to the process
And when a handler for a fault returns
It causes the faulting instruction to re-execute
So now the move instruction that faulted is re-execute,but this time there's a page hit
Now you may be interested how the cash is integrated into all of this
So the MMU send fetches page table entries
So it passes page table addresses to the cash
If those missed those go to memory
The memory returns those page table entries to the cache
And then ultimately to the MMU
The MMU constructs that physical address and then its sense that physical address to the cache
Right so with caching the way we've been caching is done using physical addresses
Okay in this case it's also possible to construct caches that work with virtual addresses but yes
[student speaking]
Yeah so, it will get into that...
Okay so the question is how is the virtual address space implemented on disk
And it when it actually does a much more efficient thing than the sort of a abstract model that I described
So most pages there's an option when you allocate a new virtual memory page
You can allocate it,so that it's all zeros
Okay so there's a special you can say I want this I want to allocate a page of all zeros
In that case you know that page doesn't need to ever get stored on disk
Right it's just the memory it's as though it was created on disk and then loaded into memory
So those pages that are all zeros don't exist on disk
You know when pages are modified
It's a little more pages can be mapped to particular files for example when we load an elf binary
The pages that correspond to the code are actually mapped to the bytes in the binary
That contain the code
So that when you miss on that page it fed it brings in those code pages
Okay so pages can be mapped to user level files on disk
Or not they can be anonymous and not mapped
So if they're mapped to user level
If they're mapped to user level files and you write to a page
Then it will get written back to the page that it's mapped to
If it's not mapped to any page it's stored in this area called the swap area or the swap file okay
yes
[student speaking]
Oh yeah so the question is when you load a page from disk into memory
Does it also get cached in the cache memory hierarchy and the answer is yes
So if you load an entire page
That page will be broken up into blocks 64 byte blocks
And and load it into the cache
So everything that you fetch from the cache goes through
The from the memory goes through the cache hierarchy
Okay so I claim that virtual memory works
Because of locality and that's true but if we still had to fetch
If every time we had a miss we still had to go to memory
It would be too inefficient
Okay so the the MMU speeds up this translation process by caching page table entries
In a hardware cache within the MMU called the translation look aside buffer or TLB
So the TLB is a hardware cache that caches is PTEs page table entries
And it contains like it contains a cache of the most recently
You know it's just like any other cache so it contains a cache of the most recently used page table entries
And so the the MMU remember the the unique part of a virtual address that defines a virtual page is the virtual page number bits
Okay so the the the TLB uses the the VPN portion of the virtual address  to access it
And so that just like any other set it has a set index a set of set index bits which are just determined by how many
How many entries that or how many sets that the TLB has
And it has a tag with for the remaining bits to disambiguate any and to disambiguate any cash lines or PTEs
The map to the same set
Okay so the the VON or the TLBI(TLB index) maps to this particular set
And then it uses the...
The TLB uses the TLBT bits to disambiguate and determine if the PTE that it's looking for is,it is really stored in the cache
Okay so the way this works is
CPU generates a virtual address it goes through the MMU
The MMU instead of looking in memory and directly going to the page table entry
It first asks the TLB if it has that it sends it the VPN
And so do you have this virtual page the PTE for this virtual page
And if it does the TLB returns a hit
And it returns that page table entry which the MMU can then use to construct the physical address
To send to the cache and memory system
Eventually I result in that the data being sent back
Now when you have a miss then there's this one the MMU checks with the TLB for the PTE
It misses so then the MMU has to go to memory just like before okay so this is
And then everything is the same the memory returns the PTE to the MMU which stashes it in the TLB
And just like before if there's no room in the
If yeah if a PTE has been modified then it has to be written back out okay just like any other cache
And eventually the MMU uses that to construct a physical address and then the data gets sent back
Okay if you've been paying attention unlike a couple people
If you've been paying attention
You're going to be very concerned about the size of these page tables
Right that I mean
We've got 4kbytes suppose we have 4kbytes pages
And our effective address space is 48 bits like it is with an x86-64 system
Then and we have an 8-byte page table entry
We need a page table 512 gigabytes
Okay the address space 2^48 bytes
Divided by 2^12 bytes per page
Okay so that's the number of page table entries that we need
And then the size of each page table entry is 8 bytes
So we need almost a terabyte of of DRAM just to hold the page table right so
So then obviously it's not going to work
And it's obviously not how their page tables are really implemented
So the solution is to to use a hierarchy of page tables
So in it so we if we have a two level page table
The there's a top of first level page table called the level 1 table
Which is always in memory ok it's never never page down
And then there's a suit a sequence of level 2 page tables and they're all the same size
Right and the first level 1 table points to the beginning of the first level 2 table
So it contains a physical address that points to the base
The second level 1 table points to the second level 2 table and so on okay
So if we have this kind of system remember most of the virtual address space is unused
Right so if we have this kind of system we can avoid creating many unnecessary page tables
Okay so imagine if we have a two level hierarchy
So let's look at our virtual address space in this example
And what I've allocated two k pages for code and data for this program
And then there's their 6k unallocated pages
And then the stack then there's a page that's allocated for the stack
I'm sorry there's a thousand 24 pages allocated for the stack
Most of which are...I'm sorry...there's a region of memory that
That's the size of a thousand 24 pages
But most of them are unallocated and I've only allocated one for the top of the stack
Okay so given this layout for my process
I only need three level to page tables
Okay the first page table covers this region of my code and data
The first thousand 24 pages
The next page table covers the remaining thousand 24 pages
Okay so these two level two page tables cover all of the code and data
Okay and similarly the what I need for my stack I just need one page table
And it only has one valid PTE it's the very last one
Okay and then I have a single level one table that points to the three level two tables
Okay so I've...with four page tables I've covered the entire virtual address space
Now the way that the MMU uses these multiple page tables to do address translation is as follows
Again we have a virtual page offset which consists of the first p bit
And then the VPN the remaining bits give the VPN
For a k level page table are broken up into k sub vpns
Okay and each is the same size
And so now in this system the upper VPN one which consists of the uppermost bits of the VPN
Are an offset into the level 1 table
Which is as before is pointed to by the page table base register
Okay so VPN1 is the index into the level 1 page table
Remember the level 1 page table points to the address of the level 2
That are an entry a PTE in the level 1 table
Points to the address of some level 2 page table
Or it contains the address of some level 2 page table
So that points to the base of this level 2 page table
And then the vpn 2 bits are used as an index into that level 2 table right and so on
Ok so eventually you get at the a PTE and the level k-1 table
Points to the beginning of the level k page table
And VPN k points to an offset within that table
Which finally contains the physical address of the page that we want to access
Okay and then that physical address is used to form the PPN portion of the physical address
And just like before the virtual page offset is just copied directly unchanged to the physical page offset
So is that clear to everybody
Yes question
[student speaking]
Let's see is it always a power of two yes
At least and it's defined by the architecture,so for intel it's a four level system
Now why would it be and then the quick could it will...it always be less than 6
Oh give us a 64-bit system yeah
Yeah there's only the block size is fixed
Right so that there's 12 bits here 2^12 is 4k
So the remaining it's that you actually have 48 bits to play with
So the remaining 48 bits could that's right so if it was 4 if it was 8  it would be 6 so you're right
In this scheme it could be at most 6 turns out in practice it's set at 4
And there was a question over here
[student speaking]
Have it like this multi-level system
Oh okay so the question
Is yeah the question is how does it save you space
So the reason it saves you space is you go back to this other figure maybe I didn't explain this well enough
So you see this
If we...okay so let's say we wanted to map this virtual address space with a single page table
We would need a PTE for every page within that address
Whether it was used or not
Okay it goes back if we had a 48-bit address space
We'd need enough,we need a page table entry for each page virtual page in that address space
Okay whether that page was used or not,so let me think about it 2^48 is a x several exabytes
We need a page table that would have an entry for each virtual page
In that to the 48th bit address space
And most of those pages by far the vast majority would never ever be used
Okay so that's where the waste comes in
Okay so here with a multi-level page system with this multi-level scheme
You only need to generate in this case these level two if it's a two-level system
You only need to generate level two page tables
Enough level two pages to cover the portion of the virtual address space that you're actually using
Okay and that portion of the virtual address space that you're not using at this gap right here
There's no need to have a page table is
Is that clear?that that's a really good important question,but you look unconvinced
[student speaking]
Well yeah yeah you still need you still need a page table that has
Let's see in this case there's 4k bite pages 4 bit PTE
So there's 1k you have 1k PTEs
So you still need you still need a level 1 page table that has 1k PTEs
But those are only 8 bytes right I mean
So you still need to you still need to have space
Because you don't know you know you're not sure which of these which reason of the address space you're going to need to cover
Ok and it's the same thing for
Here in this case, in these first two PTEs these first two level 2 page tables
They're portion of the address space was actually all being used
Right so each one of these PTEs at level 2 had to be allocated had to be initialized and used
Right but in this portion of the address space that contain the stack
This third level 2 page table has most of its PTEs or no
You still have to allocate space for them but they're there no
Ok that's a really good question it's important that I hope that's clear
Any other questions will we go on
Sorry oh okay question
[student speaking]
Exactly just
Just like here the MMU members doing all of this this is all hardware logic
So it and the art the number of page tables levels is defined by the architecture okay
So the MMU takes the virtual address that's presented to it
And it uses a portion a subset of those bits to access each page table okay
So it's just like...did I answer your question?okay
So it's just like before that
The level k,VPN k is used to compute an index into the level k page table yes
[student speaking]
Okay the question is why are the indices arranged right to left on which diagram
Oh these are the bits,this is the least significant bit it's always bit zero
Yeah that's a good question,so the question was why do these
In this diagram why are these these bits labeled right to left starting at zero
And the answer is that we're indicating the bit position
So zero is the least significant bit and n-1 is the most significant bit
Yes question
[student speaking]
Yeah so the question is what's the overhead involved in these when you have these multiple levels
Now are you talking about overhead to
[student speaking]
Yeah well so there's clearly if you don't get TLB hits
It would be a lot of overhead
Because it would be you would be fetching PTEs from multiple page tables for memory
So that but because of locality the chances are almost the...
The chances this level one table covers the entire address space
So it's always going to be in the in the PTE, in the TLB
These level two tables are covering a huge swath of the address space
So chances are they're going to be in the TLB too right so
So as long as your program has reasonable locality
Most of these lookups are going to hit in the TLB
Okay so it turns out that the overhead with reasonably written programs is negligible
But that's a very it's a very important consideration
You know maybe that's maybe that speaks against increasing at some point if you had too many page tables
You might increase the probability of misses in the TLB
So it's probably something they very carefully considered
Okay any other questions yeah
[student speaking]Yeah so if we use segmentation plus paging,so it is the addresses page table the recommended linear address of our real
Ho boy the question was how does segmentation fit into this and
We're not going to go there
So in earlier intel systems
Such as the actually the first intel system I programs it was a 286
So the 286 no is neat it was the 8086
Anyway in earlier intel systems had 16-bit addresses
Which is tiny right
It's only 2^16 for your address space
And so as a hack to try to increase the effective size of the
Of this address space the introduced the notion of segmentation
And so there were four segments 4-bit
There was a register segment registers that contain 4 bits that could be applied to the address
So an address was the combination of the segment knows more than
Yeah you need the segment formed
The address then was a combination of the segment bits plus the address
So you could use the segment bits to create an offset
So it was a - it wasn't effectively a 20 bit address space
But you can only address,you can only access it in 2^16 chunks right so the
The segment would determine an offset into the that this 20-bit address space
And then from that you could address 16 bits
So it was this very unsatisfying devilishly hard to program thing because
You can only access 16 bit chunks at a time
So anyway we're not going to a few years later they came to their senses and just created a real virtual memory system with linear drill spaces
But you know really there
Yeah I don't know we're just did
I'm not even sure if they do address translation on those actually
So I'm not sure but you really don't want to go there
[student speaking]
Yeah oh it does it does so the question is it doesn't exist anymore
Everything intel's been incredibly good about maintaining backward compatibility
So that stuff's all in there
But there's a mode bit when you boot your system up you set a bit that says I want a linear address space
Okay any other question
Oh no VPN to is the offset
Okay so the question is why do we care about VPN2 since that it points to the level 2 table
So what gives you the beginning of the level 2 table is the PTE entry in the level 1 table
Okay so the level 1 table points to the beginning of that level 2 table
And VPN to gives you the offset into that the level 2 table
So the it finds the address by taking the base address
And then VPN2 times the PTE sighs
Okay good good any other questions
Okay well that'll do it for today
Next week or on Thursday we'll look at
How how virtual memory is implemented in real systems and in Linux