Okay let's continue on in our coverage of machine level programming
The second in i think a six part series
As i mentioned yesterday machine level programming is sort of the core of this course
That it gives you a set of tools and understanding  that take you well beyond
What you're sort of average run-of-the-mill of programmer or software developer would know about
And it's very powerful in terms of your better understanding of the system
What goes wrong of why programs crash ? what the meaning of those are
So it's a fairly core part of the material
As you know the data lab is due tonight
And the next wave out is called the bomb lab and i believe that's coming out tonight as well
So the bomb lab will rely on your ability to understand machine level code
So the these two lectures will actually be enough to give
You started on some of the earlier parts of that lab
You'll learn a lot more at recitation on monday
Either in person or if you're viewing the recorded version of that
That will help you move along on bomb lab
Like all the labs in this course at least the first two we give you a fair amount of time for them
But don't be fooled into thinking that means you can just slack off or work on other courses
And then the last few moments jump in and finish this lab the bomb lab
Once you get the hang of what you're doing it's pretty you can just kind of crank along
But there's a certain learning curve that will take you to even get started on it effectively
So don't put it off
Um or is this
So last time we introduced the very basic principles of machine level programming
The idea of there being special state that you have access to the registers
Which people came out to class nesta a register is part of memory?no
Are they part of the cache ？no.through
They special,they're different they don't exist to a c level program
When you're programming and see you don't have any visibility into them
And in general today
What we're going to do then is go beyond the sort of very basics  and start talking about the control.
How you control the flow of execution of instructions in a at the machine level
And how you use those techniques to implement
Basic constructs conditional statements,loops and switch statements
And then next time we'll talk about procedures which warrants a whole lecture of its own
So that x86 and several machines of its generation
Have these curious little of one bit flags that are called condition codes
And they're the basis of how conditional operations work
So to a machine level programmer then we talked last time that
You have visibility of the set of registers and a and the memory
But you also have more things and this is only a partial list
Actually there's more and more stuff that you can add to this picture
But we talked about in the 64-bit x86-64 there's
Now 16 registers,8 of which have names that are historic based on old x86 stuff
And 8 of which were introduced and so they simply named those %r8 through %r15
And other registers for the most part the only one that's really special is %rsp
It's the stack pointer tells you where
And we'll learn a lot more about stacks starting next time
But it's sort of where the most the the state is that manages the execution of procedures
And so you can't just use that or set it in arbitrary ways
But the other ones you more or less come  in with qualifications to that statement
There's another register that they call the %rip which has nothing to do with death
It means that the %rip means instruction pointer
In ia32 is called a %eip and now it's called %rip
Just like the registry used to be %eax and now it's %rip
So all it contains is the address of the currently executing instruction
And you can...
It's not a register that you access in a normal way
But you actually there are tricks that you can find out what the value of that is
So that just tells you where in the program,what part of the program is currently being executed
And then there's these things that are called condition codes
And we're only showing four there's actually more like eight of them
But not a relevant to our general discussion
That are all one bit flags and they get set not directly
But as a side effect of other operations that take place
And they're the basis for which conditional operation gets decided
So let's go through what those mean
And they're given names, but these names are actually useful to memorize what they mean
So cf means the carry flag
And that's if you think of adding two numbers,think of them as two unsigned numbers
And you do the binary arithmetic and sometimes an extra one pops out of the left hand side right
That's the carry bit if you the numbers you added sort of were too big
To be contained in the 32 or 64-bit or even 16 or 8-bit result
And so an extra bit was generated that's called the carry bit
The zero flag(zf) is what it sounds like it's set if the the value you just computed is zero
These are set typically by arithmetic instructions by the way
The sign flag(sf) is said if the value just computed as a one in the most significant bit
Meaning it's a negative value
And the overflow flag(of) is a two's complement version of overflow
So in particular if you remember from data lab. how do you know if addition of two values is overflowed.
If the signs of the operands are the same,but the sign of the result is different than that
So either you added two positive numbers and got a negative result.that was a positive overflow.
Or you added two negative numbers and got a negative result.that's negative overflow.
You can't overflow if the two arguments are of opposite signs.right?
So those four flags get,set as a sort of normal activity by many of the instructions
Not by our friend the lea instruction
Which i mentioned is kind of a quirky instruction that gcc really likes a lot and you'll see it in a lot of places
But in general and most of the time those flags get completely ignored,because who cares right
But they do show up at various points when you're doing conditional operations
So there's some special instructions whose only effect is to set condition codes
And the one that you'll see is especially it's called compare cmp
And by the way the queue at the end of these is all just a reflection of their operating on 64-bit words
Quadword as i said
So the comparison is sort of like a subtraction instruction except that you don't
You don't do anything with the result
Normal subtraction instruction is like x minus equals y
It will read two numbers but then it will store the result wherever x is stored
But compare just takes these two values does the subtraction and doesn't do anything with the result
But it will set it's these four condition flags
And just a few things to keep in mind that are often will be sources of confuse
Remember that the arguments in the way we write them in machine code is the opposite of what you'd expect
By the way,somebody asked me last time
There's another there's sort of two dialects of assembly code used on x86 machines
There's the one that's used by intel and microsoft.and we don't use it
And then there's the one used that sort of used by linux systems and that's the one we use
And they're different and one of the quirks of them is they write their arguments in in different orders
So it will drive you crazy reading trying to read
If you're familiar with one.it's like if you've ever tried to drive a car on the wrong side of the road
You often will crash or do bad things
Um so that's just an aside that
What i find by the way when i'm looking at code and i see a compare instruction
I actually write as a comment of compare of the two but i flipped the order
So that i'm sure that i sort of keep in my mind what the comparison was of
And so these flags get set according to the rules of subtraction
And so it turns out that the carry flag and the overflow flag
You have to sort of flip your sense of what happened
Because it's a subtraction rather than addition but it's the same general idea
So that sort of shows you one particular one
In another instruction that you'll see whose only purpose in the world is to to set condition flags
Condition codes is the test instruction and this is typically used the compare as
You'd think it's when you have two values and you want to compare them to each other
And the test is if you really just have one value and you want to see what it's like is
It zero is it negative ,those are the main things you care about
In fact that's the only thing you can determine
But just because i guess they had up they had sort of a possibility of having two arguments to this
So they decided well let's to go ahead and do it
How do you have two arguments to a test instruction what's and the two results and then test that value
So what you'll typically see is a test
Where both arguments are the same so testq %rax comma %rax
Where so that you're just any register to itself and one property the end operation is
It's what they call item potent adding ending two things the same things together gives you that same thing
So we can see these
And now
So i told you that's how the condition codes get set
Now how do you actually read them how do you make use of them
Well there's two in principle you can actually extract
And get the condition code values directly out of this special status register
But that's very unusual to do that
What's more common is you either try to read it in
And set a 1 bit flag based on the result in a read some other register
Or you try do a conditional branch
So the first example where you try to read it
In a way that you can make use of it is done with the set instruction
And you'll see there's a whole range of set instructions
But their only difference is really just what the condition they're setting based on
So the what a set instruction does
Is it sets a single byte of a single register to either 1 or 0
And the basis for whether it's sets it to 1 or 0 is a based on
What the condition codes are as essence what's the
What happened your most recent instruction before hand was it a arithmetic instruction
Or a set instruction or a test instruction or a compare instruction
And as you can see there's they're all based on some logical combination of these condition codes
That correspond to what the names imply
So for example the sets instruction is true if the sign flag is true
Meaning that the most recent result was negative
And there's other ones less than less than or equal to two's complement comparisons
And they have to take into consideration did the most recent result cause an overflow or not
Because that will affect the result of the comparison
So that's part of the reason we tortured you with understanding two's complement arithmetic
And how you compare results and making you understand the bit-level behavior
So that you can understand what these instructions do
So we're cruel but we have a reason for our cruelty
So you say 1 byte how do you deal with 1 byte well here's another thing we didn't tell you yet
And we're going to keep telling you more stuff over and over again
It turns out for every one of these sixteen registers
You can directly set the lowest order byte of it to either 0 or 1
And it won't affect it it turns out it doesn't affect any of the other 7 bytes of that register
So and they all have quirky names
The l means low in there
So here's an example of using putting all this together to do something that's vaguely useful
Suppose i want to function gt, that will take two numbers and compare them and set the result
Return result value of 1 if x > y  and 0 otherwise
And so here's the assembly code with some tabbing problems
Success nothing bugs me hold on
I might know try and do this. well no
I will fix this later
Anyways it's not the end of the world
Normally an assembly code one thing you've noticed is that the instructions are indented by a tab space
And the only  thing that's way over in the left margin labels
So this is just sort of this what the the assembler is actually quite tolerant of formatting things
But this isn't the way it normally book
So anyways the point is there's a comparing the one rule that
You need to understand about procedures is that
The first argument is passed in register %rdi and the second register %rsi
And that if i'm going to return a result from a function i do that by storing it and register %rax before i return
So the first instruction compares these two
And you notice how i flip the order that
It sets %rsi which is y, and %rdi which is x
But when i annotate it i say x to y
So that i mentally am thinking in the order
That the actual comparison is made rather than the way they're listed
So i always do that when i'm looking at code to help me flip those two around
And then here's our instruction.so that compare instruction set these four condition code register
And now the setg sets.
Now set this single byte register,the lowest byte of %rax to 1
If the result was the comparison was greater
So according to this rule
And the factor that was to set just as 1 byte of this 8 bytes register to either zero or one
Now my problem is that these remaining 7 bytes have whatever happened to be there before
And i want it to be all zeros
So the the way it does it is a bit weird
There's an instruction called move with zero extension bite too long
Now you get to know these better if with time
Let me um...
And what what...
That means is you can actually copy a byte from any place
Like the lord or bite of some other register into a new register
And you'll put zeros to the left of it,that's what they mean by zero extension
That seems logical but one thing you'll notice is the destination here is %eax
Which you'll recall although it doesn't show here
That's the lower 32 bits of register %rax
And then you'd say well that only got me halfway there right
How do i make sure the upper 32 bits are set to 0
Well one of the weird quirks of x86-64 is for any computation
Where the result is a 32-bit result
It will add zeros to the remaining 32 bits of the register
And it's different for example the byte level operations only affect the bytes
The two byte or operations like what you'd have if the data type were short
Only affect those two bytes
But the four byte instructions set the upper bytes to 0
And that was some somebody at amd and i don't know who it is
Decided this was a good idea and it might be a good idea but it's really confusing
But that's something you'll have to just sort of remember in the back your mind
When you see things like this
So the effect of this instruction is to take this one bit result,which is the lower bit of register %rax
Copy it to the same place as it already is
But then set the remaining 7 bytes to 0,which is what we want
So you'll see this pattern quite
Often question got it
Okay so now that's sort of sometimes i want to do this
I just want to get a one bit flag as a result of the comparison
But more generally i want to do something with that information and not just set one bit
So the simplest version is what about a conditional  and if and possibly in else
Well that's done by this actually two ways to do it
So we'll go through the sort of general purpose traditional way
And then we'll show the more specialized newer way and we'll compare those
So the traditional way is to use what's known as a jump instruction
And the jump instruction normally instructions execute in a particular order
Just like when you're writing a program and you write a series of statements
They execute one after the next
A jump instruction is a way you can go from wherever you are to someplace else
And either skip over some instructions or jump back to some other a previous position or wherever
And there's two kinds of jumps ones that are unconditional whether several kinds
But an unconditional jump means when i say jump you jump
But there's others conditional jumps that will actually only do that jumping
If the condition codes are set appropriately
And you'll see that the names of these jump instructions are the same as
The set instructions with the same conditions
So there's a variety of different reasons that the program may be given to either jump or not jump
So i'm going to use this one example to show you several different versions of it
And like everything you'll see here these particular programs aren't that useful
But they illustrate ideas
So imagine i wanted to compute the the difference of two values and then take their absolute value
So there's various ways you can imagine doing it
By the way i'm going to do it is decide to either subtract y from x or x from y
Depending on the relative values of those two
And of course the astute observer will notice that
This has problems if you have a team in somewhere
If the result because there's no absolute value but we're not going to worry about that
Um...so...
In other words i just want to say if x is greater than y, then i want to subtract y from x
And if x is less than or equal to y, i want to subtract x from y
And here's the code for it where the blue and the red or color coding the different parts of it
So here you see the compare instruction and again i've written them out
In the reverse order to help me keep track of what the comparison is
And it says i'm going to compare x and y and if x is less than or equal to y
I want to jump to a location specified by this label l4
And so in general in assembly code if you give a name and then a colon
What's to the left of that is called a label
And it's just a tag that that it's only visible in the assembly code, it's not actually in the object code
That will later i'll be used to compute an address for determining that will encode
What where this jump will actually land
When you're looking at assembly code
One of the features it provides is a little bit easier way to understand it then to look at addresses
And so it just tells you to be looking at that the jump would occur to this position
And what you'll see here is
The in these two branches the blue code versus the red
What you're doing is in one case subtracting y from x
Here you move x into our ax and you subtract y from it
And here you do the opposite you're subtracting x from what
And in this case
So in the first case  you'll make the jump if x is less than or equal to y
You'll compact y from x and you'll do a return
And you remember that i don't have to do anything special to return a value back from a function
All i have to
And the do is stick it and register %rax
And calling function will know that's where to find the return value
So here does a rep
And here it does the subtraction and it simply does a return directly from that part of it
So it's a pretty straightforward piece of code
But you can see it's using this jumping to create two different parts of code that get executed
Under different conditions
Question ?what's that ?i'm sorry i didn't hear you
Oh well there's a couple things one is you want the result to end up in %rax
Right and remember the subtract instruction structions are just two argument instructions
There that you take two values and then you the one this,second argument the destination argument
You overwrite what was there with the new result
So this is a pretty typical pattern you'll see of
You move some value into a register and then you into %rax is very common
And then you do some arithmetic operation with that register as a destination to kind of update it
If it's like if you're writing and see if all the time you had to write sort of
X plus equals something,
X minus equals and that all your arithmetic had to be expressed in those terms
Okay so...
It's fun to look at assembly code for about five minutes and then you get sick of it
So one thing to sort of present these same ideas
But give it in a little bit more abstract form is to write it in c
But in a form of c that looks a lot like assembly code
And in particular one of the features of c
That is not generally advertised is there's a statement called go-to
And you can put labels in your code
And you can tell the program
That if something happens then you want to jump to that part of the program
So it looks a lot like that assembly code right
That you saw jump jle instead of what this says
It's like i'm doing a test
And then if the test is which in this case i call it end test because it's the opposite of the test
That's in the original program
And if that end test condition holds i want to jump to another part of the program i'm calling else
And you notice i uppercase that because it's not the actual else of a if-then-else
And same way if this one is well...
Actually to be most accurate i should have simply said return result from this point
This codes a little bit out a day
So i should have said return result
But another version would be to have done a goto down to here and return the result from there
And you'll see different compilers generate in different forms
So i'm going to typically use this way of presenting code
Just so that you can look at and understand what these control structures look like
Without having to sort of scrutinize the low-level assembly code instructions
So we consider take this...
Questions
[student speaking]
Yeah i think there's a homework or a practice problem of exactly that sort
So in general you could do it neither way and
Why the compiler picks one versus the other is
I think it's a completely arbitrary decision
But consistently i found gcc does it this way
Okay so let's sort of talking sort of imagine you're writing a compiler
How would you take this special case i just showed
And generalize it into a rule for compiling if-then-else expressions
And i'm going to use the version of in see the question mark : version
Where you kind of encapsulate that whole conditional is a single expression rather than the statement
But you can understand that these rules would be the same in either case
So imagine in general you had a c code
Where there's a test controlling whether to return the result of one expression or another
And this is what my abs diff code would look like if i wrote it in that form
And so in general what we can say is
What what we'll do is we'll compete well take the test and tit and invert it
And say if that test is not true then we will ...
So if n test is true then we will jump to some part of the code
Where we've compiled the code for the eltz expression
And if it that test fails here so that the original test condition holds
Then we'll stick in whatever code it takes to to compute the venn expression
And then we'll merge back together in the case you saw where it's just a single little function
We can just call a rep here and get out of the thing
But if this is one line of code then there's a whole bunch of lines after that
Typically you want to merge back together again and continue from there
And so that's what this show is all i'll finish by going to whatever comes afterwards
So this is a way i like to you know,although we're not writing compilers in this course
I think it helps to to think in terms of general rules
Of how a compiler would translate c code into assembly code
So that when you see that assembly code you'll recognize these patterns  and know what they mean
Question....goes to the else clause doesn't like fall through to the john.yes yes
So just as we saw yes in general what like here
It would fall through to the done good question
Okay so that's one version of a conditional and that's the most general way
And the way it used to always be done
But there's another approach that you'll see fairly common in code
It's sort of an optimization called conditional move
And it's bit non-intuitive from a software developer's perspective why you'd ever want to do this
The basic idea is i'm going to compute both the then and the else the values they'd produce
And only after that i choose which one i use
So it seems wasteful but it actually turns out to be more efficient
If there are fairly simple computations
And the reason of that is and we'll see a little bit more when we talk about performance optimization
A modern processor is a little like an oil tanker sailing in the sea
Meaning that it plows along in a certain direction
And it really is hard to get it to stop or to turn
So that's you say what are you talking about but
Think of an instruction sequences you know the ocean of code  that you're cruising through
And these things can just fly through a straight sequence of code
Because they are they do what they call pipelining
Meaning they start bringing in parts of one instruction before they're done with the next
And actually go up to depths of 20 or more instructions deep of
How far had they're working sort of fetching forward and future instructions
While finishing up the ones that still remain
So that's my ocean line or my tanker analogy
But all of a sudden you come and then what happens when they hit a branch
They'll try to guess it's called branch prediction
And guess where is this kind of branch going to go
Where it you know well the conditional branch will be taken or is it going to fall through
And they're pretty good at that they're good at it 98% of the time
So they can even anticipate suta curves in the road  my analogy is breaking down
And start going in that direction and as long as they get it right it's very efficient
But if they get it wrong it's as if you have to stop the thing
Back it up turn the other way start again
And that can take 40 instructions 40 clock cycles say to do in in bad situations
So and this is pretty common if you think of like an absolute value
Can you predict whether a value is going to be positive or negative? it not usually
So about half the time whatever you guess you're going to guess wrong
So these conditional move instructions it turns out
It's much easier to just plow through compute both
And then at the last minute all you have to do is move a value into a register or not
And that doesn't require stopping the whole processor and making this turn
So that's my long explanation for
And if you don't want to understand that i'll just say well just trust me. it's a good idea sometimes .
So the the general pattern then if i use the same idea is i want to compute both results
And i'll call the result and this is an eval this is eval the eltz value
I'll compute both of them
I'll do my test and then this red thing imagine that's all done with a single instruction
That says i'll copy the value of eval to result
But only if my condition holds so that's why it's called a conditional move
Then we'll see this is the code
By the way you saw my original version starting to have to jump back
I had to explicitly tell the gcc don't put use conditional moves
Because it really wants to a very badly
And so you have to force it not to and i did that here
So here's the actual code then and again you'll see the the color coding
That it's doing both subtractions
It's it's actually doing the move and subtract
Move and subtract so it's doing both the branches you saw before the then and the else branch
It's doing a comparison and then here is the conditional move instruction
Cmove in this case the l here is not a word size it's the less than or equal to  a direction
So in the case the that i need the red value basically
You saw the the red value is stored in register %rdx
In that case i will copy it into the result register
So again it's like this idea of just go ahead and do everything and then pick at the last end
And the point is that this one instruction it looks just as far as for this processor execution
That's sort of like a a move instruction that it's fairly straightforward to do
Okay so why doesn't it do that all the time well there's a couple reasons
One is that might be a really really bad idea to do both computations
If you have to like crack a password in one and
You know find the nth prime number and another you probably don't want to do both of those
So in general in that case
And so the and you'll notice gcc will only do this
If both branches are fairly straightforward computations that they're trying to do
And there's some times when you just plain can't do it
So for example if you're using a conditional to guard
Whether a pointer can be dereferenced or not because it's a null pointer potentially a null pointer
Then you really don't want to try that null pointer dereference
Just for the for as a way to save some time
And similarly if you could have a side-effect
If the result of executing either branch could be to change some other part of the program state
Then you don't really want to do that either
And so the conditional move only gets used then in this somewhat special case
That you have two computations relatively easy to do safe to do no side-effects
But that happens just often enough that this is actually a worthwhile thing
Okay so that gets us conditionals
And now let's look at loops that's a sort of next step up in control structures
And c actually has three different kinds of loops
It has a a while loop which you're familiar with and a for loop which you're familiar with
And it has a third one which in my whole life of writing and i've written a lot of c code in my life
I've used this like about 6 times
So but it turns out it's the simplest one to implement so we'll go ahead and do it
So that the it's called the do-while loop
And so the keyword is do and then there's some stuff you do that's the body of the do
And then there's a test at the end that tells you whether to keep repeating this loop
So it sort of flips a normal while loop you you have the conditional test at the front
And here you have it at the end
So it turns out if we think in terms of go-to that's a pretty straightforward thing to replace this
With a code that will do a test and if the test holds it will jump back
And say ok a reacts acute that part of the program i was just in
So it sets up a loop where you can think of it's literally a loop of control flow going round and round
And by the way this is actually a semi useful function it's called pop count sometimes
How many ones are there in a in a word of data  in this case it's 64-bit word
There's been some generations of data lab
Where you were required to write this function using all your favorite operations
And with a fairly small limit on operations but we're not doing that today
So here my point is you see that there's a fairly straightforward
Way of taking this particular loop and turning it into just a combination of conditional
That where you do is you jump back to where you were before
And here's the actual code for it
I won't go through all of it but you can believe from these annotations that it very closely follows the code here
And the main thing to see is this jump if not equal
To label l2 and that takes you back to here
And so the general form of it then is you take a do
And then this part of it's called the body of the loop and this is the test
And so now you set up some code where you can execute the body perform the test
And if the test holds you go back to the loop
So a while loop is really just why i could do loop
A do while loop except that you move the test to the beginning
And the only difference therefore is with a do loop you never you don't do the test it
The first time through you're guaranteed to do it the first time no matter what
While a while loop will explicitly test even at the very beginning and
And skip over the loop if the condition doesn't hold
So there's two ways to generate a code well there's more than two ways to generate code for a while loop
But you'll find gcc actually uses two different ways
A one is what we'll find when we use this optimization setting i talked about last time
Called -o which stands for optimized
G which means debug of course as you've already know
There's some history to what the -g flags means
So and as i mentioned last time this turns out to be the perfect level of optimization for this course
Where you want to be able to look at machine code and understand it
And how it relates to the c code because it does some sort of simple optimizations
But it doesn't try to rewrite your whole program to make it run better
Whereas even with -o1 one which is the next level in the optimization
You'll find sometimes it will do some pretty quirky stuff
But when you actually as a program developer as a software developer out there
Or you talk to companies and you ask what optimization level do you use
Those probably say -o2 that's sort of the common one
So usually there's higher levels optimization
And we're purposely backing off from that to make this code easier to understand
So anyways with the this default optimization we're using for this course
It does a transformation i call the jump to middle translation
These are by the way my own names you won't find them in any other document
But what the idea of it is imagine again i have a while loop of this form
Where there's a test in the body to execute
Well what out the problem i have to do compared to before is some i've to execute the test before i start
The first iteration of the loop
So the way i'll do it here is i'll just jump to the middle of the what was the old loop code
To the test portion of that loop
And then let that test determine whether i actually enter the the loop itself
And so this is an example of a go to a code version of my pop count function
So i've written the pop count function using a while loop this time
It turns out whether you use a do or a while loop you'll get the same result in this particular function
And you'll see the way it looks is  it it jumps to the test portion of the code
And then if that holds it then actually starts in the first execution of the loop
And then from there on it looks the same as the do-while loop
It just does the what was in the loop does the test jumps back to the beginning
Oh and then there's a second method which is in some ways more traditional
And you'll find that if you use optimisation one which is a fairly useful thing to do in practice
So just to show you that instead of deciding which one i was going to show you i decided to show you both
And the idea of that is to do a essentially to take a while loop and turn it into a do-while loop
But introducing a conditional beforehand
That would essentially guard your entrance to the loop
So you do an initial test
And if that's false then you skip over the loop all together
Otherwise it's performed like a do-while loop
And so that has a fairly straightforward translation into code
And that again it looks a little different from before that  it has an initial test
But then it looks so i could do while loop
So i won't show you the assembly versions of those
But if you look at it actually the code is all in directories that are linked to your the the class directory
The class webpage  so you can actually look at the code
And you'll see that it follows exactly the way i'm describing it
And then a third kind of loop is the for loop
Which in c is actually a very powerful very general type of thing and so it's very commonly used
But you can see that the for loop has four components to it has an initialization as a test
Has a rule for doing an update in case as a way to continue the loop
And then it has the body of the loop
And so here's a version of my pop count function
Where i'm just going through all the bits in the word extracting them out
And adding them accumulating them to be the result
So ripping apart this for you'll see that these four blocks of
Of the loop correspond to the initialization is to set equal to zero
The test is to compare i to the word size
Which i've set here to be eight times
So however many bytes there are in an int multiply that by 8 to get the word size
And then the update is i++
And then the body is this stuff that's within the brackets here
So i can think of that in general one
One general way to think about a for loop in c is by this rule
That will turn a for loop into a while loop
And so what it says is i first do the initialization
And then i do a loop where i i guard it with this test
And then what i keep doing is executing the body
And then performing whatever update there is  and then continuing with the test
So that's sort of the semantics the the definition of the behavior of a for loop and c
So i can take my different pieces of my for loop
And say well okay i'll take that rule and use it to pack them in  to form a while loop
And of course you know that you can sort of go between those two
It's somewhat a matter of taste whether a given loop should be written using a for loop or a while loop
So one reason why it's actually useful to do this  -o1 one optimization i talked to you about is
It's fairly common for the initial tests to be trivially trivially true
So for example in here if i=0
And i'm comparing it to the word size which would typically be 32
Well that test is true that's a certain thing
And so what you'll see is that the compiler can figure that out
And just throw away this guarding code  that would have to be there otherwise
So that i believe is the main reason why this is the transformation
That gets used with the o1 optimization level is that often times
It doesn't need this initial test
Ok so now i'm going to finish up with what's in to me at least the loop stuff is sort of what you'd expect
If you were to have to you know turn
A c code into something very low level where all you could do is jumps and test
Well maybe that's obvious but maybe not
The switch statement on the other hand is a totally different beast
And i want to show you that because there's no counterpart in normal c code  of
How you'd even think about it
And it's fairly a little bit harder to do cipher
And you're going to have to do it in the bomb lab
So here's an example of a switch statement that is of
Nothing about this is useful except to demonstrate some principles of
How to turn a switch statement into a assembly code
So the point of it is as you know and c you switch on a particular value some type of integer value
And then it will match different cases
Where each of these cases has to be some constant numeric value
Constant integer value
And one of the weirdest features of c is
If you don't at the end of the case if you don't explicitly say break
It'll do what's known as falling through
So in this example here it will divide y by z
And then it will just glide right into this statement that adds z to w
This is by the way like one of the worst design decisions in the history of programming languages
And it's been the cause of more and more
You know heartbreak and bugs that nobody could understand than any other single part of the language
And for some bizarre reason they've kept it alive even into java and all these other languages
That fixed a lot of the worst parts you know the most dangerous parts of c
But somehow they kept this future
And so just as a advice as a programmer if you ever ever use this
Where you purposely want it to go from one case to another
You should have to put a comment in there to say
Trust me i really did want it to fall through
I know you almost never want to do this but i do here
So that's a fairly common convention
I don't know how many times i've had bugs that were because i forgot to put breaks
Anyways enough of my editorializing
The other feature you see and see is
You can sort of a bunch up multiple cases
If you think of it that's just a special case of the fall through
Write the case five has nothing to do but to fall through to six
But so that's the same general way and there's nothing that's not
That's not bad and it doesn't require a comment
And the other one is that there's a default so if none of these cases match  either
Because x was 0 or smaller or x was a really big number
Or in this case if x were 4
There's no matching case
And of course you also know that these cases don't have to be in any particular order either
So that's all the sort of features of a case statement
Um a switch statements are up
So normally if you write this in sort of if you were told thou shalt not use switch statements anymore
What you'd probably do is write this big long chain of if else,if else,if else right
Uh and you'd expect that to be the machine code but it's not
And so let me show you what the machine code does
It's kind of a long story
So think of the general form of it as being some blocks of code
The entry points of which are labeled by these case values
And then the box you know string together in various different ways and do various things
What i'm going to do is compile a code for all of those blocks
And store them away in some part of memory load up memory to contain these code blocks
And then i'm going to build a table
And each entry of this table describes the starting location of one of these code blocks
And i'll put them in order of my case labels if i have
You know i want to span a scope from well let's assume zero but typically that's not the case
Zero up to n-1
I'll have this table will have that many entries of addresses to tell me
Where these code blocks are located
And then i'm going to use this really cool instruction
Which is a sort of like it's as if you it's like a ray indexing
So if you think of a ray indexing it means you can grab a value out of the middle of some...
You know array some set of values without having to step through them one by one
And it's the same idea here that i will take my value and use that to figure out directly
Where i should jump to a block of code
Without having to step through a bunch of other conditions
So and you can see the efficiency again from that it's the difference between
Sort of in one step knowing exactly where you want to be versus
Stepping through you know on average n over two conditions to get to where i want to go
So let's look at this at the assembly code level
And it's a little bit of a long thing because we have to build some machinery around this
So here's my example i've got three arguments
So just remember i told you are %rdi and %rsi for the first two arguments the third argument is in %rdx
And here's the beginning of the switch code
It's just making a copy of argument z here for some reason
And then it's looking at comparing x to 6 and y is 6 an important number
Because you see 6 was the largest value of any of my cases
And now it's using a jump instruction to go to .l8
What we'll find is that tells you what the default behavior should be
So it's sort of flushing away the default cases
The cases that are either x is too small or x is too large
And i should mention there's a clever trick there if you look at 'ja' means jump above
That's the unsigned comparison
And what it's making use of is our our result that you remember that if a number is negative
If you think of it as an unsigned value it becomes very large positive value
So by doing the "ja" instead of a "jg" i jump greater than i'm doing jump above
It's saying i want to jump to the default
If either x is greater than 6
But also it will cause it to jump if x is less than 0
Got it
So it's a clever trick of unsigned versus signed numbers it's taking advantage of
And then the final part is this is the real heart of the work this is my very special  go-to instruction
That lets me index into a table and extract out of that an address  and then jump to that address
So that's what lets me go directly up to some block of code
Based on whether my values will we'll see will be in the range between 0 and 6
So there'll be seven entries in that table
One thing just to keep track up for later
You'll see that for some reason the gcc said you know
If i look at all the code i actually don't use w as initialized very much
So i won't bother doing it until somewhere within the code blocks
So just we'll have to keep track of that here
Okay so this is the magic instruction
And now if we look and this is all assembly code
You'll see this is the actual jump table
And it's constructed it's specified in assembly code
And it's the job of the assembler to actually fill in the contents of this table
Excuse me
But what the assembly code is telling the assembler is
I need a quad is just a declaration to say i need an 8 byte value here
And that value should match whatever address
You decide you later determine is the address of
Where i'm going to stick and label 8  and all these other ones
And these are in the order as i mentioned from x equals 0 through 6
And we can already see a few cases that are interesting here
Let me see if i've got a picture on this
Yeah
So we can actually already see some of the logic of this switch statement
Built into the ordering of entries in this table
So in particular there is no case zero here
So case zero should be the default
There is no case for here
So case four should be the default
And it turns out and we already saw before the "ja" instruction going to .l8
So .l8 is actually where the code block is going to be for the default case
So you see basically you can think of this as sometimes kept having holes in your switch statement
And we're going to just fill in those holes by saying those should go to the default case
And here you'll notice that they're not put in any particularly logical order
A one thing you'll see again is .l7 is repeated twice here
Because it covers both cases five and six
So again you'll see this sort of doubling up is handled automatically
By the jump table will give you the same address for multiple different cases
Okay and now the rest of it is to look at the various code box
And this by the way i'm showing you i'm took a file and i'm you know extracted little bits of it
But normally you're looking at this whole listing in one big order
So now we can look at the individual code blocks and see what's going on
And you'll see for example case one told me to multiply two numbers
And you'll see that the break
In general it's just going to be turned into returned instructions here
Because my function...let's go sorry to jump in code
You see this function did a switch statement and then whatever
Whatever it gets computed within the switch statement gets returned as a result of this
So the compiler doesn't actually come to a single point and say okay  everyone returned at this point
It just sticks returns directly in wherever these breaks occur
And so here it does a multiply and a return
Here is actually a curious by the way i'm always somewhat surprised by what the compiler does
It is never exactly what you'd expect
So in particular
It patched together this fall through case by two blocks of code
And it had to do these separately because remember w was not set
Before i entered the this these code blocks it deferred setting that
And here i hit case three and all of a sudden i actually need
Whatever w was which was one
And so i guess the compiler said well gosh i guess i better set w to one here before we continue
So as the result it sort of creates two code blocks
But it jumps from the second one the
This block into partway through this other block
Here's some actual yeah so here's the actual code
This is the block that does the division it's very quirky how you have to write division
It's covered in the book i won't go through it here
And then this jump .l6 is what i say go to merge
And the merge is where you're bringing these two cases together
Here is where it's setting l to one
Again it's making use of this feature
And that the upper 32 bits get set to zeros
So i can use a move l instruction here
Yes question
[student speaking]
Did not have the code for what...no the jump table is sort of embedded
Let me just show you real quick
No probably bad idea
The jump if you look at the the .s file the assembly code file
Oh all this stuff i'm showing you i've extracted out of that
But it's all in there and so that the compiler generated these tables
At least the sort of framework for these tables
The details of which get filled in by the assembler
So it is generated by the compiler
Okay so that just shows you this one example of handling a particular way to handle the fall through case
And then the remaining ones again you'll see here i got if i get to this case
I need the fact that w is initialized to 1
So we'll do so here
In the default case it just assigns to 2w and so that's all it does
So anyways i've actually shown you all the code box
But i've shown you one by one but they're just all kind of strung in the file and in no particular order
It doesn't matter what order they are
Yes
[student speaking]
Yes so that was the reason for that jump above at the beginning
So this jump above .l8 was a way that if x was either less than zero or greater than 6
It would go to the default case and it will only do this indexing trick
If the if x is between 0 and 6
And that's typically the way this works that you'll see that
Whatever range of values you give it has to figure out the smallest and the largest one set up
So it goes to the default case if it's out of that range
And then set up a table for the values within that range
Question
...number two...yeah...does it try to like do the index into it with that x
So the question i'm rose i should be repeating questions
The question is of what if it's a negative number for your case which is perfectly legal
It will typically add a bias to it effectively
So that whatever your lowest value was become zero
Or it'll do something like that to avoid having to do negative indexing
Another question i see yes
....yeah so you can go from zero to a million ....
Yeah they could be you could go zero in a million and nothing in between right
So you'd have two cases you really don't want a million entry table for just two cases
So it will turn it into if felts code
But the clever thing it will do if you know binary search
It relies on the fact that it knows in advance all the values and it will actually set up a tree of if felts is
So really it will do it if you want to thank algorithmically it does it with a logarithmic number of tests
Rather than a linear number of tests
Question
Oh yes yeah so
So these two answers that
One is if which i actually answered both now
If one is what if there's some negative values or what if the lowest number is 5700 right
Well what it will typically do is put some bias
And you'll add or subtract some value so that the first case is at value 0
So that's why it handles you know ones that are just completely out of range
And the other is what if it's a really big spread of values and relatively sparse
How much you're using it and there will revert to if-else code
And the compiler has its own rules about how it does these things
You can sort of run experiments and try and reverse engineer
Those 0 these are all valid questions by the way appreciate
Okay so we're going to get through this
Oh so anyways in like i said i think in my own experience you know understanding
The conditionals you can kind of figure that out it's intuitive sort of feels like what you'd expect a program to do
Whereas the switch statement is maybe unexpected it's a way to do something
That is not totally obvious but if then when you think about it and appreciate it
It's actually it gives you a good performance boost
You know again algorithmically this jump table makes it
So it's a constant time a constant number of steps to get to where you need to in the switch statement
If you just did it linearly one after the other
Then that would be linear time and you'd expect on you know if everything's uniform and average
About how you'd be about halfway through on average
If you're if it's sparse you'll see it will set up a tree of conditionals
So it can do in logarithmic time so
No matter what it will be better than just what you'd get in the obvious form of your felts
I saw a question over here
[student speaking]
Well the good news is,i don't set up the jump tree the compiler sets up the jump tree right
But if you're asking if i were a compiler how would i set up the jump tree right
Which is a good question
If you know binary search right
That you've got a range of values and you pick you compare it to the middle value
And it's either less or it's greater or equal
And if it's less than you sort of recursively handle the one set and if it's greater at the other hip
That's exactly what these trees look like
So they're balanced binary trees and they're taking advantage of the fact
That in c which is not true in all languages
That all the this case conditions you're looking at our constants they're determined
When the compiler is doing the compilation those are constant values
So it can sort them figure out how many there are what range of values
So there are decide which version to do the clang and generate the code
Other questions
So these are all good and is a very good question so
And you're starting to think about
You know which is the way that computer scientists should think is
How do you take some idea i've seen one case of
Well how do i handle condition x and condition y and you know what happens if this that's exactly
What we do we sort of
We're never happy with a simple explanation we want to understand
How we could actually implement it as a program if we ever had to do so
So and
So just in general that the main thing you see is that there's a fairly limited bag of tricks
For which the program implements conditional constructs
You've seen basically three
One is to use conditional jumps go to different parts of the code
Another to use conditional moves
And the third is to use this jump table idea
And those are really that put plus a little bit to do of procedures  the suta all there is
And all the other stuff you see in a program that sort of changes
The flow of execution or what gets executed are all built out of those basic primitives
And that's generally true that what we see is
You know when you go from c code to machine code you often have to kind of piece together various
Low-level instructions to implement some higher-level construct
And so we've seen these all in different form stone
And next time then we'll talk about procedures
And that's as you can imagine a fairly major topic
Because it is worth one entire procedure
Okay very good thank you