all right good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you all welcome also to our our viewers on video
so last week we looked at this this virtual memory mechanism
and how it provides so many different useful functionalities to the system
along with this sort of abstraction of having this large contiguous array of bytes
now once we're given that that large array of bytes
now we have to manage it
and we have to we have to have some mechanism to to manage and use that that resource
okay so that's the topic of our our lectures this week is a storage allocation
and how storage allocators work
and how you use them to manage the matter the virtual memory in your system
so the the basic idea of a dynamic memory allocator
is that applications use it to to manipulate virtual memory to create to to allocate and free chunks of virtual memory
that you need in your program
and it's this this memory is maintained in it in an area of virtual memory called the heap
okay and although all all languages have some ask some mechanism for we're acquiring and manipulating
this this this dynamic memory
so in NC it's a phone it's the malloc package languages like Java  have the new the new method
now the allocator the allocator maintains the heap as a contiguous collection of blocks
where and it blocks can be allocated or free
ok allocated meaning that they're they're being used by some program application
free meaning that there available to be for use by an application
and there's there's two types of allocators the kind of allocator that you find in c  such as the malloc package
it's up to the application to both explicitly allocate the the memory
and explicitly free it when when the when the application is finished with it
okay so the system won't won't free up any memory that you allocate unless you do it
explicitly by calling the by calling the free function
but there's other languages that that support implicit allocators
and in these in these implicit allocators the programmer al explicitly allocates memory
but then the system takes care of freeing the memory
okay so it's that the burden of freeing the memory is shifted from the application program to the to the system
and it it frees this memory implicitly sort of behind the scenes using a process called garbage collection
okay so languages like Java,ML,Lisp um they all do implicit implicit they all support in close at allocators
now today we're going to just we're going to discuss explicit memory alligators
on Thursday we'll get into implicit alligators and how they work
now the alligator and C is provided it by the standard c library
in a set of function called malloc package
the the malloc function is used to to allocate memory
and it takes as input a size argument which is in bytes
okay and then it returns a pointer to a to a memory block that contains at least size bytes
and that block is aligned to on x86 systems to 8-bytes on x86-64 systems to 16-bytes
if size is 0 it returns null
and then it returns -1 like like most typical system calls
the programmer frees memory by calling the free function
it takes as an argument a pointer that was returned from some prior invocation of malloc
and it returns nothing
and it frees that
I've given this pointer that was returned by the prior indication of malloc it  frees the block at that address
and then returns that block to the pool of available memory
now there's some there's some other functions
so sialic is a version of malloc that gives you an initialized block of memory that's initialized to 0
and realloc you can malloc a block and then call realloc to change the size of that  previously allocated block
and then there's a function called S break which is used internally by allocators to grow and shrink the heap
so when an allocator needs more memory
it calls S break to to get that additional virtual memory
and then that that's added to the heap that the portion
that grows the heap and then it adds it to the memory that the the allocator is is manipulating
so here's an example of how we would use Malik and it's in a simple program
we have a pointer to an int  *p  and we call malloc
and we we want to allocate an array of N in
so this is that this is sort of the standard way you call it
we want n int and so we we call it with n times the size of int
because remember the argument is in bytes
malloc returns a pointer
it returns that generic pointer void* pointer so
so we cast it to a pointer to an int to keep keep the compiler happy
and then assign it to to p
we check for a we check for a null return value
so I should I should point out the it returns 0 on error
so we check we recheck recheck for this NULL, the no pointer which is 0
in print an error if it's NULL
now once we've got that pointer now P we can treat it just like an array
so we can so inside the loop if we want to initialize it we loop
across the elements of the array initializing each one to some value
now when we're finished when we're finished with this chunk of memory that we've allocated then we free it by calling free with the pointer P
okay now the so we're going to look today at how functions like malloc and free are implemented
so we're going to make a few simplifying assumptions
so I'm going to memory it is byte address
we know that but for the purposes of this lecture we're going to assume that it's it's word address
okay so we're just going to look at word size units
and I'm going to assume that words are 4 bytes
so they basically the size of an int
so this isn't actually this this isn't true I need to fix that
so basically we're going to we're going to think of words as four byte quantity sort of integer size quantities
and then our blocks or contiguous chunks of those words that can be either allocated or free
so here we have a portion of the heap
which consists of a four word allocated block followed by a two word free block
followed by another for word allocated block followed by a three word free blocking
and we'll indicate these free blocks by white and will indicate allocated blocks with some shade of color
so let's look now how a sequence of of allocations and freeze would work
and now notice I'm calling malloc with the size of in words
not bytes just to keep just to keep things keep these pictures simpler
so in this first we call malloc  and allocate of a forward block
then we can that and that gives us a pointer p1
then we call malloc again to get a five-word block
so it just takes it one of the free words and allocates it
we call malloc again to get a six word block
and then we free the block that's pointed at by P to this purple block
okay so now we that frees up that block
and then we do another allocation for a two word block
and so the the allocator looks to see if it can find a free block that has enough enough room and
it finds that it finds this free block here that has five free words and then it
allocates the the requested block inside of that that free block
now allocators work under a lot of a lot of different constraints
okay so it's hard to write an allocator because of all these constraints
applications can choose any combination of allocated and free blocks
so you can't predict what what an application is going to request
and and the application is required to free a block by when it frees a block to pass a pointer
that was returned from a previous invocation of malloc
okay so the the application has a few constraints
but but really the only one that it has is that the fact that the
when it frees something it has to be a pointer from a previous invocation of malloc
now the malloc operates or allocators like malloc operate under a lot of different constraints
they can't control the size or the number of the allocated blocks
because they have no control over the what the application is doing
if an application calls Malik Malik has to respond right away
it might you might be able to do a better more efficient version by batching up requests
and then responding to all those requests at once
which the allocator can't do it when it gets called it has to process the request and then return right away
it has to of course it has to allocate blocks from free memory
so it can't in general I can't touch any allocated block
right once it allocates a block that block belongs to the application and the
the malloc package can't touch it
now this this has a number of implications
so this means that the allocator can't it can't move blocks around like it
can't compress blocks like an alligator might want to take allocated blocks and smoosh them all together
to create larger free blocks hey but it can't do that
okay so once you know in a language like C once once an alligator
gives a block to a an application it can't touch it
okay now blocks like blocked because blocks are holding data structures like strux
or you know scalar scalar objects it has to be aligned to the size of the largest object that that can occur
okay so for 64-bit systems that's 16 byte alignment for 32-bit systems it's 8 byte alignment
now alligators are really interesting objects
because they they combine a trade-off of both
so running time sort of speed and space
so it's kind of a space and performance trade-off
you're trying to optimize both you want it to run as quickly as possible
but you want to you wanted to use the virtual memory in the heap as efficiently as possible
okay so let's and
we define these these sort of speed and and efficiency memory efficiency
metrics  we have we have two metrics that we use one is called throughput
so given some sequence of malloc and free requests  R[0] through R[n-1]
so just some where R is either a malloc or free
our goal is to maximize throughput
and the peak memory utilization
and what makes malloc such a fascinating and interesting study is that these often conflict like
it's very easy to make a really fast malloc that that has terrible memory utilization
so throughput is just the number of recomputed requests per unit time
so if we have 5,000 malloc calls and 5,000 free calls in 10 seconds
then our throughput is a thousand operations per second
so it's just measuring sort of how efficiently are our malloc can can process these requests from an application
now peak memory utilization
is a measure sort of how how much useful space
so how much it measured how efficiently the allocator uses the heat
sort of how much is wasted on sort of overheads in the data structures
that the allocator has to uses to in its implementation
so we'll define a payload
when when malloc returns a block
what when it I'm sorry what an application makes a call to malloc it's requesting a certain size block
and that that block is called the payload
so if we call malloc with an argument of 10 bytes
we're requesting a block that has a payload of it that's at least size 10
okay and the 10 bytes that we request that are called the payload
everything else in that block is is overhead
okay so after after we've run a sequence of requests
the aggregate payload is the sum of all the the payloads in the currently allocated blocks
okay so in a perfect allocator
the the aggregate payload would would would equal the amount of memory
the total size of all the allocated blocks right because there'd be no overhead
would just be we just be pure every block would be pure payload
now we're going to assume that the heap is is monotonically non-decreasing so it always gets bigger
okay so are this is a simplifying assumption it's not  it's not true in a real Malak package
but we'll just assume that the allocator never decreases the size of the heap
it only increases the size of the heap okay
so the peak given those given those notions of aggregate payload and heap size
the peak memory utilization after k+1 requests
It's the sum of all the is the sum of all the payloads  divided by the total size of the heap
so the in the best case
each each block in the heap consists of pure payload
so the utilization would be 1
that's the best we can do
but in practice each block the allocator is going to place have data structures and padding inside of each block
that that that keep it from getting a perfect utilization
now one one obvious thing is that since blocks have to be aligned
to some you know if they're 16-byte aligned then blocks have to start on 16 byte boundaries
and they have to be at least 16 bytes
so if you were to request a payload of 2 bytes
you'd have a lot of wasted bytes right that would sort of decrease the utilization
so this is some of this some of this overhead is unavoidable
but your job as a someone who writes them implements malloc is to try to keep that as small as possible
so poor memory utilization is this example that we just talked about is an example of what we call fragmentation
and there's there's two types of fragmentation
internal fragmentation occurs if the payload is smaller than the block size
so it's just what we're talking about
and this can be caused by either padding in the block or some kind of data structure in the block that the allocator needs
sometimes to it you might make a policy decision
that if at if application requests a small block you might return a larger block just to keep
so the blocks don't get sort of splintered up into little chunks you might want to keep blocks at some minimum size
now internal fragmentation you know given a series of requests
we can we can just stop and freeze the heap
and it's very easy to sort of compute the amount of internal fragmentation
we can at any point in time we can just look at all the previous requests that  we we've made
and and look at the size of the payload for each one of those requests
and so we can
so we can determine the level you know get at a point in time
we can determine the level of internal fragmentation just by looking at the previous request
so
there's another form of fragmentation called external fragmentation which is a little more difficult to to deal with
so external fragmentation occurs when there's enough memory in the heap
but there's there's no single free block that can satisfy a particular request
ok so external fragmentation occurs when the application makes a request for a block
but nowhere in the heap is there a free block a free block that's large enough to satisfy that request
so an example of this like suppose
here's the previous example we looked at
now where we have after a series of malloc and free calls
we have two free blocks in the heap
one containing five words and the other containing two words
so the total the total number of free words in our heap is seven seven words
and now we get a request for six words
hey we have enough free blocks we have enough free words in the heap
but we can't satisfy that request
and it's it's because of it's because of this phenomenon called external fragmentation
for example if we'd have if we'd have somehow allocated
Oh
yeah I don't know in this case I don't think we could have avoided the external fragmentation
but nonetheless there's enough memory here we just just the way that our blocks are configured in the
heap we can't satisfy the request
so in this in this in this case that the allocator has to go and get more more virtual memory
would have to go and it would have to get more virtual memory and extend the heap out this way
and to get a large enough free block
so you know assessing and sort of understanding external fragmentation is difficult
because unlike internal fragmentation which depended on the previous requests
external fragmentation depends on future requests
so if we look back at this point
we say is is our is our heap externally fragmented
well we it depends right we can't say
it turns out it is because the next request is is for a block of size six
but if all of the future blocks
or future requests were for bullet we're for blocks of you know say small blocks
then we be able to satisfy those than and we wouldn't we wouldn't suffer from external fragmentation
okay now when we build an alligator
all kinds of issues come up
and that I've glossed over with my simple examples right
you know how do we know
if we call free how does free know how much memory to free up
right we don't call free with a block size we call it with a pointer
so how does free know how big that block is
how do we keep track of all the free blocks
when we have you know when we're satisfying an allocation request
we're going to fight we're going to look for a free block
that is larger than the the requested size
on that that case what do we do with the extra space in the block
we do we just keep it in the block
you know and and suffer some internal fragmentation
do we split that block into a smaller block
there's a lot of free blocks  in the in the heap
how do we when we make an out when the allocator gets a allocation request
how does it pick from all among all of those different free blocks  make as many choices
and then once when free tries to insert a free block we're in the heap
you know where does it insert
it okay when it's when it's freed
and how do we reinsert a free block what does that mean
okay so today we're going to look at at all of these issues
starting with knowing how much to free
so how big our block sizes
so the typical the standard method
is to keep sort of a word sized quantity at the beginning of each block
that gives the size of that block in in some units
I'm showing them here in word size units
okay so that if if the application Malick's a payload of size wants to wants to now like a payload of size four
then the allocator needs to find a block of size five
so consisting of four payload words at least four payload words
and then a header block a header word at the beginning that that indicates the size the total size of that block
and then it returns a pointer p0 in this case to the beginning of the payload
okay so now we know how big each block is that's pretty simple
and how we keep track of the free blocks and this is where it gets interesting
the simplest method is to use that we call an implicit list
an implicit list of free blocks
and the idea here is to just put a header in the front of every block in the heap
whether allocated or free
and then we can use that starting at the beginning of the heap we can use that size to walk the heat
okay so here's a block of size five so we can we can jump
we know that the next block starts at an offset of five
with the second block we know the then the next block starts at an offset of four  and so on
okay so we call it an implicit free list
because there's there's no real list of free blocks
but we can trick an traverse that all of the free blocks in the heap
by traversing all of the blocks in the heat
and then just ignoring the the allocated blocks okay so
now another thing we could do is
we could actually use some of the some of the words in the block
to create a linked list of some kind either us
singly or doubly linked lists
and in this case we it's an explicit list of the free blocks
and we can just walk that list
so we here we visit the first free block
and then there's a pointer to the next free block and so on
so this you can see this might be a little more efficient because
if we want to traverse the free list
in this case it's a it's going to be ordered the number of blocks in the list
okay it's going to be linear in the total number of blocks in the heap
which might be quite large there could be lots of allocated blocks
in this case with an explicit list
any traversal just just be linear in the size of the free list
question
[student speaking]
yeah that's the question is done we need a free bit and we do
and I'll we have that's the next question
now another method a more sophisticated method instead of having one free list
we can have multiple free lists
where each free list contains blocks of a certain size or certain range of sizes
or we can get really fancy and use some kind of some kind of a balance tree
to sort the blocks to use the tree to sort them by size order
now today we're going to look at the implicit list
the simplest kind of free list
and this will identify a lot of basic concepts that are used in the more sophisticated free list
question
okay the question is what do you what do we mean by different free lists for different size classes
so what what I mean is that you identify a range of sizes
and you associate that range with with each of these individual free lists
okay so one free list might hold blocks of size 0 to 8
and another free list might hold blocks of size 9 to 16
and the other another free list may be 17 to 32 you know some
and so you're guaranteed you now know
when you're traversing a certain list you know the range of sizes of the blocks in that list
the the reason you might want to do that
by the way is that imagine you had an infinite number of of these  lists
one for each possible size
then every time you allocated a block
you'd get a block of exactly the size you needed
so there'd be a minimum amount of fragmentation if you had an infinite number of these of these size classes
now if we of course we can't have an infinite number but
the more of these size classes we have the closer we get to that ideal
all right so let's look at how we would build imprint implicit free lists
so as you correctly point it out for each
each block we need we need both size and the allocation status
question
[student speaking]
why can't we map every size class
yeah that's so why can't we have an infinite number of size classes
I suppose you know that'd be an interesting strategy to to think about
so you can't have an infinite number of size classes
but you could create a new size class for every new size that you get
and that that might work but it just depends on the the range of these size classes
and the frequency and one problem you might have is that you you would get
maybe if you only get it depends on the distribution of your sizes that you get
if you're getting an equal number if your distribution of sizes is is fairly uniform
that would probably work pretty well
if you're getting if you have requests
if if you have a lot of requests for different size classes you'd have a lot of sort of wasted free lists I think
so it's a good question it depends on it depends on your workload
and there and that is for that and that is a really useful strategy for
so you if you have really popular size classes in your request
then you could just make you know special case special case free lists to handle those requests
and then and then let the other free list sort of handle a wider range
and imagine if you had a free list where all the blocks were the same
it could be a lot more efficient right because
you won't make you only need like a bit vector
1 1 bit for each potential block to tell you whether it's allocated or free
so it could be very efficient you wouldn't you wouldn't need to walk any any lists or anything
that's a good question and that's the kind of thing you'll be thinking about when you do your Mallik lab it's one of
the there's a huge design space in implementing malloc function
and we just we just explored a one tiny part of it just now
so with this implicit list we're going to need both the size of the block
and then its allocation status whether it's allocated or free
now we could do this in two words right but that would be wasteful
so the standard trick is to take advantage of the fact that blocks have to be aligned
okay so this is actually it's kind of a pain in the neck to always have to align these blocks
but we can take advantage of it in this case
and the reason is is that if a block is aligned to some  say 8 by 8 or 16 byte boundary
then the lower order bits are always going to be 0
so if it's aligned to an 8 byte boundary
the lower order 3 the 3 low order bits will always be 0
right 8 is 1000.
16 10000
24(=)11000
right so there any any 8 byte
any 8 byte aligned block has to be size 8 and it has to start on address that's a multiple of 8  all right
so those the the size will always the size of that block will always have
0 the 3 3 or 4 a low-order bits set to 0
so we can take it we can take advantage of that
and we'll just make will just have 1 I will just have one header word
and we'll use the lower order bit to store the allocation status
okay and we can do that because we know it's always zero
so when we so we use that low order bit to store the allocation status
and then the remaining bits correspond to the size
and then whenever we want to extract the size we just mask out this allocation status and always set it to zero
because we know that it's zero
so let's look in detail what given this given this form of implicit list
how we might set things up
so in this case we're going to assume for bite words okay in sized words
and we're going to align on eight byte boundaries
okay so remember the payload of our blocks always has to start on an eight eight byte boundary
so the way we do that is we create this unused word at the beginning of the heap
that's aligned on this eight byte boundary
and then the the first block and the heap starts at an offset of four from that
from the beginning of the heap
so we have the header which is is not aligned
and then we have the payload which follows
in this case it's a payload of one one word and that starts on this
that begins on this this eight word boundary
and then the next block and and here we're indicating a free block consisting of eight bytes
and then that's followed by an allocated block
the one here of sixteen bytes or four forwards
and now the payload is only two words so we have to pad
right all of our blocks because we're assuming that they're aligned on eight byte boundary
all of our blocks have to be a multiple of size multiple of eight
okay so here's the case of internal fragmentation where we have this extra
this extra block in order to maintain the alignment requirement
so that that ensures that the next block payload starts at a an eight byte aligned boundary and so on
and so we can walk this heap by just following these headers masking out the allocation bits
and then we have this special epilogue block
which is a zero it's a block of with a zero sized payload
it's an allocated block of size zero
and this is a this is a trick
this is a trick you should use to
so this and we'll see when we look at coalescing why this is  why this helps
but this this allocated block at the very end
eliminates some sort of special cases when we when we start to coalesce free blocks
we'll talk about that in just a just a moment
but you can finish your
like this this this this allocated block of size zero is also helpful in terminating
when you're walking this list
you can you can check for a size allocated block of size zero to terminate your search
okay so given this kind of structure then how do we find a free block
okay there's a there's a number of different ways
the first the first way which is called first fit up
first fit is to search the free list from the beginning
and just look for the first block we can find that satisfies the request
so we're allocating we're asking for a block of size 10
we start at the beginning of the heap and we walked a list we walk the heap
looking for a free block that's at least size 10
and we needs to be actually it needs to be 10 plus the size of our header 2
so once
so that's a simple idea now
some people have proposed an alternative called next fit
so the idea here is that instead of starting over each time from the beginning of the heap  to find a block that fits
we just pick up where we left off the last time
okay so we look we scan the heap
and we find a block that's that's big enough to satisfy the request
and then we remember where that where we left off
and the next time the request comes in we pick up the search starting where we left off
now this seems like would be a good idea but but studies peer achill studies that people have done
have shown that this actually results in worse fragmentation
so you know you can you can consider it but it it generally
it's generally probably not the best thing to do
now another alternative is to find that the Block in the heap
if a free block in the heap that's the best fit
so look at so in general look at all the blocks in the heap and find the block that fits the best
ok so if we ask for 10 bytes
try to scan the heap for the block that has the closest to 10 bytes in it
okay so that's called best fit
and best fit you can see it might be more it sounds like it would be a lot more expensive right
because you'd have to look instead of just looking until you find a fit
you'd have to scan all the free blocks and then pick the best one
okay but it has a nice property that it improves memory utilization
okay so if this isn't this is a classic example the space time trade-off
so it's slower but it improves it improves our use of the efficiency of the way we use memory
and there's
now we mentioned we mentioned an alternative way to organize the free list using multiple free lists for different size classes
now going back to that example again if we had an infinite number of size classes
one for each size that would implement best fit
with a constant time search we don't we'd know exactly which free list  to get the block from
the problem of course is how much memory such  a organization would use
but the interesting thing about using multiple free lists
is that the more the more of these free lists you have the closer you get to it to a true best fit
okay so you can approach best fit
and then at some point you begin to get diminishing returns
so so that's another sort of design decision is how many of these multiple free lists do you need and what
what's sort of what what should be the size ranges associated with them
okay another question now once we found a block
so the application is made a call to malloc
the malloc package is look in the free list that somehow using some
some policy it's identified a block that
in which the requested block a free block in which the requested block will fit
okay so now what does it do it has to the malloc package has to allocate
it has to sort of take that
but so there's a question how does it it could allocate the whole block
and return that back to the programmer or it could it could choose to split out
a portion just only the portion of block that's needed and then create a smaller free block
okay so for example if if we if our
if our application is has requested a block of size 4
or I'm sorry
it if the malloc package is determined that that it in order to satisfy the application request
it needs a block of size 4
okay including the header
then it would look and it would try to find a free block  of at least size forward
so let's say it chooses this block for some reason
maybe because it was a next fit picked up here
so this free block is actually six
contains six words
so the allocator has to decide whether just to keep this block of size six
and just return that back to the to the application
or whether to split that block into two blocks into an allocated block of size four
which it then returns to the application  followed by a free block of of size two
okay now another question  is  how to free a block
so the application is requested the elec is called free and it's asked the allocator to free up a particular block
so this is pretty simple
so if we want to free up this block you just clear the allocated flag
so if we want to free up the block we just created
you just clear you just set the allocated bit to zero
and you're done it's really simple
but the problem now is this this creates external fragmentation
so here now if if we just free that block of size for
what used to be a block of size six
now consists of two contiguous smaller blocks one of size four and one of size two
and so now if that's followed by a request for five blocks
now we're stuck right so this
but we've got plenty of memory and it's even worse in this case
that memory is all contiguous just because
but just because we just oh we just cleared the free block
we didn't we didn't really notice that it was contiguous
and so we ended up in with the situation where we have these two contiguous free blocks
so this this suggests that
when we do when we free up blocks
that we somehow need to coalesce any neighboring blocks
to keep blocks as big as possible right so we cannot
one of the invariance of any decent allocator is that
they're never there never contiguous free blocks like this
it's always a free block followed by an allocated block
okay so the idea is that if we free a particular so here we have this allocated block
and if we free that block and we somehow have to check
and see if there's any adjacent free blocks either following
either neck either next in memory or previous in memory
and if there are we need to as part of the freeing process
we need to coalesce those two blocks into a into a larger block the largest possible block possible
now it's pretty easy if we're if we're asked to free this block this green block
it's pretty easy to check the the next block because you just
we have the size we have this header
so we know that the next block starts at an offset of four
so we just we just  we just check
we know and we know that the header for that block is at your offset of four
so we just check the allocated status of that next block using the
using the size using the size field in our header
but what about the previous block
what about this block how do we check that
well given given all that we've talked about
now the only thing the only way we could do it would be to start at the beginning of the heap
and now walk the free list until we get to this current block  remembering the previous block
so each time we each time we traverse we remember the previous block
okay so that but that would be very inefficient right that would be
that what that would make free linear in the size of the heat
because we'd have to in order to check the previous block we'd have to walk starting at the very beginning
and walk the entire heap
so the solution for that is was proposed by a famous computer scientist Don Knuth in 1973
it's very clever it very simple like all really good ideas
it seems obvious that when you see it but it turns out to be very clever and a very very useful technique
and the idea is just to replicate for each block
replicate the header block at the end of the block
okay so each block now contains a header and a footer identical header and footer
and then this creates sort of an implicit backwards
backwards link that we can use
so now given given some block
that we want to given some block that we want to free
we knew the size of that block will just be one one word previous in memory so
so we can just and it's always a fixed fixed offset of one word
so given you know given a pointer to the header of this block
we can look one word back to see the size and the allocated allocation status of the previous block
okay so and so that allows us to do that in constant time
and so this footer is sometimes called the boundary tag  and Knuth call that a boundary tag
but we'll just and we can call it a footer  to be sort of parallel with with with the notion of a header
but the the key thing is that it's just identical has the identical size and allocation status
and also given yes question
[student speaking]
so the question is if we want to have a boundary tag
when we allocate a block do we need to set aside space for it and the answer is yes
most of the time I'll show you a one I'll show you one optimization in a bit
okay so given given this idea of a over the boundary tag
and and and given that we have some allocated block that we want to free
this yellow block
yes question
[student speaking]
yeah we so they quit yeah so just to summarize the question
you need to when you allocate when you're looking for blocks that fit
you have to include the the size of the header and the boundary tag
[student speaking]
it would you then you'd have and then you have to insert padding to get a size a total block size
that's a multiple of that set of multiple that satisfies your alignment requirement
sorry
yeah I mean it can yeah
if you have it the question is wouldn't I use a lot of memory and it can if again it depends on the requests
the request pattern if if the application is requesting lots of small payloads then
then it's going to it's going to waste a lot of memory
if it's requesting big payloads not so bad
okay so given that we have some block that we want to free
there's four cases that we need to consider when when coalescing
the case where the the next block is allocated and the previous block is free is allocated
a case where the next block is free and the previous block is allocated
a case where the the previous block is free and the next block is allocated in the case where both the previous and next block are free
okay so in case one where we have our allocated block
that we want to free surrounded by two allocated blocks
we don't do anything right because we only call us free memory
so so in this case we just set keep the size of the header and footer stays the same
and we just set the allocation status to to shift free
now if the if the next block is is free and the previous block is allocated
what we do is we we check the boundary tag of the the previous block
and we see that it's allocated so there's nothing to do there
we use the size to check the allocation status of the next block
we use n to jump to the header of the next block
we see that it's allocations status is free
so these two blocks need to be coalesced
so we do that by just adding adding the two sizes together to create this larger coalesce block
and setting its allocation status to zero
now in the case where the previous block is is free
again we we check the boundary tech footer when we see that it's we see it it's free
so in this case we create
we have to update the size of the the old the header of the old previous block to create this now new larger coalesce block
can we and we update the header and the boundary check footer accordingly
and then in the case where where both the previous
and the next block are free
we create a single block
a single block that's the sum of all three of those sizes
okay so is that is that clear to everybody
now as you pointed out correctly pointed out that
boundary tags can create additional internal fragmentation
because they're they're not part of payload so by definition
they're their overhead
and so you might you might ask yourself are there any cases where
you don't need a boundary tag
so which which blocks need
which blocks need a boundary tag
could you get away with does an allocated block need one?
yeah you're if you're not going to if you're not if you don't need to coalesce
and you don't need to that footer and what kind of blocks don't you call us
allocated blocks
so what
so maybe we can maybe maybe we don't need those at those boundary tech footers on allocated blocks
right just on free blocks
but then how are we going to determine that the previous
block is allocated or free
if an allocated block doesn't have a boundary tag footer
yes
sorry
well yeah you would give it one when you free it
but somehow when we're doing coalescing we need to check somehow that that previous block
whether it's allocated or free okay
but how does it know it's whether it's a boundary tag
or not not sure no that's okay
okay yes
bingo you got it so remember this remember remember because of our alignment
we've got we've got multiple at least three bits in three or four bits that are always zero
we're only using one of them
so why not use another one to contain the allocation status of the previous block
okay so very good that was
it's so the idea
so here's the block that we want to free
and here's its header
and we pass the P to it and we wonder if we want to free it
and we've got we've got one bit we know that
if we have a eight byte alignment
we know that these are all implicitly zero
so we're using this is a allocated block that we want to free so it has an allocation status of 1
and let's use this let's use one of these spare bits
to indicate the allocation status of the previous block
okay so far
if the previous block is is allocated
and this would be a 1
and when we're checking to see whether we need to coalesce
we just check that we just check that
that that's 2nd allocated bit the allocated bit of the previous block
and if it's 1 we don't need to know  what its size is
okay we don't need to know where that block is because we're not going to coalesce it
okay so in that we don't need
so here we don't need a boundary tag for an allocated block
but now if that if that block is free
it'll have a boundary tag
so we'll check if that block is free
then the the allocation status will be will indicate free
and then we know we need to we need to coalesce
and we're going to need
we're going to need a boundary tag because we need to know where that block starts we need to know its size
so that we can go back and
and update this size to include the  you know the total coalesce size of those two blocks
so is that that clear yes
oh I just uh it's just the allocated bit so
zero means not allocated one means allocated
oh why are those bits that are why are the bits always zero why
okay so blocks have to be aligned to eight byte boundaries
okay oil payloads have to be aligned to eight byte boundaries
okay that means that that blocks have to be the size of blocks has to be a multiple of eight
because it's the same thing as when we were doing padding alignment instructs
the next each block has to be a size has to be a multiple of eight
so that the the block that follows that in memory is aligned properly
okay so you're guaranteed because of the alignment requirement
you're guaranteed that of eight or sixteen you're guaranteed that the size of the blocks are always multiples of either 8 or 16
okay and so that and that so that because that size is always a multiple of eight or sixteen
you're guaranteed that either three or four four bits are all zeros
okay
any other questions
okay let me summarize then some key policies
when when implementing an allocator
and I mentioned that there's the design spaces for these things is really large and really interesting
there's a lot of things that you a lot of decisions that you have to make about various policies
so the first is the placement policy where
when we when we're trying to find when we're trying to place a free block
I mean and out
when we're trying to place an allocated block somewhere in a free block somewhere in the list
what what what policy do we use first fit next fit or best fit
and generally these things they trade-off throughput for fragmentation
all right so the the faster faster versions like
if you're willing to if you're willing to deal with with lower throughput like in the case of best fit
then you can get better memory utilization
now there are interesting there are interesting ways to improve the performance of best fit
you might you might consider something like good fit
which is sort of a mix of first fit and best fit so maybe
maybe you only search the first
you know a portion of the heap and then identify the best fit
you know maybe instead of searching the entire heap
you just search some some portion of the heap
and then cut off the search and then within that region that you search do you pick the best block
so that's something that called good fit
so that that kind of approximates best fit
or you can use these multiple free lists to approximate best fit
and that's and then and there you the real advantage of using multiple free lists
Is that it not only improves memory utilization
but it improves performance too because the individual lists that you're looking for
you know that they contain blocks that are close to what you're asking for
and since you're dividing all the free blocks up amongst multiple amongst multiple free lists
those free lists will be shorter
okay so your searches will take less time
and your your probability of finding a block that fits goes up
because you're segregating these different size classes
now there's a we also have to decide on some splitting policy so
when we find when we find a free block that's big enough
what do we do with the leftover the leftover part of that block
you know once we placed our allocated block into that into that free block
what do we do with the leftovers do we just leave the leftover part
in the block itself and return that back to the application
you know avoiding so that  sort of keeping keeping larger blocks
or do we go ahead and split it like like I showed before
and splitting we go ahead and splitting that block and creating the creating the original free block
allocating a portion of it and then creating a smaller free block
so that's you know that's a policy we may you may want to
you may want to for small requests for small payloads y
You may up to a certain size you may not want to split so you may not you may decide not to split blocks smaller
you may not you may decide not to create free blocks that are smaller than some threshold
and only splitting for 4 requests for larger blocks
and then there's the there's a coalescing policy
now we've seen freeing is pretty quick now  it's constant time because of the boundary tag footers
but you may you may want to
you may want to try to just speed that up even more by by deferring the coalescing
so you could you can do coalescing it
every time the free is called like like we just looked at
or you could defer coalescing to some later time
you know maybe when you're scanning the free list
when you're scanning the free list looking
set try trying to find trying to place an allocated block in response to a malloc call
maybe as you scan that free list you could go ahead and do the coalescing at that time
right so I'm not saying which one is better it's hard to it's really hard to argue for
deferred colas and giving the constant time performance of   a boundary tag-based coalescing
but it but it is an option
okay so here's the summary then of implicit lists
this is the simplest well
it's a very simple kind of allocator i
it's it's
the cost to allocate is linear in the in the size of the heap  worst case
that the cost of free is constant time even with coalescing
memory usage will be will depend on the placement policy first fit next fit or best fit
um it's not used in practice
because of the linear time the linear time cost of allocation
okay but it it can be used in sort of special-purpose
allocators where you have a small number of size classes maybe or
you have a very you know that you have a very small or a fairly small free list
but the ideas of splitting and coalescing that we looked at or general to all allocators
okay so the idea of a boundary tag boundary tag-based coalescing
is is u is used regardless of the structure of your free list
so implicit lists are useful to study
because they introduce some important concepts
but generally they're not they're not they're not that useful
so next next class we'll look at some more sophisticated organizations of free less
the explicit list and multiple free lists in particular
alright so we'll see you then good luck on your shell lab due tonight
and we'll see you on Thursday