I see a lot of people figure it out to come early so good see you
So as you recall,my name is Randy Bryant
And I'm co-instructor of this course along with Dave Hallaron
And for the next couple lectures the first part of this course really will be talking about a sort of data representations
In particular how numbers are represented in different forms and some of the properties and you saw that
When I talked last week I showed you things like
You can multiply some numbers together that are positive and get negative result
So what we want to understand is what is the bit level representation of numbers
And how does that affect some of the properties you have when you operate them on
and especially looking at the corner cases when things overflow
We sort of don't do what, you might expect them to do
So we'll start off with very basic stuff of
How numbers are represented especially integer valued numbers are represented in bits
Um so I think you pretty well figured out in this world that the whole digital world is sort of based on on binary values
And that wasn't always the case I mean since humans have ten fingers and ten toes
A lot of the world was based on the decimal system
And it was really only and in fact the first electronic computer the ENIAC built in University of Pennsylvania  basically encoded did all of its arithmetic using base ten
They had ten vacuum tubes per digit they wanted to represent
So they basically turned on or off those tubes to represent which of the ten possible digits you could want
And it really didn't come to people until later than that
So that's 1948 that they really should just think about base two for everything
And the reason why bits are great is in the digital world you can sort of take what otherwise an analog signal and quantify it
And just say I'm going to say that one range of values
Let's say it's a low voltage I'm going to call that a zero
And a high range of values I'm going to call it a one
And if there's noise or imperfections in the circuit or anything going on
As long as that doesn't exceed these bit these thresholds you've set up
Then you'll get a nice clean signal out of it
And that's the main advantage of digital processing over analog processing
And so that's sort of at the core why everything we do
And especially for storing information
It turns out it's much easier to store one bit of information or a digital value than it is to store an analog value
And sorry this kind of slides went a little crazy on animations
So the point is that we represent all the numbers in a computer as sets of bits
And I think you generally understand that fairly well
And so of course the familiar binary representation of integers which we'll go over today
Just uses a bit position for each power of two we can also represent values that are fractional
And we'll talk about that a week from today
When we do floating-point numbers where what you do is to the right of the binary point
So this is no longer a decimal point it's a binary point
And so something to the left of that would have a weight 2^0
And the next one over would have weight 2^0
But what you do is as you go to the right that adds weight 2^-1,2^-2
In other words this is 1,this is 2, this is 1/2 and this is 1/4
So we can represent just like you do the decimal representation of fractions
We can do the binary representation of fractions
And that's the core of floating-point number of representations
And so it gets very annoying if you have say 32 or even 64-bit numbers to be writing the strings of 1 and 0 out
And so what we use,and what's become largely the most common is to group collections of 4bits at a time into
And then represent that in base 16 or what's known as hexadecimal representation
Using the letters A through F as values 10 through 15
And you'll spend a lot of time staring at hex decimal numbers this year
And you'll get pretty good at being able to look at a hex number and just write it out in binary
The way I do it just to tell you is
I mean I've got the values from 0 to 9 wired down pretty well
And then I keep track of a few special cases 1010 is A
1100 is C and 1111 is F
And for B,D and E I kind of interpolate between those
So if you want to develop that skill that's the way you can do it
...an HDMI to what...
-No,I don't think there's any connector here. -no
So that's something you're going to end up wanting to be able to do
So in C we don't...
In most declarations you don't actually are told exactly how many bytes
A byte is 8 bits
Each data value is represented as
And that's partly C was designed actually back when microprocessors only had 16-bit words
It was actually before microprocessors
So 16-bit words were a fairly standard and over time that's expanded from 16 to 32 to now 64
And so C rather than a sort of an advanced thing
Here is how many bytes every value will have has these slightly ambiguous terms
That vary actually from one machine to the next
And if you're a very careful C programmer you have to anticipate that some
But what won't deal with is x86-64 is the class of machines will be working with exclusively this term
And so you can see that when you declare something to be a care
Sometimes people call it a char that's a 1 byte value
A short is 16 bits
An int is 32 and if you want to get all 64 bits you have to declare it to be along
And then again there's two different representations of floating-point there's 4 byte
Or 32 bit of floating-point numbers and 64 bit
There's also a slightly obscure holdover from ancient days of floating-point
Where there's a special representation in Intel machines that uses a 10 bit or 80 bit representation
And when you use that on a 64-bit machine they sort of waste an extra 6 bytes out of that
So that everything is aligned in 16 byte increments
The other thing and this is an important feature is any address is find to be the sort of the word size of the machine
When they say it's a 64-bit machine,what they really mean is that the addresses are 64-bit values or 8-byte values
And that's different for example if you use a older machine a 32-bit machine
Those will only be 32-bit addresses
So the basis sent I imagine you've had this at some point of how do we then think about bits is based on boolean algebra
Which is actually comes from the 1890s that a guy named George Boole
Who recognized is sort of relation between what we'd call bits  but they weren't called bits back then
0,1 and logic are basically truth values in logic
I thinking of an algebra sort of a structured set of operations
You could apply that would capture some of the concepts that people assume in logic
So for example if we think of 1 being true and 0 being false
Then the and operation is true if both of the inputs the both of the arguments are true
so we get this chart here
Similarly the or operation is true if either input is true or 1
The NOT is just to flip the bit
And then the exclusive-or is what you get when you say it's one or the other but not both
And so it has this representation
So just as a bit of history it was a master's degree student at MIT named Claude Shannon
Who had taken a course in logic as an undergraduate at University of Michigan
And he was the one who made the connection between thinking about
This this what was at the time very obscure branch of something a rather of logic
And applying it to digital systems back in an era when they actually built
These things out of electromechanical noise
And so his master's thesis is probably the most impactful master's thesis in the history of humankind
And he always wonder well what did they do before that then
You know how do they even think about these things
Anyways the idea of applying this algebra then to bits is not
Something that should have been true since the the world began
Something that's a relatively modern concept
Now what's an important thing that might be less obvious is we can also do these over words
We can do these boolean operations where we apply them on each successive bit in that word
And these symbols we use the ampersand vertical bar carrot and tilde
are actually the ones that see use is to represent these operations
And so again if we look at here the 1 is only if both of the values 1
And the for the or for the and for the one
'Or' its if either of them are 1
The exclusive or if 1 is 1 and the other is zero
And tilde is just to invert the bits of it
So again we will spend a lot of time making use of the fact that in C
And this is one of the features to C that people like
is that you can do these sort of very low level of bit manipulations directly in the language
and um
This actually turns out to be useful in practice
And it's sort of implicit of a way of representing sets of values
So this example is a imagine we want to represent sets
Where the elements of the set are numbers ranging between 0 and 7
So 1 byte is enough to capture eight cases
And we'll just if we number the bits and we number them from right to left
So this is bit 0 so that would represent whether or not the value 0 is an element of the set
And similarly here you'll see 0,1,2,3
So we're saying that bit 3 being one here means 3 is an element of the set and so forth
and the
So the idea is then the AND operation becomes like set intersection
The OR operation becomes like set Union
And the X-OR operation is what's called symmetric difference
And so these are actually and ~ is like set complement
So these are actually very common for example
There are operations you'll learn later when we look at a file i/o
About i/o that you can track I want to know which set of possible inputs to the system
think of different network connections have an input ready for me to read
And there is a data structure that
It's sort of hidden away among some seeing library calls
But it basically is using exactly this representation about a thousand
A bits worth of information to represent these sets
And do manipulation on those sets so this is a very common
And why do we use representation of sets in computer science
so as I mentioned those are available directly and  C the &,||, ~ and ^
One thing that's really really important and that programmers screw it up all the time
Beginning programmers a lot and even experienced programmers from time to time is to mix up the & in the &&
or the | in the ||
and the ~ versus the exclamation mark which is often pronounced bang
so and the reason
So obviously there's sort of a syntactic similarity
And there's actually a somewhat of a semantic relation to that
This is another kind of AND another kind of OR and another kind of NOT
But if you mix and match these you're certainly going to have problems
So the || ones aren't thinking about bitwise operations
through thinking about something that's either true or false period
And in that representation the number 0 is the thing that's false
And anything else any other bit pattern is considered to be true
The other feature that the || give you is what's called early termination
So in particular if we do some examples
On the some hex pattern for 1, so this is a not a 0  and so that's considered true
In this interpretation and so the the bang of that the not of that is 0
The same way if you have 0 the not event is 1
And if you apply bang to a number twice you'll get back a 1 unless it was 0
And then a simile these patterns here
The reason why this returns 1 is because it's considered two cases that are true
So it's not doing bitwise operations it's just trying to create true and fault
It's interpreting arguments be there true or false and returning either true or false
But when it returns true it returns one and not whatever number you happen to give
So obviously this is a very different operations
Than you have with the single versions of those and
But it's easy just because you mentally slip or because you type something wrong to do the wrong thing
But in particularly this early termination is something that of course people use a lot
If you want to make sure that you're not accessing a null pointer
You can test whether that's a null pointer first before accessing it
And this if this is 0 or then it will do the the dereferencing of null
So it's a fairly useful feature as well
So anyways just that's an aside at this level we're mostly looking at bits
But just as a programming no don't mix these up
The other class of operations will make use of a lot our shifting
Which again is not something that you normally sort of as beginning programmers think about too much
And if there's a curious feature that a left shifts are always the same
But there's two different flavors of right shift
And we'll see in a little bit later why there's two different flavors of right shift
But um
The idea that of shifting is that you have some argument x
And you want to shift it some number of positions either to the left or to the right given by y
And so when you shift left you just fill in whatever value there was so you pick up the
I'm shifting by three,so I'll take the low order five bits move them over three positions
Then fill in with a zero
And whatever was in the upper positions of that original words they just sort of disappear into nowhere
Similarly if I do a right shift I take the upper six bits I move them over to positions and I fill in with zeros
So that's a logical shift and that's well it's logic
There's another flavor called the arithmetic shift
Which it differs in that the rule for what bits you fill in with are not based on the are
not zeros necessarily but it's whatever the most significant bit was in the original value
So it doesn't matter here because the most significant bit was zero
But you'll see in the case here of where the leading bit was a 1
That when I shift it to the right arithmetic we I'll fill it in with 1
And that'll make sense more when we understand how negative numbers get represented in a machine
And that's the purpose of it and why it's called arithmetic
Um the other thing is confusing to people is
What should happen if you say I want to shift an 8-bit number 8 positions to the left
And X is a single byte what do you think you should get
Zero that would be a pretty logical thing you kind of shift all those bits out you fill them with zeros
On most machines you'll get whatever x was
Because what will do is it will compute this number mod 8
And the reason that happens is if you think about it
It's looking at just the lower two three bits of the shift amount and ignoring all the rest
So that's effectively like module 8
So that's just a warning I and some machines it does
What you just thought it should and other machines it does this
And so there's no no guarantee and see that it will be one way or the other
Same with if you try to shift left by a negative number that might be logically
Well I guess you really want to shift right then but that usually doesn't work either
So now let's talk about number representations
And
This is sort of a very core its idea that you have to really have wired in you
And I'm going to illustrate it with some examples
So the these two equations that are everything that we'll talk about sort of stems from them
So one is if you have an unsigned number
Then basically...it keeps jumping on me
If you have an unsigned number then this is just the conversion
B2U means from a bit level representation to an unsigned number of some bit pattern
It just says we'll just add up the sum of the weighted bits
Where each bit is weighted by a power of two
And the only difference when we look at two's complement
Which is a way to represent both negative and positive numbers
It's we'll consider the most significant bit to be what's called the sign bit
So it will have a negative value
So let me just illustrate this with I'll use some running examples
We'll just use five bit numbers just as a way it really helps often if you're trying to understand  this stuff to do it for some smaller cases
So if we think about bit positions
zero through four
Then those represent of different powers of two weights of as I've shown
And so now if we take some bit a pattern
Like so
So that's what I'll call X and I want to convert that to an unsigned number
I will just combine 8 + 4 + 1 and I'll get 13
all right
So that's all that equation says the left hand equations just take the the bit positions that are ones
Use the corresponding power of 2 and you're done
And similarly if I have a number where there's a leading bit
It will be 16 + 4 + 2  so that will be 22
And so that's the unsigned case
And the sign case is the same idea
Except that most significant debt has a negative value
So it will still this is i
And our weights will be 1,2,4,8
But this will be -16
So that's what the equation on the right is saying this fit
Now we're going to change it from being a negative number to a positive
So obviously if I have this is my bit pattern it's going to be the same because
The other bits stayed at the same so let's do it for this case of 10110
So that will be -16 + 4 + 2 = -10
So you see in this case we have the same bit pattern
It's just if we interpret it you know how we think about what number this represents
Then in one case it's a positive number 22 in another case it's a negative number -10
And that's what these equations you see
And so the most significant bit is sometimes called the sign bit because
If it's a 1 the number is going to be negative
So let's sort of think about
What extreme,what are the sort of extreme ranges of numbers
We can get with these two different representations
So obviously if these are all zeros my number is going to equal zero
And if it's all 1 it will be 16 + 8 + 4 + 2 + 1 will be 31
And over here for the two's complement
The smallest number,well the largest number will actually be let me do it this way
Actually the most negative number so the smallest number and the strictest sense of the word is
is this it's -16. you can argue this by the way
This is the only bit that has a negative weight all the other ones have positive ones
So certainly one and all the rest being zeros is going to be the smallest number
And similarly the largest number you can represent
We'll be 8 + 4 + 2 + 1 which is 15
And so we call this number UMax
And we call this number TMax
And we call this number TMin
So there's a few things to observe about these numbers
That remember this is a 5-bit word size right so
You'll see that 31 is pretty close to 32 right
In fact it's 2^5-1
And in general if it's a five and that's for a 5-bit word size
So you would say in general it will have value 2^w if I have a W bit number minus 1 and that's what this shows
And similarly over here this is -2^4
And so we'd say in general that will be -2^w if it's a W bit number minus 1
Right all these make sense by the way you'll notice one other feature is
A whole string of ones like this if you sum up those digits 8 + 4 + 2 + 1
Will be 1 less than the next bit position up
And you can think about that if you were to count this number
If you were to increment this number by 1 you'd get 1 1 is 0 carry 1 and so forth
And you'd carry that value up to this position so these various ways you can think about that
And then similarly this number is 2^4-1
And so that's equal to 2^(w-1) - 1
As is shown here
So there's a lot of the book goes through formulas and does derivation
But if you just think about it in these smaller scale ways
The intuition is pretty easy to get and don't get lost in in formulas when
Really at the gut level it's a fairly straightforward sort of ideas
Or if you ever see some confusions and you're confused
Try out some small examples and see what they're saying
Another interesting number in the world of two's complement  is what happens when you have all ones in your bit patterns
And that will have mate -16 + 8 + 4 + 2 + 1 and that will equal -1
So the bit pattern all ones is always a -1 in this representation
I should mention two's complement is not the only way to represent a positive and negative numbers
what's sometimes called signed numbers
But it's so universal that you'll hardly ever encounter another case
So if you understand two's complement you have a pretty good understanding of  what really is going on
So these numbers I call UMax the biggest unsigned number
TMin the smallest most negative two's complement monitor and
TMax the largest most positive two's complement
This chart shows the range of values for different word sizes different numbers of bytes
And so you'll see that with an 8 bit number you only have 256 possibilities right
And so we can either choose to rate think of those as representing the range from 0 to 255
Or basically with two's complement numbers we're just doing a sort of a wraparound we're saying
Well we're going to have half of them be negative and the other half will be either 0 or positive
And so it's a pretty limited range of values of course
Then 16 and believe me back when computers had 16-bit word sizes
It was a nuisance to keep your numbers within that range
And 32 gives you a pretty decent range it used to be said
Microsoft had to go to 64-bit word size to represent Bill Gates's net worth but
For me at least this would easily handle my range of normal day-to-day transactions so
But now with 64 bits at least to us nowadays those seem like really big numbers and  hard to imagine exceeding the bounds of those
So one interesting feature that you noticed here was I was um
like this case here
In this case here...
And then this case here  of all ones
I was comparing it to this case here of all ones
So in other words in both these cases and it's a little hard to jump boards here
You're seeing that you have the same bit pattern in either case
But they the numeric they represent different numeric values because one is a two's complement case
And the other is an unsigned right
And you can actually see the relation between them is pretty simple
Because basically what we're doing is we're jumping between +16 and -16 between those
And so you'd expect it to change by 32 right
And you see that here that this is 31 here and -1
This is 22 and -10 so they're differ from each other by plus  -32 ,2^4,two to the word size
and so we there's sort of a long derivation in the book and things here
But that connection is actually fairly important
Because when you jump back and forth
Between unsigned numbers and two's complement numbers in C
That's the jump that you get in other words
when of and so
You'll often find cases where what used to be a very large number
Because it was unsigned all of a sudden becomes a negative number
Because it's considered two's complement
So that's what this next part covers will say that
If we take a cart of 4 bit numbers and
We write out all the possible values is unsigned or as  two's complement numbers
Then the ones where the low the higher bid is 0 will be the same in both cases
The ones where the higher order bit is a 1 in this case will differ by 16 2^4
And similarly you'll notice that these numbers there's a unique
It goes unique in both directions there's a for any given bit pattern
There's a unique number it represents and
And similarly for any number within the given range there's a unique bit pattern
So we can sort of jump between those two and say
I can make up a rule for converting between a two's complement number X
and an unsigned number UX
That basically says I'll use the same bits I'll just think of them as being different numbers
And so and you can go either way
So for example if we thought of this is a a two's complement representative representation
It's -1 this function I'm calling T2U goes from that number -1 to this number 31
Where in between the two I'm saying they both have the same bit pattern
And the reason why this rather function that would otherwise seem to have no particular use is important
Because that's basically what happens in C or actually in the program
On the computer itself has no clue whether a given bit pattern if it's something
You're thinking of as being a negative number or two's complement number it's just a bunch of bits to it
And similarly so we can go back and forth between a two's complement and unsigned  keeping the bit patterns the same
And so I'll call that T2U when I go from signed to unsigned two's complement unsigned
And say well I'll call U2T if I go from unsigned to signed
And as I mentioned the difference for the the numbers where the high-order bit is a 1
will be by a factor 2^w where w is the word size of the word
And so this can be thought of as a function
Where
Let me just draw it up
Over here with my five of bit numbers
That is the number this is two's complement again so that was the number -16
And then there'll be some other negative numbers up to all ones
This is number negative one
Then I'll have zero and so forth and then all up to
Plus 15
Destroys,I got myself in trouble
Blackboard management is they didn't teach me this in school
So I'm gonna use two boards and ones here
Okay let me send this out,okay we'll make it work
So now when we go from the T2U function then
These numbers are going to just carry over
We'll get 0 up through 15
But now this number here will become positive 16
And all ones will become positive 31 right
And so that's what this picture is showing is it for the pink numbers
are the ones that flip between negative and actually the largest of the positive numbers
And then the green numbers are the ones that stay the same because they're leading bits or zeros
So why does this matter bits or zeros
You never thought if you programmed in Python  or even Java
You don't see that and the reason is because C is one of the few languages where unsigned is actually an explicit datatype
So you can declare a value being unsigned
And it's you can if you just say unsigned what you're really saying is unsigned int
Or you can call something an unsigned care and unsigned short or an unsigned long
So and you're declaring and see that it should think about using this representation we show on the right
When it's working on those numbers
So that's sort of one thing and this it's one thing if you declare a number and use it that way
But what gets people and the often got you is if you declare something if you have a in this case
Something that's declared as a two's complement number X to TX
And you assign it a value you at Y X it'll do an implicit casting
Which is exactly based on this conversion that we've been talking about and vice versa
And so as this example goes through this goes through some examples that
If I look at two numbers and I compare them or I actually I do any operation on them
I add them divide them anything implicitly it will try to make these to be of the same type
And the way it will do that is to say if both of them are signed
Then I'll do I'll treat them as a signed case
If either of them is unsigned
Then I'll convert the other one to be an unsigned number and do the operation
And so in particular this set of examples is imagine
I'm comparing these I'm saying these numbers are either equal less or greater
What will the outcomes be and the key to answering that question is to first of all figure out
Okay is it a signed or an unsigned comparison should I convert
One of these numbers to either of these numbers to an unsigned form before I do it
And the rule was if either argument is unsigned then you got to do it
And as you see when you put a u at the end either a  u or U at the end of a numeric constant
You're saying this is an unsigned value
So for example if we compare a zero and zero unsigned they're equal
And if we combine negative one compare negative one to zero
We'll get that the first one is less
Because -1 is less than 0
But what would happen with the next one when we compare negative 1 to an unsigned 0
greater right
So this is the surprise and it has to do with...a number that I erased
but we can still get it remember this is negative one
But when I cast that to an unsigned number
I'm flipping this from -16 to +16 and turning this into 31 I'm turning it into actually the largest number I can represent
And so it will be greater than zero
So it's a little bit weird to think about I took an u0 which after all is to 0  and compared it to a negative 1
And it said oh you really meant 31 didn't you or whatever word size we're using
And so it said it's greater
And basically the rest of these you can answer in a similar way
That these two numbers are this is clearly one smaller than this
No I'm sorry this is a positive this is a negative number and
I compare those and the positive will be greater than the negative
I'll tell you in a minute why this number is written this way
The next one it's the same pair of numbers
But you see it's flipped
And the reason is this number on the left is TMax for
So it's the bit pattern in a 32-bit number
And to this day I have not memorized this number by the way
But and then this number is actually TMin
And that when I subtract you can think of it as this is negative TMax - 1 so that's TMin
So if I do an unsigned comparison between those two now think of those
This leading bit  not being a negative weight But a positive weight you'll see that this is a bigger number than this one
And so it goes that -1 is greater than -2 if they're unsigned
Because -1 is you can think of it as converts into UMax it'll be the biggest number possible
And -2 will be would be 11110
So that can get fairly confusing
One final quirk this way of writing this number is there's a little side in the book about it
If you write a business number Oh as you'd expect - as - blah blah blah 648
It will actually get the C compiler gets kind of confused by that for obscure reasons
One other thing I should point out that it's a property that I don't think we cover well enough here
Let me see
There's a few things that the tides don't really cover here and I don't know why not
They like to point out
That are kind of useful properties to keep track of
It's that you notice that if you look at the absolute value of TMax
And you compare it to the absolute value of TMin
That it's off by one right
So that the negative number is more negative
The smallest negative number is more negative than the largest positive number is positive
And the reason for that actually is fairly simple if you think about
It is that the the cases where you have zeros
Include the number 0
So you can see it better
And there's two to the half-year range is occupied by those numbers
And the negative numbers are all negative
And there's so the other half of the range is in there
And the point is that you had to use one of these four zero
And so they're only there's one left one less value left over
And that's why you end up with this through a symmetry
And this a symmetry is the cause of no end of pain in various ways
That like a few the classic example is if you implement absolute value
Like so what do you what does this return for TMin
Yeah the returns team in we'll talk a little bit basically
When you try to negate this number that's here
You'll end up with it back again
So it's always a corner case and whenever we do program testing
We always throw that case in there to break things question
well that case you said oh yeah big number but how negative - one yes
No that's what they do that if you ever look at the in the C constance
They use this as a way of representing TMin
And they do it for that reason because you see
It's exactly this problem and they put parentheses around it so there's no president's problem
But you see that number that in six for seven that's TMax
And so basically it's just saying that TMin is -TMax - 1
Question
[student speaking]
yeah hmm yes
So comparison is just a special case of the more general one
Which is addition subtraction all of those
If either argument is unsigned then it interprets remaining one as being unsigned
It turns out and we'll get into this more next time as far as bit patterns but
But it turns out that at the bit level addition subtraction even multiplication
are the same whether it's an unsigned number two's complement number
So what we'll talk about that more next time
And the other thing to observe sort of property
is you saw that UMax is sort of like  2 * TMax + 1 right so
So before UMax was 15 in our five bit numbers
And and that's again not too hard to figure out
Here's one way to think about it ,TMax is a zero followed by a bunch of ones
And if I want to double that number position
I basically shift it left by one position
And that would end up with a zero here
So this is TMax and this is twice TMax
And now if I add a one to that
That I'll just set this bit to one and get this
So there's various ways you can think about it but that's one way to do it
It's one other thing that I wanted to mention too
This can get you into a lot of trouble programming wise so let me just show you what I mean
So I mentioned I wanted to go backwards through an array
So I write a loop of the form for i = n - 1
i >= 0
i--
then I do something with array element a of i
I just call some function of
Whatever you want to do in that loop so that's a pretty standard pattern in a loop right
Except that you write this greater equal to1 0
You can imagine various uses for that
So here's an interesting question what if I were declared as being unsigned
Because it's array index after all what will happen with this loop
What's that?
Yes! So the loop will go forever what would most likely happen is
I would go from being zero to being UMax
And that's a really big number and
The ray,you'd uh, most likely cause a memory fault because it's so far out of bounds
But the point is it wouldn't do what you want it wouldn't stop where you want it to
Because of the simple reason that I is of course
i is always going to be greater than or equal to zero because it's an unsigned number
So that's one you'd say okay well you should have figured that one out
It can be fair it more subtle though
If you have something like int i
And then we say something like let me just change it here a little bit so this will be
Something like this where the I'm mixing metaphors here I have to confess
But if you use the standard the term size of which is the way you get
How many bytes it takes to represent some given data type
So this will actually be the number one
So it's not the same loop as before but imagine I'm sort of mixing in my arithmetic and making use of some of these built-in forms
What would happen with this loop
Yes right yes
Exactly so sizeof returns an unsigned value
It's not actually a function it's a built in but it's the result of sizeof is considered to be unsigned
And so just like I was saying
If you have a signed value in it unsigned in any kind of arithmetic
It'll turn treat the combination of the two is unsigned
And so it will actually do an unsigned comparison here
Which is almost surely not what you wanted
And this will just you'll look at this program and you won't have any idea why it's crashing
You'll be so confused and that's the kind of thing you have to know
It's one of the quirks of C that probably a fake could start over again and redesign it
They'd come up with some different set of conventions than they did
But unfortunately it's way too late for that so this is just one of those things you have to remember
But yes the my point is through some subtleties to spent about in signed
About this business of signed versus unsigned arithmetic
Okay so now let's look at a sort of final class of operations which is
Suppose I have a number that's so many bits say eight bits
And I want to now expand it to be a 16-bit number
There's a fairly cute rule for doing this
That's called sign extension I'm talking about two's complement numbers here
Of how you go take a and make it bigger without changing its value
And the basic rule is you do it by copying  the sign bit to the left
So let me give you the intuition behind it
So let's go get some 4-bit values
Well it's pretty straightforward if the leading bit is a zero
I'm just going to do a left shift and then fill in so
Wait what am I talking about
I got ahead of myself I'm talking about something totally different
No sorry the same number I'm not changing the number I keeping it  the same
So I just add a zero to the lead and this will be the number six still this is 4 + 2=6
But now let's think about it as a where there's a leading sign bit
So this is -8 + 4 + 2 = -2
So now look at what happens if I copy that sign bit over one position
so this becomes a 11110
And what happens is this is a now has value plus 8 here
But the sign bit has value -16
And then this is still +2 and +4 and
So it will still equal -2
So here's what happened before my sign bit had a weight of -8
My new sign bit has a weight of -16
But I converted that old sign bit into a positive number which is +8
And those 2 cancelled out sit right the duck
That you combine those two and you get a -8 which is exactly this
So you see by sort of copying that sign bit over  giving it twice the weight turning it what was the sign bit into a positive number
You don't change the net effect of the sum
And that's exactly the idea of sign extension just keep going with that as far as you need to carry it over
And each time you're doing it you're effectively doing this business of coming up with a pair of bits
that end up with the same value as this original bit
So that's the idea of sign extension and you'll see that a lot in bit patterns
Especially if you see a bit pattern with it starts with a bunch of Fs
What that tells you remember F is just four ones
is a whole bunch of leading ones that tells you the number is negative
Negative but not too far away from zero right
And you'll see that over and over again you'll see bit patterns and you just sort of want it
When you see leading Fs you say oh that's a negative number I know what's going on there
And so here's some examples but like you can see the main idea is you carry that leading bit
from the 16-bit case over and make as many copies you need to expand the word size
And I should mention with the unsigned case obviously you just want to fill in with zeros
To talk about truncation and send missing slides in this but um
A final case to look at is what happens if I make something shorter
So if I had my unsigned number from before
If this were an unsigned number this would be
1 2 8 16 14 17 right
What if I decided oh I can't afford 4 bit I don't have enough money for 5 bits I'm only going to give you 4
Well you basically just drop the most significant bit
And you get 8 + 2 + 1 which is 11
Which is 9 and the relation there is that this is a it's like modular arithmetic
Right mod 16 you're taking...no
Thank you
It's the risk of improvising so 27 and 11
Yeah it makes sense,difference is 16  that I knew that
Okay excuse me for my stumbling
But the point being that when you drop this thing effectively you're just taking the mod some power of 2 of it like
I mentioned the case where you're taking module 8
If you just keep only the lowest order 3 bits you're having a module 8
Now one really this is a sort of logical in the unsigned world
Your modular arithmetic is something that was understood by the ancient Greeks
So not too far away from human experience
But it gets a little bit funky if you're dealing with two's complement numbers
Because this is now 10 11 -5 right
But this number if I just drop this bit and
And call it a 4-bit number this now becomes -8,2,1
It's -5
You say how'd that happen well actually if you look at it this is just what you'd get by sign extension right
So this wasn't a very interesting example
But if we changed it to this
Then this would be -13
And this would be +3
And it's a little harder to think about in terms of modular arithmetic
The way you basically have to think about it is well
You know this is -13 but it's really kind of like 27 and  27 mod 16 is sort of like or,no this isn't 20
We changed our number right so this is really kind of like 19.And 19 mod 16 is 3.And this is 3
So you can sort of do it by coming back around to it
But it's not sum of arithmetic property that would jump out at you as being something logical
But that happens all the time that and it's very common
For numbers to get truncated for one reason or another
And you can see that you can have a negative number become a positive number
You can have a positive number become a negative number
And all kinds of goofy stuff can happen
And we'll see plenty examples of that when we look at arithmetic
So that's,that is what I want to cover today
And we'll cover the other arithmetic operations on Tuesday
So thank you very much