Good afternoon everyone
So i apologize i have to i'm going to sit mostly through this lecture
I managed to do something to my knee yesterday
And i'm having trouble moving around very much
But today what we're going to talk about is input/output
What it looks like from the programmers perspective
And this is a you've already learned sort of a lot of the standard unix libraries for like printf and scanf
And those routines and we'll talk about them a little but
What will first talk about is actually lower level io
Stuff that is directly interfacing to the operating system
And this is what you're going to need to learn about
Apartly some of this material you're going to need for the next lab
That comes out at midnight tonight the shell lab
And you'll need to
Also you'll be revisiting this at several other labs along the course including the final lab
The the web proxy lab
So this is sort of where we're we're really digging down deeply into this type of programming you do
If you're writing system software things that are very just barely above the operating system level
And i know for myself learning this material i actually learned this material from 213
My co-author david o'halloran is the one who knew this stuff already
He wrote that part of the book
I learned it by reading the book just like you are
But i found it actually very useful to know in a variety of different other situations
I've been in in the meantime this is quite a few years
Ago and so i think it's worth understanding
And i'll also mention this kind of material usually is taught
You don't really see it covered in most books
Except for ones that are really oriented toward system programmers and are fairly arcane
Or you try and learn it by reading man pages
And that's a fairly cryptic way to try and understand
Sort of a set of abstractions provided by an api
So i hope you'll find this useful
So what we'll talk about then is that what i mentioned this low-level i/o that
I supported by unix and other related operating systems
And then a package called rio which stands to robust i/o
And you will actually not be using this package until the last lab  for the course the proxy lab
At which time you'll use it a lot
But it's worth looking at and partly
It's in the book it's well documented in the book
And if you really want to understand how software works or a system works
The best thing you can do is if you if it there's good quality source code to look at and study
You can learn a lot from doing that
And i really recommend for that chapter in the book that you go ahead and study all of the code
That makes up rio it's not a huge amount and
Just get an appreciation for the subtleties involved in
How you deal with errors how you deal with exceptional conditions and things like that
And then we'll talk some about how files are represented the sort of various data structures behind files
How they support standard i/o and i/o redirection in unix
And we'll also talk about the so-called buffered i/o
The i/o that you're more familiar with and see when you use printf and scanf
So unix actually has a much simpler and more unified view of i/o
Than any other operating system and it's one of the nice design features of
It is that a lot of abstractions are built into the notion of a file
And a file is really just a sequence of bytes
And in unix does not distinguish between different classes of files unlike say windows or earlier versions the macintosh operating system
It just thanks to them as bytes and the operating system level has essentially no understanding of a more detailed structure inside of a file
And one of the things it does is a file is normally originally thought of is
Something that stored on say a disk drive or some other external storage device
And that you open you read it or write it you close it
Those sort of standard operations
But unix also use the notion of a file to represent many other different  things
Including for example the devices
That are the i/o devices that are connected to a particular machine the tty stands for teletype
Which is a antique terminology for how people used to actually interface typewriters to computers
The other thing that our viewed as like files are the network connections what are known as sockets
And when you do communication over the internet
You do it by you send a message by writing to a socket
And you accept incoming communication by reading from a socket
And so the same low-level api is the same
Whether you're reading or writing files on your disk drive or sending packets over the internet
So the the core operations then associated with files of course are opening and closing them  and reading and writing them
The other sort of attribute that's associated with most but not all files
Is what's called the file position so if again if you imagine
When you're reading from a file you don't want to always start at the beginning every time you do a read
You you read some data and then you read some more data
And so that's a tracked by a file position which is just a counter
That says how many bytes has have been written written read from this file so far
So that i know where to go and you can actually even alter that value with
A various classes operation called seeking
Which is just a way of changing the file pointer the position pointer
Now that doesn't work too well if your input is a terminal
Where you can't move you can't sort of back up and have a recover data
That was presented to it earlier or jump ahead and start accepting data that hasn't been typed yet
So there's some kinds of files have a file position and seeking
And others don't similar to a network socket
You can't jump a socket for it in time you can only read or write the particular packets as they come in
But in general think of it then is the file position
As part of the the data associated with an open file
That tells me how far along in this file have i read or written
And then again the files are because there's all these different things they're sort of unified in this file abstraction
But obviously these differences
And different attributes to them and so
There's sort of many different categories and subcategories
But the ones we'll think about our a regular files just think of things that are on a disk drive  directories
Which is a directory is considered a type of file meaning the data that's in there is just enough as a file
But of course it's special kind of file and that it actually does have an interpretation
That entries in that file describe the locations and attributes of other files
And then as i mentioned the term socket is a connection to a network
And it's both for sending and for receiving messages over the network
There's other files that we won't really talk about for example when you pipe
When you from one application to another
That's both the output of the first program and the input of the second are special types of files called pipes
And they're handled by writing is putting something into the pipe and reading is to take something out of that pipe
A similar something called a symbolic link which is just a way that
You can have multiple names for a file
And pointers to a file that aren't really
Without having to make separate copies of a file
And then other special types of devices
So we won't really will only consider for the first three types of files
And in fact for today mostly the first two
So the idea of a file then is it just contains arbitrary data
And the operating system really for regular file doesn't try to get into the details of what's inside that file
And there's some class of applications that will distinguish between a text file and a binary file
Not really at the operating system level but more higher levels
And the main difference with that is it a text file should only have the standard characters of ascii
Or another class would be various encoding that allow you to do
In coatings of non-english alphabets
And binary files would be things like an image or a actual object code or a video or audio file or something
That it's the you're within that code there's a sequence of bytes that are encoding numbers in some form directly
And then the main thing about a text file is that there's certain functions that
Distinguish a newline character meaning the end of it line of text
And you already learned about that character it's that got the code of a 0a as a bytecode
And that became one of the forbidden codes of your attacks
Because it would be interpreted as a newline by the function gets
Just to mention that and this is one place
When you're transferring files between say a windows machine and a linux or a mac
One of the things if it's a text file that has to be changed is
That two classes of systems have different ways of interpreting of encoding when is the end of a line
And in a linux or mac file it's just uh this character code a
Which stands for line feed
Whereas the windows files finish with a two character end of line
A carriage return in line feed
And i show you this picture of an object that you've probably only seen in museums
But it's a typewriter and just to tell you what the heck is a carriage return and what's the line feed
I thought you might like to in case you've never actually used an old-fashioned typewriter
Basically at the end of it on the left hand side of a typewriter is this bar
And when you start typing along
I'll the paid the the this roller with your page on it sinks along
And it comes to the end and then you want to get back to the beginning of the next line
So you want to both do the carriage return
Which is this thing shove it to the right
And you want to do a line feed you want the roller on it to go down to the next line
So there's a knob here that you can twist by hand
But in general what you do is you type along and then you go slam
Like that and this lever both pushes the thing back and it rotates the
The roller by one lines worth and
So carriage return line feed is where that actually comes from  in case you wonder
And then a directory as i mentioned it's it's stored as a file
But it's a file that the operating system at least the file system part of the operating system actually interprets in very specific ways
And as you know within every dot directory there's two special files
Dot and dot dot referring to the local file and its parent in the tree structure
And so in in most systems
Systems that i know of there's a sort of hierarchical organization to the files
We're not going to talk much about file systems
But there's a hierarchical organization
And that's maintained as a series of files each being the directory
And the directory then is a pointer to its subdirectory which again are files
And so what's referred to in unix terminology
And most other operating systems what's known as a path name is a way to navigate
Through this hierarchy of files and identify one particular one
And so that all comes to say that the low-level unix operations
That use to implement this are to open a file to read it and write it  and to close it
And those literally those are the names of the functions
So the open function then you give a path name
And remember pathnames can be absolute meaning that they start with a slash
And they go all the way down the hierarchy
They can be relative to a particular whatever your current directory is where
And they can also be relative to a user if you use the tilde slash or tilde l
Then that sort of a shortcut in this path name to get to particular users
So a path name can be any of those forms when you open it it just has to be some way that just like you specify
In other places that you tell where this particular file is you're trying to open
And so it's given a path name and then it's given a
Integer code that says what do you want to do when you open this file
In what form do you want to open it
And that's specified by a series of constants that are already predefined when you include the propria file
And you can and those actually get bitwise
Each of those is a one bit flag in a some power of two position
Or it's a position one bit in a field somewhere
And so you can logically or those together if you want multiple combinations
So for example i can say read-only i can say read and write
I can say append meaning don't
If i'm opening it to write don't begin it the don't start writing at the beginning start writing it wherever the end of the file
Is no so all those can be done and this is described in the book
By using the right set of names of constants and oaring them together
And that will return something that's called a file descriptor
And that's a very important idea that and one of the reasons why we're talking about this today
This is going to be very important in your lab
Is the notion of a file descriptor which is just a small integer
That lists which particular one of the open files
That's being used by this particular program are you referring to
And so it's a small number because these are a sign sequentially
When you begin your program and you run
And you're in fact limited on most machines to some
Some bounded number of open files you're allowed to have at any time
In fact if you go to
Let's see on
If you're on a machine and you type in limits limit
You'll see there that entry called descriptors
1024 says that you can't have more than 1024 files open at any given time
And in fact if you've got 1024 files open
It's a chance you're doing something really seriously wrong
Being that you haven't been closing the files you should be closing
And all the system calls including these always have return code
And the return codes very sometimes a negative number is an error sometimes a zero is an error
Now they're all different and all confusing and all inscrutable
So you have to look at the documentation for every single one of those functions
And one of the the rules we're going to hammer away at in this course
Is every time you make a system call you should check the return code
To see if there's an error and then do some appropriate way of handling the error
That's just a practice it's a pain in the butt
It makes your code look like a rat's nest of conditionals
You really would rather not because often there's an error you
Deciding what you're going to do when there's an error is harder than
Then figuring just ignoring it all together
And so there's a lot of code out there
Where people just cross their fingers and hope there's never errors in their system calls
But we're going to really push on you hard to say every time you make a system call check the return code
And do something if it's not right
And so the open will return a number so that it's an int that it returns
But if it's a negative number that means it couldn't open the the file
For example the file doesn't exist or you're trying to open it in a mode
That you're not authorized to open it in
So there's three particular file descriptors associated with every single process  that runs
One is standard input the other standard output the third is standard error
And they always have a file descriptor number zero one and two  dandumb
So that you shouldn't really refer to them by their file descriptor numbers
Even though you actually can reliably depend on those values
Same way if you want to close a file
You also open you see you give a path name and a one bit a one integer field
That gives these flags say something about the modes in which you want to open it
To close a file you just say close and you give the file descriptor number not the name of the file
And it returns a return code too
So you might say now why in the world could you ever get an error closing a file  it's open
And the answers that actually can happen
In particular we'll see when we have multi-threaded programs
Where it's possible to have to essentially two programs running at the same time sharing their data structures and
Interacting with each other sharing their memory
It's a very important kind of programming and one that you can really make bad horrible mistakes in
And one of the bad horrible mistakes is if you try to close a file that's already been closed
It'll be an error and that can happen if there's two different parts of your program running
And each of them tries to close the file
So in the book and in the in this code you'll see
We introduced some error handling routines one of which is called perror
And all it does is print some not whatever message you want to print
And then it exits the program
Or no i guess it doesn't that i'll mention in a little while
It just prints an error message
But the point is even even something as mundane as closing a file you should be checking the return code
Okay so this is the function that reads
At this low level is called read
And it's given a file descriptor
You provided a pointer to a buffer
That's you you've had to allocate either aesthetically or via malloc
And you also specify how long that buffer is  so that it can't overflow that buffer
And read just means read as many bytes as you feel like
But no more than the number i tell you to
Which sounds like a weird statement
What do you mean what you feel like
Well it has to read at least one byte so if for example it's
A standard input it will hang there and wait until
Actually with standard input it will wait until you've typed in a string and hit the return
And it will then read at least some fraction of that into the program
If it's a network connection again
The read won't just wait it will hang until something arrives
On that particular network connection and then read in some number of bytes
That have been sent to it and i'm being vague by saying some number
Because the truth is it there's no guarantee it will read any fixed number of bytes
It will read at least one
And it won't read any more than that buffer is
But the number between that might be variable
And so when it reads less than that the number of maximum number bytes
You specify that it's called a short read
And that canon does happen and you have to write your code
Expecting it and we'll talk about that a little bit
Oh and so again and by reed returns in a signed number
Actually of data type ssize_t like  s size underscore t
Which is typically a long int
So a potentially negative number  in it that that number is if it says zero
It means that it's hid its detected and into file
That you've run to the end of the stored file that the network connection has been closed or something has happened
If it's positive then that's the number of bytes that were read
And if it's negative it's an error code
So as i mentioned if it if it reads fewer than the number of bytes you specify
That's referred to as a short count and i'll talk about why that would occur
Writing is sort of the same idea that you provide a file descriptor you provide a buffer
Where the the data that you want to write out is stored
And you give up how many bytes long do you want your right to be
And it will write a sum number of bytes to the output at least one  and no more than n bytes
But it might not be all of them which is kind of weird because you said
I want to write this i want to send it to a file i want to send it over the internet
But it can potentially not send them all
And well we'll talk about that a little bit
So again that's called a short write
And simile it will return the number of bytes that were written
And so if it's less than zero that's an error code
So just to give you a really simple example of this in action
This code does what you call echoing meaning that you type in something and it will print it out
And it does it in the most mundane way possible
By reading specifying a single byte reads and single byte writes
So you remember i told you read well read at least one byte but no more than the number you've told it
So when you give it one it means it will read exactly one byte
And similarly with right if you say right one byte that's all
And so this is really really bad code
In the sense that called to read or to write
The system level call is a relatively expensive call
It means kicking your whole operation up to the operating system doing what's called a context switch
Meaning it will go into the kernel of the system invoke operating system functions
Do whatever the reader right tells it to do come back out switch back to your job
And that will typically take maybe 20,000 to 40,000 clock cycles
Which you know a clock cycle nowadays is less than a nanosecond so you say
Yeah it's a you're talking
Maybe 10 microseconds what's the big deal there
But that'll add up if you start sending long files out over
You know millions of bytes if you start sending them a one byte at a time
You'll spend most of that time sitting in the operating system going going crazy
So this is not a good idea but it does work and that's actually a easy mistake
You can make as a programmer is to not use it is to use as low level writing and reading
And the program will function fine it's just it will be really really slow
But just to give you a demo of this idea of
Our calls to the operating system
There's a pretty cool
So this program and this is on the web
Linked off the webpage the code for this lecture
So this one called cpe standard in meaning copy standard input
Is just the code i showed you and
So if you type something it will just echo it back
So it's reading in so it looks to you and to me
Like it up
Reading on line of text and then echoing it back but what it's actually doing
Is again the interface to the terminal is one that it doesn't actually wake up this code until it gets a complete line
But it's actually just printing these characters back one one character at a time
And i can demo that by there's a pretty interesting
Facility called tracing s trace then what strace
Will do if you give it the name of a program
Is it will detect every every system call that you make
Every basically call to the operating system functions
That you make when you run a program
And it will generally spew out this huge amount of inscrutable stuff that you don't really want to see
I'll just show you this
Oh it's telling you logging every single call and it's usually way too much stuff
So the more useful way to do this
Is to give it an argument that says i only want to watch some limited class of functions  of when this is running
And so what i just want our calls to the right the low level output right
And you'll see that what happens then is this string i typed in
Turned into a series of 1 byte rights
Calls to the low level right function
And of course some way i could show you the reads and writes
Let's try that
And it's all confused because i'm i'm measuring this comes out on standard error
But on the terminal it's sort of interleaving standard error and standard out so it's kind of messy to look at
But again you can see that it's taking my characters
And it's reading 1 and writing 1 in this loop
So let's see ctrl-d to get out of it back to the code
So what's this short count business why would that occur
Well there's a couple ones as i mentioned if you counter an end-of-file
You're not going to read in however many bytes you are given for the buffer
If you are reading text lines from a terminal
The terminal handler will just send a wine
It's worth at a time with the newline character terminating it
If you're reading or writing a network packet
The way network packets work is that or messages
If you have a big long message it's broken into smaller chunks
Typically about a thousand bytes or so question
[student speaking]
If you are trying to read from an end-of-file return 0
Um is that a short count it's a really short count yes but it's not a negative
Yes so as it says here if you encounter an inter file
It will actually there's two things actually it's a really good question
If you're like near the end of a file you have a hundred bytes left and you say read 200
Your first call to read will come back and
Get 100 character it would say 100 and it will get that number
And then you call again the second time and it will return zero
And so that's how you actually detect the the true end of file
As opposed to you know some other reason you might have gotten a short count is if that
You actually get a read of 0 the only case you'll get at 4 is an end of file
So that's a good question thanks
So again if over the internet typically packets are round a thousand bytes
It's actually depends on what where it's gone through what layers in the protocols it's gone through
But 1500 bytes is actually the the standard what they call minimum transmission unit
So if you have a big long file we'll come back in in blocks like that
And if you're trying to read into a larger buffer
It will typically come back in chunks
Question
No in other words you
And again if you're writing code you shouldn't expect any number particularly it will be dependent on the implementation
[student speaking]
No because i'm only i'm only reading or writing one character at a time right
So i guess you're asking what if i like spent a week typing characters in a really long string and hit return
How to know if you try it let me know the answer
But it won't cause an error but that part believe me they've really gone through that code a lot of times
And and gotten rid of all those lurking buffer overflow vulnerabilities in the code
But will let you do it i don't actually know but
But within the you should write your code again expecting short counts as a possibility
And by the way that's one of the the headaches of using this low-level i/o is
Is dealing with short counts is not is often sort of a nuisance of an application level
So you don't you usually package this up this kind of low-level file i/o into other libraries  that you're calling
It's only where are we demonstrating this is the sort of lowest level in the stack
And writing also can give you a short count
For example if you're sending packets over a network it will only send as many as is that packet can hold
And then return back to you and you have to keep pumping them out to send the different packets
And so usually when you write code that uses this goal of while you have to anticipate these short counts
So professor o'halloran wrote a package called rio
And you'll for now we'll just talk about what this package is
This is a package that you're really going to want to use for the final web for the course
And so for right now it's more of a high-level here's an example of code that uses low-level i/o
And packages up in a way that makes it a little bit more palatable
So rio provides actually a number of different two different
Well actually three
Two different levels of of interface to the file this file i/o
The lowest one is basically just a fairly small wrapper around
The the existing the the i/o  reads and writes you saw
That will handle the short count issue
And so when you say with rio if you make a call to the read end function and you say some number of bytes
Then that function will not return until it's read that number of bytes
So better be careful that that that many bytes are there if it's a network socket or a file
Well because it will flag an error message
If it's what will actually hang up if it's a network connection  waiting to read the bytes
Or return an error if it hits a none to file what it's not expecting
And similarly with write n is sort of a wrapper around the write function
That we'll deal with just loop until the short counts are taken care of
And then there is a another class of of i/o that's called buffered i/o
And this is what you really want to use in practice
And what you mostly use with the standard unix io at functions
Is it you want to within the the user code build up a little buffer of
Of bytes that have either been read in but not yet consumed by the application program
Or you accumulate some number of bytes in your program
Before it's actually shoved out into the file or out onto the network
And there's two versions of that one is a text oriented wine oriented i/o and the other is just a byte oriented i/o
So let's go through the what the functions are and actually look at the code for them
So as i mentioned the ones called read and write n are just very thin
They have the same general semantics as the read and write
But they deal with the short count issue
So let's actually take a look at read n
So again read n is given a file descriptor
A destination buffer
And a indication of how many characters
How many bytes it's supposed to read and it's supposed to
It's supposed to meet a return i guess it will return either a negative number if there's an error 0
If it's at an end of file
Or the number of bytes read
So i guess i was a little bit i should have been more careful
If it hits an end of file partway through it will return a short count
But that's the only case it won't return a short count
If if there really it could have read more bytes
So the main loop here you see is it keeps calling read over and over again until it's happy
Ah one way it can be happy as if it's read as many bytes
As it was supposed to write read in the first place
The other is that if it hits an error code
And you'll notice that
Oh and that there's some subtlety of tracking which type of error that is
But in general the common cases it will return the negative number indicating an error
If it if the number read is zero
Then that indicated an into file
And so what it will return is as many bytes as it's read
So return the short count
And here it's just saying okay i've read this number of bytes  and increment and decrement the right values
So the point is it will keep looping keep doing reads until it either gets the number of bytes it should
It hits an error or it encounters an end-of-file
And you'll see it has its checking for all these different error conditions for every call
It makes so this code by the way is sort of typical that
It looks a little messy when you first look at it but if you sort of study it all makes sense
Um so now let's talk about buffered i/o and
What buffered i/o is and this is a very important concept
So it's part of the reason we want to show you the code for it
So the idea of buffered i/o is that there's a buffer meaning just an
Array of byte character's array of bytes
They're allocated and associated with this particular file
And the program if it's on to read what it will do is it will fill up
This buffer if it will give a read with a much larger number
With a large number basically the size of the actual
How much memory you've allocated for this buffer
And the system will fill that up with  up to that number of characters
And then when the user program wants to now look at this get some bytes
It will first check do i already have some in the buffer that haven't been read yet
And if so i'll just return those
Ah and if not then i'll refill the buffer
So the idea of it is instead of every time going to the operating system
And asking for one character small number of characters
The called the operating system says give me pretty much as many characters as you've got up to some limit
And then i'll just go away and what the application program
I sort of pull these out a couple bytes at a time
But i won't bug the operating system to do it i being the real function
And the way it does it is by just keeping a pointer  of that indicates
What part of the the bytes
That i've already brought in from the operating system call
But the haven't been supplied yet to the application program
And so in this sort of larger picture of things if you imagine you're you're walking through a file
At any given point in time this buffer will represent some a range of in that file
Where the green is the stuff that's already been read by the application program
The pink is the stuff that's been read
But from the operating system out of file
But not yet read by the application program
And the way this is implemented once you think about
It it's not too hard to do is
It associated with every file connection then is a file descriptor
Account that tells you how many bytes
There are that have not been read yet
A a pointer to where this this changeover is
And then the actual storage of the the buffer itself
The characters allocated the bytes allocated to the buffer itself
And so here's an example then of of using rio to do this
Echo that you first read online and reading a line means it will look for and stop at a line feed character
And writing it back out and again if you do the demo
Of this code
It's a little again you get let me just trace rights cuz it's a little hard to see the reeds are hard to figure out with...
So you'll see that it
Read the whole line and now it's done to add the operating system level
It's written just one chunks worth one call to the operating systems write function
Instead of a byte by byte
Okay so again i'm not going to go through all the code
But it's actually worth your while to do this
And by the way i've actually done some applications where i took the real code i want to add some features to it
But it's a very useful starting point to be able to build your own customized routines
Okay so let's talk about some other parts of files
One is that associated with a file is what they call metadata
So the data are the actual contents of the file actual bytes inside that file
But there's a whole bunch of other stuff that's associated with the file
Information about what type of file it is
What protection read/write/execute protections it has
Some information about the ownership of that file
What type it is and also the times associated with it
When was it created when was it last accessed in when was the west notified
So that's known as a metadata and every a file has that kind of information associated with it
And you can actually and it's in a data structure called a step
Data structure
And you can if you want to write code that then sort of probes the directory structure of a of a file system
You can make a call to the stat function
And it's given the the path name of the file you want to stat
And then a a pointer to it one of these step data structures and then that
Our data structure will get filled in by the information for this particular file
And then you can test various attributes about that file
And see basically get the information that
That's stored here
And there's all these nasty compile time constants
That you use or macros that use to look at and examine these these metadata
So here's an example i will do it but
But it's a function called stat check it's in the same directory
And so if you check some file or typically say well it's a regular file
And yes you're allowed to read it
But now if i a to call chmod to eliminate set all the protections to zero
It'll say no you can't read it now
And so again that's just making use of this data here
So now this is the part that gets a lot more tricky
Is how our files how are all this information about file is actually represented by the programs
Question yes stat gist
I'll tell you one way you can find out what step does
If you say man 2 step
You'll get more than you want to know
So in general you know if you say man's debt
It'll give a unix of command that you can use to step a file
So i can say stat
Top and it will print out some information about a file
In this case my local directory let's see
I can stat any file
Here and it will print out some some cryptic information about it
But if you say man 2 stat
The unix man pages are divided into different categories
And things that our system calls
Unix system library calls are typically in section 2 of the man pages
And so that will return information about it
But the main point of it is stat is then a function that you call
Where you give it a path name and a pointer to a buffer that you want it
And it will then fill in the contents the buffer with the information about that particular file
And the form that it fills it in is one of these data structures called a struct step
And that's pretty typical of a lot of these functions is that they have some predefined struct
And if you want to get the if you want to get information you pat
You allocate one of those struts you pass a pointer to it
And then the library function will fill in the details
Does that make sense okay
Okay so now let's look at some of the internal data structures that
The operating system maintains regarding the files associated with a program
And this is a source of really nasty exam problems
I'll just warn you so you're going to want to read this part of the book carefully
Study the practice problems look at the old exams
Because i can guarantee you you're going to get some of these on the final that's a promise
And they can be infinitely obscure so
We can we can torch you with these
So that the main point is that associated with any executing process
Which you can think of a process is a running program
Is a something called the descriptor table
And what that contains is
For every open file that you have
It has a pointer to a data structure called
An entry in a table that's maintained by the operating system globally
Which describes each of the open files
Actually each of every time a file is opened
That allocates a record in this open file table
And so as i mentioned file descriptor 0 1 and 2 have specific  meanings
And the other files are other ones that you've opened up during the course of your program execution and have not yet closed
So that's so each of these then is a reference to a particular open file
And it gives information about that file
And it also gives the position in the file that
Currently is that i told you every time you open a file there's
A for a regular file at least
There's an associated position of where in the file was your last reader right
Or where would you be your next reader right
And so that's the file pause
And there's also a reference count which is used by the operating system to keep track of
Because we'll see it's possible to have multiple  multiple processes sharing
An entry in this open file table and
It uses this reference count which is standard way of keeping track of memory allocation
To know when it no longer needs that entry if when there's been enough
When the file is no longer accessible and therefore this entry is not needed
So for every one of your open files that will have an entry in this table
And this table as i said is shared across the whole operating system
And then associated with every file is called a v node
Which stands for virtual node
And this is where that contains the sort of information about this file
In particular where is it stored on this information that you can get from stat and things like that
How big it is and things like that
So that's for every every file in the system actually has a v node entry
Whether it's open or closed
Now this can get complicated
So for example if within a single program you call open twice on the same function
You'll actually get two different file descriptors
And you'll be able to access that same file  and have two different positions in it
Then it makes sense if you imagine you're reading from a file
And you might want to read from two different positions in that file
Within the same program and you can do that that's perfectly legal
You just call open twice and that will keep track of two different positions
So the point is these file descriptors might be referring to the same file
But they're actually at different positions within the file
And that can happen also if you're if you've opened a file for both reading and for writing
And you're writing ahead and then reading characters bytes that have already been written
That makes sense
It's not such a good idea to have two different write
File opens that are writing simultaneously you can mess up the file pretty badly that way
But there's nothing in the operating system that prevents you from doing that
So it won't it's not a good idea but it's a legal operation
So that's the point is you have to distinguish at what level is sharing taking place and you see that
If you have two different oh table entries sharing one file
Then that what's different there is that you can be working at different file positions
Uh similarly of course the more common thing is
You have two different open files in there refer to different files
But now and this is where life gets exciting
If you call fork you remember about fork that it spawns a child
But that child inherits a lot of information from its parent
And one of the things it inherits
Is its descriptor table it gets a replica of that descriptor table
And so now both the parent and the child
Have identical entries in their descriptor table
And so they're sharing files
But not at the file level but at the open file table
And what that means is if the parent does a read
It'll bump along the file position
And if the child now doesn't read
It will it will see oh this from this new position
So you can see why the exam problems get really interesting
That will keep track of all these different possibilities
And they'll do different things
And so
And then of course the parent or the child can start opening and closing their own files as well
And that will get very messy
And here's what you see the reason for having reference counts here that
If you have a lot of forking going on
Then you can create multiple pointers to this a table entry
And in order to really really close the file each of these has to call closed
Before the file is truly truly closed from an operating system perspective
So there's other fun things that make a wife interesting too and contribute to the exam problem possibilities
What is it called called dup2
And the purpose the dup2 is -
Excuse me duplicate a.m. entry in the descriptor table
And the most common use of that is is a io redirection the either greater or less than sign to either
Redirect read the instead of from standard input from the file
Or instead of writing to standard output to write to a file
And the way the operating system actually implements that is shortly after starting the program
It will call called dup2
To make it so that the file descriptor 1 is not the standard output of the for this process
But it's actually the original standard output
But it's actually a descriptor for the file that it's supposed to write
And same width of it's doing input redirection
And but you can call dup2 yourself
And do these kind of things and there's actually good reasons for doing so
So in particular imagine i open the file
And standard output points to the sort of normal thing
And i open a new file i call it b
And then i call dup2
Excuse me
And now what both file descriptor 1 and file descriptor for are sharing
This entry in the file table and you see the reference count of 2
And so in order to really close it then
What would typically happen at this point is the this has happens before
It starts to your program you'd want to close file descriptor for
And in fact there's a lot of bugs you can make by not closing files
It's easy to make mistakes when you have multiple entries in these tables
Yes
/no see if i call closed this one it just decrements this reference count
But this remains a valid entry here
[student speaking]
Yes but dupe 2 will decrement the reference count of the original
So it's dup2 goes backwards from where you think it should
So dup2 is the
I want what what i referred to for example file descriptor
I want file descriptor for to become what i can use to and refer to with file descriptor 1 here
It will actually decrement the reference count
Of this before it it done does the copy
Otherwise it would create like a an orphan in this table right
Um so anyways dup2 also is a powerful but dangerous mechanism
So now finally let me just mention the much more common i/o that
Application programs use
Is what's known as the standard i/o and that's what's documented in k&r and
It's actually part of the the c standard
All these different functions
And so the main feature it adds is sort of like what you saw with the reo package it adds buffering
So it doesn't have to do this low-level stuff
And it voids all than some of the nastiness
And the the way it works is what we've already seen it uses buffering to do the i/o
So just in it is an example
Here's some code that calls printf
One character at a time to print the word hello
But if i run that and is trace it
You see that there's only one system call to 2 right
And it works the same way you saw with the real code
It builds up a buffer and it's not until this call to f flush
That forces the output to actually be a printed output
Usually that happens automatically actually if you print f up a line feed it will flush it
So but that i think that call to f wash is probably redundant here
So and so that's the benefit so buffered i/o is much more efficient
Because it because of the buffering
So as a result we've now seen three different types of i/o
There's the low-level i/o called you referred to as unix i/o
You saw this package that was written specifically for the book and for the course called rio
And then there's a much larger
And in fact richer set of i/o functions
Provided by the unix standard library
So you might ask a couple questions one is why the heck did you write this when you've already got that
If if unix provides buffered i/o why did you do it yourself
And the reason is this stuff doesn't it works really well for
The i/o you do to a terminal or to files
But it doesn't do very well with network connections
It wasn't really designed for that and so it gets really messed up
And so the main reason you're going to find yourself using this is when you're starting to use network connections
The other thing is these do not coexist very well buffered i/o with a rio i/o
Because they each maintain their own buffers and they don't know about each other
And they get terribly confused
So you kind of have to pick one or the other with respect to any particular i/o connection
And don't try to mix and match them
So like i said unix i/o then the low-level stuff from an application perspective
It's like really painful to use especially with short counts and error codes
And and all that stuff and
So in general you want to either write your own package or use some other package around it
And so as i said standard i/o it gives you printf and scanf and all these nice features
It's uniform it exists on all systems
It's reasonably standardized
So in general then use the the standard i/o for most year
Day-to-day uses of files
I'll use a raw io for low-level stuff like when you have to
And partly it turns out signals are not
You shouldn't use standard i/o when you're writing signal handlers
And then the reo you're going to find useful for in pre curricular for doing networking
One other thing that you should one bug that students do over and over again in this course
Is they try to do a line oriented i/o on things that aren't lines
So like a jpeg image or something like that
And the reason that's important is that these functions
Are treat the end of line character 0a is a very special character
They'll stop reading or something like that or if it's going between windows and unix
It will actually change one from carriage returned from line feed to carriage return line feed
Same way functions like sterlin and ster copy will stop when they hit a null byte
And that's not what you want to do when these are network packets you're trying to send out
So be careful some of the functions you've used a lot and you're very familiar with
May be completely inappropriate for things where you're doing binary of data
Or you're communicating over networks and things like that
So be sure you understand what you're doing when you start to use these kind of functions
So those who you really want to know this stuff
There's a there's a fellow named richard stevens who unfortunately died
Awhile quite a while ago
But his books live on and there's various people have signed up to become co-authors with him  in his absence
And creating new editions of these books that used to date back way far
So and if you really want to know how this stuff works you want to be the ace programmer
These books are the best you can get
But i'll also warn you your bookshelf will become very heavy laden because there's
There's the volumes one two and three and then there's networking books and
Stevens is like a encyclopedic reference
But they're excellent books if you really want to understand something  read stevens
And there's another book that is just specific to linux that's fairly nice and somewhat it's very detailed
But since it's only trying to deal with linux it's a little bit less weird than trying to read stevens
Because stevens will say in this version of unix it works this way in this version it works that way and blah blah blah
And it's all different and it will drive you crazy
But stevens is still it's an outstanding set of books
Ok so
This is an example and i'm not going to go through it
But these are the kind of things that we use to torture students that you
Open some file descriptors and you do some dupes and you do
Some forks and so you end up with a real spaghetti for all the pointers and
What's shared and what's not shared and then you ask what will this print
And of course you'll have to trace through in great detail what's really going on
So those are in the book and i recommend you work on some of those
Ok that'll do us for today then
ok that'll do us for today then
You
you