all right good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you so today we're
going to look at an idea called
exceptional control flow that's a very
important part of making modern systems
and it exists at all levels of the
system from the lowest level Hardware
all the way up to software so the idea
is when when you turn on a computer
from the very from the very first time
you turn it on it just does execute one
instruction after another until that you
turn it off okay and if each core if you
have multiple cores then each of those
cores are executing instructions one
after the other
now the the sequence of instructions is
called the control flow okay and the the
actual sequence of instructions that the
hardware is executing is called the
physical control flow now normally
normally this control flow that executes
just one instruction after another just
sequentially in memory and we've so far
we've seen two two mechanisms for
altering the control flow so that it's
it's not so that we're not executing
just the next instruction so that's
branches and jumps and procedure call
and return okay now now jumps and call
it branches jumps call and return those
are reacting to changes in program State
so when you do a branch you check the
control condition codes and then based
on some the results of that comparison
then you then you do the branch okay put
it real system needs to be able to adapt
to changes in the system State okay so
for example data arrives from a disk F
or some ro network user types control C
okay the program executes an illegal
instruction
okay all of these represent some change
some kind of change in the in the system
State and we need some way to react to
that so this the so what we need is we
call this exceptional control flow
because it's sort of outside of the
normal control flow that we we see in
our programs
now exceptional control flow or ECF
exists at all levels in the system from
the very lowest level of hardware at the
very lowest level we have what are
called exceptions and these are changes
in the control flow in response to some
low level system event so this is a or
and by event we mean a change in the
state now exceptions are implemented
using a combination of hardware and os
software which we'll see in it in a
minute but these these exceptional
control flow exists at higher levels too
so in the a process context switch is an
example of exceptional control flow
that's also it's implemented by a
hardware and the operating system kernel
and it so a process context switches
we'll see later
later today you're executing you're
executing your code in the current in
your current process and then all of a
sudden this the system is executing code
from another process right so your
process gets like suspended and so
there's a so that's a form of
exceptional control flow where you're
executing statements instructions within
one one process and then all of a sudden
you're executing statements instructions
in another process um at a higher level
are totally in software we have the idea
of a signal and this is implemented by
operating system software and we'll
learn all about signals next lecture and
then even higher at an even higher level
you have non-local jumps in C which are
just implemented by the C run
library so this allows you non-local
jumps allow you to break the normal call
and return pattern so from one from
within a function normally you can only
return to the the function that calls
that called you non-local jumps allow
you to within a function break that and
return to some other some other function
or some other part of the code so we'll
look at signals and non-local jumps next
lecture today we're going to look at
exceptions and processes so an exception
is a transfer of control to the
operating systems kernel where the
kernel is the memory resident part of
the operating system you know so an
operating system provides all kinds of
programs like to list files to change
directories to list the current
processes so all of that stuff
constitutes the operating system the
kernel is the part of the operating
system that's always resident in memory
so an exception is this really low-level
transfer of control to the operating
system because something happened in the
system so you're executing your code
user code and then something happens
some event so by event we mean there's
some change in the system state in
response to that there the exception
transfers control from from your user
code to code in the kernel which is
called an exception Handler and then the
kernel responds to that change in some
way this is called the exception
processing and then there's three
there's three things that can happen
after the kernel handles the exception
it can return and re execute that the
current instruction okay and we'll see
this is this is useful for things like
page faults allows us to implement
virtual memory it could return to the
next instruction which I've shown here
or it could abort now exceptions are
implemented by hardware and software so
the the actual transfer of control you
know the change in the program counter
or IP is is is done by the hardware but
the code that executes as a result of
that exception is set up and determined
by the operating system kernel so every
every type of event has a unique
exception number which serves as an
index into a jump table called an
exception table okay and so when when
event K happens then the hardware looks
uses K as in as an index into this table
and gets the address of the exception
handler for that for that for that
exception and so every time that event K
happens that handler handler K is
invoked now there's a different kinds of
exceptions we distinguish them as being
asynchronous or synchronous asynchronous
exceptions happen as a result of changes
in state that are occurred outside the
outside of the processor so these are
called interrupts and those changes in
state are are the processor is notified
about those changes in state by setting
a pin on the on the processor an
external pin called the interrupt pin so
this is the kind of when say a disk
controller finishes doing a direct
memory access and copying data from the
disk into memory it notifies the
processor that it's finished that copy
by setting the interrupt pin hi okay
and so after an interrupt happens the
handler returns to the next instruction
so an interrupt typically it's the so
you're running your program you're
running your program and then there's
like this little there's like this
little pause while the interrupt handler
runs and then your program just
continues to run okay so it's it's
usually sort of done behind the scenes
and doesn't doesn't affect your
execution of your program now the most
common or a common example of a
interrupt is the timer interrupts so
you're all systems have a a built-in
timer that goes off every few
milliseconds and when it when the timer
goes off it sets the interrupts in high
and there's a special exception number
four for timer interrupts and this is we
need this in order for the this allows
we need this to allow the kernel to get
control of the system again otherwise a
user program could just run forever in
an infinite loop and no one would be no
way for the operating system to get to
get control so every few milliseconds
this timer goes off that causes a
transient exception into the into the
kernel and then the kernel can as we see
the kernel can decide what to do maybe
maybe schedule a new process or let the
current process run and then and then
this an i/o interrupt from an external
devices is also a common example now the
other class of exceptions are
synchronous exceptions and there are
three classes of those one is that one
class is called the trap a trap is a
intentional exception so this is an
exception that's caused intentionally by
the program and the most the most common
form of a trap is a system call so you
know the operating system kernel
provides all kinds of services to to a
program but your program doesn't have
direct access your program can't call
functions in the kernel it can't access
data directly in the kernel
because that memory is protected and and
unavailable to user programs so what the
kernel does is they provide a interface
that allows programs to make requests to
effectively call functions within the
kernel and to make requests for various
services and this this interface is
called a system call ok so a program
makes a system call and and and requests
various functions from the kernel the
kernel provides those sort of reacts to
that request and then returns control
back to the the function there the
calling program so you can think of a
system call as kind of it's a it looks
like a function call but it's really
transferring control into the kernel
okay then there's some so traps are
intentional faults are unintentional but
but may be recoverable okay so things
like page faults which when we will
learn more about these when we study
virtual memory but something like a page
fault it's actually recoverable it just
that the kernel has to it means that the
the data the portion of the address
space that your program referenced isn't
actually in memory it needs to be copied
from disk where it's stored into memory
and then the instruction that that that
caused a fault needs is just restarted
and then it works that the the memory is
is there and then the instruction works
properly but other faults are
unintentional unrecoverable like
protection fault so if you try to access
a portion of memory that's that's not
allocated or floating-point exceptions
often times those those can be
recoverable so eat in either case when
there's a fault it either re-execute the
current instruction or to boat or or the
boards and then there's unintentional
and unrecoverable exceptions which are
called the boards and those those always
abort
so if you execute an illegal instruction
if there's a problem with your memory
memory and it's it's corrupted or if
there's some problem with the machine
those creative warts that that always
that are unrecoverable and never return
back to the to the program now system
calls there's many different kinds of
system calls and they all have their own
unique number which is assigned by by
Linux so in a for example to read a file
there's a system call called read which
is number zero opening a file a system
call number two and so on and there's a
there's an instruction called syscall
which actually performs the the system
call now you usually don't use this
system call and strike the syscall
instruction directly in your program the
Linux wraps those in system level
functions which actually call it for you
but it it's interesting to see how it
actually works so opposed you want to
open a file you call the system level
function called open with a file name
and some options say read only write
only and so in at the syscall
instruction takes the first the syscall
number is in our ax and then other other
arguments are in our dir si
RDX our 10 r8 and r9 so you can see if
we look in the the open function calls
the underscore underscore open function
which actually invokes the syscall so if
you look at that code you see it moves
the two which is the sis call number for
read into into a a X and then it does
the sis call and then the the sis call
returns its status in our a X if it's a
negative number then that means
something some error occurred if it's a
positive number then that means
something that no error occurred so in
this case and I in it the open it's
returning a file descriptor a small
integer called the file descriptor which
then you you can use in subsequent calls
to read and write and then you can see
the code is checking for this negative
return value too and there's a whole
series of these compares so let's look
at an example of a fault so here suppose
we have this program that we're writing
into a valid region of memory but it's
it's not actually stored on it's not
actually in the memory it needs to be
loaded from disk into into memory so
this is a so-called page fault so this
this instruction this move L because
this because the memory at this address
isn't isn't available triggers a page
fault so that that creates an exception
a transfer of control into the the page
fault handler in the kernel which copies
that page from disk to memory and then
it returns and when it returns it reacts
Acutes the move l instruction so that's
kind of cool so now the memory is
available and now that the move l this
move l instruction when it's reacts
acute 'add completes and then we
continue now another type of fault is an
invalid memory reference so here we have
a we're accessing an element of a which
doesn't exist and it's an illegal it's
an invalid reference so in this case the
move l instruction it looks like a it
looks like a page fault but the kernel
detects that it's an invalid address
that there isn't anything that can be
loaded from disk this is an invalid
region of the the virtual address space
so it it sends a signal to the to the
process and then never never returns
yet so the the signal that sends is the
infamous segmentation the signal that
causes the infamous sauce segmentation
fault message to print out and we'll see
you next lecture we'll see we'll see how
these signals actually actually work
okay so I said we've seen exceptions or
very low-level transfers of control that
are implemented by both hardware and the
operating system software it could sue
at the higher level is another form of
exceptional control flow called and we
see it in the in the context of a
process context switch so let's look at
and let's look at what what a process is
so a process the idea of a process is
one of the most fundamental and
important ideas in computer science and
this classical definition of is that a
process is an instance of a running
program okay it's different from a
program a program exists can exist in
many different places right a program
exists in yourseif as text in a C file
it can exist as the dot text section of
a binary it can exist as bytes that have
been loaded into memory a process is an
instance of a program that's that's
running that's in execution and
a process provides two key abstractions
okay it's the first abstraction is that
it gives it gives you the illusion that
you have exclusive access to the CPU and
thus and the registers okay so when
you're running when you're running your
program in a process you never have to
worry about any other any other programs
modifying your registers and and you
can't even tell that there's even other
processes running on the system right it
looks except for occasional delays like
an instruction that just takes a little
longer to run except for that it looks
like you have unique exclusive exclusive
use of the of the processor and it's and
it's registers the the other abstraction
that it provides is the illusion that
you have your own address space okay so
you have and this is provided by a
mechanism called virtual memory so each
each running program has its own code
data heap stack and you never see that
the code and you never see the memory
that's being used by other processes
okay so it looks for all intents and
purposes process gives you this illusion
that you have access to the exclusive
access to all the the memory and the and
the processor now that the system runs
many of these processes simultaneously
even even on a system with a single core
many of these multiple processes are
actually running at the same time
concurrently and you can see this if you
look at this here I ran top on on my Mac
and you can see it's running 123 123
total processes five of which are
actually running and each one of these
processes has its own unique process ID
this is integer
now the way so it looks it looks like
you have unique access or exclusive
access to the to the system but in
reality on a suppose we have a single
core on a you're actually sharing the
system and the the operating the
operating system is is sort of managing
that sharing so what it does is it we
have a process that's running and it has
its own it has its own address space and
and it has it sits and it has its own
registers and at some point either
because be cut at some point an
exception occurs either because of a
timer interrupt or a fault of some kind
or a trap at some point the the
operating system gets control of the
system and and in this case let's say it
decides that it wants to run another
process so it copies the the registers
the current the current register values
into memory and saves them and then it
schedules the next process for execution
and it loads the the registers that were
saved from the last time that process
was was running it loads those into the
CPU registers and then it switches the
address space to the address space for
for this process so this this the
address space and the register values
are the context and so the context
switch is is what is the change in the
in the address space and the registers
ok so then at that point the that
process is running now in reality on
modern systems with multiple cores the
operating system will schedule processes
on those multiple cores and then if
there's no if there's not enough course
to handle the processes then it will do
the context switching just like we
showed before
now each process represents a what we
call a logical control flow so if you
were to you know there's a physical
control flow which if we just looked at
all the PC values we'd be executing
instructions from one process and then
all of a sudden we'd be executing from
another process but within a single
process there's a logical control flow
which are all the instructions for that
process now we say that two processes
run concurrently if their flows overlap
in time otherwise they're sequential so
let's look at let's look an example we
have three processes process a runs for
a while and then it's it's interrupted
by process B and process C and then
eventually it it continues running and
then it terminates process B interrupts
process a and then it runs for a while
and then it terminates process C once
when process B finishes then process C
gets to run for a while then process a
runs for a while and then process C
terminates okay so given given this
definition of concurrency which which of
these processes are running concurrently
what about a a and B yes so so a and B's
flows B B's flow overlaps with A's flow
right so B B finishes starts and finish
some portion this portion of Bees flow
overlaps with A's flow right because b
is still running hasn't finished ok so
so a and B are concurrent as and
similarly C and a overlap so they're
concurrent but B and C are not
concurrent right B finishes before C
starts now this idea of concurrency it
doesn't this this definition of
concurrency holds regardless of the
number of cores right if even if you
have one core this example that I showed
you was on one core but even if you have
multiple cores as long as the flows
overlap in time
they're concurrent but we can think of
these no matter what we can we can think
of these as running in parallel with
each other at least from the point of
view of these individual processes
now this this notion of a context which
is it's managed by its managed by the
kernel okay and it's important to
realize that the kernel is not like a
separate process that's running it
always runs in the context of some
existing process and it's it's it's it's
just code that's in the upper portion of
the address space that gets executed as
a result of an exception so what what
happens the way to think about this is
that you have this process a that runs
and then an exception occurs which
transfers control to the kernel the
kernel invokes its scheduler which
decides whether to let a continue to run
or to to do a context switch and run a
new process another process so in this
example the scheduler is decided to to
run process B so it executes code and
then sort of changes sort of once it
repoint s' the address space then it's
running in the context of process B and
it finishes loading the registers for
for process B general-purpose registers
and then transfers control to b and b
picks up where it left off okay and that
at some point another exception occurs
and in the kernel decides to transfer
control back to process a which picks up
where it left off right here so whatever
instruction it finishes executing
whatever instruction instruction was
executing at the time of the exception
execute the next instruction here
now Linux provides a number of functions
that you can you can call from a user
program to manipulate processes and this
this this process this act of
manipulating processes we refer to as
process control now all of these
functions most are I should say most of
these functions call invoke system make
system calls but they're they're they're
wrapped in higher levels what we call
system level functions that that are the
things you actually call from your user
program now system level the Linux
system level functions that will
typically return a minus one if there's
an error and then they'll set a global
variable called error no to indicate the
reason so there's a hard and fast rule
when you're doing when you're invoking
system level functions you must check
the return values from those functions
you should and this you never you'll get
it you'll get into huge trouble if you
if you neglect to check the return
values okay so you should never make a
system a system level function call
without checking the return value the
and the only exception there's some
functions that return void such as exit
or free don't return anything so the way
the typical way you would do this is
like the fork call which we use to
create processes returns the process
idea of the of the the process that it
created which is always positive if
there's an error returns minus 1 so we
check for the return value to be less
than 0
and then we we deal with that error
somehow ok in this case we're just
printing a message and exiting now this
gets although it's essential to do this
it gets sort of forked from from my
point of view we're trying to present
code to you
it gets really messy it takes up a lot
of space yes
I'm checking that it's less than zero oh
yeah that probably that should be
normally the convention is to return non
zero so you're right that it's it's not
a hard and fast rule but that's that's
typically the convention so I guess it
should be exit one so what we'll do to
simplify this in the code that we
present to you and in the code that we
present you in the book
well we'll define error reporting
functions so unix-style errors where the
function returns minus 1 and then sets
there are no will if we get that kind of
if we get that kind of error will will
print the will print a message and we'll
report what that error was before we
exit and so then in the code we can
replace that that that body of that if
statement with just a single line okay
so that that makes the code a little
tighter but we'll go even further than
that and we'll define these wrappers
which were pioneered by a great
technical writer named w richards of
stevens and what we do here is we we
replace each function with a an error at
a wrapper that has the identical
interface as the function the original
function and it has the first the first
letter uppercase and then what this
wrapper does is it calls it calls the
original function checks for the errors
and then and then if there's no error
returns what the original function would
have returned so the behavior of this
wrapper is identical to the wrapped
function if there's not an error okay
and if there is an error then it deals
with it somehow and prints a message and
so then this allows us to make our code
really compact without violating this
hard and fast rule that we have to we
have to check for errors
okay the simplest function process
control functions are functions that
allow you to get the pig for the current
process which is getpid or the the
processor idea of you if the parent
process that created the current process
okay so this these take no arguments and
they return an integer which is a
process ID now linux provides ways to
create and terminate processes and from
a programmers perspective we can think
of a process as being in one of three
states running so in this case the
process is actually running and executes
instructions or its it can be scheduled
maybe it's not running but it can be
scheduled at a later time right and it's
waiting is waiting to be scheduled it
can be stopped which means that
execution is suspended and won't be
scheduled until further notice so we'll
see how this works when we study signals
in the next lecture but usually a
process is stopped because it receives a
certain kind of signal and then that the
process becomes stopped in ways it won't
be executed it won't be scheduled until
you explicitly tell it to be scheduled
or process can be terminated which means
it stopped permanently okay so it'll
never be scheduled again it's done now a
process can be terminated for one of
three reasons so one it receives a
signal whose default action is to
terminate it or your your program
returns from the main routine so you
know you can if you know the definition
for main is int see main routines always
return an int so you can return from
main and that will terminate your event
it will terminate the process or you can
explicitly call the exit function the
exit function exits the program with an
exit status of the of its argument so
as as you pointed out that the
convention is that for normal return is
to return zero and then non zero on
error or you can another way to do this
is just return an integer value from the
main routine and that will that will set
the exit status now exit is kind of
unusual and you'll see this is typical
of all these process control functions
that they normally functions you call
them once and then they return once okay
but exit you call once and then it never
returns okay so that's so that's a
little unusual now a parent process can
create a child process by calling the
fork function so fork takes no arguments
and it returns an integer it it creates
a new child process and then it returns
in both the parent and the child so this
is a little hard to wrap your head
around at first it's called once by the
parent but it then it returns in both it
creates a new process and then it
returns in both the parent and the child
and to the child it returns zero to the
parent return it returns to the child's
process ID okay
the child gets an identical copy of the
parents virtual address space but
separate right there they're distinct
but immediately after the fork returns
the the addresses the address space is
identical so that means that all the
variables all the global variables the
stack the code everything is identical
and the child
it has the exact same values as it as it
does in the parent the the child gets
identical copies of the parents open
open file descriptors so the child has
access to any open files including like
standard in and standard out that the
parent had and the only difference is
that the child gets a different process
ID than the parent so fork is really
strange because it's called once but
returns twice once in the parent and
once in the child so here's an example
of this here's a this is an example
program that has a it has a local
variable called X on the stack
initialized to 1 and then it calls fork
and fork creates the child and returns
the it returns a value to that both the
parent and the child we the only way we
can distinguish whether we're executing
in the parent or the child is to check
that return value okay so here if the
process ID if pit is zero then we're
executing in the child now remember the
child got exactly the same has exactly
the same
memory and encode is the parent so X in
the child is is one so when we print we
print this message from the child we
increment X and then print this this
message so the child will print 1+1 2
and then exit in the parent when we
check that this process ID it's going to
be non zero because it's the process
idea of that of the child so in this
case so so the parent won't execute this
the body of this conditional so the
parent will execute this printf and in
the parent we decrement X before we
print it so the parent prints out 1
minus 1 is 0 now there's no guarantee we
have no guarantee whether the child or
the parent executes first it could at
with the fork when the fork returns the
the kernel may decide to schedule the
child first okay in which in which case
this code in the body of the conditional
would run or it may it may decide to run
the parent first okay and and there's no
way to predict and you it's is wrong
it's an error to make any assumption
like that about what's going to run
first the parent of the child and you
can see that they share the same open
files because both the parent and the
child print to standard out and it
prints on the terminal okay yes Oh what
if the question is what if you call fork
multiple times I'll show you some
examples of those it gets a little hairy
will have a will use a model called the
process graph to sort sort of understand
what happens
okay so like just like you said forks
forks are kind of can be kind of complex
and time to sin especially if they're
nested or you call them multiple times
so we use a tool called the process
graph to to capture sort of what what
could happen when we call Forks right we
can we can't we can't make any
assumption about the ordering of of
different processes but we can capture
the partial ordering of events using
this this tool called a process graph so
what we'll do is we'll let each vertex
correspond to the execution of a
statement and then an edge is that
happens before relation so a happens
before B and we will label edges with
current values of variables if we have a
printf vertices a printed X that
corresponds to a printf we can label
that with the output and then the every
graph starts with a vertex with no edges
so given this graph then any topological
sort of the graph represents some
feasible some feasible total ordering of
events and by topological sort we mean a
total ordering of the vertices where all
the edges go from left to right okay so
let's look at how this would work for
our example program here we have the
parent initially X is equal to 1 and
then the parent calls fork the fork
returns in both the parent and the child
the child prints and both the parent and
the child print the value of x after
incrementing or decrementing and then
they both exit ok so you can think of
these as as happening so these happen
concurrently right which means they can
be interleaved in in in any way so the
the topological sort of this graph will
tell us a feasible what's a feasible
water feasible interleavings
okay so we can so if we if we real able
the graph just to keep it simple so if
we if we real able these edges with just
single letters then this total ordering
ABEC FD represent is represents it's a
topological sort and thus a feasible
total ordering so here we have a
executing then B then I execute CIN the
child and then at this point the the
kernel decides to swap out swap out e
swap out the child and now let the
parent run so the parent picks up and
executes C and then and then it gets
rescheduled to chat then the child gets
scheduled and executes F and then the
parent the parent runs and finally
finishes right so this is this is very
unlikely that it you only execute one
instruction and then and then B and then
have a context switch but it's it's
feasible right because it represents
because the the total ordering is a is a
is a topological ordering on the other
hand this is this is infeasible because
F here in this total ordering we're
executing F before E and you can see
that this that just can't happen right
so the the edges on these the logical
flow represented by this child have to
occur in this order first E and then F
right by the just because F follows E in
the code right that the compilers not
going to it's not going to alter those
okay so what happens if now if we have
two consecutive Forks well let's draw
the the process graph will help us
understand this so in the parent we
print L 0 and then fork and that creates
a child and both and so the fork returns
to this printf in both the parent and
the child so they both the parent and
the child print L 1 and then both parent
and child execute a fork so that creates
that creates another child that creates
two more now two two children okay and
then and so that returns to the printf
which says bye so the result of this of
calling Fork twice like this is that it
creates four processes okay and you can
and if it's confusing you can always
work it out with the the process graph
like this okay so we can weaken us we
can see feasible and infeasible
orderings so this one's feasible take my
word for it this one is infeasible and
let's see why so L 0 and there's no way
to to print by before the first fork all
right so that's infeasible if we if we
drew out this process graph we'd have a
backward a backward edge okay now what
happens if we nest Forks in the parent
okay I'm not sure why you'd want to do
this except maybe to torture to 13
students but
so we can just work this out by drawing
the process graph so here we have the
parent it prints L 0 and then it does a
fork so that creates a child so the
child if fork is not equal to 0 then
we're in the parent right so this code
executes sin the parent if fork is 0
then we're executing the child and the
child just prints by and then and then
terminate it eventually terminates I
didn't show it here but calls exit think
the function that called this function
calls exit so the parent so fork not
equal to 0 indicates that this is the
parent so the parent prints l1 and then
it does another fork that fork creates a
child so if if fork is not equal to 0
then we're in the parent so the parent
prints l2 and then exits this
conditional and prints by if if fork
returns 0 then that means we're
executing the child so we don't execute
this code we jump out of this
conditional and then the child just
prints by okay and we can so this this
represents an infeasible output from
this program l0 Fork week so L 0
followed by by that's feasible and then
followed by L 1 that's okay and then the
next by is okay but it since we can't
have this we can't have this by
proceeding this L 2 because L 2 will
this printf will execute before this
printf
okay and I'll let you work out this one
as a as an exercise all right now when
up when a process terminates for
whatever reason the system actually
keeps it around for until it's reaped
and the reason until it's reaped by its
parent and the reason it does this is
that the parent may want to know about
the exit status of the child so but if a
parent creates a child it may want to
wait for that child to finish and and
check its exit status so when when any
process terminates the system leaves
that it doesn't it doesn't remove it
entirely from the system it it keeps it
a little bit of state associated with
that child in the form of a the exit
status of the child and the in some
other tables some other OS tables so
because this child that's terminated but
it's not gone it they're called zombies
so there's sort of half half-living
half-dead and so a process a zombie
remains a zombie until it's it's it's
reaped by its parent using a function
called weight or weight pit and as a
result of as a result of doing weight or
weight pit the parent is given the exit
status information and then the kernel
deletes the zombie process now what if
the parent doesn't reap it's one of its
child zombies so it if any parent if the
parent terminates then the system
arranges for the very first process that
existed in the system called the init
process which has a process ID of one it
arranges for the anit process to reap
that that child so there's so orphaned
orphaned children will always be reaped
by by the anit process so we only really
have to worry about about reaping
zombies in
in the case where we have long-running
parents like shells or servers because
in that case a server may create
millions of child processes each one of
those each one of those does each one of
those child processes when they
terminate become zombies and they they
have state that takes up room in the
kernel so you can get this it's a form
of memory leak if you don't if you don't
reap these zombie children that can
eventually fill up the memory space and
crash the kernel so for for cases where
you have long-running programs then we
have to we have to use wait or wait pit
to reap the children so let's look at an
example first let's let's look at an
example of this zombie phenomenon so
here we have a function we call fork and
then within the child we print a message
of the process idea of that child and
then we exit the child within the parent
we print a message and then we go into
an infinite loop okay so this is a
parent that's that never never reaps the
child that it created so if we run this
program called Forks you can see it
prints these two messages the parent
prints a message and the child prints a
message and then and we're running it in
the background with this ampersand okay
because we're going to otherwise it
would it would it's it's it's still
running and we wouldn't be able to
inspect it so after we run this program
in the background then we use PS to
print the current processes and we can
see that there's two we can see here at
the parent which is process ID 6 6 3 9
and then the child which is 6 6 4 0 and
that the defunct indicates that it's a
zombie
okay now if we kill six 6:39 that's the
parent and then do another PS you see
that the zombies gone that the child is
gone because it's been reaped by the
init process one now what happens if the
child doesn't terminate you might wonder
like if if a parent creates a child and
then the parent and then the chattin the
the child never terminates and and the
parent terminates then what would happen
right mark
so let's just let's look at an example
of those in C so here we're we're
calling Fork we're creating a child
within the child we'd print a message
and then the child goes into an infinite
loop and the parent prints a message and
then exits so if we run this program you
can see that the two messages from
parent and child and then if we look at
the if we look at the processes we can
see we can see that the child is still
running
okay so the channel process is still
running even though the parents's has
terminated and now if we kill this child
six six seven six
and then if we kill it then we can see
that it's it's gone it's no longer in
the system okay so that child when we
when we killed it that terminated it it
had no parents so the unit process
reaped it and it it's no longer a zombie
so the the the function that we use to
to synchronize with children and reap
them the simplest one is called wait and
wait
it takes an optional status where you
can get the exit status of the inspect
the exit status of the child basically
wait suspends the execution of the
process that calls it until one or one
of its children terminates and it
doesn't specify which one it just waits
until one of the children that it
created terminates and then if this
child status is is not null then the
integer that it returns or the integer
that it points to this is a pointer the
integer that it points to will be set to
some value that indicated the reason the
child terminated and its exit status and
you can you can check that using these
macros which your your textbook
describes in more detail and let you so
let's look at how how this works in a
simple example so here we're calling
fork and creating a child which prints a
message and then exits the parent prints
a message and then it waits for the
child to terminate and when the child
terminates it prints a message and
indicating that the child terminated and
then prints by so if we were to look at
the the process graph for this you would
see that we would have the fork creates
the parent and the child both the parent
and the child do they're they're
printouts and then the parent waits it
suspends until that the child terminates
in this case by calling exit
okay so what that means is it's it's
infeasible so you can say hello from the
parent it's infeasible though for this
this child terminated message CT to
occur before the bye because
because the the child hasn't yet
terminated so it's these two these two
messages will never be printed until the
child is terminated by calling exit so
is that clear yes so the question is can
you have an output HP HP HC C T bar yes
yes because the parent ex-prince HP
there's a context switch the child
prints HC and then exits and now the
parent will the wait will return and
then it prints CT by
okay here's this is a and this is a
little more a little more involved
example so here what we want to do we're
going to create a bunch of children and
then we're going to wait for them all to
terminate and we're going to wait but we
won't be able to wait in any specific
order right we're just so here we have a
loop 0 through n and in each loop body
we're going to we're going to fork a
child and exit with a return status that
that's going to tell us which child it
was ok so in the parent so we do this we
do this a n times and then and then
afterward the parent inside inside a
similar loop zero to add waits for a
child to terminate so it'll it'll work
it will wait for M children to terminate
wait returns a way returns the the
process ID and then a status which is in
in this child status variable and so we
take that variable now and we can use
this w if exited macro to determine if
it terminated normally with an exit by
calling exit and if so then we can check
its exit status using the W exit status
macro otherwise if it if W if exited it
is false then that means some something
the child terminated for some other
reason not not because it called exit
okay there's a weekend we can actually
use wait pit which is similar to wait
but it allows us to wait for a specific
process a specific child a specific
process a specific child with a specific
process ID to terminate and I'll I'll
let you
you can wait pit is really involved and
it's described in detail in the in your
textbook and so you'll need to look
you'll need to look there for the
details on how that works now another
important so we've learned how to create
new processes the but we haven't learned
how to when we when we call fork we just
create an exact copy of the the child is
just an exact copy of the parrot running
the same code same program same
variables okay to run a different
program inside of a process we use a
function called X ik ve and exit loads
and runs within the current process it
loads and runs the executable file name
which is its first argument and file
name can be either a binary executable
binary okay or it can be a script it can
be a text file a so-called script file
that starts whose first line starts with
a pound bang and then and then that the
path of some interpreter so for example
if you if you want to write a shell
script you the first line of your shell
script is is a pound bang and then the
the path name of the bass show and then
that will that will execute - and then
bash will will read in that the lines
following and interpret them as just as
though you'd type them in at the at the
command line so in either case it
executes either an interpreter or it
executes a binary with who's argued with
the argument list Arg V and a list of
environment very
in env pee okay now by default are the
first argument in RV is the name of the
file that that's being executed so it
it's it's this file name so what that
allows you to do is in your code you can
check our v-0 if you want to print out
the name of the file the name of the
program that's executing you just print
out our v-0 okay now and exits all of
the code and the data and the stack it
overwrites the completely overrides the
virtual address space so once you call
eggs AK within a within a process it
blows away the current program that's it
okay however it retains that it's still
the same process it's just running now a
different program and so it retains the
process ID and any open files that you
have so x''k is really is really
mind-blowing because it's called once
but it never returns except if there's
an error so if this file doesn't exist
for example then then exec will return
on -1 but otherwise in normal operation
it never returns all right so let's look
at the structure of the stack when this
new program starts so after app after
exit after the eggs egg ve finishes its
work it creates a new stack it loads in
new code and data creates a new empty
heap ok everything's new and the stack
that it creates has the following form
ok at the bottom here's the bottom of
the stack and our stack is growing this
way so the first function that executes
is is a function called Lipsy underscore
start underscore main
so that has it that has a stack frame so
let's look this is what I'm showing here
is the situation right before the
startup code calls main so there's
there's the future stack frame for main
will be here at the top of this
following the top of the stack there's
some padding and then the argument list
in RV is contained on the on the stack
so that the RV is a list of pointers
terminated by the null pointer and each
one of these pointers points up into a
string that corresponds to an argument
okay so when you run a program you
specify the program name and then
arguments separated by spaces okay and
so these these arguments this arc V is a
list of pointers to those arguments
strings and it's pointed to right right
as main is called it's it's it's it's
the second argument to main so it's
contained in R si the address of this
argument lists the number of arguments
is contained is the first argument arc C
and that's contained in R di by the x86
64 parameter passing convention now the
environment list is also contained on
the stack and it too consists of a list
of pointers each of which points into a
environment string which is a set of key
equal value pairs okay and it's pointed
to by the global environment variable
environ and if it's passed in it's
pointed at an MVP it which is contained
in RDX which is the always holds the
third argument
okay so let's look now how how we would
use this so we want to within our
current program we want to execute the
LS command with two arguments - LT and
slash user slash include so what this is
saying is list list the files in slash
user include show the long form of the
listing and sort them in time order from
most recently used to at least recently
used so so the way we do this if we just
called eggs-actly e it blow away our
program so assuming we want to continue
to do work after we execute LS the the
standard way to do this is to to create
a child using Fork and then X act within
the child right have the child do the
work and then the child terminates and
the parent maybe will wait for the child
maybe not right just usually it will
wait for the child so within the parent
we we we fork a child check that it's 0
and so if it's 0 then we're executing
that this code executes within the child
so the child does the exact it it passes
the name of the function since the the
name of the function that we want to the
the program that we want to execute is
always contained in the first element of
vard V we call exit with a parameter of
my arc v-0 and we've set up the argument
list in my RV and we pass the global
environment variable environment we're
just going to use the current list of
environment variables that we have in
the parent okay and these environment
variables are things of the form user
equaled Rho current working directory
and so the the if there's if this
program in my art v-0 doesn't exist then
exact will return minus one so we check
for that that condition and then exit
otherwise it never returns right it
executes cell s LS the code for LS this
is the name of a binary this is a slash
bin slash LS is a binary file that
binary file gets loaded into memory that
code gets executed and it terminates
okay so the child at this point after
the exit the child is running that the
LS code and it's no longer running any
of this code now this seems the first
time you see this this combination of
fork and exec it seems it seems a little
odd doesn't it why not just why not just
have one command that creates a new
process and runs and runs a program in
that process why why separate why have
these these two separate fork and exec I
mean in fact Windows does this Windows
has like one command that creates a
process and executes sit but it turns
out that having having a separate
function like fork just to create
processes is actually really useful
I mean sometimes you just want to create
replicas of your current process for
example let's say you have a server and
you want to create a concurrent server
you want to create multiple copies of
that server then you just fork a bunch
you have the main the parent server can
fork a bunch of of children so that's
useful they're just all running the same
code but what's all what this also
allows you to do is it allows you to
execute code in the child before you
call x'q so you may want to set some you
may want to set some like some signal
with
is especially useful when you're dealing
with with things like signals if you
want to block certain signals or unblock
certain signals you can do it right here
in this this gap between the fork and
the exact
okay so so that's it so just to
summarize what we've we've talked about
today exceptions are in response to
events that require some kind of
non-standard or exceptional call
exceptional control flow they can be
generated internally in the form of
interrupts or internally in the form of
traps and faults so it at any point in
time a process has multiple a system as
multiple processes only one of which can
execute on a single core so the process
execution is interleaved by the kernel
and each process thinks that it has
total total control of the processor in
its address space there's only one
mechanism to spawn processes that's fork
and it's called once and returns twice
we can terminate our process by calling
X exit which is called once and never
returns we reap and wait for processes
using wait or wait pit and we load and
run programs using exact ve or one of
its one of its variants and this one is
called once and and normally never
returns okay so that's that's it for
today and we'll see you have a good
weekend and we'll see you on Tuesday