well good afternoon everybody welcome
good to see you so this week we're going
to study how to incorporate concurrency
into into programs now we've seen
concurrent concurrency before in the
form of processes exception handlers and
in the in the case of processes it was a
Mac we use we used processes as a
mechanism to run multiple independent
application programs now but you could
concurrency also exists in application
programs now we've seen a little bit of
this when we when we studied signal
handlers okay so a signal handler is
that is a concurrent flow that runs
concurrently with your with your main
application program okay and we've seen
we've seen how some of the difficulties
that can arise when we introduce
concurrency in our programs so even with
something like a signal handler which
isn't doing very much it's very hard for
us to reason about this kind of kind of
thing we have to two concurrent flows
running at the same time like there's
our brains just tend to be kind of
sequential we want to think about things
happening one after the other you know
it is and it's much easier for us to
reason about that reasoning about
multiple things happening at the same
time really causes problems and that the
fundamental reason is that - really -
really reason about say - two
independent two concurrent flows we have
to account for all of the possible
interleavings of those flows okay and
that's where and that's that grows
exponentially with the the with the
number of flows okay so you had you saw
this with your signal handlers when you
did shell lab you had you had two
concurrent flows the main program and
and your signal handler both accessing a
shared resource in the form of
the jobs list right and you had to be
very careful to prevent an interleaving
where that where that data structure was
being referenced in an inconsistent
state okay so what we're going to do
this week and into next week is we're
going to we're going to look at that
kind of application level concurrency
but in a more principled in a more
principled way than than we encountered
with with signal handlers so as soon as
you have multiple flows accessing shared
resources all kinds of bad things can
happen in your program and these these
have been these bad things these
problems that occur been objects of
study in computer science for four
decades but the the kinds of things that
can happen are our races which we've
seen in when we did the shell lab where
the the outcome whether good or bad
outcome depends on some some arbitrary
scheduling decision right in the case of
you know one of the races we saw in the
case of a shell was the case where that
a child just because of a scheduling
decision by the kernel runs and finishes
before the parent has a chance to add
that child to the job list okay so
that's that's a classic example of a
race and similarly if you have two
people that are trying to making
accessing a reservation system on a bird
for an airline
who gets the if they both access at the
same time who actually gets a seat just
depends on those various scheduling
decisions that are going on in the the
reservation system another kind of a
problem that occurs is deadlock so a
deadlock is a condition that exists
where you have multiple flows waiting
for an event that will never occur okay
so using printf in a signal handler is
an example of this kind of of this kind
of problem or introduces the potential
for that kind of problem
okay so in your main routine uxu you
execute a printf and that printf
acquires a lock on some system resource
I I think it's a terminal lock and then
after that that main printf acquires
that lock it gets interrupted by a
signal handler and now the signal
handler if it does a printf that printf
will try to acquire that lock but it
won't be able to get it because the the
printf and the main routine has it so
now your signal ham the printf and the
signal handler is waiting for an event
that will never occur it's waiting for
that lock to be released and it will
never occur because the main the printf
in the main routine can't release the
lock until the signal handler returns
and the signal handler can't acquire the
lock until the printf in the main
routine terminates so that's that's a
classic example of deadlock another more
from from real life imagine that imagine
that you're all drivers follow the rules
very precisely and and and the rule for
a four-way stop is that whoever gets
there first gets to go first okay so if
four cars arrive at the intersection
exactly the same time then you have a
deadlock you have none of the drivers
was first so no but of the drivers goes
and so they're all waiting for a
condition that will never occur and then
other classical things that can go wrong
or things like liveness starvation
fairness of this starvation occurs when
you fail you're trying to do something
but you fail to make progress because
somebody else keeps getting all the work
right so if you were if you had two
processes and the kernel always
scheduled process a instead of process B
process B that would be an example of
process B being starved out because of a
improper scheduling decision and we then
we would say that that that scheduling
policy always schedule
B is unfair right so it doesn't have
this this property of fairness where
every every entity in the system gets
gets sort of a reasonable chunk of the
processor so like I said I mean this
concurrency has been studied for years
it's a very it's a very deep difficult
topic because of this because of this
sort of exponential explosion in the
number of interleavings so we can't
we're not going to cover all of them but
we will cover some so as you get a
reasonable idea of how to incorporate
concurrency in your programs now for for
our study of application level
concurrency we're going to use servers
as a motivating example and and the
reason is that you cannot write a
correct server without using concurrency
okay so it's a good it's a really good
good motivation and here's the reason so
so far we've looked at servers that are
iterative okay so they only the only
process requests from one client at a
time and once they finish processing a
request from a client then they go on to
the next client so they so like with our
iterative echo server you can see the
each each of these clients makes a
connection request then it writes a line
of text to the server and then it waits
for the server to echo that back and in
this case this simple case it just then
it just closes okay and the server waits
for a connection requests and accept and
then and then waits waits for and then
once it accepts that connection requests
it it reads and when waits for what
waits for that client to to to write
something to the connection and then it
echoes it back and then it and then it
waits for the next line until the until
the the client closes that
that connection and then the server
closes this connection and then only
them does it does it do another except
to wait for the next connection request
okay so in in in this example client two
is also making a connection request but
it never it never runs it has to wait
until the server actually echoes back
the response now there's a there's a
little subtlety here that in where
exactly that this client Waits so the
the semantics of connect you would think
that connect would block until the
connection was established but actually
if you tried this out it turns out that
connect actually initiates the
connection process inside the kernel but
then it returns okay before the the
connection has been established and then
it does a right and that right also
returns immediately so right so it
doesn't it doesn't wait until the server
reads that the the string that was
written and it doesn't block until it it
calls the read function wait waiting for
the echoed response from the server and
so it actually it it doesn't block until
it hits this read and then it spends all
it waits waits waits Waits and finally
the server accepts the connection
requests and then writes the writes the
string echoes the string back to the
client
so the the call to connect actually
returns immediately and it's it exploits
this feature in the kernel that can
queue up these connection requests okay
so that the kernel now is going through
all the process of setting up the
connection but the application program
continues and then the right the right
inside the client doesn't block because
the the the kernel can also queue up the
data that's written so it'll little
queue it up remember that it was written
when the connection actually gets
created then it'll it'll send that data
along and but there's no way to avoid
the the read from from blocking write a
read can't return until it gets some
data okay so read has to block okay now
here's the fundamental flaw of an
iterative server and the reason the
reason why we have to write them using
with with the concurrency okay so let's
say in our echo server example we have a
client that creates a connection or
request a connection it's accepted in
the server does the write the server
echoes back one you know one string and
then the client blocks again or instead
of doing the next write or closing the
connection the person it
the the user goes out to lunch and never
types in a string to the the echo client
okay so at this point the server calls
Reed and then it blocks waiting for this
user to type in something and so that
the client can send it to the server to
be echoed but the user is gone gets hit
by a truck who knows anyway so this
never this Reed then blocks for an
indeterminate amount of time right and
while it's blocking client to which also
wants service it has to block okay so
now you you're in an untenable situation
where one client has sort of totally
affected all of the other clients in the
system and none of the other clients can
get service it's so if this were a web
server if if one client for some reason
blocked no other no other users would be
able to use that that web service or
look at pages on that that's site so
obviously this we can't have this okay
so the solution is to use is to write a
concurrent server instead of an
iterative server where we'll have a
separate concurrent flow handle each
clients request and interact with each
client so now if one client for some
reason is slow or misbehaves or blocks
the system other clients won't be
affected because those clients will be
handled way by concurrent flows
so there are several ways a number of
ways to create these yes from multiple
in class probably say four or five of
their other clients contacted and put
their rights over and queue of all those
it actually could and in fact that's
that's a form of concurrency okay so the
question is could the because could the
server queue up requests from from the
from clients it could but it would you
know I guess actually it would have to
queue up it would somehow have to accept
those connections right so that no so
that wouldn't work so somehow you have
since the since the accept calls are
iterative sequential there's no way to
get data from those those other clients
okay but but actually what you're
suggesting is very similar to something
called an event-based server that that
will which is one of the ways we can
create concurrent flows so there's
there's there's three ways to to create
these concurrent flows one is to use
processes okay like we've already seen
okay so the kernel and so in this case
the kernel handles all the the
scheduling for us and interleaves it it
interleaves the process execution
automatically for us and then as we saw
before each flow has its own private
address space so that each flow is
independent and scheduled by the kernel
okay now there's a another another
approach called event based where the
programmer manually interleaves the
flows okay so instead of relying on the
kernel to interleave these different
flows that the user the programmer
creates this flows and then manually
interleaves them okay
and since it's one program all of the
flows share the same address space right
so they have access to all the same
global data structures and they they do
they do this inter interleaving using a
technique called IO multiplexing you
know I'll talk briefly about that but
it's it's it's addressed much it much
more detail in your book the the third
approach which is kind of a hybrid of
process based and event based is thread
base so used each each each of these
flows is is implemented using something
called a thread the the kernel
like like processes the kernel
automatically interleaves these these
different threads
but unlike a process each each thread
shares the same address space okay so
each thread has access to all the global
variables declared in the program so in
so it's like process based and that the
kernel automatic automatically schedules
it for us but it's like event based in
the sense that every flow shares the
same address space okay so we'll look
let's look at all three of these
approaches in more detail so the first
approach is to create these flows using
processes so in this case this is our
echo server example the the client
requests a connection and then calls F
get us to wait for the the user to type
something in at the at the keyboard but
the user is gone and so F guest F get us
this client just blocks in the call to F
get s so the server when it gets a
request it accepts the connection
requests and returns from the accept
call
and after it returns from the accept
call it Forks a child and then that
child interacts that child process now
will be responsible for interacting with
client number one so the child blocks
waiting for data from client one which
is never going to show up because the
the user left okay but it that's okay
because it doesn't stop the server the
server after it Forks the child goes
right back and calls accept and now
accept can accept the connection request
from from client to and fork off another
a different child that can interact with
with client two so that child will read
waits for data to show up from the
client and then it echoes it back and at
some point then closes the this
connection okay so you see that this
misbehaving client number one now
because we have concurrent flows
interacting with all the clients this
misbehaving client can't adversely
affect other clients okay so now that's
and this is this idea of creating
concurrent flows to to interact with
clients is is fundamental there you have
to do this in order to to have a sort of
a working server implementation alright
so how would we actually program this
process based concurrent server it's
actually surprisingly compact right so
we're going to pass in in art V we're
going to pass in a port number that we
want this server to listen on we've got
a listening descriptor and a connected
descriptor we've got and then we've got
a length and a an address address field
and
the address is declared in a protocol
independent way using this sock outer
storage type which is guaranteed to be
big enough as you saw last time it's
guaranteed to be big enough to handle
any type of address either ipv4 or ipv6
okay so we install a sick child handler
and then we use the the open listen FD a
call from your from your textbook to
create a listening descriptor on port
the port that we pass in as the as the
argument to this program and then the
server goes into an into a loop and in
each iteration it it gets the size of
the socket or storage type and puts it
into client client lend and then it
calls it except with pointers to the to
the clients address and client line
using the listening descriptor that was
returned by open listened FD the accept
call after it gets a connection request
it returns with the address of the
client that made the that at the other
end of the connection along with the the
at the true length of that of that
address so the case of ipv4 before for
bytes and then the acceptor turns this
this connected file descriptor that the
then that that the the child that that
it can use to to read and write and
interact with that client so it creates
say it Forks the child and then the
child closes it's listening descriptor
and then it calls the echo routine to
interact with the to interact with the
client and when the echo routine
returns the client closes this connected
descriptor and then exits and so this
close isn't isn't absolutely necessary
but we just did it to be careful okay
now the parent and this is important
closes the connected descriptor because
it's not going to use that connected
Scripture only the child's will use that
connected descriptor so in order to
avoid this memory leak it's very
important for the child to to close this
descriptor okay because remember this
the server's running in an infinite loop
i mediate in in theory it would never it
would never terminate okay and then and
then to avoid and to avoid a memory leak
we have to in our handler we have to
have a sick child handler that will will
reap all of the children that have
terminated okay so let's look a little
more detail how this how this except
works so you have a client with a client
file descriptor and then you have a
server that creates a listening
descriptor so let's say that's you know
descriptors are indexed by small
integers so let's say that that index is
three the description number is three so
the server blocks and accept waiting for
this connection request the client makes
a connection request using the connect
call
okay the server accepts the connect call
and then it creates a child and then the
child interacts with the client using
the the connected file descriptor that
was returned from the accept so that
would be say descriptive number four
just be some different number okay so
are the execution model we have for
these process based servers is that we
have this the server processor listening
for connection requests one after the
other from clients and then we have
multiple clients interacting
concurrently with with multiple children
interacting concurrently with multiple
clients okay since each of these each of
these children are processes there's no
shared state between them and both
parent and child inherit the have they
inherit the descriptor table so they
have they both have copies of listen F T
and and can end the listening descriptor
in the connected descriptor okay and as
we saw before the parent must close its
it's copy of the connected file
descriptor the child should close the
listening descriptor but it's you know
just to be just because it's not needed
all right when you so these are actually
pretty simple to create and there's just
a couple of things you have to keep in
mind when you when you build a process
based server so firstly as we as with
any any any process that creates
children it has to reap these children
that have terminated to avoid this
memory leak the parent process has to
close its copy of the connected file
descriptor and there's a couple reasons
it fact if it doesn't it will not only
create a memory leak but that the
the state associated with that
descriptor will actually stay around
forever because the the kernel won't
close that connection so it as we saw
when we looked at at file i/o this is
just enough this is the same kind of
file i/o we looked at before so the
kernel keeps a reference count for each
each socket that's open so after the
fork now there's there's two there's a
parent and the child which are accessing
the file table associated with the
connected file descriptor okay so that
and the connection won't be closed until
the reference count for that connected
file description is zero right so the
that file table entry won't be removed
from the kernel until until there's only
there until there's zero references to
it okay
so both the parent and the child have to
close that that descriptor okay now the
good thing about process based servers
is that they they do the job for us that
we asked them to do right we wanted them
to handle to interact with multiple
clients concurrently or have that
ability there's a very clean sharing
model right so there's private address
spaces between the NE all of the
children and the parent they shared they
have separate descriptors but they share
they have separate copies of the
descriptor table but they share the same
Open File table okay
and there's so in some sense this is a
simplest possible way to create a
concurrent servers and if you can get
get if you can get by with not sharing
any global variables or sharing address
basis then this is this is the way to go
all right now the disadvantage is that
there's additional overhead for
processes even even with this
copy-on-write trick that we saw for
sharing the sharing the address space
between the parent and the child still
it's still non-trivial overhead and it's
it's you have to actually do a lot of
work if you want to share data between
processes so like let's say you want to
have some kind of a shared cache between
multiple processes either have to use
files okay on disk or if you want to
share memory you have to use some kind
of you have to use some kind of memory
mapping or you have to use what's these
inter process communication mechanisms
which we haven't we haven't talked about
but there's there's ways pipes are
probably the ones you're most familiar
with so a pipe allows one process to to
send data to another process and there's
ways to share memory between processes
but they're they're cumbersome and
require I have to be implemented with
care okay now the second approach is is
we call an event-based server so the
idea here is that the server maintains a
set of active connections so it it it
has an array of of connected file
descriptors from different clients okay
and then it determines which of those
and it also has a listening descriptor
descriptors have pending input and it
determines this using a system call
called select or eople there's several
ways to determine this
but but basically using select or a poll
you can determine which of a set of
descriptors has pending input right and
then this this and so the arrival of
input at a descriptors is called an
event because it changes the state of
the descriptor okay so an event is
always event in general is always some
kind of state change so in this case
when data arrives on a socket that's a
change in the state so there was no data
before the event after the event now
there's data that the server can read so
if if the listening descriptor has input
then the server calls except to accept
the connection and for all and then all
connected descriptors that have pending
inputs it services those it reads from
those in some order okay now that the
details for how to do this are described
in the book but basically I mean the
conceptually is pretty simple it's
actually tricky to implement but the
idea is that there's some set of active
descriptors right there's some set of
descriptors connected descriptors that
you're using that are being used right
now to to interact with a client there's
some that are inactive so if descriptors
descriptor was closed then it's it's
it's no longer active right and then
there's other descriptors that have
never been used so we just have this
array of descriptors and then and then
we record there you know the the
descriptor number for each of those
connected for each of those descriptors
and then using select or a poll or some
other mechanism we somehow determine
which of those active descriptors have
input and then we service each of those
in the case of listen FD by calling
except in the case of these connected
descriptors actually these are this
should be con up D not client of D but
in the case of these connected
descriptors we we read the data from
them and the when we when we read the
data from each each descriptor we do
some work okay so so data arrives that a
descriptor and then we read that data
and then we do some kind of work okay
maybe in in the case of an echo server
we echo it right back okay
in the case of a web server we may if
that data was HTTP request we might go
and fetch a file from disk and return it
okay but but in any case we we notice
that the descriptor has some data we
read that data and then we respond to it
in some way okay so that response those
multiple responses are concurrent flows
okay the the we're interacting with that
client we're interacting we're creating
concurrent flows while concurrent flow
for each each client and we're servicing
those clients concurrently okay so even
though it's a sequential program right
we're not using fork or anything it's
it's a it's just a sea program
straightforward C program we're writing
in such a way that we're creating our
own concurrent flows
so there's uh as with any any approach
there's there's advantages and
disadvantages so the a big advantage of
event based servers is that it's just a
sequoia it's one process with the st.
with one address space
right so it's very easy you can use
conventional debugger gdb to step
through you can see everything you have
access to everything so in that sense
they're much simpler to debug understand
and then there's no process or thread
control overhead so when we when we
service a particular descriptor it's
very it's there's very little overhead
right we just the only overhead is sort
of determining that that descriptor has
input available okay and so because of
that this is the high performance web
servers like nodejs nginx tornado they
all use this event based approach gates
if you want to get over 10,000 10,000
requests per second you have to go with
something like this okay the
disadvantage is it's much harder to more
complexed it to code up then the other
processor thread based designs and it's
very difficult so one of the the hardest
aspects aspects of the writing and event
based server is that you have to figure
out how much work you're going to do in
response to an event okay so let me give
you let's say that this server is a web
server and you get input on on one of
your connected file descriptor the
simplest the simplest thing to do would
be to then assume to read the entire
HTTP request and not and not return
until you've read the entire request
okay so in that case the the amount of
work that you do in response to an event
is very coarse-grained there's a lot of
instructions because we're going to read
every single every single line in that
HTTP
request header but it's so that's course
that's an example of coarse grain it's
very simple because every time you get a
request on a connected descriptor you
just read the whole you just read the
whole HTTP request and then send a
response
okay so there's on the other hand it's
vulnerable because what if a client
misbehaves and doesn't send the entire
HTTP request what if it sends half of
the requests so if you were doing to
design an event based web server you
probably wouldn't want to do that right
because that a single client we would be
back in the situation we were before
where a single misbehaving client could
sort of shut down the whole server so
you might say well I'm going to I'm
going to my unit of work that I do in
response to a request will be to read a
single line from the request
okay so I'll read a single line and then
I'll and then I'll return okay so every
so now we're interleaving reading single
lines and once I've read the entire
request then out then I'll send the
response so that's better right so a
misbehaving client if it if it's sending
like whole whole text lines at a time
even if it stops halfway through we'll
still be able to make progress in
service other other clients so that's a
finer grained approach it's better it's
probably more robust than waiting for
the whole the whole request but it's
still vulnerable because the client
could just send a partial line so now
we're back so really the only way to
write a robust event based web server is
to be able to handle partial lines just
read when there's data available on a on
a on a descriptor you just read whatever
data is available you remember how much
you read if it's not a whole line you
somehow have to remember that you have
to buffer it remember it
so now it's getting really complicated
right but that's what you that's the
price you pay for this for this low
overhead sort of easier to debug kind of
kind of model and then another
disadvantage is that you can't since
it's it's really a sequential program
right it's one C program you can't take
advantage of multiple cores so the only
way to get sort of more performance out
of something an event-based servers just
to replicate copies of that that server
but you can't make an individual server
go faster by using multiple cores okay
the third approach is to use threads to
create these concurrent flows it's very
similar to processes but there are some
important differences so let's look
first at what we mean by a thread so
let's go back I'm going to let's go back
in and look at the traditional view of a
process so we think of a process as some
context that's data structures in the
kernel okay data that the kernel keeps
about that process as well as this
private address space which contains a
stack code and data and then the stack
okay and then as part of the and then
the the process context consists of
context that's associated with the
program like the the registers condition
codes program counter stack pointer okay
and then it contains kernel context
which is information in the kernel that
the the kernel needs to to implement
this idea of a process okay so all of
this data is actually stored in the
kernel but some of the data is is
directly associated with the program and
other other other data is sort of
support data that the kernel needs to to
implement processes
okay so let's just take this picture and
we're just going to just move things
around a little bit so what I've done is
I've taken the stack off of the this
virtual address space and sort of pulled
it out along with its stack pointer and
the the contacts that's associated with
the program so the data registers the
condition codes the stack pointer the
program counter okay and I've just
renamed a thread context instead of
program context but it's it's the same
it's the same thing and then I'm going
to call this this whole thing the
combination of the of a stack and this
thread context I'm gonna call that a
thread
and then everything else remains the
same it's it's we have we still have our
code and data and we have the kernel
context
okay now by by doing this sort of
refactoring and just moving things
around
I can now imagine so this stack isn't
very much right it's so there's that
there's this there's the stack space and
then there's a little bit of data here
in the form of some registers and some
things to be stored but in this is a
fairly small amount of data now when I
really like an think about there being
multiple threads associated with the
same process if I if I just keep
different set of data thread context for
each thread and then a private a
separate portion of the stack that's
associated with that thread so now each
thread shares the same code and data
same virtual address space has the same
kernel context okay the same i/o
structures but now it has it has its its
own separate individual stack okay so
local local variables things that you
would store on a stack now would be
would be private sort of independent and
it has its own set of its own program
counter its own stack pointer its own
set of registers and condition codes
and then the one difference is now is
that each thread instead of there's
still a process ID for this process
that's pointed part of the kernel
context but each thread now has its own
thread ID as part of its thread context
okay so now the kernel can just treat
each of these as separate flows right
there's a separate so it's just like a
process now the kernel can remember
where the each thread has its own
program counter and but they're running
code out of the same that code the same
code section in the in the virtual
address space so the sharing code
sharing data but they have their own
program counter so they can the kernel
can provide can create each of these
threads as a as a separate flow of
control that it then schedules just like
it does of a process or in a similar way
that does is a process but the
difference is the reason the reason that
for threads in the first place is that
when the colonel wants to contact switch
from one thread to another there's not
that much information that has to be
saved and restored it's just a small
amount of data so the kernel has to save
this the data thread one context in some
data structure some way and then restore
the context for thread two but we're
talking about a very low overhead kind
of operation right it doesn't have to
mess around with page tables virtual
address space or any other of the
process context
so so threads are luck kind of like
processes it but they're different in
the sense that they share the same
virtual address space and unlike
processes which are created by fork
which creates a strict process hierarchy
threads are just pools you can think of
threads as pools of concurrent flows
that access the same code and data and
then the current the kernel is
responsible for scheduling those flows
and if in a way that so each flow gets
gets time on the processor so much like
much like processes much like concurrent
processes we say the two threads are
concurrent if their flows overlap in
time otherwise they're sequential so
this is the exact same example that I
showed you when we looked at processes
so here you have instead of three
processes we have three threads running
it within the same process
thread a runs for a little bit and then
the kernel just decides to walk it out
and and run thread B so then thread B
runs for a little bit and then the
kernel decides to give thread C some
time so it it saves thread B's context
restores thread C's context and sets the
PC to the the PC value and thread C's
context and so C runs and then the
kernel decides to give a some time again
so then a runs some more so because
thread a and B overlap in time they're
running concurrently B and C don't
overlap in time so they they're not
running concurrently but a and C are
concurrent because they overlap in time
and so you can you also have the option
if there's multi multiple cores than
multiple threat a thread can run on each
core so then you can have true
parallelism
okay
okay so like I said threads and
processes are similar ideas but in the
sense that they they each stage kinase
and process corresponds to some kind of
logical flow and they can run
concurrently with with other flows and
each is scheduled and contact switched
by the kernel okay but they're different
because threads share all code and data
except their local stacks okay and in
fact those local stacks although they're
each thread has its own it's it's really
just sharing the same stack and so it's
really the same portion of the virtual
address space it's just that each each
thread is assigned its own part of that
stack okay so even though threads have
their own individual stacks since it's
all part of the same virtual address
space a thread can access the the stack
of any other thread if it's and that's
not a good thing to do but it's possible
okay
so processes don't share any of the
state right they they have their own
private address spaces and threads are
less expensive than processes the it's
it's cheaper to create them and the main
reason is that there's just less context
associated with the thread than there is
as a process and so on our system when
we measure a bunch of we just create in
and wait for a bunch of creative process
wait for word process over and over
again and measure the time turns out to
be about twenty thousand cycles to
create and reap a process about ten
thousand cycles to create an reapeth
thread so that the kernel provides
threads to us using an interface called
the P threads POSIX threads so this is a
fairly recent standard that all all
Linux
UNIX systems and and Windows Macintosh
so every this is a sort of standard
POSIX standard for for manipulating
threads and so you can do things like
create and reap threads so there's this
is sort of sort of like fork and this is
sort of like weight but not not quite
because it doesn't create there's no
hierarchy associated with these you can
you could just like get pit you can
retain there's a function to to get your
thread ID you can kill threads so one
thread can kill another thread a thread
there's a there's a function to exit a
thread the normal exit system call
terminates all the threads and return is
similar to P thread exit in the sense
that just terminates the current thread
the thread that that calls it and then
there's ways to access synchronize
access to shared variables which which
we'll look at on Thursday more detail
okay so here's the the pthreads hello
world program you know your K in our
book the the C the C reference manual
the the very first the very first thing
that it does is it shows you how to
write the simplest possible C program
called so the famous hello world program
so that goes all the way back to like
1978 when K in our book was first
written but that's that's caught on and
and whenever we like learn a new
language or we learn a new concept we
always write the hello world program for
that concept so the hello world program
for threads this is this is a simplest
threads program that I can think of so I
call it the hello world program for
threads so this program defines a
function so court by in POSIX a thread
is actually executed by executing the
the code and a function called the
thread routine okay and POSIX imposes
this thread routine takes a generic
pointer as an argument
optional generic pointer and it returns
a generic pointer okay so anytime if you
want to pass anything to a thread you
somehow got to pack up all that data
into a single object then you can take
an address up but it's it you can see
that this is extremely general-purpose
so our hello world program creates a
thread by calling pthread create and we
say instead of a child we call this a
peer thread okay so that there's no
parent-child relationship any any
threads can threads can reap other
threads whether they created those
threads or not okay so you don't have
the strict parent-child hierarchy Pizza
create creates a thread that executes
the thread routine in this third
argument and returns the thread idea of
that thread in the address and the
integer pointed at by the first argument
the second argument is set up there's
there's ways to set attributes of
threads that are beyond the scope of
this course and will always just have
those no and then that this fourth
argument is the optional argument that
you want to pass to your thread routine
okay so in this case we're saying call
the thread routine that's that's called
thread with no arguments and then our
thread routine just prints out hello
world and then it returns in this case
it doesn't return anything so it returns
no but if we wanted to return something
to the to the calling program we could
have returned something a pointer to
some generic object okay
okay so the thread ID the thread
attributes are null that the thread
routine the thread arguments are void
star P and the return value is a void
double so it's a pointer to the pointer
that you want to return okay all right
so let's look at what happens when we
execute hello world so the main thread
runs for a while then it calls pthread
create which creates the pure thread
which now is a concurrent flow that's
running once once the pthread create
returns then we're running two
concurrent flows or running the main
thread and we're running the the peer
thread
and so in this case our hello world
waits for the peer thread to finish by
calling P thread join the peer-to-peer
thread after the calls it's printf it
returns no which terminates the thread
at that point the P thread join returns
and the main thread continues okay so
using using these create this create
function how would we write a thread
based concurrent echo server and again
it's very similar to the way we did it
with the process based design so we call
we acquire a listening descriptor by
calling our au s-- open listen FD
function just as before and then inside
this infinite server loop we we get the
size of the we get the size of the
client adder struct so which is which is
going to be a large enough to fit any
address and then we we malloc space for
the connected file descriptor so we're
making a one integer sized portion of
dynamic storage for this connected
descriptor that were that we're going to
get back from accept and we're going to
this is actually really important to
avoid a nasty race condition they'll
show you in a second so now we call
except with our listening descriptor and
client address and client length just
like before and except returns the
connected descriptor and then we
dereference this connected descriptor
pointer and so and store that the value
returned by except in this in this
location in the heap
and then we call pthread create by
giving it the name of our thread routine
which in this case is just simply a
function we defined in our program
called thread and the pointer to the
connected file descriptor okay now our
client which our client which our thread
routine then will use to interact with
the client okay so the thread routine
dereferences the argument a member is a
pointer to a connected file descriptor
so it dereferences that pointer to get
the to get the actual integer connected
descriptor and then it detaches the
thread so by default threads Threat
threads run an independent and attached
mode so they can be you know they can be
joined by other threads and they can be
killed by other threads but by default
if it's similar
when threads are running in sort of
unattached mode detail or undetected by
a join function to to acquire those
resources but if we detach a thread then
it can't be it can't be joined by any
threads but when it dies the kernel will
automatically restore the the resources
associated with that thread so in this
case we're going to just detach this
thread so we're not to worry about
reaping it when it when it finishes and
then we're going to free this this
memory that was malloc so this is
important we have to free this memory
that was malloc by the the main thread
in order to avoid a memory leak and then
we we call our echo function so we
interact with the the echo client until
the echo clients finished
and then we close this descriptor again
to avoid a potentially fatal memory leak
so this thread based education model is
very similar to the execution model that
we saw with with processes so we have a
list of a main thread that's listening
for connection requests they were
waiting for connection requests via
accept and then we have for each client
we have a peer thread that interacts
with that client using the connected
descriptor that was passed in when we
created the thread and then each thread
has its own since it has its own stack
it has it has separate space for its
local variables and this is really the
powerful thing about threads now we can
with these things they by declaring
these local variables we can we can
create threads that won't interact with
each other it won't and can run
independently yes
drunky cash
I guess yeah the question is is there
any time you wouldn't want to run
detached so when you run detached you
give up the the power to kill other
threads so so I don't know if you it's
hard to it's hard to come up with good
example right that but if you wanted the
ability to to be able to terminate other
threads you know maybe if you had maybe
if you if you were running a pool of
like worker threads and at some point at
some point if I mean I guess you can
imagine a scenario where suppose you're
running a pool of worker threads you
give them all jobs to do the first one
that finishes you take the result and
you don't need the results from the
other threads so you might you might
just want to kill those threads but it's
yeah it's hard it's hard to come up with
a really compelling reason
okay so there's a few things to think
about when you're when you're writing
thread based servers so the first is
that yet you need to run detach to avoid
potential memory leaks I'm sorry I
forgot this word so it the opposite of
detached is joinable and so joinable
threads like I mentioned can be reaped
and killed by other threads detached
threads cannot and their resources are
automatically claimed on termination so
the default states joinable and you have
to use this detach function call to make
to make the thread detached the biggest
the biggest issue with threads though
like the beautiful thing about threads
is that you're sharing the same global
address space so it's very easy to share
data structures you know if you had
multiple threads if you had a web server
a concurrent web server that was built
with multiple threads be very easy to
implement a cache that all the threads
could could use right because they're
all sharing that same virtual address
space but the thing that makes threads
so nice this ease the ease with which
you can share resources is also the
thing that makes them very tricky to
deal with so as soon as just like we saw
with our shell lab handlers you know as
soon as you're as soon as you have
multiple flows accessing shared
resources you have to be very careful
it's very easy to make mistakes and it's
it's very it's very easy to or it's
possible to to share resources in
unexpected and unintended ways for
example if if one if one thread passes
the address of a local variable on its
stack to another thread then now that
that the called thread now has access to
the callers thread and there's nothing
to prevent that that that called thread
from manipulating local variables on the
caller stack you know that would be a
very bad thing to do but it's possible
you might you might forget you know you
might you might forget
that the variable you're passing is a
local variable no not a not a global
okay and a really bad mistake in our in
our hello in our echo server example you
notice we were very careful to malloc
space for this for this connected file
descriptor that we passed into that the
peer thread that we are creating would
have been much easier just to pass the
address of the connected file descriptor
into our peer thread be much easier but
it would also be wrong
can you see why
okay let's say right here when we call
pthread create instead of passing a
pointer to a separately allocated region
of the heap instead of doing that we
just pass the address of the connected
file descriptor same thing right okay
and then in our thread routine we
dereference that pointer to to get the
connected file descriptor okay if we
just pass the address of the connected
file descriptor this is real it's really
bad can you see why yes it does okay
that's true and why is that bad I mean
just
that's yeah that's right so what what
this is assuming this entered this
bypassing the address of this connected
file descriptor we're introducing a race
okay in the race what we're assuming
that the peer thread will be able to
dereference that pointer before the main
thread goes back up and gets a new
connected file descriptor right so what
happens what happens right we can't in a
concurrent system we can't make any
assumptions about how the kernel is
going to schedule things right we saw
the same thing with processes so what
happens if after pthread create the main
thread runs instead of the peer thread
okay so we've passed the we've passed
the address of the connected file
descriptor for this client that that we
accepted the connection requests from
and then before the before the peer
thread can dereference that argument we
get a new connected file descriptor okay
and now the child runs and it
dereferences that that descriptor but
what it gets now is the descriptor
that's that's corresponding to the
second the second child not the first
child so now we have two threads talking
to the same client using the same
descriptor
so do you see them hope so it's very
tricky this is like a real subtle this
is an example of sort of subtle errors
that you can introduce because of this
unintended sharing and it's cause the
root cause is as you correctly pointed
out is that they're both sharing the
same memory on on the caller stack yes
in this case of what you could do
there's another there's another thing
you could do you could just pass the
descriptor itself
okay avoid so you could just cast the
descriptor to a generic pointer and just
pass that and that that's just kind of
yucky though that that would work
because instead of dereferencing it the
child would would just use it directly
okay so good that's good
okay the so the so the really good
things with with threads is ease of
sharing but that that sharing also
introduces can introduce introduces
complications in fact that's we're going
to look at ways to sort of control the
the sharing so that so that we do so
that we don't get unintended unintended
sharing okay so to summarize the the
approaches to concurrency that that
we've looked at we have process based
concurrency so it's hard to share
resources but it's easy to avoid
unintended sharing so in some ways it's
safer and easier to program event based
so it's it's very low-level very tedious
you have to be very careful about how
you the granularity of the work that you
do in response to events but you have
total control over scheduling so you can
decide which which descriptors you're
going to service and in which order it
sits since there's a single flow of
control you can debug it with a debugger
but it doesn't make use of multi-core so
there's a handful of trade-offs there
and with thread based systems it's very
easy to share resources but that that
sharing can create problems of its own
it's fairly efficient compared to two
processors you don't have much control
over the scheduling so just like we saw
you're not you can't really control
which which threads get executed in
which order and it can be difficult to
debug because there can be races that
occur very rarely very infrequently and
so the probability of sort of creating
one of those race conditions is is
difficult
okay so that's it for today tomorrow
we'll look at thread based servers in
more detail and how to write thread
based systems efficiently and correctly