don't get afternoon everybody welcome
good to see you and welcome to all those
who are watching on videotape as well I
want to clear up I realized after the
last lecture that I didn't explain the
idea of peak memory utilization very
well to you so I want to just explain
that it's an important idea and I want
to make sure that that we have it clear
so if you recall recall from we have
we're executing a series a sequence of
requests R 0 R 1 R 2 R K up to our n
minus 1 and at any point in time after K
1 k plus 1 requests we have H K which is
the the heap size
after K plus-1 requests now we have a PK
which is the aggregate the the sum of
all of the payloads after k plus 1
requests okay so what we're trying to do
with this this PK measure this aggregate
payload is at any point in time so as we
as we execute requests one after the
other the sum of all the payloads in the
heap is going to either increase or
decrease right so if we execute a an
allocate then the size of the payloads
will increase if we execute a free the
size of all those allocated payloads
will decrease right so so as we're
executing this the sequence of requests
these the aggregate the sum of all the
payloads is going to be increasing and
decreasing okay and so what were what
we're capturing with the sum of all
these payloads is like a perfect
allocator that has no overheads and and
even more so one that we can where we're
allowed to compact blocks so the sum of
all of the the payloads is the minimum
possible heap size or it's the minimum
possible number of bytes required by
those allocated blocks okay so it's very
very aggressive and it's impossible to
achieve but we're going to use that as
sort of our best case okay and so to
measure a peak
peak memory utilization after K plus-1
requests which will denote U of K that's
going to be equal to the the max for all
I less than or equal to K
of our aggregate payloads divided by the
size of the heap after after K plus-1
requests okay so what what we're doing
with this max is we're remembering the
high-water mark you know as our as our
aggregate payloads increase and decrease
we're remembering the high-water mark
right so that was sort of the worst that
was like the biggest set of payloads
that we had and then so the max is
remembering his room is remembering that
high-water mark and then we're dividing
by the total size of the heap in order
to get an efficiency measure okay so so
this max PK is kind of this is the best
we could have done divided by the total
the total heap size okay so yes
well that the allocator keeps track of
of how big the heap is so that's pretty
easy right so as every time it every
time it does every time it calls s break
it just that that adds to the size of
the heap and remember we're we're
assuming that the heap in this case is
always increasing okay so but even if
even if we allow the heap size to
decrease could just if the allocator is
controlling the size of the heap by
calls to s break okay so is that clear
so for UK the higher the better okay and
for any sequence of allocates and freeze
this max PK will be the same
okay that's constant right but what what
varies is H of K and that depends on how
efficient your your allocator is is
using the heap storage okay yes question
so what we're doing is at any point in
time after we're after K plus-1 requests
we're about we're evaluating the
utilization of our heap up till that
point so it should be K
for I I less than or equal to K oh I'm
sorry
yeah sorry good good catch so that
should be an eye right we want to look
at all the all the for all the requests
that came before okay any other
questions okay
all right so last time we looked at some
simple the basics of dynamic storage
allocation a we're going to look at some
more sophisticated techniques using
different data structures to store the
free list primarily we'll look at
implicit allocators so we'll get a sort
of a brief survey of how garbage
collectors work and we'll just look at
one just just one very simple kind of
garbage collector but it will give you
an idea of of what that means and then
we'll finish up we'll finish up by
looking at all the ways you can get
yourself into trouble by using
dynamically allocated storage so once
once you once you use once you start
dynamically allocating storage things
can go really bad really quickly and so
we'll go over some of those some of
those bad things that can happen and try
to alert you to those so you don't do
them in your programs
okay so we looked at how to store a free
lip free list in this sort of implicit
form by just walking the entire heat and
and thereby sort of being able to visit
all the free blocks but we can do better
if we actually have a EE if we store the
free block the free list is using as a
doubly linked list so in we call these
explicit free lists so the idea with an
explicit free list is that we put
pointers we put the pointers that
implement the the doubly linked list
inside the the body of the of a free
block say where the old payload used to
go so allocated blocks look exactly the
same as they did before right there's a
header boundary tag optional boundary
tag footer and then this the payload and
any padding free blocks though the
allocator and the allocator is not
allowed to touch anything in the inside
the the the payload of an allocated
block but free blocks are free right
nobody's using them and so we the
allocator can put the the pointers that
implement the data structure inside the
what was the old payload so logically
this is just a simple doubly linked list
okay that you've all seen before but
actually these things can be anywhere in
memory right and so you know here we
have we have a block of size six and it
has a four word pointer that points to
some other link and it has a backwards
pointer that points to this block which
happens to be have a greater memory
address than then it okay so just the
idea is you can't you know unless unless
you make unless you go to great pains to
maintain this sort of address ordered
structure these these these blocks can
be sort of scattered anywhere in memory
several times on that long oh yeah so
this is after several you know just sort
of indefinite number of Malik's and
fries and yes oh yeah good question it's
like so the question is what would
happen if you free to a block that was
in between two free blocks and so you
have to coalesce it gets a little tricky
and I'll show you in a second good
now allocating oh yes questions
so the question is what happens with
locality so you still get you still get
block locality you know use blocks are
still contiguous so if but if if you're
scanning sort of a set of allocated
blocks it would be better if you could
keep them all contiguous right that so
that's really and so there's a you know
that's a trade-off I don't it gets
difficult if you think how can you
maintain so you don't really care about
the locality of free blocks right you're
just walking a linked list well no I
shouldn't say that that's if you're
walking that list if you hit one one
free block it would it would bring in a
whole page so it'd be better if you were
walking if the list you know if as much
of that list was contained within that
page so even that's so you would benefit
you could benefit eat with both
allocated blocks because applications
would be using them and with free blocks
because the allocator would be walking
that that free list so question so even
though say you only need even though say
you're like alkane interest constructor
if you know the feature can allocate a
thousand of them somehow let me out the
other day you're going to try to help
you knowledge it didn't work that's a
really good question so the question is
could would it be possible for an
application to sort of give hints to the
allocator that would increase that
improve the allocators performance or
memory utilization the the answer you
absolutely could but it's if you did it
wouldn't be a general-purpose allocator
so like malloc is a general-purpose
allocator so it and it provides no
there's no option it doesn't provide any
arguments in its interface for passing
that information in but it absolutely if
it had some knowledge about the future
behavior of a program that could benefit
right so especially I consider you
always have this decision when you place
an allocated block whether to split that
block or not well if you knew that you
were going to get a request you know for
if you split that block and and you knew
that you were going to get requests
coming in the future first for sizes of
the original block then you wouldn't
want to split it because then you would
want it you would just keep it unsplit
and then when you freed it then you'd
have a block that would be the right
size for that that future request and so
it's you can absolutely benefit from
that and so although you can't if
general-purpose allocators there's no
provision for that kind of hinting but
there's nothing to prevent an alligator
from doing predictions based on the the
previous pattern of requests you know so
if you're getting a pattern of requests
it's alternating large block small block
large box small block you could you
could exploit that maybe maybe predict
that the next request will be for a you
know if it if the previous request is
for a large block the next one might be
for a small block and you could
that's good question any any other
questions wizard yes I don't know I so
the question is are there are there
intelligent alligators that do that kind
of prediction and if there are I don't
know of them but I wouldn't I wouldn't
say no yes what would happen you end up
with a free buckets of block just like
just a single block oh well so the
question is what if you ended up with a
free block that's a single block
surrounded by two allocated blocks well
in fact I mean that's one of the
invariants that a good alligator has to
maintain you should never have two
contiguous free blocks right the
alligator should always be coalescing as
much as it can and if it if it does that
coalescing if it if it always does that
coalescing then then there will never be
two contiguous free blocks okay
yeah it's question oh you'll see when we
it comes into play when we free a block
because you have to sort of stitch up
when you free a block you have to sort
of stitch up the the linked list and so
you need both you need both pointers you
can do it with singly linked lists so in
your in the K in our book there's a an
alligator that uses a singly linked list
but the the disadvantages that free
requires a search so it requires a
search from the beginning of the list to
find the previous block okay
and there are questions these are good
yes question okay so the question is for
memory utilization how does the header
and footer count towards memory
utilization and so those those are
overhead that decrease memory
utilization okay because they're not
payload so when we were computing memory
utilization we're doing it by we're
using the payload the aggregate payload
to to to estimate our utilization or to
compute our utilization so anything
that's not payload sorry is is overhead
okay was also one word so we had if all
of our payloads were one word and our
overhead was was one word then there'd
be 50%
yes if you have the book this pointer to
the next and previously block you still
need yeah so the question is do you
still need a boundary tag if you have
these these next and previous pointers
and the answer is yes absolutely and
you'll see in a second why yes okay
that's a really good question so you
know what do you do if you have next in
previous pointers what happened what
happens if there's a request for a
smaller a smaller block so the answer is
that all of those things the the header
the footer the next and previous
pointers impose a minimum block size so
if you have a one word header one word
footer one word pre even one word next
then your your minimum block sizes is
four bytes and that would be with a zero
a zero size payload so you can never
allocate a block smaller than your
minimum block size so that's very good
very good question so it makes a
difference right even though even though
we're you know it looks like we're
getting these it looks like we're
getting these pointers here for free but
we're not really because of this minimum
block size requirement yes
their weight of course to allocate a
gigantic block and export Malecha give
you specifically parts of that so say c1
CY allocate 100 trucks can you allocate
the side 120 today you just work against
one space to let you use it right but if
you wanted to like take the first half
make them take second have taken
integers or something and 50 say all the
stuff might program ridiculous it's like
here explicitly asking for that one
gigantic block yeah okay so the question
is can you just get a get one large
block and then split it up and I guess
you're assuming that the request would
be four equally sized objects right so
this and and that's a really good
strategy actually so if you if you know
or if you think that your workload is
going to have no you can't do this in
general-purpose allocators but for like
a special-purpose allocator if you know
that you're going to be asking for
objects that are all the same size like
compilers for example may maintain
abstract syntax trees and and they're
allocating nodes dynamically and those
nodes are the same size so if you can
you can exploit that by just allocating
a large chunk and then allocating all
the objects of that size out of that
chunk it's very efficient you don't even
need pointers or anything all you need
is a bit vector to tell you which chunks
are allocated in which chunks are free
and then and you also has a side effect
you'll get that contiguous that
contiguous access so if a program access
those those objects like to be part of a
linked list there was something that it
was going to traverse you could allocate
those in order and contiguously now with
with a general-purpose allocator where
you don't really know what's going to be
requested that it's
probably going to allocate also a
vector-based absolutely you could do
that you can make general assumptions
about the sort of behavior of your
programs and you know you could you
could run traces or like in the case of
malok lab you could look at the traces
but that's no that's a really good thing
you know you can't you're you can't just
like do if statements to say well if the
size is 42 and then the next size is 24
then I know it's this trace okay but you
can look at a trace and say whom there's
an interesting pattern here I'm going to
account for that pattern I'm going to
optimize for that pattern and that that
would just and that's perfectly valid
that's just like taking advantage of
your workload right that's what we do in
systems all the time yes
but can we divided up in and at the end
of the first part
Oh Oh so the question is why can't we
why can't we sort of have separate areas
of the heap for the pointers and the
payloads all right join them up with
pointers oh why not
okay so the question is why not why
can't we split up payloads and link them
together with pointers the answer is
that the applications expecting a
contiguous block you can't allocate or
can't put anything in the payload write
it all I can do all it's allowed to do
is return a contiguous block of the size
of the application requested and app
once it does that it can't touch it okay
all right good good all right so let's
look at how we'd allocate and free once
if we have this this explicit list how
we would allocate and free blocks so
allocating is pretty simple we'll have
so here's our sort of a graphic of our
free list so we have four word pointers
and backward pointers and the idea is we
want to allocate out of this middle
block so we allocate the block of the
size that we need and then we just
update the forward and back pointers of
the the previous and next blocks to
point to this new free block okay so
that's pretty simple we're just we're
updating one two three four five six six
pointers
okay now it gets it gets trickier when
we have to free because because we
require coalescing so when you free a
block that's that was previously
allocated the question is what do you do
with that free block right it wasn't in
the free list because it was an
allocated block so now that you've freed
the block where do you put it which
you've got to put it somewhere so that
the simplest thing is is this LIFO
policy so the simplest thing is just put
it at the beginning of the list so the
last block freed is the the first block
allocated if it did fit fits okay so
that's so-called LIFO now this is simple
because you're always doing the same
thing you're just putting the block at
the beginning the list and it's constant
time you're just updating a few pointers
okay but the studies suggest that the
the fragmentation can be worse than the
alternative technique which is to keep
the blocks ordered by address okay so
why not if you if you if you choose this
address ordered policy when you when you
free an allocated block you're going to
somehow figure out you're going to
somehow place that block in the list so
that the previous block begins at a
smaller address and the next block
begins at a larger address right so this
generally involves some kind of search
right you don't you're just given this
allocated block and then somehow you've
got and you know it's address and so now
you've got to somehow search the the
free list to find the you know the
proper place to insert it now I suppose
you could do better if you had some kind
of so if you could speed up that search
with some kind of balance tree that
would be one option right but then that
the the problem we always run into with
balance trees and usually one student at
lis somebody always tries to implement
malloc with some kind of balance tree
red-black tree or something and it seems
like a really good idea but you have to
realize that you're you're competing
with with other techniques specifically
segregated lists that are very fast they
have
very small constant factors and there's
even though even though ordered lists
are I think it's usually n log n to
update an order tree a binary ordered
tree the constant factors can be can be
quite large and so usually get nailed up
with the constant factors of maintaining
the tree and you don't get help that the
search time is log n but as we'll see
with segregated lists in the in the
limit has it in the limit as the number
of different size classes increases the
the search time approaches constant time
and if you if you have size classes that
cover ranges of powers of two then the
search time reduces to log time anyway
because the the size of each classes are
now logarithmic the log so you know I
would suggest on you know just doing the
simple thing usually whenever you're
you're dealt with sort of large design
space like malloc it's you're better off
doing the simple thing and then
optimizing only when you see that
there's that you need to optimize okay
so remember last time we talked about
this trick to to eliminate the boundary
tag footer and allocated blocks that's
an example of an optimization you should
defer so that wait you know wait get do
the simple thing and then try to improve
incrementally by bayi by you know this
this optimization or another
optimization so there's this this
phenomena of a lot of lot of programmers
make the mistake of what we call
premature optimization so try to think
of all the fancy things they can do and
then they put all those in at the
beginning and before they even know that
it needs to be optimized okay so the
sort of the way you want to work on this
and any any sort of complex problem like
like an alligator is to you know first
do fairly simple things and then look
and see where where the slowdowns are
your inefficiencies are and then just
sort of hit those one after the other
and optimize only for the things that
are necessary
and this is a good example of that okay
now to get to your question about
freeing freeing is tough because we
always have to do this coalescing right
because of this invariant that we can
never have to free blocks to adjacent
free blocks so let's go through each of
those four cases that we went over last
time and see how we would do it now that
we have this this this explicit free
list so here we have the root of our
free list pointing to the first block in
the free list there's an all back
pointer and then that there's a null
prief pointer and then the next next
pointer points to some unspecified block
and so we have this yellow block which
is allocated and now the application is
called free free with a pointer that
points to the beginning of this block so
what do we do well this case is pretty
simple because there's no coalescing
because both the predecessor and
successor blocks are are allocated okay
so we just this newly freed block now
becomes we're going to do a LIFO policy
so this becomes the first block in the
free list and so we update the root to
point to this this newly freed block and
we update the forward pointer of that
block to point to what used to be the
first block in the heap
now I'm going to be careful it's a
little bit confusing because we've got
sort of two notions of like previous and
next right there's the you know given
some given some block
there's the predecessor block in memory
which may or may not be allocated or
free right it may or may not be in a
free list and there's a successor block
okay so we'll use predecessor and
successor to distinguish adjacency in
memory okay and we'll use pre even next
to denote adjacency in the free list
okay so this this block is the next
block for the current block and it has
no previous block okay
all right now what about case to
remember case to the predecessor block
is free and the successor block is is
allocated and now we want to free this
what was an allocated block denoted by
yellow and we have that this this
successor this predecessor block is part
of the free list right so it has it has
previous and next blocks that are just
part of the free list and so our route
points just the first block in the list
and then eventually you get to this free
block which points to this free block
which points to this free block ok so
what we have to do then is we have to
coalesce these two these two blocks into
one big free block okay and then we have
to splice it out and stick it at the
beginning of the list ok so what that
looks like
conceptually is we we we coalesce these
two blocks now to form this one free
block and then we splice it out by
having what was the what was its
previous block now point to what used to
be the next block okay of the current
block okay so this
the pointer from this block now points
to this block okay and then the so we've
effectively spliced that that current
block out of the free list and then the
route we have the route point to that
block so that's now the new first block
of the list okay and then we have to
update what used to be the first block
in the list so now it points back to the
the newly freed coalesced block so that
cleared everybody it yes so with the
route be a global variable it could be
or it could be there's there's two ways
to do this right it could just be a
global variable or it could be a it
could be a struct that of like previous
and next pointer so sometimes it's
easier if you keep the same you know
when you're doing a linked list that the
route if you just make it the same as
all the other nodes it can simplify
things but yeah it could be a global
variable global scalar in the allocator
okay so case oh now one thing one thing
that comes to mind there is like there
is an optimization that we could do in
this case do you see when we when we
coalesce we could just lead that block
right there in the free list right we
didn't although we've adopted so the
examples I'm going to show you are
assuming a LIFO policy for insertion we
could just leave it there right that and
just don't update anything just increase
create this newly coalesce block and
then mentally we don't require in this
case we wouldn't require any free list
manipulation okay but that would be that
would be one of these optimizations
right that now case three if you recall
is the case where the the predecessor
block is allocated and the successor
block is free
the successor block is free so in this
case what we have to do is we have to
create we have to coalesce the newly
freed block with the with the successor
block and then we have to splice it out
in just the same way we did in case two
so we splice it out of the the list and
then put it at the beginning of the list
by pointing the root at it and then
updating what used to be the first block
in the list updating its back pointer
it's pre pointer to point to the this
newly coalesced block okay so it's this
is completely symmetric with the case
that we looked at before but now we no
longer have it's a little bit trickier
if we just wanted to leave this block in
the free list we'd have to update all
these pointers to point back to the
beginning of the newly created block
okay so there's so in this case there's
no performance optimization right we're
still updating the same number of
pointers whether we put it in the
beginning of the list or if we if we
splice it or if we leave it there okay
and now case four is the that's the case
where both the predecessor and successor
blocks are free so we have to apply the
same splicing technique to both the the
predecessor block and we have to we have
to create this new coalesced block and
then we have to splice we have to we
have to sort of splice it out by
updating two different sets of previous
and successor blocks okay
so when we're when we're finished with
that the this newly coalesced block now
is the first block in the in the heap
the four in the free list and we've
spliced it we splice it out from these
two different parts of the of the free
list
okay so any questions about this is this
is where you really it looks it looks
really simple to do but I guarantee you
this will be some of the hardest it's
only like 200 lines of code but some of
the hardest code you'll have to write
because you you're sort of free of the
C's types us that you have to do
everything by explicitly casting these
pointers are just in the middle of
arbitrary blocks and so it looks simple
with the diagram but you're going to
have to be really careful when you do
this in fact what I would suggest the
best suggestion I can give you is if is
to start with the implicit list
allocator that we describe in the book
which is too slow to get any credit it's
a terrible allocator but it contains all
the basic ideas and then write function
write a function called insert block and
write another function called remove
block that inserts a block into the free
list and removes a block from the free
list respectively
and if you if you write if you abstract
it like that if you use that kind of
abstraction it's pretty simple to to
convert the implicit list allocator to
an explicit list allocator okay
it'll still be too slow to get so then
that'll go from like a F allocator to a
b- allocator and then to really make a
good allocator like an a allocator you
need to use segregated lists which we'll
look at in a second okay so the explicit
lists now the the allocation time is is
linear in the number of free blocks
instead of the total size of the instead
of the total size of the heap so it's
this is much faster than that when you
have a lot of allocated blocks it's a
little more complicated because of all
the splicing business and and you do
need some extra space in your for these
these pointers which increases the
minimum block size and creates
additional
and overhead now the link list the
explicit list allocators aren't really
efficient enough to be used for sort of
general purpose real-life allocator but
they are useful in as part of a
segregated list allocator so you can
have you can have multiple free lists
each of which is an explicit list and
this it's fine for that for that
application alright so let's look at our
third method which is to create call a
segregated free list which is to have
multiple free lists with different size
classes so the the idea is that each
each class of sizes block sizes has its
own free list and that that class can be
singleton so you know maybe a one
particular size or it can be a range of
sizes so you might you might have a
number of different you know if you're
if you're if your workload consists of a
lot of these small blocks and you know
that there's going to be a lot of
requests for blocks of 1 through 4 you
can have different free lists for those
small for those small block sizes and
then after that you can go and just do
ranges of power of two so that's a
that's a common technique so here we
have a size class that covers blocks
from size 5 to 8 and then the another
size class that covers everything else
so the idea with the seg list allocators
that so given a given an array of these
free lists one each one for for some
size class if we want to allocate a
block of size n then we we go to the
appropriate free list right there's only
there's always going to be one free list
for any any n and then we search that
list just like we did before for some
size at a block size M greater than n
and then if if we find it then we place
we place the new block we place the
block in that in the block that we found
we split it and we take this the split
block and we put it into the appropriate
size class so that the block that we
split off may or may not may or may not
belong to the current size class anymore
right so we may have to move it and
insert it into a whatever the
appropriate size class is if there's no
block if we can't find a block then we
have to try the next larger size class
okay so it's possible for a given size
class they're just there might not be a
block that fits so I mean one so we just
have to we go to the next size we try
the next larger class and chances are
we'll find a block that fits there and
if we and you keep doing that until you
eventually if you can't find it you're
eventually looking in the size class
that that that covers all the rest the
last size class and if then you can't
find it then that the allocator has to
allocate more memory with by calling s
break
okay to free a block you coalesce like
before and then you place it on the
appropriate list so that's that's
straightforward and again you have this
option to try to maintain a listed
address order or just do the simple
thing and put it at the beginning of the
list okay so say egg list alligators are
that by far the best type of alligator
because they're they offer you
improvements in both performance
throughput and memory utilization so
they're faster they have higher
throughputs because the the individual
size classes are are smaller then than
just like the one giant free list but
also you're searching you're you know
that the the list that you're searching
is going to be close to the size that
you're looking for so the chances of
finding something quickly in that in
that particular size class are higher
than they are if you're just searching
on you know a single free list that
holds all different size classes okay so
search is faster so that increases
increases throughput but the big thing
about egg list alligators is that like
we talked about before they approximate
best fit without sacrificing performance
right before if we wanted to do best fit
on a single a free list we had to search
the whole free list and then choose the
block that fit the best in this case we
get we get best fit for free by by
virtue of having these size classes and
so this is you know this is this is how
you can improve your your memory
utilization yes
we just allocate and more bytes or oh
yeah yeah good question so the question
is is is is break constant time it is
but it's very expensive so it's a sis
call so it has to pass from user space
into the kernel that involves changing
contacts changing stacks so sis calls
generally you can you can count on
assist call being like several hundred
microseconds okay it's a non-trivial
overhead and so in that case you
wouldn't want you you want to amortize
the cost of the of the break by
allocating is somewhat larger chunk but
you have to be careful if you allocate
too large of a chunk then your memory
utilization goes down so it's a
trade-off it's another one of these
space-time trade-offs question so where
do you store this array of free lists so
you store it in the beginning of the
heap yeah in fact for your malloc lab we
require you to do that we don't know and
the reason is we can't that that array
affects in some small part depending on
how large that array is it affects your
memory utilization and so it should be
at the beginning of the heap
okay there's a allocators have been
around forever and that the the classic
references canuse 1973 text and there's
also this great paper which you can get
from the the books website from 1995
that does a survey of you know literate
dozens and dozens of techniques like
we're just scratching the surface here
so if you're really interested in this
stuff that that is that papers a
fascinating read and it may give you
some ideas for your free lab ok now so
far we're assuming that the application
is responsible for both allocating
storage and freeing storage but there's
a form of memory managers called
implicit memory managers that do the
freeing for you so so applications
allocate space but they never have to
worry about freeing space the system
does that automatically and so the the
idea is to identify so-called garbage so
areas of memory that can never be
referenced anymore
and then free up those blocks okay so
what's garbage well here's an example we
have a function foo that Malick's 128
bytes it stores the address in this
pointer P and then at some point when it
returns from foo this pointer is lost
forever right because P is a local
variable on the stack so once once this
function returns that the block of
memory pointed to by P is garbage can
never be referenced again because
there's no way there's no way for the
program to get get access to that and so
what an alligator will recognize at some
point that this block of memory is is
garbage and that it will free those
blocks by calling free it's the same
kind of exactly the same free call as
we've discussed but now it's it's it's
it's called by the garbage collector not
by the application
okay so you see this in all different
kinds of dynamic languages and there's
there's there's also variants available
for C but because of C's pointer
properties that the garbage collectors
for C are conservative in the sense that
there's some blocks won't be freed
there's some garbage blocks that that
won't be free because the allocator
can't determine that that they are
indeed garbage so it has to be careful
when it whenever there's a doubt it it
leaves it doesn't reclaim the the
allocated block so it gets to this
question of like how does the memory
manager know when memory can be free and
you know if we knew if somehow we knew
we could predict all of the future
requests and then if we knew that there
were no future requests access that
block then we could free it okay but we
can't predict that okay so we have to
but if there's no pointers if no
pointers exist to a particular block
then we know that it can't be accessed
okay and so that we can predict right if
there's some way we can sort of scan the
program identify or scan the memory
identify all the pointers in that memory
and and see which which blocks are
pointed to and if they're if they're not
pointed to by any pointer than then
they're garbage by definition okay so to
do this though it's it's it's difficult
so first of all the memory manager has
to be able to distinguish pointers from
non pointers which we can't do and see
right there just these they're just
these integral values right we don't
know it could be it if we see this large
integral value this large long a 8 byte
value it could be it could be pointing
to a data structure it could just be a
large integer right we don't know and
then we also all pointers have to point
to the start of a block which is not
true and see either
okay so if we have a pointer and we
identify that it's a pointer then we
know that it points it points to some
block if it points inside of a block how
do we how do we find the beginning of
that block you know how do we know how
big that block is all right so it has to
point to the beginning of the block
where the header tells us the size and
the and and and there can't be a way to
hide pointers the point that the
property of being a pointer has to be
some kind of static thing that doesn't
that can't change so that's sort of the
challenges if you're thinking about how
in the world can you implement a garbage
collector so those are some of the
challenges that that they present and
because of that this is this been a the
history of research and garbage
collectors is is old its ancient and
ongoing it's still it's still ongoing
today particularly in the context of
parallel programs and garbage collecting
programs that are running multiple
threads so there's a whole bunch of
these things that people have looked at
going all the way back to 1960 today
we'll look at we'll look at the simplest
what one of the simpler variants called
mark-and-sweep
and we won't we won't discuss the rest
but if you're interested in them there's
a pretty good book that describes that
describes these things all right so how
do we build an allocator so we start by
viewing memory as a directed graph where
each each node in the graph corresponds
to a block okay a block a heap block and
an allocated heap block and each edge is
a pointer that's contained somewhere
within that block okay a pointer to
another block and then there's a and
then there's special nodes called root
nodes that contain pointers into the
heap but they're not part of the heap so
for example pointers that are stored on
the stack pointers that are stored in
registers they point to memory locations
in the heap but
nothing nothing and but there outside of
the heap so and we call those route
notes so nothing points to them or at
least if something does point to them we
don't care about what it is okay we're
only we're only concerned about
characterizing nodes that correspond to
memory in the heap so I we say that a a
node or a block is reachable if there's
some path from a root node from a root
node to that block so and we've denoted
those by green so all of these green
blocks in the heap are reachable because
you can start at a root node and just
follow some some sequence of pointers to
get to that node okay
notes that aren't reachable are called
our garbage because there's no there's
no way to get to them from the root
nodes okay so there's no node inside the
heap that points to them and there's no
node there's no root node that points to
them so basically there's just no path
from a root node that'll get you to one
of these non reachable or garbage nodes
and since they're non reachable the
application will never be able to
reference them in the future so we can
predict with certainty that that those
are garbage and they can be freed okay
so basically after we free these then
they're removed from the graph
so now we can we can build a simple
garbage collector on top of the existing
malloc and free package right so you
implement malloc and free just like
before and then you the program calls
malloc just like before and you just you
do malloc exactly the same way until you
run out of space by whatever different
definition you want to use of running
out of space maybe you have some kind of
maximum heap size you're willing to use
or at some point the OS will just stop
giving you virtual memory when you run
out of space you you add an extra mark
bit into the header of each block so
this could be you know we have like
three or four spare bits that we can use
in the header so we can denote one of
those as the mark bit and then we are
garbage collection our garbage
collection phase when we run out of
space consists of two two different sub
phases one is the mark phase which
starts at all the roots and then and it
just traverses this from the roots it
traverses the set of of nodes that are
reachable from the root and it sets the
mark bit in each each one of those nodes
okay and then once after you finish
marking all of the all of the reachable
blocks then you sweep through the entire
heap starting at the very beginning of
the heap and you look for you look for
all allocated blocks that aren't marked
KB so they're not marked they're not
reachable in their garbage
so first so you do this so you sort of
do - you do a search from the from the
roots and then you do a sweep of the
entire heap
so let's say before before mark we have
before the marks phase we have a heap
that looks like this we have a single
root that points to this block and what
we're going to do here we're always
going to point to the payload right of
the of the block it's just a convention
that we use so we're pointing to the
beginning of the block because we know
that it's we know that the the header is
one one word behind it and so let's say
and in this case the the edges denote
pointers that are contained in the block
so they're not the previous and next
pointers that we were maintaining these
are just pointers that the application
has put into those blocks so we have so
here we have the root pointing to this
the central block and then there's an
and there's a pointer that points to
this block and there's another pointer
that points to this block and and
there's a pointer in this block that
points to this block so after we do the
mark and we search this we search these
blocks then all of the reachable blocks
have the mark bit set which is denoted
by pink and so then you see in that and
then the the blocks that aren't aren't
marked then we can free and return to
the free list
okay so let's look at the assumptions
for a simple implementation just to make
make sure this is clear so the
application calls new to get a pointer
to a block with with all the values
cleared it calls read B I to read
location I of Block B and it uses write
B IV to write a value V into location I
of Block B then each block will have a
header word which will address as B of
minus 1 and then the garbage collector
has it has functions that it uses to
identify whether a pointer whether its
input parameter is indeed a pointer okay
so there's some way to distinguish a
pointer from an on pointer and it can
get the length of some block not
including the header and it can get a
set of all of the routes so given those
given those assumptions we our
pseudocode for the mark step it takes so
this initially is a is a pointer a route
pointer okay and then we check as our
terminating condition we check to see if
that that input is indeed a pointer and
if so we return okay and then then we do
a depth-first traversal of the of the
graph so if and this so we're doing a
depth-first traversal of the graph and
this is pointer is sort of our
terminating condition for that that
depth-first traversal then we check the
mark bit and if it's set then that's
another terminating condition there's no
there's no reason to search once we find
a marked marked node we know that all of
will from that node is is marked so we
we can terminate our return and just
stop the search if it's not set then we
set the mark bit and then we look at
each word in the block
and we recursively call mark on each one
of those words now each one of those
words may or may not be a pointer right
so if it's not a pointer then mark will
just return instantly immediately if it
is a pointer then it will continue the
recursive depth first search okay so
does that make make sense it's just
familiar the familiar def first graph
traversal bit that we all know about
okay and then the sweep sweep takes a
pointer to the beginning of the heap the
first it takes a pointer to the first
block in the heap and then some a
pointer to the end of the heap and then
in a while loop then it scans the heap
each block if the mark bit is set it
clears it
if it's if it's allocated it frees it
right and then it updates and then it
gets the address of the the next block
and then just continues until the end
okay so how do we do such a thing in C
right because all of these assumptions
I've made don't hold and C right you
can't tell a pointer from an on pointer
pointers can point anywhere so what you
could do so the big issue is that if we
get some value we it even if it is a
pointer it could point right into the
middle of the block so given that so
first of all we don't know if that value
really is a pointer it could just be a
big integer but it also could be a
pointer that's pointing into some data
structure so if it is a pointer how do
we how do we find the beginning of the
block so what we could do is just assume
that every value is a pointer and then
we maintain a balance tree to keep track
of all the allocated blocks and so
whenever we encounter a particular value
we would search that binary tree to see
if it if assuming it is a pointer if it
falls within the the beginning and end
of some allocated block okay if if that
condition is true then we assume that
it's pointing that that's a pointer to
an allocated block and we assume that
that block is reachable now the reason
it's conservative is because it really
may not be a pointer it might be this
integer and we'll we'll assume it's a
pointer and assume that the block that
it purportedly points to is is allocated
but it may in fact be not be a pointer
and the block that it points to is
garbage right so what with this with
this scheme we would leave some some non
non reachable blocks we will indicate
that some non reachable blocks are are
really reachable
okay so so once now that we've got this
great tool to dynamically allocate
memory we can use it in our programs and
shoot ourselves in the foot in all
different kinds of ways okay so I'm
going to I'm going to try to help help
you out here by identifying some of the
perils and pitfalls that that we can run
into with with with memory related
operations or operations on memory and
opera errors errors involving memory are
the worst the worst kinds of bugs to try
to find out and the reason is that
they're distant in both space and time
so let's say you write to the wrong
memory location and corrupt some data
structure the right doesn't elicit any
error you only find out about that illy
that erroneous right when you try to
reference that data structure or that
particular part of the data structure
which may be in a part of the code
that's way far away from the right that
caused the problem both in space you
know in distance you know lines of code
it could be a completely different
function and a completely different
module but also in time it may not you
know you may do the right and then eons
later other some read and it fails right
so this is a fundamental thing that
makes memory related bugs just so nasty
and another big thing another thing that
makes them hard to deal with is people's
misunderstanding and misuse of pointers
right so usually an erroneous right is
some is some either a misunderstanding
of pointers or an improperly initialized
pointer so it all boils down to these
pointers okay and so I'm going to show
you how to understand pointers okay for
the first time in your lives
I don't know about you but when I
learned C I learned about pointers
I just knew about what a few different
types of pointers were by and I did it
by pattern matching so I knew that int
star P was a pointer to an int I knew
that int star star P was was an array
I knew that int star P open bracket
closed bracket was also an array just a
different way to express that array so I
had a small handful of pointers types
that I could deal with but I had no
underlying understanding of what that
meant or anything was just pure pattern
matching and I'll bet you that's the way
you do it too all right but that's all
going to change today
all right so in order to really
understand pointers you need to
understand the precedence of various
operators in C because the pointer types
are declared using these operators and
so my copy of K and R is it has a
dog-eared at page 53 this table comes
from page 53 of knr and you should have
a paper clip or have that folded over
for reference now the thing to notice is
that function and array and then and
these struct these various struct
operators have the highest priority
highest precedence and that and then
that's followed by unary operators so
the star this is the dereference
operator and then the the address of
operator the they fall right below the
the highest the highest precedence
operators and then the binary versions
of operators you know that you use in
arithmetic operations are below those
okay so just remember that function and
array is higher than star okay
that too deep the dereference now the
great thing about pointers although they
always seem really complicated is that
there's there's an algorithm for it for
there's an algorithm for constructing an
English sentence that explains exactly
what what that pointer what that
definition of the pointer means okay and
if you're interested it's in the KN are
in Section 5.1 - but I'll I'll explain
it to you now now I don't know I don't
know how much in this class you're going
to remember okay but I guarantee you're
going to remember this as the day you
finally understood pointers okay so all
right so here's how it works
you always start it the this is a
definition of a pointer some kind you
always start with the variable name
and then you use your precedence then
you look for operators on either side of
that variable name and you choose the
one that has the highest precedence okay
so we start with the variable so we say
P is a then we look to the left and the
right there's nothing to the right but
there's a there's a pointer symbol to
the left so we say P is a pointer and
there's nothing more and then we always
end up with the the type of thing that
it points that so P is a pointer to an
int
right so P is P as a pointer to some to
some integer in memory okay so we all
know that one that's pretty easy okay
what about the next one you've probably
seen something like this
some programs declare our V using this
notation and so this you can have an
optional size or not so so we always
start out we say P is a well now in this
case there's operators to the left and
the right
remember the array operator has higher
precedence than the the the
dereferencing operator the pointer
operators so we say so P is an array 13
array of size 13 of so there's nothing
more so we go to the left of pointers so
P is an array 13 of pointers to ends
so P is an array of 13 pointers each of
which points to an int right in this
case P is just the name of the array so
by default P P is a is equivalent is the
address of the array when you reference
an array name you're you're you're
addressing your ax dressing the address
of the first element okay how about the
next one here we're being if we put
parentheses around things then we can be
explicit okay and this is a good
practice so here we're saying P and we
have to look at this one first because
of the parentheses so P is an array
thirteen of pointers to ents so that's
the same thing and here we're just being
more explicit now what about star star P
so P is a pointer to a pointer to an int
okay so this is a different type of
array
so P is a pointer to a pointer to an int
okay and and typically so this is
another way to do arrays so the same way
the char star points to a string this
this can point it points to it points to
a pointer but then you can index on that
each one of those then points
corresponds to a pointer
whoops okay here's another one now P
because and because of the parentheses
we have to go left so P is a pointer to
an array thirteen of its okay so P is an
appointee to an array of 13 inch
right now what about this one f is a
function or RF is it a function or a
pointer F is a function right because of
the precedence so f is if f is a
function returning pointer to int okay
so if we go if we go P equal F then that
returns that initialized P to point to
some int
all right and I'm going to do this one
let's jump down in the interest of time
totally ridiculous case just so you can
see that this algorithm works
all right so X is an array of pointers
to functions returning pointers to an
array five events and if you ever use
anything like that in your code shame on
you
all right so there you go so that's now
you know now you understand pointers
simple as can be and all you need is
page 53 of knr is a handy reference all
right so let's we'll take the last five
minutes and I'll show you some some of
the ways you can trip yourself up when
you're accessing memory
okay so first is the classic scanf bug
you probably you've probably all done
this where you forget to pass it the
address of a variable instead you pass
it the address so scanf doesn't know
where to put the you know put the put
the data
okay another another common mistake is
to read uninitialized memory so suit you
can't really assume that your heap data
is initialized to 0 so here we're we're
Malachy an array of an inch and then
we're going through and we're doing
we're updating this vector this Y vector
we're reading Y I
we're taking Y with y I equal Y I plus a
IJ times XJ okay so we're using we're
assuming that Y that malloc returns
memory that's all zeros so that'll get
you
it's also easy to allocate the wrong
sized object so here we want to create
an array of n pointers of n pointers to
int okay and then for each one we want
to allocate M ends all right so this
work we're creating a two-dimensional
array and can you see the mistake which
which line is buggy this one this one or
this one the first one right because we
really want size event star right so
we're we're erroneous incorrectly
assuming that intz are the same sizes as
pointers this is a classic on this this
assumption is true for 32-bit code intz
and pointers are the same size but it's
not true for 64-bit and so this is why
when you when you port when people port
32-bit code to 64-bit machine a lot of
times it breaks because they have this
assumption okay another way you it's
easy to overwrite memory so here we're
creating correctly creating this array
but then when we create each of the each
of the sub arrays instead of I less than
or equal to n we're actually we only
created n of these things but we're
traversing n plus 1 because of this less
than or equal so this is a classic off
by one bug ok another another problem
you saw it with the code injection
attacks from your attack lab not
checking the the size of a buffer so get
get ass is a classic example of this so
that will get you into trouble another
another classic mistake is
misunderstanding pointer arithmetic all
right so if you increment a pointer then
it point it's incremented by the size of
the object that pointer points to right
so if you increment an int star by one
it actually increments it by four
because that's the size of an int
he's got that's a really important
distinction and so people will often so
here it's assuming that incrementing so
P is a pointer and the programmer here
assumed that he wants to increment the
pointer to sort of traverse it an array
so he he doesn't understand pointer
arithmetic and so to get to the next in
increments P by size event okay this
will really increment it by sixteen not
by four okay overriding memory that's a
really nasty one and a lot of times this
can happen if you don't understand the
precedence of the of the operators that
you're working with so this is a heap
not not too kind of heap we've been
talking about but oh the heap data
structure and this is a this is a
function to delete from a heap and this
actually is from my own code I have to
admit and so I wanted to leave I want to
delete in it an element I want to delete
the first element of the heap right and
then I want to reify it okay so I and
then I want to return I want to return
that so I I get the first element the
heap I that the size of the heap or I
take the the last element and make that
the first element and and now I want to
decrease the size of the heap because
this delete operation will will delete
the heap size by one so notice here we
passed size n as a pointer and when this
when this function terminate when this
function return size should be updated
dated size as a pointer the value that
it points to you should be decremented
okay that's our intent and we do it
right here with the size minus minus
star so what we want to do is we want to
dereference size and then decrement that
value but because the unary minus minus
has higher of precedence than then the
dereference what we're really doing is
we're decrementing the pointer and then
dereferencing the value that's one word
less than our size variable all right so
these are nasty and it would have been
much cleaner if I had just put
parentheses around like I intended just
parentheses star sized parentheses
alright another another way you can mess
up is referencing forgetting the local
variables disappear so if you have a
function that returns an address of a
local variable no good okay no good at
all
it might be okay for a while until
somebody another function reuses that
space that could be a return address it
could be another another functions local
variable another terrible mistake this
is a really bad one is freeing a block
multiple time now you know from from
your understanding now of malloc that
free actually writes to the heap right
it's coalescing it's changing pointers
it's changing size block sizes so if you
free a block that's already been freed
terrible things will happen another
thing you can do wrong is to reference a
block you forget that you freed a block
and then you reference it so here we
free of this block X and then we're
referencing it here another another big
problem is memory leaks so failing to
free block so allocating some block in a
function and then returning that block
will stay there forever right because
it's garbage
okay so there's a there's a number of
ways to deal with memory bugs gdb is
sometimes good at least it'll tell you
where a seg fault occurs then you got to
track down what the right that sort of
caused that seg fault the best thing you
can do but gdb falls down whenever
you're doing manipulation of complex
data structures
it's just simple sort of looking one
instruction at a time what you really
need to do is identify any complex data
structure like a heap for example is
identify invariance for that structure
that that data structure should always
maintain and then you write a function
that iterates over that structure that
data structure and checks that all those
they're invariants are true so for
example in it and in allocator one of
the invariance is that there should be
no that there should never be two
contiguous free blocks right so your
your consistency checker should go
through the heap and make sure there's
no no contiguous free blocks or another
invariant is that every free block
should be in a free list somewhere right
so you would you would you would up your
consistency checker would scan the heap
count the number of free blocks and then
scan the free list and make sure that
the number of blocks in the free list is
the same as the number of free blocks
okay so this idea of a consistency
checker is something you'll use in your
malloc lamp but it's something it's also
something you should you should use
whenever you're updating any kind of
complex data structure and the and you
know about valgrind but the great thing
about these heap checkers ok I'm
passionate about heap checkers or
consistency checkers the really powerful
thing about them is you write them to
run silently they don't print anything
unless they find that a violation of the
invariance if you write your consistency
checker like this then you can use it
like a probe so your program crashes so
you do it you use this heap checker to
do a binary search to isolate the cause
so you know you put your you put your
heap checker here everything is ok and
then later the program crash
so now you stick the heap checker here
and now it crash the heap checker
detects an in violation so you know that
the problem is somewhere here and you
can just keep narrowing it down so it's
just like a probe surgical probe that
you can use to to track down bugs and so
that's if you do this like it's I don't
know how anybody debugs malik without
this kind of tool okay so that's it for
today have a good weekend we'll see you
on Tuesday