good afternoon everyone
so I apologize I have to I'm going to sit mostly through this lecture
I managed to do something to my knee yesterday
and I'm having trouble moving around very much
but today what we're going to talk about is input/output
what it looks like from the programmers perspective
and this is a you've already learned sort of a lot of the standard UNIX libraries for like printf and scanf
and those routines and
we'll talk about them a little but what
will first talk about is actually lower
level IO stuff that is directly
interfacing to the operating system and
this is what you're going to need to
learn about apart ly some of this
material you're going to need for the
next web that comes out at midnight
tonight the shell lab and you'll need to
also you'll be revisiting this at
several other labs along the course
including the final web the the web
proxy web so this is sort of where we're
we're really digging down deeply into
this type of programming you do if
you're writing system software things
that are very just barely above the
operating system level and I know for
myself
learning this material I actually
learned this material from 213 my
co-author Dave o Halloran is the one who
knew this stuff already
he wrote that part of the book I learned
it by reading the book just like you are
but I found it actually very useful to
know in a variety of different other
situations I've been in in the meantime
this is quite a few years ago and so I
think it's worth understanding and I'll
also mention this kind of material
usually is taught you don't really see
it covered in most books except for ones
that are really oriented toward system
programmers and are fairly arcane or you
try and learn it by reading man pages
and that's a fairly cryptic way to try
and understand
sort of a set of abstractions provided
by an API so I hope you'll find this
useful
so what we'll talk about then is that
what I mentioned this low-level i/o that
I supported by UNIX and other related
operating systems and then a package
called Rio which stands to robust IO and
you will actually not be using this
package until the last lab for the
course the proxy lab at which time
you'll use it a lot but it's worth
looking at and partly it's in the book
it's well documented in the book and if
you really want to understand how
software works or a system works the
best thing you can do is if you if it
there's good quality source code to look
at and study you can learn a lot from
doing that and I really recommend for
that chapter in the book that you go
ahead and study all of the code that
makes up Rio it's not a huge amount and
just get an appreciation for the
subtleties involved in how you deal with
errors how you deal with exceptional
conditions and things like that and then
we'll talk some about how files are
represented the sort of various data
structures behind files how they support
standard i/o and i/o redirection in UNIX
and we'll also talk about the so-called
buffered i/o the i/o that you're more
familiar with and see when you use
printf and scanf so UNIX actually has a
much simpler and more unified view of
i/o than any other operating system and
it's one of the nice design features of
it is that a lot of abstractions are
built into the notion of a file and a
file is really just a sequence of bytes
and in UNIX does not distinguish between
different classes of files unlike say
Windows or earlier versions the
Macintosh operating system it just
thanks to them as bytes and the
operating system level has essentially
no understanding of a more detailed
structure inside of a file
and one of the things it does is a file
is normally originally thought of is
something that stored on say a disk
drive or some other external storage
device and that you open you read it or
write it you close it those sort of
standard operations but UNIX also use
the notion of a file to represent many
other different things including for
example the devices that are the i/o
devices that are connected to a
particular machine the tty stands for
teletype which is a antique terminology
for how people used to actually
interface typewriters to computers the
other thing that our viewed as like
files are the network connections what
are known as sockets and when you do
communication over the Internet you do
it by you send a message by writing to a
socket and you accept incoming
communication by reading from a socket
and so the same low-level API is the
same whether you're reading or writing
files on your disk drive or sending
packets over the Internet
so the the core operations then
associated with files of course are
opening and closing them and reading and
writing them the other sort of attribute
that's associated with most but not all
files is what's called the file position
so if again if you imagine when you're
reading from a file you don't want to
always start at the beginning every time
you do a read you you read some data and
then you read some more data and so
that's a tracked by a file position
which is just a counter that says how
many bytes has have been written written
read from this file so far so that I
know where to go and you can actually
even alter that value with a various
classes operation called seeking which
is just a way of changing the file
pointer the position pointer now that
doesn't work too well if your input is a
terminal where you can't move you can't
sort of back up and have a recover data
that was presented to it earlier or jump
ahead and start accepting data that
hasn't been typed yet so there's some
kinds of files have a file position and
seeking and others don't
similar to a network socket you can't
jump a socket for it in time you can
only read or write the particular
packets as they come in but in general
think of it then is the file position as
part of the the data associated with an
open file that tells me how far along in
this file have I read or written and
then again the files are because there's
all these different things they're sort
of unified in this file abstraction but
obviously these differences and
different attributes to them and so
there's sort of many different
categories and subcategories but the
ones we'll think about our a regular
files just think of things that are on a
disk drive directories which is a
directory is considered a type of file
meaning the data that's in there is just
enough as a file but of course it's
special kind of file and that it
actually does have an interpretation
that entries in that file describe the
locations and attributes of other files
and then as I mentioned the term socket
is a connection to a network and it's
both for sending and for receiving
messages over the network there's other
files that we won't really talk about
for example when you pipe when you from
one application to another that's both
the output of the first program and the
input of the second are special types of
files called pipes and they're handled
by writing is putting something into the
pipe and reading is to take something
out of that pipe a similar something
called a symbolic link which is just a
way that you can have multiple names for
a file and pointers to a file that
aren't really without having to make
separate copies of a file and then other
special types of devices so we won't
really will only consider for the first
three types of files and in fact for
today mostly the first two so the idea
of a file then is it just contains
arbitrary data and the operating system
really for regular file doesn't try to
get into the details of what's inside
that file and there's some class of
applications that will distinguish
between a text file and a binary file
not really at the operating system level
but more higher levels and the main
difference with that is it a text file
should only have the standard characters
of ASCII or another class would be
various encoding that allow you to do in
coatings of non-english alphabets and
binary files would be things like an
image or
a actual object code or a video or audio
file or something that it's the you're
within that code there's a sequence of
bytes that are encoding numbers in some
form directly and then the main thing
about a text file is that there's
certain functions that distinguish a
newline character meaning the end of it
line of text and you already learned
about that character it's that got the
code of a 0a as a bytecode and that
became one of the forbidden codes of
your attacks because it would be
interpreted as a newline by the function
get ass just to mention that and this is
one place when you're transferring files
between say a Windows machine and a
Linux or a Mac one of the things if it's
a text file that has to be changed is
that two classes of systems have
different ways of interpreting of
encoding when is the end of a line and
in a Linux or Mac file it's just uh this
character code a which stands for line
feed whereas the windows files finish
with a two character end of line a
carriage return in line feed and I show
you this picture of an object that
you've probably only seen in museums but
it's a typewriter and just to tell you
what the heck is a carriage return and
what's the line feed I thought you might
like to in case you've never actually
used an old-fashioned typewriter
basically at the end of it on the left
hand side of a typewriter is this bar
and when you start typing along I'll the
paid the the this roller with your page
on it sinks along and it comes to the
end and then you want to get back to the
beginning of the next line so you want
to both do the carriage return which is
this thing shove it to the right
and you want to do a line feed you want
the roller on it to go down to the next
line so there's a knob here that you can
twist by hand but in general what you do
is you type along and then you go slam
like that and this lever both pushes the
thing back and it rotates the the roller
by one lines worth and so carriage
return line feed is where that actually
comes from in case you wonder and then a
directory as I mentioned it's it's
stored as a file but it's a file that
the operating system at least the file
system part of the operating system
actually interprets in very specific
ways and as you know within every
directory there's two special files dot
and dot dot referring to the local file
and its parent in the tree structure and
so in in most systems systems that I
know of there's a sort of hierarchical
organization to the files we're not
going to talk much about file systems
but there's a hierarchical organization
and that's maintained as a series of
files each being the directory and the
directory then is a pointer to its
subdirectory which again are files and
so what's referred to in UNIX
terminology and most other operating
systems what's known as a path name is a
way to navigate through this hierarchy
of files and identify one particular one
and so that all comes to say that the
low-level UNIX operations that use to
implement this are to open a file to
read it and write it and to close it and
those literally those are the names of
the functions so the open function then
you give a path name and remember
pathnames can be absolute meaning that
they start with a slash and they go all
the way down the hair
oki they can be relative to a particular
whatever your current directory is where
and they can also be relative to a user
if you use the tilde slash or tilde L
then that sort of a shortcut in this
path name to get to particular users so
a path name can be any of those forms
when you open it it just has to be some
way that just like you specify in other
places that you tell where this
particular file is you're trying to open
and so it's given a path name and then
it's given a integer code that says what
do you want to do when you open this
file in what form do you want to open it
and that's specified by a series of
constants that are already predefined
when you include the propria trials and
you can and those actually get bitwise
each of those is a one bit flag in a
some power of two position or it's a
position one bit in a field somewhere
and so you can logically or those
together if you want multiple
combinations so for example I can say
read-only I can say read and write I can
say append meaning don't if I'm opening
it to write don't begin it the don't
start writing at the beginning start
writing it wherever the end of the file
is no so all those can be done and this
is described in the book by using the
right set of names of constants and
oaring them together and that will
return something that's called a file
descriptor and that's a very important
idea that and one of the reasons why
we're talking about this today this is
going to be very important in your lab
is the notion of a file descriptor which
is just a small integer that lists which
particular one of the open files that's
being used by this particular program
are you referring to and so it's a small
number because these are a sign
sequentially when you begin your program
and you run and you're in fact limited
on most machines to some some bounded
number of open files you're allowed to
have at any time in fact if you go to
let's see on if you're on a machine and
you type in limits limit
you'll see there that entry called
descriptors 10:24 says that you can't
have more than 1024 files open at any
given time and in fact if you've got a
thousand 24 files open it's a chance
you're doing something really seriously
wrong
being that you haven't been closing the
files you should be closing
and all the system calls including these
always have return code and the return
codes very sometimes a negative number
is an error sometimes a zero is an error
now they're all different and all
confusing and all inscrutable so you
have to look at the documentation for
every single one of those functions and
one of the the rules we're going to
hammer away at in this course is every
time you make a system call you should
check the return code to see if there's
an error and then do some appropriate
way of handling the error that's just a
practice it's a pain in the butt it
makes your code look like a rat's nest
of conditionals you really would rather
not because often there's an error you
deciding what you're going to do when
there's an error is harder than then
figuring just ignoring it all together
and so there's a lot of code out there
where people just cross their fingers
and hope there's never errors in their
system calls but we're going to really
push on you hard to say every time you
make a system call check the return code
and do something if it's not right and
so the open will return a number so that
it's an int that it returns but if it's
a negative number that means it couldn't
open the the file for example the file
doesn't exist or you're trying to open
it in a mode that you're not authorized
to open it in so there's three
particular file descriptors associated
with every single process that runs one
is standard input the other standard
output the third is standard error and
they always have a file descriptor
number zero one and two dandumb so that
you shouldn't really refer to them by
their file descriptor numbers even
though you actually can reliably depend
on those values same way if you want to
close a file you also open you see you
give a path name and a one bit a one
integer field that gives these flags
say something about the modes in which
you want to open it to close a file you
just say close and you give the file
descriptor number not the name of the
file and it returns a return code too so
you might say now why in the world could
you ever get an error closing a file if
it's open and the answers that actually
can happen in particular we'll see when
we have multi-threaded programs where
it's possible to have to essentially two
programs running at the same time
sharing their data structures and
interacting with each other sharing
their memory it's a very important kind
of programming and one that you can
really make bad horrible mistakes in and
one of the bad horrible mistakes is if
you try to close a file that's already
been closed
it'll be an error and that can happen if
there's two different parts of your
program running and each of them tries
to close the file so in the book and in
the in this code you'll see we
introduced some error handling routines
one of which is called P error and all
it does is print some not whatever
message you want to print and then it
exits the program or no I guess it
doesn't that I'll mention in a little
while it just prints an error message
but the point is even even something as
mundane as closing a file you should be
checking the return code okay so this is
the function that reads
at this low level is called read and
it's given a file descriptor
you provided a pointer to a buffer
that's you you've had to allocate either
aesthetically or via malloc and you also
specify how long that buffer is so that
it can't overflow that buffer and read
just means read as many bytes as you
feel like but no more than the number I
tell you to
which sounds like a weird statement what
do you mean what you feel like well it
has to read at least one byte so if for
example it's a standard input it will
hang there and wait until actually with
standard input it will wait until you've
typed in a string and hit the return and
it will then read at least some fraction
of that into the program if it's a
network connection again the read won't
just wait it will hang until something
arrives on that particular network
connection and then read in some number
of bytes that have been sent to it and
I'm being vague by saying some number
because the truth is it there's no
guarantee it will read any fixed number
of bytes it will read at least one and
it won't read any more than that buffer
is but the number between that might be
variable and so when it reads less than
that the number of maximum number bytes
you specify that it's called a short
read and that Canon does happen and you
have to write your code expecting it and
we'll talk about that a little bit
oh and so again and by Reed returns in a
signed number actually of data type s
size T like SS ize underscore T which is
typically a long int so a potentially
negative number in it that that number
is if it says zero it means that it's
hid its detected and into file that
you've run to the end of the stored file
that the network connection has been
closed or something has happened if it's
positive then that's the number of bytes
that were read and if it's negative it's
an error code
so as I mentioned if it if it reads
fewer than the number of bytes you
specify that's referred to as a short
count and I'll talk about why that would
occur writing is sort of the same idea
that you provide a file descriptor you
provide a buffer where the the data that
you want to write out is stored and you
give up how many bytes long do you want
your right to be and it will write a sum
number of bytes to the output at least
one and no more than n bytes but it
might not be all of them which is kind
of weird because you said I want to
write this I want to send it to a file I
want to send it over the Internet but it
can potentially not send them all and
well we'll talk about that a little bit
so again that's called a short write and
simile it will return the number of
bytes that were written and so if it's
less than zero that's an error code so
just to give you a really simple example
of this in action this code does what
you call echoing meaning that you type
in something and it will print it out
and it does it in the most mundane way
possible by reading specifying a single
byte reads and single byte writes so you
remember I told you read well read at
least one byte but no more than the
number you've told it so when you give
it one it means it will read exactly one
byte and similarly with right if you say
right one byte that's all and so this is
really really bad code in the sense that
called to read or to write the system
level call is a relatively expensive
call it means kicking your whole
operation up to the operating system
doing what's called a context switch
meaning it will go into the kernel of
the system invoke operating system
functions do whatever the reader right
tells it to do come back out
switch back to your job and that will
typically take maybe 20,000 to 40,000
clock cycles which you know a clock
cycle nowadays is less than a nanosecond
so you say yeah it's a you're talking
maybe 10 microseconds what's the big
deal there but that'll add up if you
start sending long files out over you
know millions of bytes if you start
sending them a one byte at a time you'll
spend most of that time sitting in the
operating system going going crazy so
this is not a good idea but it does work
and that's actually a easy mistake you
can make as a programmer is to not use
it is to use as low level writing and
reading and the program will function
fine it's just it will be really really
slow but just to give you a demo of this
idea of our calls to the operating
system there's a pretty cool
so this program and this is on the web
linked off the webpage the code for this
lecture so this one called
CPE standard in meaning copy standard
input is just the code I showed you and
so if you type something it will just
echo it back so it's reading in so it
looks to you and to me like it up
reading on line of text and then echoing
it back but what it's actually doing is
again the interface to the terminal is
one that it doesn't actually wake up
this code until it gets a complete line
but it's actually just printing these
characters back one one character at a
time and I can demo that by there's a
pretty interesting facility called
tracing s trace then what s chase will
do if you give it the name of a program
is it will detect every every system
call that you make every basically call
to the operating system functions that
you make when you run a program and it
will generally spew out this huge amount
of inscrutable stuff that you don't
really want to see I'll just show you
this oh it's telling you logging every
single call and it's usually way too
much stuff so the more useful way to do
this is to give it an argument that says
I only want to watch some limited class
of functions of when this is running and
so what I just want our calls to the
right the low level output right and
you'll see that what happens then is
this string i typed in turned into a
series of 1 byte rights calls to the low
level right function
and of course some way I could show you
the reads and writes let's try that
and it's all confused because I'm I'm
measuring this comes out on standard
error but on the terminal it's sort of
interleaving standard error and standard
out so it's kind of messy to look at but
again you can see that it's taking my
characters and it's reading 1 and
writing 1 in this loop so let's see
control D to get out of it
back to the code
so what's this short count business why
would that occur well there's a couple
ones as I mentioned if you counter an
end-of-file you're not going to read in
however many bytes you are given for the
buffer if you are reading text lines
from a terminal the terminal
handler will just send a wine it's worth
at a time with the newline character
terminating it if you're reading or
writing a network packet the way network
packets work is that or messages if you
have a big long message it's broken into
smaller chunks typically about a
thousand bytes or so question if you are
trying to read from an end-of-file we
turn 0 um is that a short count it's a
really short count yes but it's not a
negative yes so as it says here if you
encounter an inter file it will actually
there's two things actually it's a
really good question if you're like near
the end of a file you have a hundred
bytes left and you say read 200 your
first call to read will come back and
get 100 character it would say 100 and
it will get that number and then you
call again the second time and it will
return zero and so that's how you
actually detect the the true end of file
as opposed to you know some other reason
you might have gotten a short count is
if that you actually get a read of 0 the
only case you'll get at 4 is an end of
file so that's a good question Thanks so
again if over the Internet
typically packets are round a thousand
bytes it's actually depends on what
where it's gone through what layers in
the protocols it's gone through but 1500
bytes is actually the the standard what
they call minimum transmission unit so
if you have a big long file we'll come
back in in blocks like that and if
you're trying to read into a larger
buffer
it will typically come back in chunks
question no in other words you and again
if you're writing code you shouldn't
expect any number particularly it will
be dependent on the implementation
no because I'm only I'm only reading or
writing one character at a time right so
I guess you're asking what if I like
spent a week
typing characters in a really long
string and hit return how to know if you
try it let me know the answer but it
won't cause an error but that part
believe me they've really gone through
that code a lot of times and and gotten
rid of all those lurking buffer overflow
vulnerabilities in the code but will let
you do it I don't actually know but
within the you should write your code
again expecting short counts as a
possibility and by the way that's one of
the the headaches of using this
low-level i/o is is dealing with short
counts is not is often sort of a
nuisance of an application level so you
don't you usually package this up this
kind of low-level file i/o into other
libraries that you're calling it's only
where are we demonstrating this is the
sort of lowest level in the stack and
writing also can give you a short count
for example if you're sending packets
over a network it will only send as many
as is that packet can hold and then
return back to you and you have to keep
pumping them out to send the different
packets and so usually when you write
code that uses this goal of while you
have to anticipate these short counts so
professor O'Halloran wrote a package
called REO and you'll for now we'll just
talk about what this package is this is
a package that you're really going to
want to use for the final web for the
course and so for right now it's more of
a high-level here's an example of code
that uses low-level IO and packages up
in a way that makes it a little bit more
palatable so Rio provides actually a
number of different two different well
actually three
two different levels of of interface to
the file this file IO the lowest one is
basically just a fairly small wrapper
around the the existing the the IO the
reads and writes you saw that will
handle the short count issue and so when
you say with Rio if you make a call to
the read end function and you say some
number of bytes then that function will
not return until it's read that number
of bytes so better be careful that that
that many bytes are there if it's a
network socket or a file well because it
will flag an error message if it's what
will actually hang up if it's a network
connection waiting to read the bytes or
return an error if it hits a none to
file what it's not expecting and
similarly with write n is sort of a
wrapper around the write function that
we'll deal with just loop until the
short counts are taken care of and then
there is a another class of of i/o
that's called buffered i/o and this is
what you really want to use in practice
and what you mostly use with the
standard UNIX IO at functions is it you
want to within the the user code build
up a little buffer of of bytes that have
either been read in but not yet consumed
by the application program or you
accumulate some number of bytes in your
program before it's actually shoved out
into the file or out onto the network
and there's two versions of that one is
a text oriented wine oriented i/o and
the other is just a byte oriented i/o
so let's go through the what the
functions are and actually look at the
code for them so as I mentioned the ones
called read and write n are just very
thin they have the same general
semantics as the read and write but they
deal with the short count issue
so let's actually take a look at read n
so again read n is given a file
descriptor a destination buffer and a
indication of how many characters how
many bytes it's supposed to read and
it's supposed to it's supposed to meet a
return I guess it will return either a
negative number if there's an error 0 if
it's at an end of file or the number of
bytes read so I guess I was a little bit
I should have been more careful if it
hits an end of file partway through it
will return a short count but that's the
only case it won't return a short count
if if there really it could have read
more bytes so the main loop here you see
is it keeps calling read over and over
again until it's happy ah one way it can
be happy as if it's read as many bytes
as it was supposed to write read in the
first place
the other is that if it hits an error
code and you'll notice that
oh and that there's some subtlety of
tracking which type of error that is but
in general the common cases it will
return the negative number indicating an
error if it if the number read is zero
then that indicated an into file and so
what it will return is as many bytes as
it's read so return the short count and
here it's just saying okay I've read
this number of bytes and increment and
decrement the right values so the point
is it will keep looping keep doing reads
until it either gets the number of bytes
it should it hits an error or it
encounters an end-of-file and you'll see
it has its checking for all these
different error conditions for every
call it makes so this code by the way is
sort of typical that it looks a little
messy when you first look at it but if
you sort of study it all makes sense um
so now let's talk about buffered i/o and
what buffered i/o is and this is a very
important concept so it's part of the
reason we want to show you the code for
it so the idea of buffered i/o is that
but there's a buffer meaning just an
array of byte character's array of bytes
they're allocated and associated with
this particular file and the program if
it's on to read what it will do is it
will fill up this buffer if it will give
a read with a much larger number with a
large number basically the size of the
actual how much memory you've allocated
for this buffer and the system will fill
that up with up to that number of
characters and then when the user
program wants to now look at this
get some bytes it will first check do I
already have some in the buffer that
haven't been read yet and if so I'll
just return those ah and if not then
I'll refill the buffer so the idea of it
is instead of every time going to the
operating system and asking for one
character small number of characters the
called the operating system says give me
pretty much as many characters as you've
got up to some limit and then I'll just
go away and what the application program
I sort of pull these out a couple bytes
at a time but I won't bug the operating
system to do it I being the real
function and the way it does it is by
just keeping a pointer of that indicates
what part of the the bytes that I've
already brought in from the operating
system call
but the haven't been supplied yet to the
application program and so in this sort
of larger picture of things if you
imagine you're you're walking through a
file at any given point in time this
buffer will represent some a range of in
that file where the green is the stuff
that's already been read by the
application program the pink is the
stuff that's been read but from the
operating system out of
file but not yet read by the application
program and the way this is implemented
once you think about it it's not too
hard to do is it associated with every
file connection then is a file
descriptor account that tells you how
many bytes there are that have not been
read yet a a pointer to where this this
changeover is and then the actual
storage of the the buffer itself the
characters allocated the bytes allocated
to the buffer itself and so here's an
example then of of using Rio to do this
echo that you first read online and
reading a line means it will look for
and stop at a line feed character and
writing it back out and again if you do
the demo
of this code
it's a little again you get let me just
trace rights cuz it's a little hard to
see the reeds are hard to figure out
with
so you'll see that it read the whole
line and now it's done
to add the operating system level it's
written just one chunks worth one call
to the operating systems write function
instead of a byte by byte
okay so again I'm not going to go
through all the code but it's actually
worth your while to do this and by the
way I've actually done some applications
where I took the real code I want to add
some features to it but it's a very
useful starting point to be able to
build your own customized routines okay
so let's talk about some other parts of
files one is that associated with a file
is what they call metadata so the data
are the actual contents of the file
actual bytes inside that file but
there's a whole bunch of other stuff
that's associated with the file
information about what type of file it
is what protection read/write/execute
protections it has some information
about the ownership of that file what
type it is and also the times associated
with it when was it created when was it
last accessed in when was the West
notified so that's known as a metadata
and every a file has that kind of
information associated with it and you
can actually and it's in a data
structure called a step data structure
and you can if you want to write code
that then sort of probes the directory
structure of a of a file system you can
make a call to the stat function and
it's given the the path name of the file
you want to stat and then a a pointer to
it one of these step data structures and
then that our data structure will get
filled in by the information for this
particular file and then you can test
various attributes about that file and
see basically get the information that
that's stored here and there's all these
nasty compile time constants that you
use or macros that use to
look at and examine these these metadata
so here's an example I will do it but
it's a function called stat check it's
in the same directory and so if you
check some file or typically say well
it's a regular file and yes you're
allowed to read it but now if I a to
call chmod to eliminate set all the
protections to zero it'll say no you
can't read it now and so again that's
just making use of this data here so now
this is the part that gets a lot more
tricky is how our files how are all this
information about file is actually
represented by the programs question yes
stat gist
I'll tell you one way you can find out
what step does if you say man 2 step
you'll get more than you want to know so
in general you know if you say man's
debt it'll give a unix of command that
you can use to step a file so I can say
stat top and it will print out some
information about a file in this case my
local directory let's see I can stat any
file here and it will print out some
some cryptic information about it but if
you say man 2 stat the UNIX man pages
are divided into different categories
and things that our system calls UNIX
system library calls are typically in
section 2 of the man pages and so that
will return information about it
but the main point of it is stat is then
a function that you call where you give
it a path name and a pointer to a buffer
that you want it and it will then fill
in the contents the buffer with the
information about that particular file
and the form that it fills it in is one
of these data structures called a struct
step and that's pretty typical of a lot
of these functions is that they have
some predefined struct and if you want
to get the if you want to get
information you pat you allocate one of
those struts you pass a pointer to it
and then the library function will fill
in the details does that make sense
okay so now let's look at some of the
internal data structures that the
operating system maintains regarding the
files associated with a program and this
is a source of really nasty exam
problems I'll just warn you so you're
going to want to read this part of the
book carefully study the practice
problems look at the old exams because I
can guarantee you you're going to get
some of these on the final that's a
promise and they can be infinitely
obscure so we can we can torch you with
these so that the main point is that
associated with any executing process
which you can think of a process is a
running program is a something called
the descriptor table and what that
contains is for every open file that you
have it has a pointer to a data
structure called an entry in a table
that's maintained by the operating
system globally which describes each of
the open files actually each of every
time a file is opened that allocates a
record in this open file table and so as
I mentioned file descriptor 0 1 and 2
have specific meanings and the other
files are other ones that you've opened
up during the course of your program
execution and have not yet closed so
that's so each of these then is a
reference to a particular open file and
it gives information about that file and
it also gives the position in the file
that currently is that I told you every
time you open a file there's a for a
regular file at least there's an
Associated position of where in the file
was your last reader right or where
would you be your next reader right and
so that's the file pause and there's
also a reference count which is used by
the operating system to keep track of
because we'll see it's possible to have
multiple multiple processes sharing an
entry in this open file table and it
uses this reference count which is
standard way of keeping track of memory
allocation to know when it no longer
needs that entry if when there's been
enough when the file is no longer
accessible and therefore this entry is
not needed so for every one of your open
files that will have an entry in this
table and this table as I said is shared
across the whole operating system and
then associated with every file is
called a V node which stands for virtual
node and this is where that contains the
sort of information about this file in
particular where is it stored on this
information that you can get from stat
and things like that how big it is and
things like that so that's for every
every file in the system actually has a
V node entry whether it's open or closed
now this can get complicated so for
example if within a single program you
call open twice on the same function
you'll actually get two different file
descriptors and you'll be able to access
that same file and have two different
positions in it then it makes sense if
you imagine you're reading from a file
and you might want to read from two
different positions in that file within
the same program and you can do that
that's perfectly legal you just call
open twice and that will keep track of
two different positions
so the point is these file descriptors
might be referring to the same file but
they're actually at different positions
within the file and that can happen also
if you're if you've opened a file for
both reading and for writing and you're
writing ahead and then reading
characters bytes that have already been
written that makes sense it's not such a
good idea to have two different write
file opens that are writing
simultaneously you can mess up the file
pretty badly that way but there's
nothing in the operating system that
prevents you from doing that so it won't
it's not a good idea but it's a legal
operation so that's the point is you
have to distinguish at what level is
sharing taking place and you see that if
you have two different Oh table entries
sharing one file then that what's
different there is that you can be
working at different file positions uh
similarly of course the more common
thing is you have two different open
files in there refer to different files
but now and this is where life gets
exciting if you call Fork you remember
about fork that it spawns a child but
that child inherits a lot of information
from its parent and one of the things it
inherits is its descriptor table it gets
a replica of that descriptor table and
so now both the parent and the child
have identical entries in their
descriptor table and so they're sharing
files but not at the file level but at
the Open File table and what that means
is if the parent does a read it'll bump
along the file position and if the child
now doesn't read it will it will see oh
this from this new position so you can
see why the exam problems get really
interesting
that will keep track of all these
different possibilities and they'll do
different things and so and then of
course the parent or the child can start
opening and closing their own files as
well and that will get very messy and
here's what you see the reason for
having reference counts here that if you
have a lot of forking going on then you
can create multiple pointers to this a
table entry and in order to really
really close the file each of these has
to call closed before the file is truly
truly closed from an operating system
perspective so there's other fun things
that make a wife interesting too and
contribute to the exam problem
possibilities what is it called called
dupe - and the purpose the dupe - is -
excuse me duplicate a.m. entry in the
descriptor table and the most common use
of that is is a IO redirection the
either greater or less than sign to
either redirect read the instead of from
standard input from the file or instead
of writing to standard output to write
to a file and the way the operating
system actually implements that is
shortly after starting the program it
will call called dupe - to make it so
that the file descriptor 1 is not the
standard output of the for this process
but it's actually the original standard
output but it's actually a descriptor
for the file that it's supposed to write
- and same width of it's doing input
redirection and but you can call dupe to
yourself
and do these kind of things and there's
actually good reasons for doing so
so in particular imagine I open the file
and standard output points to the sort
of normal thing and I open a new file I
call it B and then I call dupe - excuse
me
and now what both file descriptor 1 and
file descriptor for are sharing this
entry in the file table and you see the
reference count of 2 and so in order to
really close it then what would
typically happen at this point is the
this has happens before it starts to
your program you'd want to close file
descriptor for and in fact there's a lot
of bugs you can make by not closing
files it's easy to make mistakes when
you have multiple entries in these
tables yes/no see if I call closed this
one it just decrements this reference
count but this remains a valid entry
here yes but dupe 2 will decrement the
reference count of the original so it's
dupe 2 goes backwards from where you
think it should
so dupe 2 is the I want what what I
referred to for example file descriptor
I want file descriptor for to become
what I can use to and refer to with file
descriptor 1 here it will actually
decrement the reference count of this
before it it done does the copy
otherwise it would create like a an
orphan in this table right
um so anyways dupe 2 also is a powerful
but dangerous mechanism so now finally
let me just mention the much more common
i/o that application programs use is
what's known as the standard i/o and
that's what's documented in K&R and it's
actually part of the the C standard all
these different functions and so the
main feature it adds is sort of like
what you saw with the REO package it
adds buffering so it doesn't have to do
this low-level stuff and it voids all
than some of the nastiness and the the
way it works is what we've already seen
it uses buffering to do a vio so just in
it is an example
here's some code that calls printf one
character at a time to print the word
hello but if I run that and is trace it
you see that there's only one system
call to 2 right and it works the same
way you saw with the real code it builds
up a buffer and it's not until this call
to F flush that forces the output to
actually be a printed output usually
that happens automatically actually if
you print F up
a line feed it will flush it so but that
I think that call to F wash is probably
redundant here
so and so that's the benefit so buffered
i/o is much more efficient because it
because of the buffering so as a result
we've now seen three different types of
i/o there's the low-level IO called you
referred to as UNIX i/o you saw this
package that was written specifically
for the book and for the course called
Rio and then there's a much larger and
in fact richer set of i/o functions
provided by the UNIX standard library so
you might ask a couple questions one is
why the heck did you write this when
you've already got that if if UNIX
provides buffered i/o why did you do it
yourself and the reason is this stuff
doesn't it works really well for the i/o
you do to a terminal or to files but it
doesn't do very well with network
connections it wasn't really designed
for that and so it gets really messed up
and so the main reason you're going to
find yourself using this is when you're
starting to use network connections ah
the other thing is these do not coexist
very well buffered i/o with a reow i/o
because they each maintain their own
buffers and they don't know about each
other and they get terribly confused so
you kind of have to pick one or the
other with respect to any particular il
connection and don't try to mix and
match them so like I said UNIX i/o then
the low-level stuff from an application
perspective it's like really painful to
use especially with short counts and
error codes and and all that stuff and
so in general you want to either write
your own package or use some other
package around it and so as I said
standard i/o it gives you printf and
scanf and all these nice features it's
uniform it exists on all systems it's
reasonably standardized
so in general then use the the standard
i/o for most year day-to-day uses of
files I'll use a raw IO for low-level
stuff like when you have to and partly
it turns out signals are not you
shouldn't use standard i/o when you're
writing signal handlers and then the REO
you're going to find useful for in pre
curricular for doing networking one
other thing that you should one bug that
students do over and over again in this
course is they try to do a line oriented
i/o on things that aren't lines so like
a JPEG image or something like that
and the reason that's important is that
these functions are treat the end of
line character 0a is a very special
character they'll stop reading or
something like that or if it's going
between Windows and UNIX it will
actually change one from carriage
returned from line feed to carriage
return line feed sim way functions like
sterlin and ster copy will stop when
they hit a null byte and that's not what
you want to do when these are network
packets you're trying to send out so be
careful some of the functions you've
used a lot and you're very familiar with
may be completely inappropriate for
things where you're doing binary of data
or you're communicating over networks
and things like that so be sure you
understand what you're doing when you
start to use these kind of functions so
those who you really want to know this
stuff
there's a there's a fellow named Richard
Stevens who unfortunately died awhile
quite a while ago but his books live on
and there's various people have signed
up to become co-authors with him in his
absence and creating new editions of
these books that used to
date back way far so and if you really
want to know how this stuff works you
want to be the ace programmer these
books are the best you can get but I'll
also warn you your bookshelf will become
very heavy laden because there's there's
the volumes one two and three and then
there's networking books and Stevens is
like a encyclopedic reference but
they're excellent books if you really
want to understand something read
Stevens and there's another book that is
just specific to Linux that's fairly
nice and somewhat it's very detailed but
since it's only trying to deal with
Linux it's a little bit less weird than
trying to read Stevens because Stevens
will say in this version of UNIX it
works this way in this version it works
that way and blah blah blah and it's all
different and it will drive you crazy
but Stevens is still it's an outstanding
set of books ok so this is an example
and I'm not going to go through it but
these are the kind of things that we use
to torture students that you open some
file descriptors and you do some dupes
and you do some Forks and so you end up
with a real spaghetti for all the
pointers and what's shared and what's
not shared and then you ask what will
this print and of course you'll have to
trace through in great detail what's
really going on so those are in the book
and I recommend you work on some of
those ok that'll do us for today then
you