okay so this is the last lecture for the class
and I'm sure that you've got a lot of other things going on as well
so thanks for showing up
today this is as I said last time these two lectures are not part of the course syllabus
they're not on the final exam they're more looking to the future
and in particular what I want to talk about today is some kind of studying I did over the past year
about how the electronics industry
what we now call the semiconductor
industry but it might be something
different in the future as new
technology comes along but what what
directions it's going to head and will
we be able to assume the kind of
progress that we've come to know and
expect over the past several decades
so in particular and this is important
for obviously for people involved in ECE
but also for people involved in computer
science and software because the fact
that we have this massive collection of
computers data centers powerful cell
phones and things obviously the software
people are important to that but the
reality is it's the hardware base that
makes it possible so it's really an
important thing even for software people
to have a fairly decent understanding of
how the actual systems work what their
technology is and what set could look
like in the future
so in particular we've been riding
enjoying the benefits of what's commonly
referred to as Moore's law and Gordon
Moore is he's still alive and was one of
the earlier pioneers in the
semiconductor industry he worked for
William Shockley who's one of the
inventors of the transistor and set up
there's a company called Shockley
semiconductor that Shockley set up in
the Bay Area in Palo Alto and the wait
in the early nineteen know in the 1950s
somewhere and then he
and a group of them left because
Shockley was such a jerk and found and
found a home at an existing company
called Fairchild that did things like
aviation electronics and set up
Fairchild Semiconductor and so that was
really the start of Silicon Valley from
the silicon perspective actually they
were using germanium at the time but
what we think of a Silicon Valley really
got its start there so he was the the
the head of the research part of
Fairchild Semiconductor when he wrote an
article for a what's really just a trade
press magazine electronics magazine we
wouldn't consider it a very important
publication these days but back then it
had some fairly leading articles and so
he wrote an article and this is in 1965
so almost exactly 50 years ago and what
he done was he just sort of eyeballed
what his company was able to do in terms
of of building the very new of
semiconductors and it was the very very
early days of integrated circuits when
you could put multiple transistors on a
single chip and what he recognized was
there is sort of a curve of met that on
this axis it's how much does it cost to
per transistor to manufacture a system
and on the right hand side it's how many
transistors there were on a single chip
and what he observed was through sort of
a sweet spot and if you're to the left
you're basically you're not putting
enough things on the chip and so you
have too many chips and they cost a lot
to connect them together and you're not
making use of the technology and if you
go too far to the right then you're
trying to squeeze more on that chip than
it was economically feasible at the time
and what he also observed was and this
is 65 remember so he was basically
projecting from 3 years worth of data
that that curve was dropping that and so
this sweet spot was shifting to telling
you what's the optimum number of devices
to put on a single chip from like 20
here 250 there too and then he projected
out and said well gee by 1970 we should
be able to get a thousand devices on a
chip and that was sort of just a
prediction he made and then that became
known as Moore's law and that name was
not made up by Moore but by actually a
professor at Caltech so what we now know
of is Moore's law was really started
with this prediction and two things are
worth noting one is it's a technology
prediction it's based on what this
company and other companies were able to
do but the other was an economic one it
was saying if you want to make the best
use of this technology and get the most
sort of electronics for your dollar then
you should be following these principles
so and that that combination is actually
quite important
so I went off and found a Wikipedia page
that lists a bunch of different chips
for microprocessors and other types of
processors that has the both the chip
area and how many transistors who were
on that and I mapped it out so it starts
the first microprocessor was the called
the 4004 made by Intel in 1971 and up
through here you see that I sort of
partitioned these into different types
of processors so a desktop processor
would be like what you'd have in a PC
and they sort of drove the industry for
this middle part of the time embedded
systems are chips that aren't designed
to be computers that you're using as
computers but they're inside of
something for
example the earliest micro processors
the 4004 was created by Intel to to run
a calculus cop calculator built by a
Japanese company they came to Intel and
said could you make us some electronics
to implement this and somebody within
Intel I had the inspiration to say well
if we just implement this as a
microprocessor then we can write the
code to implement a desktop calculator
and it's what they call 4-bit
microprocessor so you're used to 32
mentioned 4 so the word size is 4 and
how do you do that it's actually you
have to think about how you even do that
but that's what it was a 4-bit
microprocessor so anyways embedded
systems sort of some of these were
really a pre PC era and then these
diamonds are ones that sort of drove the
PC era and then the yellow are more
recent graphic processor units which are
some of the biggest fastest chips out
there the x's are ones that are really
server class machines for example the
sharp machines and are designed to be
inside of a big computer room and down
here for exempt these blue ones are
actually for cell phones but this is
just this is not a scientific sample
it's just a ones for which I could find
the appropriate data oh and you might
ask why did you start in 1971 if this
paper came out in 65 well back in 65 the
technology was what they called bipolar
technology which is not a mental
condition here and the it's very
different
so the first microprocessor and all the
successor ones are done in a technology
called MOS which stands for metal oxide
semiconductor which isn't a very useful
name but basically chips since the early
70s have dominantly been using this
technology and the current one is called
CMOS
so anyways the interesting thing you'll
see here is on this vlog scale you'll
see that this doubling every two years
has almost exactly matched what's
happened so the gray line is if I just
extrapolated from from 50 transistors in
1965 and predicted they would double
every two years you get the gray line
and the black line is what I get running
a regression on this data and you'll see
that their scopes are exactly the same
and what that means is the doubling
every two years is absolutely true and
the black line what it says is well
actually they in the early days they got
ahead of a curve somewhat so that the
first microprocessor for example the
four thousand four had around well
actually I have the numbers actually add
1700 transistors so not too far off of
what word predicted for 1970 so anyways
that's the point it's an amazing thing
this is held and you might ask why was
like Gordon Moore the the best a
forecaster of the future ever to be able
to nail this number so precisely and
also why do you call it a law so there's
two things going there's a few things
going on here first of all this is not a
law it's not a law of nature it's not a
law of our country it's not a law of of
anything it's just a statement that he
made but also it's become a
self-fulfilling aw meaning that because
Gordon Moore who was a very prominent
tourist at that time said this and said
his company in that direction and he
then went on to found in tell by the way
he and and all of his colleagues and his
sort of burgeoning business have just
been dedicated to the task of making
this a law so it was a prediction but
not in a sort of objective sense it was
a prediction by somebody who then
motivated other people to fulfill it
so anyways it's pretty interesting that
just collect and if you can collect all
kinds of data and you'll find this this
this doubling pretty much holds by the
way in general you should whenever
you're looking at a semi-log pot if you
have a straight line that's a sign of
exponential growth so what does this
really mean then it's hard for you to
appreciate how much different the world
of computing is today than it was even
20 30 40 years ago so for example in
1976 if you had a lot of money in other
words your Los Alamos National
Laboratory and you really wanted a big
computer you could buy it by basically
getting a hand-built machine from a
company called Cray headed by Seymour
Cray who is one of the legendary people
in the world of computing at the time
but this machine is you see all the
numbers for it are way off what even
I've got on my phone and what you have
on your phone to write in terms of
performance in terms of density this
thing weighed 5,000 kilograms and used
115 kilowatts where is now we have these
ones that are powered by batteries and
fit in your pocket and the other is
numbers that the whole life of the crane
this was considered an incredibly
successful supercomputer the first real
supercomputer in the whole lifetime they
manufactured 80 of them and as you know
phones sell in the millions so it's
really very very different world we live
in because of of the progress of
integration and so again to put yourself
back back in 65 what I can like I'll
date myself I was a young person at that
time and for me the coolest thing to get
was a portable transistor radio
like this one that would play am
stations
okay now today what young teenagers
crave for is a sort of waitest a
consumer product of a high-end phone so
part of it is if you look at this they
even advertise that this transistor
radio had nine transistors on it whereas
the chip inside of a this is last year's
the the iPhone six had has if you still
have one a chip with two billion
transistors on it and that's the main
chip there's about eleven chips in an
iPhone in a phone by the way but that's
the main processor chip so that's really
the fundamental difference of why what
you've got today is so different than
what you could get in sixty five so it's
hard to even think about two billion
transistors and what that really means
so here's an analogy imagine a
transistor where the size of a grain of
sand they're actually a lot smaller than
that but just that's about the smallest
thing you can think of sort of picking
up and feeling then if you look at
here's this original four thousand four
had twenty three hundred transistors I
didn't have my numbers quite right so
that's if you think in sand grains it's
um actually I calculated this out it's
170th of a teaspoon so just a very very
small pinch of sand is about 2,300
grains of sand and nowadays if you think
of two billion transistors in in terms
of sand that's about a 200 pounds of
sand so if you go to Home Depot and you
buy a bag of sand for your children's
for somebody's a sandbox or whatever
it's about 50 pounds so about four four
bags of sand is 2 billion two billion
grains so that sort of where we are
today where
sort of a it's the same as if you filled
up big Paint Bucket three of them sort
of that level we're at so just to give
you a sense where we are and so what I
claim is and this isn't just my claim
it's sort of self-evident that there's a
sort of virtuous cycle that's driven
that drives the technology and the
economics together so in particular the
more things they can sell that they have
chips in them the more money that gives
for companies and more incentive that
gives them to invest in research and
development to improve the technology to
buy it's a very expensive capital
equipment to run a semiconductor
fabrication facility and so that money
comes from ultimately because they're
selling this stuff and because of that
they're then able to improve the
technology pack more transistors on a
chip make them run faster reduce the
power all those good things and then
that's coupled with people who are good
at a product design and of course the
software designers as well to improve
the product so that you want to buy more
stuff right and that causes more sales
so this cycle is very important that if
it weren't for that looping around then
these improvements wouldn't be happening
so right now the semiconductor industry
is worldwide and it's very much a
international industry is about three
hundred billion dollars a year so it's
pretty big and so what does that meant
well one is simply let's just take the
example of phones that the iPhone the
first iPhone was on 2007 or so and
there's been nine generations of them
including the most recent which isn't
shown this picture and so more or less
every year they come out with a new
phone and for example this phone I'm
carrying around is one I bought this
fall even though I had a phone of from
two years ago that was really okay but
I was sufficiently motivated to shell
out the money and now it's not hidden in
our plans anymore so I know this
actually cost me $750 but I and many of
my friends and people around the world
did exactly that and created a huge pile
of of cash that infused Apple and part
of the reason Apple now is the largest
company in the world in terms of market
capitalization so that cycle you can see
here you know better products more sales
you you see that happening all the time
but underneath it all what's driving
that then is the ability to improve
these products so you've probably heard
the other kind of stuff people are
talking about is artificial intelligence
and will it basically eliminate all your
jobs and the famous sort of person
behind that it's a guy named Ray
Kurzweil and so he proposed this idea
they call the singularity which is the
the day this is I'll just describe it to
you can tell I'm a skeptic on this the
day that computers become more powerful
than humans actually that he's not the
one who invented that term then it's all
of a sudden going to create this massive
switchover where the computers are going
to get smarter by teaching themselves to
be smarter and so off into infinity
of and making humans obsolete that's the
idea of the singularity and part of the
argument behind this is basically from
Moore's Law
so what Kurt's while did in this picture
and it actually started with some work
by a person who used to be the robotics
Institute here was he plotted based on
this his measure was calculations per
second per thousand dollars so how much
computation could you buy for a thousand
dollars and he started back at 1900 with
mechanical adding machines and stuff
like that
and added these plots you see this was
around 2000 and somehow this is an
article of amazing a potting he figured
that this wasn't even a straight line it
was an upward curve so an upward curve
on a semi-log paper is more than
exponential it's like e to the x squared
or something like that right so but
anyways based on that projection and
based on some notion of the relative
power of human versus mouse versus
insect brains he came out with this
projection that in 2030 roughly
computers would become smarter than
humans and if you just keep that on Kim
eight computers would become smarter
than all humans combined so that we can
talk about this projection and I'm sure
you guys do at times too but my point of
it is this argument is fundamentally a
Moore's Law argument right that the
argument is basically as computational
power increases because of this
continuing progress of technology it's
inevitable that because humans aren't
really getting smarter much of a very
fast rate that it's inevitable that
computers will become smarter than
humans it's sort of the argument but
it's very much based on this assumption
that computer technology is going to
continue to progress at an exponential
pace
so let's now imagine and this is
something that you know you could be
thinking about is is what will this mean
50 years from now so if Moore's law
looks back over the past 50 years now
let's look forward for another 50 years
and see what that would mean and what
would possibly be so here's a one claim
I'll make is that whatever is the most
important thing it will be something
that is in the hands of everyone or is
even more ubiquitous than there are here
on the planet right in other words that
what I claim is the thing that will be
the most important technology-wise will
be what's the largest volume product so
I'm not sure what that will be in 2065
it certainly will not be called a cell
phone it won't look like what we think
of as a phone after all of all the
things people own cell phones for what
do you use it for the least making calls
right at least for me so who knows what
it will be but I claim that and this is
a key part of this argument that claim
it's got to be a portable low power
system so it has to be powerful
computation but as to be physically
small and it can't draw much power and
that will be and so it might be you know
the Internet of Things where everything
is networked together and there's
computer chips or various chips and
everything that those kind of things
would also have the kind of volumes
needed to drive the market forward so
based on that sort of let's make that
one part of assumption is whatever
drives the future it's going to be
something that is portable low power and
low cost you know consumer grade or
something that you can afford to just
sprinkle across the whole planet or
across the whole galaxy if we're beyond
Earth at that point so that means for
example that it's not going to be a
quantum computer right quantum
cholesterol so make breakthroughs in
superconducting something that you have
to cool down to near absolute zero
requires a big room a lot of equipment
and a lot of power and a lot of things
to manage it so you're not going to
carry that around in your pocket I can
promise you that so all the people
talking about a quantum computer well we
can just rule that out that's not going
to be the the most important thing out
there but it
and it also you know if you could
imagine building this huge machine
that's occupies many acres of buildings
that's not going to be the most exciting
thing out there because it's it there's
not enough of those to sort of drive the
market and without that market there
won't be in the investment in the
technology so it has to be inexpensive
and what if we think of it in computer
science terms big o-notation it can't be
you know the cost to produce these
things can't be very much so for example
the chip that's in the cellphone that
Apple AAA costs somewhere between ten
and twenty dollars for Apple to procure
that from its suppliers which are in
Taiwan and in Korea so they're not very
expensive
that said it need not be anything based
on the technology we use today as I
mentioned currently things are CMOS and
it's been some kind of moss MOS since
the 1970s so for a long time but
probably won't continue to be that way
at least not the way we know it and
there's various other ideas people have
had for future computer technology that
beyond this and some of it's being
worked on here at CMU and I will predict
what those could be but they have to
have these characteristics s being
expensive has being low-power has to be
scalable so that's my one assumption
then I'm going to add is whatever it is
we're going to want a lot of them a lot
of transistors or devices of some sort
so what does that mean if we project
that out in terms of how many devices
are on a chip not not how many
transistors but devices so one great
thing about semi-log pots is you can
just extrapolate to your heart's content
so if we just run those two curves that
I showed you before out ah you get
somewhere we'll just you know pick a
number that's sort of roughly in the
middle of those two projections of ten
to the seventh
so 10 to the 17th things devices in a
single integrated system of some kind
that would be what we'd be looking at so
how big is 10 to the 17th well if we go
back to our sand analogy this is a
picture I found on the internet of some
young man in Brazil on the beach
making a scale model of the Empire State
Building out of sand so my estimate is
this is roughly something like 3 billion
grains of sand in that thing I didn't
count them I have to admit but so so
think in terms so something you know
roughly the same scale I showed you of
those four bags of sand from Home Depot
something that's roughly comparable to
what we'd get on a chip today if if
transistors were the size of a grain of
sand so what does 10 to the 17th mean
well if you actually built a sand model
of the Empire State Building at one to
one scale right then that's a million
cubic meters and then if you made two
replicas of that then and some of those
three together then you'd get about 10
to the 17th grains of sand so of course
we're assuming this is going to be
something a lot smaller than a grain of
sand but just to give you a sense of
scale of how big a change that would be
going from a few billion to 10 to the
17th is a pretty big jump in terms of
how many devices are involved so let's
figure out how could we make things you
know let's just say well let's just try
running the numbers and seeing what
would happen if we just took our current
technology which is more or less what
we've been using since 1970 of putting a
lot of transistors on a single chip
actually I happen to bring some toys
with me today this is a wafer
so this is what comes through a
fabrication plant and it's got typically
about 700 individual whether they called
dye on them
the then they slice up and they put in
packages so these are some old packages
but now on your phone or your laptops
whose packaging in there so they package
the the chips inside of there so
typically then this is the current size
that a company manufactures a diet it's
30 centimeters so about 1 foot in
diameter and you get about 700 chips on
it
chips are typically around one square
centimeter so let's just say well let's
just take that technology which over the
years these these die of
these chips have gotten the wafers have
gotten bigger the dive gotten a little
bit bigger and we've also been able to
make much finer geometries on these
chips so let's sort of see how we've got
this over history and what the
projections that would mean and what the
data show is that the way we've achieved
is sort of doubling every two years in
how many transistors were on a chip is
one the trips have gotten bigger they've
doubled in size at a rate of once every
10 years and also the geometries have
gotten finer that we've they've doubled
in size or halved in size well the
density we can get as a result has gone
by a factor to every about four times in
ten years and so you sum those up you
get five doublings every ten years and
that's how you get more squat so in
particular if you look at the earliest
chip the four thousand four was about
twelve square millimeters so that it's
pretty small and a modern chip is
typically around a square centimeter so
and this is actually to scale to a
there are some bigger chips out there
and they're not really blue they just
did this to make it look nice but IBM
for example makes a server where the
chip size is almost 10 times larger than
than this processor so you can get some
pretty big dye out there but those are
typically only and also some GPUs can be
pretty big dice so those are used either
in servers or in places where they're
pretty specialized for more portable
battery-powered things you have to go
with smaller chips so this is the data
showing the area for these different
microprocessors for time and you can see
that you're kind of all over the map so
it's a little risky to do any kind of
extrapolation here but this is where I
got the number that it's doubled roughly
every 10 years the area of the chip so
if we project that out then then we get
something of 173 square centimeters so
those of you metrically challenge that
number probably doesn't mean much to you
but just to give you a sense like if I
just extrapolated then by the Year 2065
I should be up to the Apple model a 59
because right
today's the a6 of s and so anyways and
well as we said 10 to the 17 transistors
it will be 173 square centimeters the
problem with that is it's actually
bigger than a dollar bill it's about two
dollar bills in size 173 square
centimeters and you're not going to fit
that in your pocket unless you have
really big pocket so that is not the way
things are going to work we can't just
keep scaling up area and expect that to
happen well the other factor which is we
showed is more critical as things have
gotten smaller and so the way I'll I'll
measure that is I'll take this measure I
call L this linear metric
of chip density I'll say the area of
that chip divided by the number of
transistors and so one way to think
about it is if the transistors were
spread in a sort of uniform grid across
a chip then their spacing would be this
number L of course they're not there
they're denser in some places and more
spread out and others but sort of if you
think of this as a way to look overall
how close we packed our transistors to
each other oh and this is the curve you
get from our existing set of processors
and you see this one really is a pretty
strong trend of getting a finer and
finer geometries over time and it's so
the linear scale it drops by a factor of
two every five years but if you think
about the number of things the density
therefore goes by a factor of four every
five years and so that's or equivalent
we have gotten twice as many transistors
in a given area every two and a half
years
and we can see that again in practice
that if you measure out for the Intel
4004 it comes out to 72,000 nanometers
10 to the ninth meters is this measure
and where's EPEL a 8 is 211 nanometers
so those you know about chip technology
might know that the AAA
was manufactured with what's called a 22
nanometer process so when they measure
when you hear people talking about a
process you know the the actual
fabrication process and they give a
number of nowadays and nanometers what I
mean is the sort of closest spacing you
can make two wires on a chip the sort of
finest geometry there but this measure L
is bigger because it counts for not just
out what how closely you can pack wires
but all the other stuff you have to put
transistors there you have to route
power and ground and signal wires to
them and they have to be isolated from
each other so this is actually a more
useful measure of of the effect of
spacing on a chip um so just to again if
you're not so familiar with this kind of
geometry let's just give you some idea
of it so this range in nanometers then
between a thousand and a million then is
is sort of something smaller than a
millimeter right a million nanometers is
a millimeter so a thousand nanometers is
a micron or a micrometer and so this
range which is where semiconductor
processing was up till ten years ago
you'd call it the submillimetre range
and in this it's in the sub micrometer
range so just to give you some sense of
what those scales mean and I'll point
out that it's pretty incredible to talk
about something over six orders of
magnitude in scale right that's in the
physical world six orders of magnitude
is a lot so again if you look at here's
examples of things of how big is a
micrometer often called a micron so you
know things at the are almost visible at
this scale a human cell how thick a
piece of plastic saran wrap is how thick
a a strand of spider silk is gives you
some rough number and so this Intel chip
from the seventies was somewhere in that
range and now if we look somewhere
between a nanometer and a micrometer and
again this is a log pot or so these
things go pretty fast so for example all
a visible light is in this range between
400 and 700 nanometers and the the
spacing of transistors on an Apple chip
are therefore closer than then the
wavelength of visible light by the way
which makes for kind of a challenge for
manufacturing something like how thick
is a cell membrane or how what's the
diameter of a strand of DNA are down in
just a few nanometer range what they
call carbon nanotubes which people
predict will be possibly a successor to
transistors their diameter not their
length is one nanometer so those are
pretty small when you're getting down
here and nowadays modern processes
they're trying to create features down
in this range of 14 nanometers for
example okay but we can do our our plots
and if you just project out you'll get
down to this linear spacing of 230 Pico
meters in 50 years so what does that
mean how big is a Pico meter well Pico
meter is really small in fact if you
look at the spacing between two atoms in
a silicon crystal they're about 1/2 of a
nanometer and if you look at the space
thing between the two atoms in a
hydrogen molecule there are 74
picometers so what the main thing to
realize is this ain't going to happen
there is absolutely no way that we'll be
able to create systems where things are
spaced only 230 Pico meters apart
right because presumably whatever we
build is going to be bigger than a
hydrogen atom or molecule so or you know
so this really is not in the range of
physically possible and that's one of
the annoying things that physics has
sort of gotten in the way of progress
recently so in particular you know could
we imagine then let's just suppose we'll
allow a chip we'll say let's let a chip
be as big as 400 square millimeters just
about twice as big on a side as a
current chip current standard chip that
would still require this spacing metric
of 63 Pico meters wait a minute is that
right yes because I'm not allowed to
make chips the size of $2 bills
so it requires even finer spacing here
and we saw that's just 63 Pico meters is
actually closer than the two atoms in a
hydrogen molecule the two nuclei in a
hydrogen molecule so the answer is no
this isn't going to happen this just
point is not possible at least not you
know so we have to back off and say well
what's our defect on our thinking one is
to assume that we're going to just take
this current technology of two
dimensional things and just shrink it
and one reason we look at that way
because that's exactly what's happened
over the past 50 years but we have three
dimensions in this world and so maybe
there's some prospect there so let's say
instead okay let's imagine
a little brick of stuff and I'll just
make up some numbers I'll say it's 2
centimeters on a side and 5 millimeters
high it's almost exactly the same shape
and volume as a stack of five nickels
and so and now let's just imagine okay
how are we going to integrate a bunch of
things well presumably we're going to
build it out of layers and so let's just
assume that there's about a hundred
thousand layers worth of stuff and those
are what I'll call logical layers
meaning that they'll be about a million
physical layers because we have to have
wires and these whatever we're building
will be just these totally flat things
nowadays there's a modern chip has more
like 20 physical layers on it so but the
point is that we'll have to have about a
million physical layers worth of stuff
to get a hundred thousand logical wires
but that would allow us a spacing on the
linear spacing of about 20 nanometers so
20 nanometers is a lot better than a 63
picometers right if we go back 20
nanometers is up in here so it's really
really small but it's not it's not
beyond a physical possibility let's just
put it that way so you can imagine some
technology that would give you that so
at least at some level it's it's vaguely
you know it's aggressive but but
possible to imagine in 50 years be able
to manufacture in a shape like that
something with 10 to the 17th devices
but there's a few problems one is
actually the manufacturing how we do
actually do this is no small thing
another I'll talk about some is
do we do this and not spend a whole lot
an exorbitant amount of money doing it
and the other is a huge huge problem of
power consumption how can we actually
have a system that complicated and keep
it at the limited energy level we have
available so let me go into that some
more so just is a sort of tutorial the
way these chips are made and part of the
reason they're so cheap is it's it's
sort of a photo process meaning that
every step of the way is done by putting
a some kind of material down and
exposing it to a light a laser light and
then that's this material that you put
down as light-sensitive and so there's a
mask that defines how things should be
patterned and the light only hits where
the mask is allows it to and that's how
you get different shapes and things and
you can either add material or you can
remove material by these masking steps
so nowadays a modern chip takes about 60
of these steps we're involving a mask
and some type of either depositing
something or removing something or
shining light on it or a beam of ions or
some other process step to do it so it's
very complicated than the technology is
quite remarkable but what you could say
is that the even though there's a couple
billion transistors on a chip
it still is a constant time process some
fixed number of steps and it's done and
each successive generation maybe the
number of masking steps is increased a
little bit over time but roughly
speaking it's always a constant time
operation and it turns out that the
bottleneck in this and the performance
one is actually this photolithography
exposing the chip the the the wafer
using a mask and the way that's done
nowadays is a machine called a stepper
that
basically is used to scan over the wafer
and expose with a laser sort of flashing
as it goes to expose the wafer to this
mask and so current-day that's done it a
on a size of about eight hundred nine
hundred square millimeters so you know
about this bigger size how much they can
expose at a time
and the the fastest steppers out there
can do a whole way for in 18 seconds
which is pretty good if you think of
waving over this whole area flashing and
exposing it with extremely high
resolution and very high alignment of
reliability well but that's sort of the
thing that sort of limits how many chips
you can run through a fabrication
facility per day is this stepper and the
stepper is the most expensive piece of
machinery in the building so you don't
want to buy a whole lot of them so
that's sort of my point is that
lithography is the expensive thing so
every layer we have to do if we have to
expose it using this technique is
expensive and so there's no way you
could do a million layer system using
photolithography and keep the expense
down to the range where it would be
something you or I would would be able
to afford as a consumer device as I said
a modern chip is somewhere between ten
and twenty dollars so we're not talking
a lot of money right if you increase
that cost by a hundred then people
aren't going to buy it because if you
think if a ten dollar chip powers at
$700 phone then there's a big multiplier
there so there's various options you can
imagine one is what they call chemical
self-assembly where basically whatever
you're having sort of patterns itself
just like the crystals would in a you
know in a block of
or something like that if you can
imagine various chemical processes where
things just form into the particular
shapes so this is an area that's been
tried and worked on for electronics for
several decades and never really
succeeded yet but maybe that's possible
and another possibility would be some
interesting ideas in in multiple working
with multiple layers at once so in
particular one technology that's really
been able to scale into three dimensions
are flash chips and that's part of the
reason why my phone has 64 gigabytes I'm
not bragging I'm just telling you my
phone has 64 gigabytes of memory you
know why is there so much memory a flash
memory available on it flash as you know
is sort of the the storage of choice in
a solid-state disk on cell phones
nowadays and so it's a it's based on
semiconductor devices so for example
this is a electron micrograph of a chip
from Samsung showing how they are able
to create a sort of three-dimensional
layering of of memory cells so basically
every spot in x y&z here is a 1 bits
worth actually 2 bits worth of memory
cell and there's some device there that
can store it and then there's ways that
you can access it to either read it or
write it and they're able to do it this
whole layering but by using only a fixed
number of masking steps so basically
what they start off with is they build
up layers without any masking and then
they put some masks there and then they
zap down and they can sort of carve away
up using basically ion beams to carve
down wherever the mask is and pattern
then they can pour various types of goop
in there that will fill up these spaces
and so by some patterning only at the
very top layer they can actually create
this three-dimensional matrix of memory
cells and they can now the most recent
technology gets about 48 layers and
there's projections that they'll be able
to keep doing that at least through
several hundred layers so my point is
that you can actually do you don't
necessarily need to do masking at every
single layer to create a 3-dimensional
structure now this doesn't scale in an
obvious way to computers or
microprocessors or anything with
computation it relies very heavily on
the fact that the particular circuit of
flash memory is very simple and fairly
easy to build in this 3-dimensional
structure but at least this is the kind
of idea of what will have to happen if
we're going to get this kind of
integration
but here's the harder one and this is a
problem just in general we're already up
against a serious power issues now so if
I look at a modern phone it only draws
even when it's sort of working hardest a
couple of watts typically when it's just
if you want to walk around if you want
to have the battery be good for a day at
a time it has to draw a lot less power
than that so typically when your phones
in standby it's only drawing a few a few
milliwatts so maybe a hundredth of a
watt but when it needs to like you've
just taken a picture and it wants to do
some image processing on it or you're
taking a video or something like that it
can crank up to a couple watts of power
so why can't it go more than that one is
as I mentioned is the battery but the
other is if your phone draws more than a
few watts then you won't really want to
walk around with it in your pocket
because it'll be too hot so you know
just imagine a 25 watt light bulb if you
put that in your pocket and walked
around as far as the extension cord
would let you that wouldn't feel too
good so that limits the power isn't just
battery or so even if we come up with
better battery sources the other thing
is cooling so contrast that to the human
brain is actually pretty amazing as a
low power system so a human brain
contains roughly 64 billion neurons up
but it and it draws a few tens of watts
so more there's reasons then that so
it's a higher powered thing than a phone
but it's still a very low power system
so high power it's partly that it's a
liquid-cooled system your brains
circular your body circulation system
puts a lot of its work into keeping your
brain from overheating and your body's
metabolism are you
for example you guys sitting here each
of you are drawing about sixty watts so
you like a 60 watt light bulb but about
a quarter of that power is is powering
the neurons in your brain so it's a
fairly big chunk of the human energy
budget is the brain which makes sense
but it's still more power than we're
really going to allow in our portable
devices if we don't want to our pits to
catch on fire and now the crazy thing is
but wait a minute I wanted to go up to
10 to the 17th of these devices five
hundred thousand times more and I don't
want to add any more power to this so
how is that going to happen well it's
certainly not going to happen with the
technology we have today that's just
can't possibly meet those so we'll have
to have some fairly radically different
technology from a power perspective as
well and this goes also not just for
portable devices but even room size
building size computers for example
right now the fastest computer in the
u.s. is at Oak Ridge National Labs
it's called Titan the fastest in the
world it's in China and both of them
draw
roughly 10 megawatts okay of power so
the high-end supercomputers and one of
the goals that the supercomputing people
talk about is to scale up to what they
call exascale meaning the ability to do
10 to the 18th operations per second
whether they call flops floating-point
operations per second so if you just
took Titan and said okay we want to make
it go a hundred times faster we'll just
put more so for example Titan is built
out of 28,000 micro processors and
28,000 GPUs so if we just go crank all
that up by a factor of 100 then you're
talking Costa gigawatt of power so and
just roughly in rough terms the entire
output of the Hoover Dam is is would be
enough to power a one gigawatt system so
a a small nuclear power plant could do
it too but the point is power is going
to be a big issue for both portable
things and for all of computing as we go
forward okay so that's sort of some of
the technical challenges accommodation
but another is an economic challenge is
that it turns out that semiconductor
business has become more capital
intensive and harder to to sustain and
so this is a example of all the
companies that we're able to manufacture
chips at different physical sizes so
that it's a little bit out of date the
the latest chips are are 14 nanometers
but you see that we're basically down to
four companies in the world who have the
wherewithal to manufacture Stevi our
semiconductor systems and and so and
these are just to let you know TSMC is
Taiwan semiconductor manufacturer
they're huge in producing chips for
other customers basically what they call
a foundry so other designs come in so
for example TSMC historically has been
the main vendor for Apple for almost all
Android phones are manufactured by GSM C
Intel you know Intel but they very much
rely completely for their business on on
microprocessors and other things they
are that and they only with a small
exception only manufactured chips for
their own use their own company Samsung
as you know is in Korea is a leading
manufacturer and a lot of what they do
is produce chips for Samsung products
but they also are one of the biggest
vendors of memory they also actually
interestingly manufacture some of the
chips for Apple so if you think about
the phone business who are the big
competitors Samsung Apple but Samsung
actually builds Apple's chips Apple has
no manufacturing capabilities whatsoever
and then the fourth one is the one
called Global Foundries which is a
company that sort of swept up all the
second string players and it's actually
owned by the sovereign wealth fund of
the Abu Dhabi so one of the United Arab
Emirates so really if you're you can
sync then there's two companies in Asia
one that's headquartered in Abu Dhabi
but it's actually physically other
manufacturing facilities are in the u.s.
in Germany and in Singapore Intel all of
its manufacturing is in the u.s. Taiwan
is at least for the leading-edge all in
Taiwan and Samsung they have a fab in
Texas and in Korea so anyways my point
is
isn't very many if you think of a 300
billion dollar industry and sort of
where we're betting our future on you
only have four companies really that are
in the business right now is a little
bit scary and as you see if this trend
continues things wouldn't go well in
particularly if we want innovation and
progress to happen we need competition
and if the number of companies drops too
small then the competition won't be as
significant either so these are
interesting questions
another thing that's making life
difficult and it's been making life
difficult for the last 10 years is
what's sometimes referred to as Dennard
scaling and this is a term that you'll
hear said nowadays and just a few years
ago if you mention that term people
would have no idea what you're talking
about
unless you were pretty heavy into chips
but there's a fellow named Robert Denard
who has had a long career at IBM he
actually got his PhD here from Carnegie
Tech in the 1950s and among other things
he invented the dynamic RAM so d Ram you
know he's the guy but he wrote a very
interesting paper in in 1974 that sort
of sketched out why it is that by
shrinking chips we a life gets better
and it's a very simple model sort of
simple area geometry basics of Ohm's law
kind of stuff that that tells you what
it's doing but he said imagine we can
shrink a chip all the features on a chip
by a factor of some number K typically
we say 2 or the square root of 2 so if
you can shrink in both of x and y
directions by a factor of K and this is
a big important hand and we also reduce
the supply voltage to the chip by that
same factor then obviously we're going
to increase the number of devices by a
factor of K squared right but also we'll
be able to make these run faster and
we'll be able to do it without requiring
more power per chip so if all this
scaling holds then we can get more stuff
on a chip run it faster and not use more
power so that's sort of the principle of
Dennard scaling and that's really what
was followed by the industry for from
about 75 to about
2004 this is a chart that shows how
technology progressed so the top curve
here is Moore's law how many transistors
were on a chip
this next curve down was how fast could
a microprocessor go running a single
thread of execution and you see it was
following a sort of nice steady growth
curve what was the frequency the clock
frequency of the chip you saw also
followed this nice growth curve until it
hit about 2 gigahertz how many watts per
chip well it's kind of variable but it
was more or less it was scaling faster
than Dennard scaling predicted but still
pretty reasonable and how many cores
would we put on a chip well it was one
for a really long time and then they
started adding more so that the main
point to notice is
somewhere actually it was a right around
2005 things stopped progressing Moore's
law continues it continues today we can
get more stuff on a chip than before but
how fast are given thread goes has not
really improved much in the past of 10
years and that's why the shark machines
which are already 5 years old are
actually pretty viable computers which
and the number of watts has went leveled
off not because that's the best thing
computing wise but that's because you
just can't afford to the cost the actual
electricity cost as well as all the
requirements for cooling and things that
comes with increased power and so that
combination is the reason why we've gone
multi-core that we couldn't get improved
single-threaded performance but we could
improve the number of transition
per chip so what do we do we just make
more cores and so my so so some will
tell you that Moore's law is already
dead in the sense that for a while there
is this sort of miraculous things just
kept getting better and better every
year because of Moore's law and now
we're already in an era that even though
the transistor density part of Moore's
law holds some of these other
performance factors have not improved so
it's in all ready getting difficult to
sort of out use this technology to make
things faster and more powerful and so
I'll mention for example part of the
reason why this phone actually I don't
know how many transistors are in this
phone but if you think at two billion
transistors the model before that had 1
billion you say well what's what all
these transistors doing part of what
they've done is and part of the reason
they're able to keep the power down is a
lot of what's on a they call the the
chip now it's not called a
microprocessor it's called a system on a
chip
because embedded on it will be a couple
of arm microprocessors several graphic
processing units to handle the video the
image processing and other specialized
pieces of hardware that are only used
for very specific things so for example
there's a JPEG encoding and decoding is
directly integrated into Hardware on
this chip there's a actually some
special logic for when you take
panoramic shots and then you merge those
all together which I don't know about
you but I don't do that very often
but there's still some special dedicated
Hardware on those chips to do that
because it takes a lot of power
otherwise so in general if you can take
a some compute computing and turn it
from software and migrate it to hardware
you get a big performance increase and a
major power reduction so they're putting
more stuff on a chip not to give you
more possible
full processor but to be able to do more
stuff at lower power so that's why these
chips get more so my point is that
they're already sort of we're already in
an era when the driving reason for
Moore's Law isn't so much to get raw
performance out of these systems but to
give you more features of various sorts
okay so looking to the future then as I
said if you can look at since 65 it's
been a very long set of incremental
improvements to get from the chips of
Gordon Moore's early career to where we
are today we got more stuff on a chip
vastly more capable much more affordable
huge impact on it but from a technology
point of view has been a fairly
incremental road to travel we can see
that that's not going to work in the
future we're not going to be able to
scale transistor logic to the level that
you'd need to keep this going so at
least two-dimensional semiconductor
chips aren't going to carry the way so
they're sort of issues then and you and
your careers will be dealing with these
is will we be able to build systems of
this complexity in a way that's
commercially viable because if it's not
economically viable it's just not going
to happen and power is going to be a
huge problem as we go along and then you
know what would it mean if you actually
had 10 to the 17th I can't think of what
possible capabilities this would give us
that we'd actually want use but again if
I don't think Gordon Moore would have
thought back in 64 actually if you look
at the 65 paper I recommend you do he
actually did predict things like
personal computers and cell phones
believe it or not it's really true um so
he was definitely pretty good but for me
I can't predict what I
have in 50 years what I do with it and
then for more the software people you
know what what mean will there be
programming we certainly won't be
writing lines of code in C in order to
power systems like this so what will
that mean for the future those are all
big questions that you and this point of
your careers get to look forward to so I
I wish you the best in doing that