okay so let's get started so today's
recitation is on virtual memory so we're
sort of between two labs here your shell
lab is due tomorrow 11:59 p.m. as normal
and the Mallik lab will come out
tomorrow but Malak lab is a longer lab
you get a couple weeks to do it and so
we're not going to talk about it much
today we're going to talk about Malak
lab more next week in two weeks from now
but today we're going to talk about
virtual memory instead in the meantime
so a couple things about malloc lab
though we're going to talk about mild
lab and she'll every flea before we get
to virtual memory malloc lab will then
be due November 19th
once it's out tomorrow but even though
that's a lot of time you should start
early because it is traditionally the
longest most involved lab for the course
as long as you start early it shouldn't
be too bad
but you will you know you will want to
spend a significant amount of time
designing it so that you don't make a
mess of everything once you could
implement it you will probably need to
do at least a little bit of debugging
and the debugging can be tricky because
you've got a lot of low-level stuff
going on so a couple things about shell
lab based on what we've heard so one of
the things about the traces in case you
haven't noticed is the way the traces
work is they run echo to print out what
it's about to actually run during the
trace file so if you are seeing echo in
your job list when you run a trace what
that means is that you didn't remove it
properly because the echo is a
foreground process and it should go away
before it actually runs the real process
so if you're seeing something with that
go there the reason that is there is
because that's how the trace file works
is the reason why I got put there and
the reason why it's still there is
because there's something wrong with
your removal on your job list so you
know make sure you're actually opening
the trace file to see what exactly what
it does if you're confused about what's
going on
six suspend so six to spend maybe a lot
of you have found is helpful for this
lab if you have not realized that yet I
will tell you now six suspend is helpful
for this lab so you might have noticed
that you know there's sort of two places
where you want to be able to use weight
pit because you know you have to handle
these background jobs and you also have
to be handling a foreground job and
maybe a background job is going to stop
while your foreground job is running and
you don't know you know what order these
things are going to happen in but you
can't have weight pigs in both places
because each weigh pit just sort of gets
whatever children happen to be
terminating and so you might have said
well I'll just use weight paid for the
background jobs and then just like to
make the foreground process not do
anything I'll just sort of sit there and
I'll sleep Earl
I'll just have a while loop that just
Waits and that's a bad idea yeah you
couldn't either you'll be wasting a lot
of CPU power we'll be introducing race
conditions or both if you do that and
those are undesirable so you should look
into how you can use six suspend because
with six to spend you can sort of get
your process to just only check and see
what's happened every time a new signal
arrives and you do get a signal when
children die so that's good and you can
sort of just every time a signal arrives
you check and see if there's something
you need to do too and you know the
foreground job being blocked and if not
you can just go back and sick suspending
it so you should think about how exactly
to implement that if you haven't gotten
that already there's some details about
how sick suspend works there you can
also read the man page and then we even
have a great example of it for you
and so these you know this will be
online and you can look at that in
detail by the I mean are there any
questions about it from here it's it's
not too complicated system calls an
error handling so you should always
handle the errors from any system call
that you might be making so anytime you
know if it's a fork if it's an exact if
it's an open file whatever it is you
should be prepared for
fact that maybe there will be a error in
that system call and you should be doing
something reasonable to handle it if
that occurs so the reasonable thing you
know it's different depending on what it
is for some things maybe the reasonable
thing to do is to just print out an
error message by your shell keeps going
so for instance maybe maybe I try to
exact a process that doesn't exist
because the user typed in something bad
on the command line
well you shouldn't just shut down the
host shell because of that it would be
much better to handle that error by
printing out an error message but keep
going yes you need to handle errors for
that or should be so okay yeah so we've
got wrappers for you and what these
wrappers do is they handle errors by
exiting in some cases that's what you
want in other cases that might not be
what you want it these wrappers will be
too aggressive about just terminating
the program in some cases where you
could have kept going and so you should
think about you know in any particular
case if the correct behavior is to
terminate the process if this is
something that what we can't recover
from it or if there's a way that we can
keep going and you can of course modify
a copy of the wrapper to do something
else that you want if you sort of just
want to have the wrapper function there
but have a different error handling
behavior inside it okay and of course
you know you've many of you have seen
from cache lab that yes we do take off
style points for things this is one of
the things that we would take style
points off if you didn't handle these
errors so make sure you do that
when you go the app ever do function
that I've given you in the hand of
Coachella this function called add a
pair not a PP app I'm not sure what that
function is for the UNIX era one is part
of the CSAP P wrappers that's what they
use to just print out the error message
in and then exit I'm not sure with the
AP Pierre does that would be different I
don't have a copy of the handout
download okay let's see
audio basics okay so one of the things
about shell lab that we did not talk
about last week was i/o so the very end
of shell lab you're doing a bit of i/o
redirection it's like the last two
traces if you haven't gotten there yet
so some things about i/o there's sort of
four basic operations so we've got you
know we've got these files and what do
we do with them well we can open files
we can close files we can read bytes out
of a file and we can write bytes to a
file and then the way that we reference
these files from our program is that we
have file descriptors so when you do an
open you get back a file descriptor to
the file that you opened and it's you
know some positive integer or negative
one in the case of the errors the error
code and so what happens is you start
with three file descriptors every
program starts by default with three
file descriptors and zero is standard in
so that's the things you type into your
terminal going into the program one is
standard out so that's the stuff being
printed out to terminal and to a
standard error which is a separate
output stream so that you can redirect a
separately from standard out which is
typically used for error messages and
stuff so the way it looks is every
process gets a file descriptor table
this is all of your file descriptors
which are just these integers mapping to
an Open File table so you've got a table
of all of the open files and it's shared
by all of the processes and what that
does is it keeps track of where in the
file you are and how many file
descriptors are pointing to it
so that position sort of is you know
when you do a read on a file you know
you want to be able to like read some
number of bytes and then the next read
you do should be the byte that comes
after what you just read it shouldn't it
start again at the beginning and so it
keeps track of where it is in the file
with position and then it keeps track of
how many file descriptors are pointing
to it because once there's no more file
descriptors pointing to it we can close
it and then those just point to actual
information that's pertaining to the
real file on the disk so stuff like it's
a its size what type of file it is and
the details of that are important we
shall lap that right hand side but if
you want to know more about that that's
in the textbook it's sort of the
descriptor table on the Open File table
that we care about here for shell lab
because we're going to be manipulating
the descriptor table and sort of the
arrows between them so in this example
we've got now we've got our standard out
is pointing to file a which we say is
the terminal which is what it points to
when you open it up by default and then
we've opened up some other file we
opened up one that's a file on disk and
it has file descriptor four so we can
have multiple and we can have multiple
files in the file table pointing to the
same file on disk so this is what
happens if you just open the same file
twice so on the disk it's actually the
same file if you you know if you're
writing to it then both copies know that
you're writing to it you can see those
changes across both but you can be
reading independently with two
independent positions through this same
file just by opening it twice and then
so yeah question
reference comfy too so we've got two
different files and each has one file
descriptor pointing to it so it's two
different entries in the file table but
both point to the same file on disk and
so what this means is that they can keep
separate positions in reference counts
but ultimately they are you know
referring to the same bytes on disk so
one of the question is okay what happens
when we fork so we have a process and
it's got a couple open files here file a
and B are open point to some things on
disk and we're going to do fork so what
happens
so the descriptor table is one per
process so obviously we're going to have
to get a new descriptor table because we
got a new process through the fork but
what does it point to is all going to
point to the same entries in the file
table that the parent did both the
parent and the child have the same thing
so we get an extra reference count on
all of those and it's at the same
position that the parent was at when it
did the fork but they're still the same
you know it's still only two files on
disk
we're not copying and pasting files on
disk by doing a fork that would be a
resource nightmare make it very easy to
use up a lot of dismiss so okay so any
any questions about that
if sort of just duplicated all of these
errors on the on this side over here
okay and so then the part that you're
actually doing so you know you'll do a
fork you do fork and sometimes this
happened so you need to know what this
picture looks like but what you actually
need to implement for the last couple of
traces is i/o redirection we asked you
to be able to handle the carrot and I'll
care at the sort of greater than and
less than symbols which do i/o
redirection so that you can output to
something other than the terminal or
take input from a file and so the
function you'll want to use to do that
is a function called dupe - so dupe - is
after Dupin before dupe 3 neither of
those are as useful as dupe 2
doop to what it does is it takes to file
descriptors and old file descriptor in a
new file descriptor and it takes the
entry for old file descriptor and it
sets it to be equal to the entry for new
file description which I personally
think is kind of backwards because you
end up with two copies of old file
descriptor and no copies of a new file
descriptive but that's the way it's
named and if you look at all of the man
pages that they're going to have the
same old menu so what happened is we
gave it we gave it 4 1 so 4 is our old
file descriptor and 1 is our new file
descriptor and after the dupe 2 what
happens is both file descriptors are
pointing to the same file so what this
is doing is it's taking that arrow in
the file descriptor table so we have
this error for is pointing to B and 1 is
pointing to a and now we're going to do
it dupe 2 and what happens is now one is
also pointing to B so we're just taking
that arrow from the file descriptor
table and sending it equal to the other
arrow it's sort of like a pointer
aliasing thing that we're doing here and
then of course the ref counts change so
you know the the because it's the old
file
yeah the old file gets an increment and
it's reference count because it's got
another arrow pointing to it now and
then the other one gets its reference
count decremented and so in this case
this actually becomes 0 so it can be
closed if there were other arrows still
pointing to it it would remain open with
whatever reference kind of had before
the dupe to by decremented by 1 and so
now we have two different file
descriptors and if we write to either of
these it's going to write to the same
file B and so this will be useful for
you to make make your shells write to or
read from files other than standard in
and standard out any questions about
that yeah
possible aliasing bugs so what do you
worried my alias yeah yeah so they have
the same they have the same file table
with the same position in it and stuff
so if we're reading from one it's
changing this position that the other is
going to see so if we read from the
child and then read from the parent we
can't get we won't get like by a if the
first fight is by day we don't get it
twice we get by day and then whatever
comes after it yeah so you do have to
watch out for that if that's something
that might be bad any other questions
okay so a quick sneak preview of MATLAB
before we move on to virtual memory so
malloc lab you're going to be writing
your own storage allocated so you're
going to be implementing malloc free
realloc and kalloch so those are sort of
the four main functions for memory
allocation and so in class you're going
to be learning about different ways to
keep track of free and allocated blocks
so the purpose of the memory allocator
so you know these are the ways you get
heap allocated memory and the heap is
just this huge chunk of memory that you
know can be shared by all different
parts of your program and you need some
way of keeping track of which bytes are
being used by the program and which
bytes you're allowed to give back when
someone asks for more bytes with a
malloc or a cowlick and so you know the
way you know the way a user asks for
more vices they do malloc is they do
cowlick and the way they say I'm done
with these vices they do free but your
memory allocator needs to keep track of
well when I do a free how many bytes
were allocated that address that I'm now
allowed to use for whatever else and
stuff like that so you need to sort of
keep track of what memory is free and
what memory is allocated so that when
these different function calls come in
you can
give back memory appropriately so
there's a couple couple different ways
of keeping track of these they're called
like implicit linked lists explicit
linked lists segregated lists of
different sizes so sort of it's
different ways of prioritizing well what
do we want to do quickly do we want to
be able to quickly find free blocks do
we want to be able to quickly you want
to be efficient in how much memory were
actually using because you know the
thing is if I if I say say I've got a
you know the memory is just a big long
sequence of bytes if someone asked for
some bikes and I say okay here you can
have these bytes these are in use now
and they ask for some more bytes and I
say okay can have these bytes these are
induced now if someone asks for a chunk
of memory that's bigger than this we
can't give them this so it just remains
empty and so one of the things we are
concerned about is you know given an
arbitrary sequence of allocations and
fries how do we make sure that we
minimize the amount of unused space at
the end of the run because this is sort
of spaced that but we can't use it for
anything unless someone asks for an
amount this small it's effectively used
its effectively wasted if we never are
able to allocate it so that's one of the
things you're dealing with you're
dealing with you know can I get back
memory quickly and can I can I get back
memory in a way that overall I've
efficiently used the memory and haven't
left a bunch of empty space on the heap
that's not allocated for anything and so
you know there's there's agreement
you're going to make a bunch of
different design decisions about how
you're going to look for free chunks of
memory the linked list that you're using
to keep track of this deal want them to
just be singly or doubly linked and
stuff like coalescing so sort of if is
another thing so I have a chunk of
memory and I've got some allocated bits
and say this gets freed and then this
one gets freed now I actually have this
much free space so at some point it
would be nice to go along and say this
isn't true
all blocks this is one big block because
they're right next to each other and so
you'll have to be able to think about
things like that and make design
decisions about when and how that's
going to happen so pay attention in
class because the stuff that's talked
about in class will be very useful then
here's another thing about a version
control so if you're if you if you're
familiar with version control it might
be helpful for mallik lab if you're not
familiar with region control I wouldn't
recommend trying to learn it while doing
Malick lab I would instead recommend
just you know copying and pasting your
file every now and then and we're
submitting to OTO lab so that you have
backup copies of the different versions
in case you totally mess something up
and want to just say I want to undo my
last several hours of work it's it
happens sometimes or maybe you don't
want to undo it but you just want to
refer back to what it was because you
changed something you forgot how how it
was before and you knew that whatever
you did was wrong and you want to see
what it was before you doing it okay so
now we're going to talk about virtual
memory so there really isn't a lab on
virtual memory since this is sort of
between shell lab and Malak lab but this
is something that might be and really
probably will be on your final exam so
it's still something you need to know
and you know is also useful in terms of
understanding how computers work so so
far you know we've been talking about
memory and we just say you know we've
got this flat array of addresses and you
know the stack starts somewhere and
there's a heap somewhere and there's all
this other stuff on it but we're also
running multiple processes at one time
and you saw that in your shell lab you
know you've got a ton of processes you
know running all at the same time even
just that have been forked off by your
shell in addition to the other ones
running on the system and you know you
might open them up in gdb and notice
that sort of they're reading and writing
to addresses that are the same and so
the question is well how does that work
because they can't possibly be reading
and writing to the actual same addresses
otherwise they'd be constantly
corrupting each other and everything
would crash as soon as you opened a
second process and so the answer is
those aren't the actual addresses that
they're reading and writing - there's a
secret layer in between the process and
the actual hardware where the process is
writing to virtual addresses and then
the hardware is actually turning those
into real addresses in your RAM that are
distinct and disjoint so that nothing
conflicts with each other so the
question is how does it do this
because that sounds pretty fancy so you
have your program and it's got all of
its virtual addresses the ones that the
program sees that it gets to use and
then you've got some physical address
space and it actually turns out that the
physical address space is tends to be
smaller than the virtual address space
and this isn't too surprising because
the physical address space is actual
bytes that are addressable in your
computer in the actual hardware and your
computer probably has like somewhere
around a gigabytes of RAM no plus or
minus you know a factor of four you've
probably got somewhere between two and
thirty two gigabytes on any computer you
have and so you know that's a lot but
it's not nearly as much as can be
addressed with you know 64 bits and so
you know there's this you know there's
this physical space it's actually
smaller than the virtual space your
current current virtual addresses don't
even use the full 64 bits because that's
just way more than you ever need but
it's still more than what you get
physically and so what has to happen is
the virtual addresses that are used need
to map to real physical addresses so
sort of what we have here in this
diagram is we're saying well you know
because some virtual addresses up here
and it's going to map to this physical
address and this one to this one this
one to this one and then over here you
know these red ones you know there's
other processes and they also get
distinct physical addresses that this
process doesn't get to use they can't
share anything and over here we actually
even see that this virtual address maps
down to this physical address which is
in a totally different order than the
the virtual addresses are sort of these
these guys are below
in the virtual address space but above
it in the physical address space that's
perfectly fine the computer is just
going to translate from virtual
addresses to physical addresses in these
chunks and they don't need to maintain a
particular order they don't need to be
they don't need to be contiguous we can
interleave the physical spaces of the
different processes and that's fine so
this sort of this diagram makes sense
what we're doing here
yes virtual space then physical space
doesn't mean and some of the virtual
spaces they point to the same address in
a physical space or how to stuff so it
means that some of the virtual space is
not going to actually point to anything
in the physical space so we haven't used
the whole virtual space here there's
like big empty chunks and these aren't
going to map to any real memory and
we're not going to hopefully we're not
going to actually try to put anything in
them so it'll be okay that they don't
map to memory if eventually use more
virtual space than we have physical
space available our computer is going to
complain and it's either going to like
crash or just like refuse to run the
program or do something because it
literally doesn't have any more memory
left basic you can never use such a more
or is it where sometimes you
think about the virtual address space
with an engine so okay so there's a
couple a couple useful things about
having the big virtual space even with
the small physical space one is that we
want to be able to just compile our
programs and not care about how much RAM
is going to be on the computer that
they're going to run on so you know
theoretically we could quadruple our
physical space just by adding more RAM
and it would be nice if you know we had
a mapping like this where nothing about
the mapping had to change in terms of
like recompiling the program to now be
able to use more addresses so that's one
reason another reason to keep these sort
of separate concepts is that we want all
the processes to not be able to touch
each other's memory but theoretically
any one process could be using like most
or all of the memory depending on how
how many are running at a time we don't
know how much of the memory each process
is going to be allowed to have so we
want to sort of allow it to have you
know as much as as possible and then
only in the cases where we actually
don't have physical memory to support
more things deal with saying this is bad
rather than constricting it in the
virtual case and saying that we're not
going to allow you to write a program
that might use more memory that is a lot
yeah pointing to something at the disk
which is something on this yeah so these
will all point to things on in RAM is
what they do yeah not on the disk now
there's different mechanisms there's a
different thing called a page file these
are all called pages of memory and
there's a mechanism called page files
where what you can actually do is
reserved a chunk of dicks disk space
that ends up being like extra RAM and it
sort of just swaps between RAM and this
file on disk to treat it as this extra
chunk of memory that it can keep stuff
in
that's really slow because of the fact
that disk reads and writes are really
slow but in a way it makes it it makes
it almost as if you're pointing to
things on disk although it will load
them up into RAM before it can actually
use them every time does that make sense
okay any other questions about this
picture before we move on okay so yes
okay so here's a here's a different
picture of it so you know we've got
these virtual pages they're pointing to
physical pages we can actually in the
case of read-only code like a library
function so maybe we have our code for
printf for malloc or something and
everyone shares this and you can only
read it you can't write to it so in
those cases we can actually have a
couple different virtual pages pointing
to the same physical page which is nice
we've actually reduced the amount of RAM
we have to use but for the most part the
pages are distinct so okay so let's say
so we need a couple different things so
we need a page table so all of these you
know we block up memory into chunks we
don't want to do it one bite at a time
so we block it up into chunks and those
are called pages so we can look up in a
page table the translation from virtual
addresses to physical addresses so you
know you give it a virtual address and
it's going to tell you okay this is the
physical address that you need to go to
to get that we're going to have
something special called the translation
lookaside buffer so we'll get to the
details of that later but essentially
it's a special cache to make these
lookups to this table faster and it's
implemented the same way as the caches
that we've seen before
and of course we can sort of take this
idea and just iterate it a bit and
instead of just having you know one one
translation from virtual to physical we
can sort of put several layers and each
layer you know does a little bit more
and then you sort of get a hierarchy
where you can say all of these things
you know are and you know chunk it up
and say like all of these things are
unmapped and then you don't have to put
them in your page table
it's sort of like a it's almost like a
bounding volume hierarchy if you if
you've done any computer graphics it's
sort of a way of describing a whole
bunch of pages all at once in different
levels of this we'll look at a quick
example of that at the end so okay so
how does this address translation
actually work so you know we actually
you know we have a virtual address how
are we going to get into a physical
address so what we're going to say here
is that we're going to have a virtual
address space and there's going to be n
possible virtual addresses so that means
that each one is n bits long right and
bits gives you 2 to the n - 2 where n is
you know 2 to the n lower case n lower
case n bits gives you 2 to the N
possible addresses and similarly with
the physical address space there's going
to be M physical addresses so lower case
M is going to be the log of uppercase M
so that we get 2 to the M equals M
uppercase M okay and then we're going to
have pages with size P so what that
means is that the address offset is
going to be lowercase P and what the
address offset is is you know how far
into the page we need to go to get a
particular byte of memory this is very
similar to like how we had block offset
in caches if we had that number where we
said ok we've got this chunk of memory
we've looked it up how far into it do we
have to go to get the one we're looking
at that's what this address offset is
we've got a page of memory how far into
it do we have to go to get the byte we
actually want and we're going to make
these two the same we're going to make
the offset for virtual pages and
physical pages the same so that the
translation between them is just the
identity function we just copy it over
we don't have to change it at all that
makes things faster so ok so here's a
diagram maybe a little bit confusing
with all of these arrows but here's
what's happening so we've got a virtual
address that we want to look up so we
split it up we've got
the offset based on how big our pages
are the lower bits of it are going to be
the offset and the upper bits are going
to index into a virtual page number this
is very much like how we had sort of a
set index in a and a block offset in our
caches and so we've got our page table
which starts at some page table based
registered which is you know just stored
somewhere else for the process and each
entry in the page table was a
combination of a valid bit and then the
physical page number that this address
this virtual page should actually go to
so we look up our virtual address we're
going to do a couple things so if it
happens that the valid bit is zero then
what that means is that we don't have
the page in our memory right now it's a
page fault and so we talked about faults
last week you know what we can do is we
can go and handle this fault
and hopefully the kernel will be able to
load up some memory and put it in our
page table for us and then it'll reacts
accute that instruction and try to get
this memory again and so that's what
happens if the velebit is 0 if the valid
bit is 1 then we know that we actually
have a physical page corresponding to
this virtual address and so you know ok
so this page fault thing is to continue
the analogy with caches is similar to
when you do a cache miss and you have to
go load something up and now you know
you can do it again it'll work so then
we put in this virtual page number index
into the table say the valid bit is 1
now it maps to a physical page number so
in order to actually construct our
physical address we just copy over the
page offset because we've said let's
make them the same size so that they're
always the same and then we take the
physical page number that we got based
on the lookup in the virtual page number
and we smash them together and now we've
got a real physical address and if we go
there and Ram will get the address that
we were looking for it will get the the
bytes that we were requested to get by
the program with its virtual address so
does that sort of make sense what's
going on here cut it in half use the
page number to look up a physical page
number and then put them together if it
fails then the operating system
handles loading up a new page for us
okay so here we have okay an example so
we've got fourteen bits for a virtual
address is 12 for a physical and we said
the page size is 64 bytes so what that
means you know thirteen or fourteen bits
of virtual 12 bits of physical and then
since we have 64 byte page sizes that
means we need six bits to index into
them because two to the sixth is 64 so
our offsets are going to be six six of
these bits and then the rest are for the
page numbers okay so here's an example
now so I just told you the answer the
first part pages are 64 bytes how many
bits is the offset it's six because two
to the six is 64 so do two six equals 64
64 because what we know is that is that
the number of bits we have the page size
is equal to two to the number of bits in
the offset plus the formula from before
so this is 64 so that means lower case P
is 6 ok so here's an example that we're
going to do so why don't we want to find
0 3 d 4 and we've been given this page
table and so we're going to fill out
we're going to first find out you know
the virtual page number and then the
physical page number and then construct
the actual address ok so let's start
with the virtual page number so okay so
we've got fits 13 12 11 10 9 8 7 6 5 ok
so what is our address or address is 0 3
d 4 so how do we fill in if just we've
realized that this is the VPO and the V
and ok so I want to fill in the bits of
this address what are the bits of this
address let's uh let's go from low to
high what are the first what are the
first four bits
we're doing a hex to binary conversion
here 0 0 1 both plus 1 0
okay okay so this gives us this gives us
a 4 yeah this gives us 4 right so 2 to
the 2 is 4
okay and so what's the next byte the
next byte is d so what's D D is equal to
let's see a is 10 B is 11 C is 12 D is
13 so we want to somehow get to 13 so
what's that that's about 8 12 13 right 2
to 3 plus 2 to the 4 plus another one ok
so the next byte is 3 so how do we get 3
thanks someone knows 3 what's 3 what I
know I have a byte there's 4 bits in it
how do I get the number 3 there was 0 1
1 ok here 0 1 1 and then the last one is
0 how do I get 0 hopefully well no this
yeah just zeros okay very good so ok so
now we have we have the bits
corresponding to this address so we
determined before that there's 6 bits
for the virtual page offset and then the
remainder are the virtual page number so
this is our virtual page number so what
number is this in hex because it looks
like our table is indexed by hacks what
is it
okay so this is zero X F we've
translated this part into 0 X F x0 F ok
so what do we do so we've got the
virtual page number right that's what we
just figured out here virtual page
number now we want the physical page
number so how do we get the physical
page number yeah we just look at the
table so the table says virtual page
number is F what is the physical page
number it's D okay and look the valid
bit is 1 if it weren't 1 we want to be
able to use that entry same as caches
but the valid bit is 1 so that means our
physical page number is D ok so what's D
in binary let's write this out again we
get let's see 1 2 3 4 5 ok so D we
already figured out D D was over here
right 1 1 0 1 and we've got 2 6 of these
ok so what's in our physical page offset
then it's the same right we just copied
this over they're the same size and that
makes it convenient because we can just
copy it over they're going to be the
same offset because we're keeping these
pages the same size ok so now we just
have to translate this back into hex so
what was that that was a for that one
what's that that looks like 1 plus 4 is
like what 5 like doing that right and
then we use that it 0 X 3 5 4 yep okay
so what did we do so we figured out that
the page offset was 6 because we knew 64
bytes so we just took the log we filled
out the bits here by doing hex to binary
which was quite the struggle so maybe
you should practice that and then we you
know we just took this upper half and
looked it up in the table to get the
physical page number and then we copied
that down there and now this becomes a
new hex number that's our physical
address yes
first our en+ video so people um plus
BPO we knew because what we said at the
beginning was the addresses are 14 bits
so then it's just going to be VPN is the
number of bits in the address minus the
number of bits in the offset you'll be
you'll be given some numbers that
correspond you'll be given enough
numbers that you can figure out the
remaining ones the standard 464 I think
is a 40 bits but that would be a bit one
yes or like we're not going to do that
the this that's used right now by Intel
machines is 40 I mean ideally in the
future they would scale all the way up
to the full 64 because that's how many
is supported but right now we don't need
that much RAM and so you might as well
not spend time translating that rest is
that big okay so that's that one okay so
then there's the whole translation
lookaside buffer thing so right now you
know we just did this one and we didn't
have a translation lookaside buffer
implemented and what that means is that
you're going to do twice the number of
memory accesses you know that we have in
our code because what we have to do is
first we have to go to memory to get
this page table and and do this
translation and then we have to go to
memory again to get the actual thing
there so you know it would be nice if we
could when we're accessing addresses
repeatedly because we know you know
locality we tend to do that we tend to
access the same addresses over and over
it'd be great if we didn't have to go to
memory to do this translation especially
if we've just done it and so the
solution to that is the translation
lookaside buffer so this is a special
cache that is used by this memory
mapping device in order to keep track of
some of the information that I might be
reusing over and over so what we're
going to do is we're going to take
the VPN part just the VPN part not the
whole thing you don't care about the
offset that's just being copied over
we're going to take this and this is
going to become something that gets
split up into an index in a tag and goes
into a cache so now we're going to
repeat the cache recitation so what do
we have so we said okay this in this
case this is a new example I don't know
if I should I guess I'm going to erase
this one so to leave the top of it up
for now what we're doing so we're going
to have one megabyte of virtual memory
we're going to have 256 kilobytes of
physical memory four kilobyte pages and
in our translation lookaside buffer has
eight entries in its 2-way
set-associative so now we've got a
couple questions that we have to answer
you should be good at this sort of stuff
because this is the sort of stuff
they'll be expected to do efficiently on
the final exam for instance so how many
bits are needed to represent the virtual
address space got one megabyte
20 ok so we're going to say 20 so we
want to do log base 2 of 2 to the 20
Evil's 1 okay cool it works ok and we
have so this is how many bits
I guess we'll label them 1 2 3 4 5 and 6
so that's that's part 1 how many bits
are needed for the virtual address space
so we took 1 megabyte that's 2 to the 20
bikes how many bits do you need it take
log base 2 you need 20 ok how many bits
are needed to represent the physical
address space we've got 256 kilobytes so
what's 256 kilobytes the kilobyte is 2
to the 10 so we're doing log or 2 of 2
to the 10 times 256 that's what 2 to the
8 times 2 to the 8 equals 18 does that
work out that seems to work out because
that's 2 less than this and their factor
for different so that seems believable
ok how many bits are needed to represent
the offset someone else answered this
one so we've got 4 kilobyte page size
how many bits do we need to represent
the offset
twelve okay yeah so how did we get that
we want to take log base two of the page
size so what's the page size it's well a
kilobyte is two to the ten and then four
is two to the two so then the log base
two of that is just twelve
okay so twelve bits for the page size
okay now what do we know we say that the
translation lookaside buffer is eight
entries 2-way set-associative and we
want to know how many bits are needed to
represent the virtual page number and
then how many bits how many bits are in
the TLB indexed and how many bits are in
the tag okay so part four how big is the
virtual page number we know that this is
our virtual address space sighs this is
our physical address space size and this
is our offset size our page offset so
okay so how many how many bits do we
need to represent just the virtual page
number part of our addresses eight yeah
okay so how did we get eight so eight
bits how did we get it from these
numbers I only see one reasonable way to
combine these to get a we took the
number of bits in our virtual address
space and subtracted out the number of
bits used for the offset because the
virtual address space the bits are just
split into the page number and the
offset we've got the patient over here
and we've got the offset here so if we
have 20 bits total and this is 12 of
them then the remaining ones have eight
okay so we've got eight bits for a
virtual page number and now we're going
to use these Inc bits so that's all
great this happens to be eight okay so
we have eight bits and we want to use
them as an index as a entry that we're
going to cache so we're only using the
virtual page number part of it we don't
care about the offset so how do we know
so we want to know how many bits are in
the index and how many bits are in the
tag and we know that it's 8 entries
2-way set-associative okay so the
question is how many sets are there
total it's the first question we're
going to ask how many sets are there in
this cache 16 so there's 8 lines and
2-way associative so force that's right
so there's 4 sets and each one has two
lines in it okay
so the index is used the set index is
used to get the set how many bits do we
need for the set index if we have four
sets - yeah two bins two bits for the
set index this is the TLB index he'll be
indexed and then how many bits do we
need for the tag
what was the answer just the rest yeah
yeah so this is the same cache stuff
we've used before you know you have your
address so your caching and so sort of
have your set index and you've got your
tag and in this case we don't have a
block offset because that's not what
we're doing so we've just got the
remaining six bits as your TLB tag so
then when we want to look something up
in the translation lookaside buffer we
first cut off this virtual page number
and then we can cut off two bits check
and see if there's an entry at that set
number so this would be set three
because we've got one one and we check
well is there tag that matches this so
this is three again is there something
in one of those two lines that has
tagged three and if there is well then
what that can do is that can just give
us back the correct physical page number
right away and we didn't have to go all
the way down to main memory to the page
table to look it up we sort of bypassed
the page table and just got it straight
out of the lookaside buffer okay so now
you know sort of out of time so I'm just
going to skip through this quickly but
you can check the slides online if you
want to see it in more detail so sort of
what we did but actually maybe maybe I
won't go through quickly because I don't
want you to see the answers if you want
to go through yourself but what we do
you know we we have the translation
lookaside buffer so we're going to do
the same thing where we fill in the bits
but now we can check and see if it's in
the buffer or not if it's in this buffer
then we can just give back the physical
page number that we had before if it's
not then we have to go all the way to
the page table which is in the memory
any questions
okay