good afternoon everybody welcome good to
see you as always
today we're going to learn about a
important concept in computer science
called virtual memory so consider a
system that uses physical addressing
right we've always our idea about memory
so far has been that it's a a contiguous
array of physical physical bytes that we
can access just by giving some an offset
called an address so in a system that
uses physical addressing the CPU
executes like say a move instruction
which generates an effective address the
physical address and this address is
actually the offset of a byte in in main
memory so you know here the CPU has
generated a physical address of four
since that address to the to the memory
and then the memory fetches the the word
from at that address and then sends it
back to the to the CPU now this is in
fact the way that very simple
microcontrollers work but it's not the
way most systems work including your
your phones your desktops your servers
these systems instead virtualize this
this main memory now the idea of
virtualization is a very important one
in computer science and it and it
expands a lot of it applies to a lot of
areas of computer systems now when you
virtualize a resource you you present
the user of that resource with some
different kind of view of that resource
you present typically some kind of an
abstraction or some kind of a different
view of the resource and you do it by
interposing on accesses to that resource
so in all cases there's some resource
and you want to virtualize it and you do
that by
cepting or interposing on the accesses
to that resource okay and then once you
we saw this when we created wrapper
functions for like malloc when I was
showing you inter positioning the same
technique is used to virtualize a
resource and and once you've intercepted
that access then you can deal with it
any way you want so that's how you have
sort of full power to change a person to
change the view of that resource okay so
a good example you saw this when we
looked at disks and you know physically
disk consists of cylinders tracks
sectors platters surfaces and and to
access a particular sector on one of
those disks you have to specify the
cylinder and the track and the surface
okay but we saw that the view that disk
controller is present is actually
different it's a virtualized view of the
disk and the controller instead presents
to the kernel a view of the disk as a
series of a sequence of logical blocks
and it presents that view by
intercepting the requests from the seat
from the kernel for i/o and changing
those logical block numbers that that
that the kernel sends into the actual
physical address ok so that's a very
very important example of virtualization
in a system now the the memory is is
that is a very is it is a crucial
resource in the system and what we found
is that it's it's useful to virtualize
that that memory resource okay and the
way this is done remember before we
virtually the disk by having the disk
controller intercept request in the case
of the the main memory resource the
requests are actually intercepted by a
piece of hardware called the MMU the
memory management unit so the way this
works is that the CPU executes an
instruction say it's a move instruction
that generates some effect
of address so this is actually a virtual
address
it's the CPU sends that address to the
MMU
which goes through a process called
address translation which will will
study later today and it converts that
virtual address in this case 4 1 0 0
into a physical address 4 which actually
corresponds to the address of that the
data object that we want ok so once once
the MMU translates the virtual address
to a physical address then the memory
will return the the word at that at that
address so this might wonder why in the
world would you want to do this well it
turns out there's all kinds of good
reasons to virtualize the the address
space and so before I can explain those
to you I let me just define a few a few
toff you terms so a an address space is
a set of addresses ok so an address
spaces is a set not of not of data bytes
but of the addresses of those bytes and
a linear address space is a content is a
contiguous set of contiguous
non-negative integers okay so just 0 1 2
3 4 5 and so on the virtual address
space is a set of n equal to 2 the end
virtual addresses a linear it's a linear
address space and the physical address
space is a set of m equal to M physical
addresses ok
and so typically the virtual address
space is is is usually much larger than
the physical address space okay the
physical address space corresponds to
the amount of DRAM that you actually
have in the system the virtual address
space is the same for all all processes
running on that system okay now why why
do we want to implement virtual memory
why do this why do I do this level of
indirection with the MMU well there's
really three big reasons so the first is
that virtual memory uses the uses the
DRAM as a cache for the actual data
stored on disk okay so you can think of
virtual memory as it as a dram cache for
data stored on the disk and this allows
us to to use the memory much more
efficiently because we only need to
cache items that are frequently used
right just the same idea that we learned
when we we talked about caches and
locality so that's one thing we can use
we can use the memory much more
efficiently by only using the portions
of the virtual address space by only
actually storing the portions of the
virtual address space in the physical
memory okay the second thing is it
greatly simplifies memory management so
we saw it every process has the same the
same view right there's code loaded at
code and data are always loaded at the
same address the stack is at the top of
the user visible address space so every
process has the same similar-looking
virtual address space but in actual in
actuality that the the memory that
corresponds to those those addresses is
actually scattered all over main memory
okay so so that's a really important
important benefit of virtual memory and
then finally it allows us to protect
accesses so remember we had to
a process we saw that a process provides
the separate address space that's that's
protected from accesses by other
processes
okay so virtual memory allows us to
create these these separate protected
private address spaces okay and so what
we'll do today we'll look in more detail
at these three ideas and then we'll and
then we'll go into the specifics of
address translation so I'm going to for
the first the first part of this lecture
we're going to talk about address
translation just in kind of high-level
terms but then we'll go into the details
at the end you can see how it how it
really works okay so let's look at VM as
a tool for caching so conceptually you
can think of the your virtual memory as
a sequence of bytes stored on disk okay
and then the contents of that of the the
contents of that virtual memory stored
on disk are cached in DRAM okay so think
of the the DRAM is a cache for this this
array of contiguous bytes stored on the
disk and just like any cache the data is
broken up into blocks okay and then we
have so so here we have the and those
blocks for virtual memory systems are
called pages they're typically typically
larger than much larger than the cache
blocks that we that we study done so for
K bytes typically instead of the 64
bytes like that we that we learned about
in when we studied cache memories so
this virtual memory conceptually you can
think of it as as being a sequence of
pages stored on the disk so called
virtual pages and each of these pages
will identify with a number so here's
virtual page 0 virtual page 1 and then a
subset of those pages are stored in in
the physical memory in the physical DRAM
memory and then there's some mapping
function that tells us which pages have
been cached ok so in this case I've just
shown a snapshot
where we have three virtual pages cached
somewhere in DRAM okay and there there's
no relation between the virtual page
number and the the physical page number
that it's mapped to some of these pages
are are not cached so they're at they're
still stored on disk so in this case VP
2 is still stored on disk and there's
some pages which aren't even allocated
so they're they don't exist on the disk
yet it's a way to think of that right
because we really wouldn't want to store
every single page in address space with
that's to the size to the 48th we really
wouldn't want to store all those those
on disk so most of the address space is
unallocated ok so we can just think of
this so this this DRAM is just a cache
but it has a much different organization
than the cache memories we studied
earlier and the difference is driven by
that the enormous miss penalty when you
go from if you have a cache and DRAM the
the Miss penalty would to fetch a data
item from the disk is huge so the the
design of this virtual memory cache is
totally driven by this enormous miss
penalty and so as a result that blocks
are larger so remember we talked about
that the block size is kind of a
trade-off between sort of useful getting
used being able to usefully amortize the
cost of fetching that block versus sort
of consuming too much of this scarce
cache space right so in this case our
cache memories were 64 byte blocks
virtual most virtual memory systems have
like 4 K byte blocks with with an option
to increase to 4 megabytes in the case
of x86
and now this cash and other consequence
of the enormous missed penalty is that
you really want to have as large
associativity as you can remember we saw
with direct mapped cache --is that were
subject to to these conflict misses and
and if you if you increase the
associativity of the cache you reduce
the the probability of those conflict
misses but you never completely
eliminate them until you have a fully
associative cache with just one set okay
so in a virtual memory in a virtual
memory cache it's fully associative
there's one set and each virtual page
can go anywhere in the cache okay so
this requires a really complicated
mapping function somehow we're going to
have to keep track of where all these
cached pages are and we can't really do
a search that would be that would be way
too inexpensive so you remember when we
with a cache memory the hardware
actually did a search within the set a
parallel search to to to find try to
find a cache line but with a software
cache like this that that's not feasible
all right so somehow we're going to have
to remember where these cached blocks
are in this very large set and again
because it's so expensive if you make a
mistake when you're trying to identify a
victim victim page if you make a mistake
and you evict a page that then is
referenced again in the near future you
pay a big price for it okay so virtual
memory caches have much more
sophisticated replacement algorithms
than like simple LRU that that we saw
with cache memories now they're these
replacement algorithms are outside of
the scope of this course you'll you'll
you'll learn about them and when you
take os but because it's in software we
can we can afford to do very expensive
replacement algorithms and we can take a
long fairly relatively long time to
execute the code for those algorithms
because any time we spend
figuring out a victim block will be much
less than the cost of making a mistake
and paying the the access time the miss
time the miss penalty to to disk and
then also as a result of virtual memory
systems never use right through just
because it takes to one right so they
always use right back and they try to
defer writing anything back to the disk
as long as possible alright now how do
we keep track somehow we have to keep
track of this complicated cache and DRAM
and the the data structure that keeps
track of the location of the virtual
pages in in memory is called the page
table now a page table is just a data
structure in memory that the kernel
maintains for as part of each process
context okay so every process has its
own page table and it's just a it's an
array of so called page table entries or
PT es where PT ek contains the physical
address of physical page K in DRAM okay
so here's how it works there's there's
this page table in DRAM there's virtual
pages stored on disk and then there's
their stuff and then there's physical
there's virtual pages stored in various
physical pages in DRAM and then the page
table keeps track of where those are
stored so here we have a case this PT e
1 corresponds to virtual page 1 and in
this case it says that virtual page 1 is
mapped into physical page 0 virtual page
2 is mapped into physical page 1 and so
on ok now some of these the pages that
aren't in memory are stored on disks the
allocated pages and so for those pages
the page table entry contains a pointer
to the location of that that page on
disk so think of it as a logical block
number where that page can be found on
the disk and then some of the pages are
not allocated so there's there's a null
null entry in the page table
now a page hit so this is just a cache
right so we have hits and misses so a
page hit occurs when there's a reference
to a word and vert in the virtual
address space that's contained in a page
that's cached in the DRAM okay so let's
say that we have you know the CPU
execute this and move instruction it
generates a virtual address the MMU
looks up in the page table and let's say
this virtual address is somewhere within
virtual page two okay so that the MMU
looks up the page table entry number two
and it fought it extracts the physical
address of that of that virtual page -
okay so that's a hit so in this case in
this case the the page is in memory it's
cached in memory and so we have a hit
and now the the memory can can return
that can return that physical address to
the MMU okay
now a Miss is a reference to a word
that's not cashed in in in physical
memory so in this case virtual page 0 1
2 3 is not cached in DRAM it's stored
it's stored on the disk so now that
triggers a an exception ok page fault
exception in the hardware the hardware
triggers the exception and that causes
the transfer of control to a chunk of
code in the kernel called the page fault
handler which then selects a victim to
be evicted in this case virtual page
four and it fetches virtual page three
from the disk loads it up into memory
and if and then changes and and then
updates this page table entry to reflect
the fact that virtual page four is now
stored on disk and if virtual page four
had been modified at any time it would
have to write the contents of it that to
disk as well so once the once the
handler is copied virtual page three
into memory the instruction that caused
the page fault now can be re executed
okay so once the so when the page fault
handler in the kernel returns it returns
to the faulting instruction which then
reacts Acutes and now that page is when
the MMU checks that the Pte
corresponding to that page it finds that
it's indeed cache so so now the
instruction can continue and we can
fetch that whatever whatever word at
that virtual address from from the DRAM
okay now we can we can allocate a new
page of memories so in this example
virtual page 0 1 2 3 4 5 is not
allocated so if you need to let's say
you do malloc of a very large chunk of
virtual address space if if those pages
if one of those pages hasn't been
allocated yet then the kernel actually
or the malloc function actually has to
create allocate that memory by calling a
function called s break okay and then
what s break does is actually allocates
this this page and records where it's
loaded now would probably actually put
it up into now I guess it would it would
it wouldn't actually show up in that in
the DRAM cache until it was that page
was touched
okay so just allocating space just
changes this page table entry and then
when that page is actually touched then
it'll be brought into the cache so I
don't know about you but the first time
I learned about this I was I was pretty
appalled it just seemed like the most
inefficient terrible idea right how in
the world can you afford to on every
single every single instruction that
that uses memory do all this copying
back and forth and looking up in tables
and it just seems like an awful idea
but once again locality saves us okay
and it it actually works because
programs have locality okay and it it's
actually fairly efficient and the reason
is that at any point of time programs
tend to access a set of pages called the
working set okay just by locality right
by by temporal locality by the principle
of temporal locality and spatial
locality you tend to sort of reuse the
same things reuse nearby things okay and
so if that working set is less than the
main memory size then all of the pages
in the current were
that will fit in memory and then things
will be great okay but if the some of
the working set sizes for for every
process right our systems running
multiple processes if it exceeds the
main memory size then you have this this
meltdown where processes are thrashing
each other and causing pages to be
copied back and forth so you never ever
know process ever gets it's working set
fully into into memory okay and we'll
look at a technique when we look at
address translation we'll look at a
little hardware cache called a
translation lookaside buffer that that
further exploits the locality property
of programs okay so that's virtual
memory is a tool for caching it's also a
member of tool for memory management and
it greatly simplifies all kinds of
aspects of memory management for the
kernel so the key idea is that each
process has its own virtual address
space the kernel the kernel implements
this by giving each process its own
separate page table in the context of
that process so it's it's just a data
structure in the kernel that the process
key that the kernel keeps for that
process and the the page table for each
process Maps the virtual address space
for that process now what's interesting
so you have that these these pages
contiguous pages in the virtual address
space can be mapped anywhere in the in
the in the DRAM in the physical address
space so and they can be scattered all
over the place
and different virtual pages and
different processes can be mapped to
different physical pages so here we have
virtual page one which is mapped to
physical page two in process one but in
process two virtual page one is mapped
to physical page eight okay so in this
way we can present a view to two each to
the programmer and to the tools that
each process has
a very similar address space virtual
address space same size address space
code and data start at the same place
but then the actual pages that that
process used can be scattered in memory
okay and then it gives us the most
efficient way to use the memory if we
didn't have this mechanism think about
how would you keep track let's say you
had 50 processes running on the machine
at any point in time how in the world
would you keep track of where all of the
the data those processes were using well
one technique that you could imagine in
fact it was used in the in the bad old
days
but before virtual memory one thing you
can imagine is that just give every
process its own chunk of the physical
address space just take your physical
address space partition it and then each
process gets loads and runs and it's its
own part of the address space well this
has all kinds of problems right I mean
you could if you what do you do if you
add a process so you really can't
partition the address space you really
have to sort of say well each process
gets some little chunk and I'm going to
reserve some of the address space in
case there's new processes that need
memory another problem is that now you
have to write your programs
you can't just link your program ahead
of time because it has to be relocated
when it's loaded right because you don't
you know a process you don't know where
in the memory it's going to go it's
going to get some chunk so you have to
either relocate all the the references
that the references to global symbols at
when it's actually loaded or you have to
create a system where all of the
instructions are relative so there's
there's no absolute addresses all
addresses are relative to say the start
of the program something like that so
anyway all of these things are just
terribly complicated and they're all
solved beautifully by virtual memory
so the each virtual page can be mapped
to any physical page so that really
helps simplify things and even at
different times the same virtual page
can be stored in different physical
pages at different times
all right so if a page for it for a
while it might be cached in one physical
page then it gets swapped out and the
next time it's referenced it can get
cached in a different physical page if
that if it's no longer available right
so it provides so the most flexible
scheduling freedom in the way that we in
the way that we manage the memory and it
also provides this really neat
capability where you can map virtual
pages to the same physical page so
there's this is a very simple
straightforward way for multiple
processes to share certain code or data
okay and what what you do is you just
that the page table entry in these
different processes just points to the
same physical page so in this case
virtual page two points to physical page
six in each of in each of the page
tables for process 1 and process 2 so
this is how shared libraries are
implemented right so Lipsy is the same
code for every process running on the
system so Lipsy just needs to be loaded
once into physical into physical memory
and then processes that want to access
functions and data in Lib C just map the
pages in their virtual address space to
the physical pages where Lib C is
actually loaded ok so now there's only
one copy of Lib C everywhere in the
system but every process thinks it's got
its own copy
now this this virtual memory for met
using virtual memory to help simplify
memory management greatly simplifies
linking and loading ok for the reasons I
mentioned before linkers now can assume
that every every program is going to be
loaded at exactly the same place so the
linker knows ahead of time where
everything is going to be and then it
can resolve it can relocate all those
references accordingly now it really
makes loading as simple so what so x AK
ve the loader if you want to load a
program now exec ve looks at the elf
binary the executable binary ok it sees
how it identifies how big the code and
the data sections in that binary are it
allocates virtual memory starting at a
fixed address for the code and data ok
it creates PT es for them and marks each
of them is invalid ok so each each PT e
contains a valid mapping so each PT e
that's mapped to code and data contains
a valid physical page number but then
the it does this trick of setting the
valid bit to 0 so when the when the MMU
X encounters a PT e whose valid bit is 0
it triggers a page fault right it looks
as though that page is not has not been
initialized yet so it's kind of a trick
right and then that triggers a page
fault to the kernel and then the kernel
will then can then copy that that page
into into physical memory ok so this the
the loading actually programs and data
aren't actually they're not low loaded
you know they're not just like copied
into memory it happens as a result of
of page faults it happens as a result of
misses when and it's deferred to until a
bite in that page is accessed okay so
this is called demand paging okay but
it's really just like any any of the
other caches we've looked at right you
don't you don't load a block into the
cache until a word within that block is
is accessed okay so so loading actually
so loading is actually this is a very
efficient mechanism right because you
may have a program that contains a huge
say a huge array a large array but
you're only accessing a portion of that
array so that that entire array won't
actually be be allocated the pages will
only come into DRAM when they're when a
word within that page is touched so if
you're only accessing a portion of this
extremely large array only the data that
you access gets gets loaded and used so
it's a it's a very very smart mechanism
and extremely helpful for for allowing
us to use this precious memory resource
okay so the third the third motivation
for virtual memory is that it helps us
protect portions of memory so you recall
that our processes
you know portions of our virtual address
space or read-only like the the code
section okay and there are other
portions of the address space that can
only be executed by the kernel okay so
on on systems like x86 64 it's it's a
64-bit system so the pointers and
addresses or 64 bits but in actuality
the real virtual address space is 48
bits okay so it's it's only it's 2 to
the 48th and then the the high-order
bits after bit 48 are either all zeros
or all
okay so and that's so that's just the
that's the that sort of Intel's rule
okay for and so the the addresses where
the high order bits are all ones are
reserved for the kernel the kernels code
and the kernels data okay
the addresses were all the bits are zero
or reserved for user code okay so so any
reference any address that contains all
ones in those higher order bits is by
definition either code or data in the
kernel and so you can you can add bits
to the Pte that specify whether certain
virtual pages can be accessed by user
code or if they have to be accessed by
the by the kernel so this so-called
supervisor mode and you can also add
bits that control whether that that page
can be read written or executed okay so
this this executes bit is new with x86
64 it didn't exist in 32-bit x86 systems
and this is that this is the this is the
technique that's used now to try to
prevent against attack lab code
injection style attacks because it makes
it impossible if this bit is set you
can't load instructions from from any
any byte within that page and so in fact
it was it was this the introduction of
this execute bit that's or led to things
like return-oriented programming attacks
like you did in your attack lab okay so
this by just the simple technique of
adding adding bits to the Pte we provide
a way attic way to to protect different
parts of our virtual address space from
unauthorized accesses and then the the
MMU actually checks these bits on each
access and if there's if there's a
problem you know if if you're trying to
do a right and the right the right
that's not enabled then it throws an
exception which then the kernel the
colonel deals with ok so so far I've
been talking about address translation
it kind of high-level high-level terms
so let's let's get down to details and
see how it really works
okay so we're given a virtual address of
n elements physical address of M
elements like I said before n is usually
larger than M but it doesn't have to be
okay it's perfectly there's no reason m
M could be much larger than n and there
it's typically not but but it could be
and so given these two address spaces we
have a map function that takes that maps
from V to P with an optional empty set
or with an additional empty set and so
for virtual address a map a is equal to
a prime if the data at virtual address a
is a physical address a prime okay so I
mean that's just what we it's just a
little more formal way to say what we've
been talking about before with our
diagrams and then map a is the empty set
if the data at virtual address a is not
in physical memory okay so just for a
summary I'm going to put up a list of
all the symbols we're going to be using
in address translation but this is just
for summary this is just for reference
if you're using the slides later on okay
so here's how address translation where
the page table works so we're given some
virtual address that consists of n bits
and we have blocks that consists of
whose size can be represented with P
bits okay
so think about this now thee so this is
very similar to what we looked at when
we did caching you know the address bits
for a cache so these first P bits
correspond to the page offset so this is
analogous to the blocks offsets that we
saw with caches and then the remaining
bits correspond to the the virtual page
number this is so member this is fully
associative right so there's only one
set so in a fully associative cache
everything after the block offset is
tagged so think of this as like a tag
this is the this is what uniquely
identifies this block and we in virtual
memory parlance we refer to it as a
virtual page number now the page table
the beginning of the page table is
pointed to by this page table based
register on intel systems that's it's
called cr3 control register 3 but this
reg this register contains the physical
address of the page table in memory ok
the beginning of that and so when the
when the CPU presents a virtual page a
virtual address to the MMU it it takes
the virtual page number and uses that as
an index into the page table ok and then
it and then it into and that identifies
a page table entry which contains if
this is mapped into memory I contains
the physical address of the of the
corresponding physical page ok so the
whole purpose of address translation is
to come up you're given a virtual
address and you want to come up with a
corresponding physical address ok so the
physical address the physical the
physical page number portion of the
physical address comes out of the page
table entry and this is interesting the
the physical page offset portion of the
physical address comes out of the
virtual page offset and it those bits
are identical
okay so now you should you should
convince yourself that this is true
right the the the offset in a virtual
block is going to be the same as the
offset in a physical block they're the
same size blocks and and you can also
see why this virtual page number it
identifies the the that the page number
in the in the page table so imagine so
imagine a virtual address that's all
zeros okay all zeros so it's virtual
address zero and now that that will have
a virtual page number of zero and the
byte at that address will be at offset
zero
okay now increment by one virtual
address one so that will be in an offset
of 1 and it will be in the same virtual
page of zero right now keep incrementing
until all of the all of the bits in the
virtual page offset are ones and the
virtual page numbers is zero okay so
this is the last byte in in that virtual
page zero now increment one more time
the one bit carries over to the virtual
page number so now now we go to the next
virtual page and it's at an offset of
zero okay so so can you see it's it's
it's sort of sort of obvious when you
think about it like that you know why we
can just take these these bits after the
virtual page offset and use them to
uniquely identify what virtual page were
we're working with okay so let's see how
I let's see how it works in this system
in more detail so our system our CPU
sends a virtual address to the MMU as a
result of executing a move instruction
or call or return or any kind of control
transfer the MMU looks up the the Pte so
it fetches the Pte from the page
cable stored in memory so this is
actually going off the chip onto memory
into this Pte stored in memory it gets
the it fetches the Pte extracts the and
uses that Pte to construct the physical
address okay and then it it sends that
physical address to the cache and memory
system which eventually results in the
data being returned back to the CPU okay
so even for a hit
we still have memory references right
because we have to fetch that that page
table entry
now miss is in this parlance is called a
page fault so in this case the same
thing happens as before that the CPU
sends the virtual address to the MMU
Yemen the MMU fetches that the Pte for
memory but then when it looks then when
the MMU looks at the Pte it sees that
there's either an invalid valid bit or a
zero valid bit or the the it's indicated
that the data stored on disk and so in
that case it the MMU triggers a page
fault exception which transfers control
to this page fault handler the handler
identifies a victim and if it's been
modified copies it out to disk then it
fetches the new page from disk into into
memory and up through the cache
hierarchy ok and then it did and then it
causes that the then the handler returns
to the to the process and when a handler
for a fault returns it causes the the
faulting instruction to re execute so
now the the move instruction that that
faulted is re-execute but this time
there's a page hit
now you may you may be interested how
how the cash is integrated into all of
this
so the MMU send fetches page table
entries so it passes page table
addresses to the cash
if those missed those go to memory the
the memory returns those page table
entries to the cache and then ultimately
to the to the MMU the MMU constructs
that physical address and then its sense
that physical address to the cache right
so so with caching the way we've been
caching is done using physical addresses
okay in this case it's also possible to
construct caches that work with virtual
addresses but yes
yeah so it will get into that okay so
the question is how is how is the
virtual address space implemented on
disk and it when it actually does a much
more efficient thing than the the sort
of a abstract model that I described
so most pages there's an option when you
allocate a new virtual memory page you
can allocate it so that it's all zeros
okay
so there's a special you can say I want
this I want to allocate a page of all
zeros in that case you know that page
doesn't need to ever get stored on disk
right it's just the memory it's as
though it was created on disk and then
loaded into memory so those pages that
are all zeros don't don't exist on disk
you know when pages are modified it's a
little more pages can be mapped to
particular files for example when we
load an elf binary the pages that
correspond to the code are actually
mapped to the to the bytes in the binary
that contain the code so that when you
miss on that page it fed it brings in
those code pages okay so so pages can be
mapped to user level files on disk or
not they can be anonymous and not mapped
so if if they're mapped to user level
if they're mapped to user level files
and you write to a page then it will get
written back to that to the page that
it's mapped to if it's not mapped to any
page it's stored in this area called the
swap area or the swap file okay yes
rage from this
oh yeah so the question is when you load
a page from disk into memory does it
also get cached in the cache memory
hierarchy and the answer is yes
so if you load an entire page that page
will be broken up into blocks 64 byte
blocks and and and load it into the
cache so everything everything
everything that you fetch from the cache
goes through the from the memory goes
through the cache the cache hierarchy
okay so I claim that virtual memory
works because of locality and that's
true but if we still had to fetch if
every time we had a myth we still had to
go to memory it would be too inefficient
okay so the the MMU
speeds up this translation process by
caching page table entries in a in a
hardware cache within the MMU called the
translation lookaside buffer or TLB so
the TLB is a hardware cache that caches
pges page table entries and it contains
like it contains a cache of the most
recently you know it's just like any
other cache so it contains a cache of
the most recently used page table
entries and so the the MMU remember the
the unique part of a virtual address
that defines a virtual page is the
virtual page number bits okay so the the
the TLB uses the the VPN portion of the
virtual address to to to access it and
so that just like any other set it has a
set index a set of set index bits which
are just determined by how many how many
entries that or how many sets that the
TLB has and it has a tag with for the
remaining bits to disambiguate any and
to disambiguate any cash lines or pts
the map to the same set okay so the the
VPN or the TLB I TLB index maps to this
particular set and then and then it uses
the the TLB uses the TLB LBT bits to
disambiguate and determine if the the PT
II that it's looking for is it is really
stored in the cache okay so the way this
works is CPU generates a virtual address
it goes through the MMU the MMU instead
of looking in memory and directly going
to the page table entry it first asks
the TLB if it has that it sends it the
VPN and so do you have this virtual page
the Pte for this virtual page and if it
does the TLB returns a hit and it
returns that page table entry which the
MMU can then use to construct the
physical address to send to the the
cache and memory system eventually I
result in that the data being sent back
now when you have a Miss then there's
this one the MMU checks with the TLB for
the Pte it misses so then the MMU has to
go to memory just like before okay so
this is and then everything is the same
the memory returns the Pte to the MMU
which stashes it in the TLB and just
like before if there's if there's no
room in the if yeah if a Pte has been
modified then it has to be written back
out okay just just like any other cache
and eventually the MMU uses that to
construct a physical address and then
the data gets sent back
okay if you've been paying attention
unlike a couple people if you've been
paying attention you're going to be very
concerned about the size of these page
tables right that I mean we've got 4
Kbytes suppose we have 4k by pages and
our effective address space is 48 bits
like it is with an x86 64 system then
and we have an 8x8 byte page table entry
we need a page table 512 gigabytes okay
- - the address space - - the 48th bytes
divided by 2 to the 12th bytes per page
okay so that's the number of page table
entries that we need and then the size
of each page table entry is 8 bytes so
we need almost a terabyte of of DRAM
just to hold the page table right so so
then obviously it's not going to work
and it's obviously not how their page
tables are really implemented so the
solution is to to use a hierarchy of
page tables so in it so we if we have a
two level page table the there's a top
of first level page table called the
level 1 table which is always in memory
ok it's never never page down and then
and then there's a suit a sequence of
level 2 page tables and they're all the
same size right and the the first level
1 table points to the beginning of the
first level 2 table so it contains a
physical address that points to the base
the second level 1 table points to the
second level 2 table and so on okay
so if we have this kind of system
remember most of the virtual address
space is unused right so if we have this
kind of system we can we can avoid
creating many unnecessary page tables
okay so imagine if we have a two level
hierarchy so let's look at our virtual
address space in this example and what
I've allocated two K pages for code and
data for this program and then there's
their 6k unallocated pages and then the
stack then there's a page that's
allocated for the stack I'm sorry
there's there's a thousand 24 pages
allocated for the stack most of which
are I'm sorry there's a region of memory
that that's the size of a thousand 24
pages but most of them are unallocated
and I've only allocated one for the top
of this for the top of the stack okay so
given this layout for my my process I
only only need three level to page
tables okay the first the the first page
table covers this region of my code and
data the first thousand 24 pages the
next page table covers the remaining
thousand 24 pages okay so these two
these two level two page tables cover
all of the code and data okay and
similarly the what I need for my stack I
just need one page table and it only has
one one valid Pte it's the very last one
okay and then I have a single level one
table that points to the three level two
tables okay so I've with with four page
tables I've covered the entire virtual
address space now the way that the way
that the MMU uses these multiple page
tables to do address translation is as
follows
we again we have a virtual page offset
which consists of the first p beds and
then the VPN the remaining bits give the
VPN for a K level page table are broken
up into K sub VPNs
okay and each each is the same size and
so now in this system the upper VPN one
which consists of the uppermost bits of
the VPN are an offset into the the level
1 table which is as before is pointed to
by the page table base register
okay so VP you want VP 1 is the index
into the level 1 page table remember the
level 1 page table points to the address
of the level 2 that are an entry a PT e
in the level 1 table points to the
address of some level 2 page table or it
contains the address of some level 2
page table so that points to the base of
this level 2 page table and then the VPN
2 bits are used as an index into that
level 2 table right and so on ok so
eventually you get at the a PT e and the
level K minus 1 table points to the
beginning of the level K page table and
VPN K points to an offset within that
table which finally contains the
physical address of the page that we
want to access okay and then that
physical address is used to form the the
PP n portion of the physical address and
just like before the virtual page offset
is just copied directly unchanged to the
physical page offset so is that clear to
everybody
yes question
let's see is it always a power of two
yes at least and it's defined by the the
architecture so for Intel it's a four
level system now why would it be and
then the quick could it will it always
be less than six Oh give us a 64-bit
system yeah yeah there's only the the
block size is fixed right so that
there's 12 bits here 2 to the 12th is 4k
so the remaining it's that you actually
have 48 bits to play with so the
remaining 48 bits could that's right so
if it was 4
if it was 8 it would be 6 so you're
right
in this scheme it could be at most 6
turns out in practice it's it's set at 4
and there was a question over here
the head of the CUA having the one
have it like this multi-level system oh
okay so the question is yeah the
question is how does it save you space
so the reason it saves you space is you
go back to this other figure maybe I
didn't explain this well enough
so you see this if we okay so let's say
we wanted to map this virtual address
space with a single page table we would
need a PT e for every page within that
address whether it was used or not okay
it goes back if we had a 48-bit address
space we'd need enough we need a page
table entry for each each page virtual
page in that address space
okay whether that page was used or not
so let me think about it to to the 48th
is a X several several exabytes we need
a page table that would have an entry
for each virtual page in that to the
48th bit address space and most of those
pages by far the vast majority would
never ever be used okay so that's where
the waste comes in okay so here with a
multi-level page system with this
multi-level scheme you only need to
generate in this case these level two if
it's a two-level system you only need to
generate level two page tables enough
level two pages to cover the portion of
the virtual address space that you're
actually using okay and that portion of
not using at this gap right here there's
there's no need to have a page table is
that clear that that's a really good
important question but you look
unconvinced
well yeah yeah you still need you still
need a page table that has let's see in
this case there's four K bite pages for
bite Pte so there's one K you have 1 K P
tes
in this so you still need you still need
a level 1 page table that has 1 k PT es
but those are only 8 bytes right I mean
so you still need to you still need to
have space because you don't know you
know you're not sure which of these
which reason of the address space you're
going to need to cover ok and it's the
same thing for here in this case in
these first two PT's these first two
level 2 page tables they're their
portion of the address space was
actually all being used right so each
one of these PT es at level 2 had to be
allocated had to be initialized and used
right but in this in this portion of the
address space that contain the stack
this third this third level 2 page table
has most most of its pts or no you still
have to allocate space for them but
they're there no ok that's a really good
question it's important that I hope
that's clear
any other questions will we go on sorry
oh okay question page entry level the
page table
it just looked at part of the address
exactly just just like here the MMU
members doing all of this this is all
hardware logic so it and and the art the
the number of page tables levels is
defined by the architecture okay so the
MMU takes the virtual address that's
presented to it and it it uses a portion
a subset of those bits to access each
each page table okay so it's just like
did I answer your question
okay so it's just like before that the
level K VPN K is used to compute an
index into the level K page table yes
okay the question is why are the indices
arranged right to left on which diagram
oh these are the bits this is the least
significant bit it's always bit zero
yeah that's a good question so the
question was why do these in this
diagram why are these these bits labeled
right to left starting at zero and the
answer is is that we're indicating the
bit position so zero is the least
significant bit and n minus one is the
most significant bit yes question
yeah so the question is what's the
overhead involved in these when you have
these multiple levels now are you
talking about overhead - yeah well so
there's clearly if you don't get TLB
hits it would be a lot of overhead
because it would be you would be
fetching PT es from multiple page tables
for memory so that but because of
locality the chances are almost the the
chances this level one table covers the
entire address space so it's always
going to be in the in the PT in the in
the TLB these the level these the these
level two tables are covering a huge
swath of the address space so chances
are they're going to be in the TLB -
right so so as long as your program has
reasonable locality most of the most of
these most of these lookups are going to
hit in the TLB okay so it turns out that
the overhead with reasonably written
programs is is it's it's negligible in
but that's a very it's a very important
consideration and you know maybe that's
maybe that speaks against increasing at
some point if you had too many page
tables you might you might increase the
probability of misses in the TLB so it's
probably something they very carefully
considered okay any other questions yeah
yeah so if we use segmentation plus
paging so it is the addresses page table
the recommended linear address of our
real
homeboy the question was how does
segmentation fit into this and we're not
going to go there so in in earlier Intel
systems such as the actually the first
Intel system I programs it was a 286 so
the 286 no is neat it was the 8086
anyway earlier in earlier Intel systems
had 16-bit addresses which is tiny right
it's only 2 to the 16 for your address
space and so as a hack to try to
increase the effective size of the of
this address space the introduced the
notion of segmentation and so there were
four segments 4-bit there was a register
segment registers that contain four four
bits that could be applied to the
address so an address was the the
combination of the segment knows more
than
yeah you need the segment formed the
address then was a combination of the
the segment bits plus the address so you
could use the segment bits to create an
offset so it was a - it wasn't
effectively a - 2 xx xx bit address
space but you can only address you can
only access it in 2 to the 16th chunks
right so the the segment would would
determine an offset into into the sum
and offset into the that this 20-bit
address space and then from that you
could address 16 bits so it was this
very unsatisfying devilishly hard to
program thing because you can only
access 16 bit chunks at a time so anyway
we're not going to a few years later
they came to their senses and just
created a real virtual memory system
with with linear drill spaces but you
know really there
yeah I don't know we're just did I'm not
even sure if if they do address
translation on those actually so I'm not
sure but you really don't want to go
there yeah oh it does it does so the
question is it doesn't exist anymore
everything Intel's been incredibly good
about maintaining backward compatibility
so so that stuff's all in there but
there's a mode bit when you when you
boot your system up you set a bit that
says I want a linear address space okay
any other question
oh no VPN to is the offset okay so the
question is why do we care about VPN -
since that it points to the level 2
table so what what what gives you the
beginning of the level 2 table is the PT
II entry in the level 1 table okay so
the the level 1 table points to the
beginning of that level to pay table and
VPN to gives you the offset into that
the level 2 table so the it finds the
address by taking the the base address
and then VPN 2 times the PT II sighs
okay good good any other questions
okay well that'll do it for today next
week or on Thursday we'll look at how
how virtual memory is implemented in
real systems and and in Linux