well good afternoon everybody welcome
good to see you and welcome to our
viewers on video as well okay so today
we're going to look at some additional
issues around the problem of
synchronizing threaded programs first so
let's review from last time of a few of
the concepts so recall that a semaphore
is a non non- global synchronization
variable it's manipulated by P and V
operations and the P operation takes as
an argument a semaphore if the semaphore
values nonzero it decrements the
semaphore and then continues if the if
the semaphore values zero then it blocks
waiting for that that semaphore value to
be incremented by a V operation after
the V operation increments after some V
operation increments the semaphore the P
operation continues by decrementing s
and then returning control to the caller
the V operation never blocks it it first
it increments the semaphore value s and
then it looks in the queue of four to
see if there's any processes that are
blocked waiting for that some afford to
be nonzero if if there are then it
selects one of those using some
unspecified criteria and then it
restarts that it restarts that thread
that's or that P operation that's
waiting waiting on the semaphore okay
and then this the semantics of the P and
V ensure that semaphore values are
always greater than or equal to zero now
the first thing we saw how to protect
shared variables by by using a semaphore
called the mutex that guarantees
mutually exclusive access to the
critical sections that are updating that
those variables are
structures and and the the way that we
do this is very simple we initialize the
mutex to one and then surround the
critical section with a P and a V now
there's a there's other ways that we can
so so here here's an example where we're
using semaphore is to provide mutual
exclusion but we can also use seminar
semaphores to coordinate access to
shared data structures in different ways
and so the idea here before we were
using the the semaphore just to protect
the access to a shared variable but we
can also coordinate access in different
ways by keep and this in this in these
in these kind of scenarios we're using
the semaphore to keep track of State to
count to count things to keep track of
State and to notify other other threads
of changes in state okay so it's a very
different usage model and two classic
examples that we're going to look at are
the producer consumer problem and a
readers writers problem so let's look at
producer consumer first so the idea in
the producer consumer problem is that
you have a resource in the form of a
buffer the buffer has a bounded size so
it consists of n slots and each slot can
hold an item okay the there's a producer
thread which produces items and then
inserts them into the buffer and there's
a consumer thread that retrieves removes
items from the buffer and then consumes
them by acting on them in some way
processing on them in some way so the
the synchronization variable the
synchronization pattern is that the
producer waits for an empty slot right
so if there's if the buffer is full the
producer can't insert an item into the
buffer so it waits for an empty slot and
then when it finds an empty slot when an
empty slot becomes available it inserts
the item into the buffer and then it
notifies the consumer that there's now a
new item in the
in the in the buffer the consumer of
course that has to wait for an item to
show up in the buffer right otherwise I
mean you can't remove an item from an
empty buffer so it has to wait for for
an item to be available in the buffer
and when an item becomes available it
removes it from the buffer and then
notifies the the producer that there's
now an available slot okay so this
actually this very simple pattern is
actually really really useful and shows
up in a lot of applications so for
example a multimedia application in a
multimedia application the producer
might be producing say MPEG MPEG frames
in it in a video and a consumer would be
consuming those those MPEG frames and
then painting the screen appropriately
another important application is in
graphical user interfaces so graphical
user interfaces are typically
implemented using this producer-consumer
model where the mouse clicks motions and
the in the of the mouse keyboard clicks
those are all recorded as events they're
detected by the system recorded as
events and placed into a some kind of a
queue and then up various other parts of
the system retrieve items from the queue
and and react to them so for example the
graphic system will retrieve events like
Mouse events and mouse movements mouse
clicks and it will paint the screen
accordingly right a soda little it will
reflect it will repaint the screen so
that the two so that to show you that
the cursor is moving right or if you
change the focus it will it will repaint
it so it's it's a very very common model
and as we'll see later multi-threaded we
can build multi-threaded concurrent
servers using this this model ok
so let's see how we would implement
producer/consumer on an n-element buffer
so this the implementation requires a
mutex to guarantee mutually exclusive
access to the resource of course and
then it requires then two other
semaphores counting semaphores slots is
a semaphore that counts the available
slots in the buffer and items is counts
the available items okay
and we've can implement it with this
this package called s buff so S buff the
s buff package defines a type called S
buff underscore T that packages up all
of the data structures that are needed
to implement the the shared buffer so
there's a pointer to the the buffer
which we were going to implement as an
array and and we'll implement a circular
buffer on this array the maximum number
of slots n so the size of the buffer and
then two pointers front and rear to keep
track of the the front and rear of the
of the buffer so to keep track of the
first and last items in the buffer and
then the three semaphores the mutex and
in the two counting semaphores and then
the package consists of these four
public functions S buff an it which
creates the is called once to create the
the buffer and initialize everything
allocate the space and initialize things
and the D in it which which frees up the
space and then a function to insert an
item into the queue and a function to
remove an item from a queue and return
that item so in this case items are just
in
so to create the to initialize the this
buffer with n slots we first allocate
the space for the buffer and n n we set
the we set the size to be the value n
that was passed in we indicate the empty
buffer by setting front-and-rear to be
zero okay and so whenever front and rear
are zero that's we have an empty buffer
and then we initialize the three
semaphore so the mutex like all meu
Texas is initialized to 1 the slot
semaphore which keeps track of the
number of available slots is initialized
to N and the item semaphore is
initialized to zero okay and D and it is
really simple it just frees up the the
heap space that we allocated okay so now
let's look at how we insert an item into
the buffer so we call we want to insert
this integer item into this buffer
pointed at by SP so first the thread
waits for an available slot okay by
doing a P on the slot sim before
alright so P will block until the slots
is greater than or equal to one okay
once there's an available slot then it
if then it's going to it's going to
update the the rear of the of the buffer
okay so we're going to put this item on
to the rear of the buffer and so it
needs to protect that access to that
shared buffer with the mutex then it
does the bike bike by doing a pee on the
mutex updating updating our rear pointer
okay so we pre increment it so we
increment the rear pointer and then take
take the mod of that n2 to compute the
index that we're going to insert the
item
- okay then we do a V on the mutex okay
so that other other threads can can
update that that shared data structure
and then we do a V on the number of
items to notify any consumers that
there's now an item in the in the buffer
so this this V is kind of interesting
you think it was kind of like a signal
right so you're sort of signaling
consumers that now some event has
occurred in the system now to remove an
item it's it's symmetric but instead of
instead of operating on the slots that
before it operates on the items
semaphore so to remove an item a
consumer first does a P on the items
semaphore so this now is waiting for an
available item it's waiting for the
semaphore to be greater than equal to
one when that happens then the P the P
returns and then we do we do the update
protected by a mutex by pre-incrementing
front taking the mod n and then reading
that value and returning it and placing
it into this local local variable item
then we release the mutex and then we do
a V on the number of slots which which
is an announcement to the to any
producers that there's now a new
available slot okay
three questions about that
so it's a little more subtle this looks
really simple but like all concurrency
problems it's actually very subtle so
you can have potential you can have many
producers and many many consumers all
operating on the same you know the same
the same shared buffer so this so what
would happen if if we had two two
consumers did a a P on this item
semaphore at the exact same time say
we're running on two cores and and we
have two threads and they each each
execute that P at the same time on that
that same that same item semaphore okay
so even even though they access it at
the same time the kernel will make sure
that one of them will execute first okay
so the kernel will serialize those P
operations and it there's no telling
which one gets it first but whoever acts
whoever runs there P first will will
decrement this this item semaphore and
then when the next when the next thread
executes its P items will either be zero
or nonzero okay as a result so somebody
wins there's kind of a ton of like a
controlled race and somebody wins the
race always wins the race because the
kernel is serializing these P operations
and it's executing them atomically okay
okay now the the there's a
generalization of the mutual exclusion
problem called the reader writer problem
so with with the mutual mutual exclusion
problem we were guaranteeing each thread
mutually exclusive access to to its
critical section that's updating a
particular resource or accessing a
particular resource and we did this the
exact same way whether that access was a
read or write okay but that's that's
overly conservative in this case because
we could if all we were doing if we had
multiple threads that were just reading
the resource there would be no reason to
do peas and Vees on that resource or if
we're not changing if we're not changing
the resource for just reading it and
there's nobody else writing it then then
there's no need to protect right so it
for readers we can have as many readers
as we want all at the same time reading
reading the the resource the variable or
set of variables and there's no need for
any kind of synchronization at all okay
so the producer consumer is sort of a
generalization of that mutual exclusion
problem which enforces mutual exclusion
only when it's absolutely necessary okay
so there can be is there there can be as
many readers reading the resource but
when a writer wants to write then it it
has to have mutual exclusive access to
the resource okay
so this is a kind of thing this is also
a very useful pattern you have in an
online airline reservation system you
have multiple clients accessing a shared
database okay so as long as those
clients are reading the database you can
have they can all be reading at the same
time but as soon as somebody wants to
make a reservation and update the
database then that update has to happen
a mutually exclusive way you know if you
had also if you had like any kind of
shared data structure like a cache in a
in a concurrent proxy like that you're
going to be writing soon or if you
haven't already started that cache is
being shared by multiple threads and
multiple threads may be reading that
cache but when some when you when you
get a new page and you want to cache it
then that that that constitutes a right
and that right needs to happen in our
mutually exclusive way now the initial
research the researchers that that pose
this readers writers problems in define
sort of several classes of reader writer
problems the first reader writer readers
writers problems is an implementation
that favors readers right so the idea is
that no reader should be kept waiting
right unless an a writer already has a P
as has sort of acquired the lock on that
or the mutex on that on that resource so
it in this case you know say there's a
writer waiting to get to acquire the
mutex and another reader comes in then
in this implementation that reader would
give priority over the writer and it
would be able to to read the to add to
do its read and the writer would have to
wait and so of court now if multiple
readers keep coming in then this could
starve out the writer write that
so a writer could be starved sort of
indefinitely waiting for all these
readers to finish and it's just based on
you know based based on how the
operating system decides to schedule
these these various reader reader
threads the the writer could be could be
starved out so that's what that's what
we mean by when we say that it favors
readers
now the second reader saris problem is
the sort of the opposite of that so it
favors writers right so any once a
writer is ready to to write then it gets
priority over any waiting readers so in
in this case if we have if we have
multiple writers that want to write they
could starve out readers and now there's
there's other variants that sort of deal
with this starvation issue this
potential starvation issue but we won't
look at them here so the let's look at
the solution to the first readers
writers problem so write initially a
thread is either a reader in this sort
of simplification or it's a writer if we
look at the writers this is pretty
simple it's just the writers are just
doing a peon this semaphore
so this this the semaphore W is the sort
of serves as like a mutex that protects
the resource for writer so it it ensures
that there's at most one writer at any
time executing its critical section and
it does that by just this this very from
this familiar P followed followed by a V
key no readers are a little more
interesting so with a with the reader we
have the shared this global variable
called read count which is going to keep
track of the number of readers that are
waiting to to read the to read the
resource and there's a mutex semaphore
mutex that protect protects
the accesses the updates to read count
okay the reads and the rights to up to
read count and then there's this W
semaphore which as we saw here is used
to protect the critical section in the
writer and initially both of these are
set to one so the reader in this
infinite loop in each iteration of this
infinite loop it is going to increment
read count so it protects that that
access by by doing a pee on the mutex
which is associated with recount so only
one only one reader can can be so this
this this region between the p and the v
constitutes the critical section
corresponding to read count so after the
p completes then it then we increment
the read count so now there's an
additional reader alright so we can have
potentially arbitrary number of these
reader threads right so this we're
indicating that there's there's there's
a new reader now and if read count is
one that that means we're the first
reader okay so this is sort of the first
reader into the this this implicit queue
of waiting readers so if read count is
one if we're the first reader then we do
a p on w okay which now will lock out
any any any future writers now if
there's already a writer that's done
it's P of W then this will block waiting
for that writer to finish okay but if
there's no writer in inside of its
critical critical section then this P
will just decrement the semaphore W from
1 to 0 and then lock out any subsequent
writers
okay after so now after it's done this
increment and read of the recount
variable then it releases the mutex so
that other readers can can access
recount okay now but it's still holding
it's it's it's it's holding so this is
this is kind of interesting right it's
it's it's holding the semaphore that
that locks out the writers but it's not
holding the any-any mutex right so the
reader now can just can just read it can
do its read and other readers that are
in the same the same section of the code
can also do their reads right so so
we're not so we're allowing multiple
readers now inside this critical section
but but no writers okay so everything so
everything works looks like it works
good now after after we read now the
number of readers now is going to be we
want to decrement the number of readers
so we acquire the mutex on on read count
we decrement read count and then we
check to see if we're the last reader
okay so if there's no more readers in
other words if read count is zero then
with now we can release the mutex for
the writer so that any now writers can
can access that resource and after we
release that the writers the writers
mutex then we release the mutex for
recount
so any questions about about this
so an interesting for you to think about
just uh if you have any spare time is
how you might how you might write a
version of this readers writers problem
or that favors writers instead of
readers yes oh no okay so the question
is a mutex allows for multiple readers
the fact that we know the fact that
we're releasing this mutex here that
this mutex is only only protecting
access to read count so we acquire it
here and we release it here after we've
after we've accessed read count okay but
we're not protecting the critical
section of the reader with any with any
mutex except for we're we're keeping
writers out by if we're the first one in
if we're the first reader you commanders
like this implicit queue of readers that
we're keeping track of with read count
okay so if we're the first ones in
meaning we're the first reader then we
we acquire this the p on the writers
mutex now if there's of course if
there's a writer inside this critical
section then this p will wait until the
writer releases okay but once once we've
acquired this this this mutex w then
we're block we're locking out any
writers okay because they'll any writer
that that arrives we'll do a p and it
will block right here on waiting for
that w to be nonzero okay so so we're
just we're blocking out any writers but
then we're allowing any readers to just
to access the resource
okay
okay good yes question question is
blocking slow it can be depends well
first of all you're making a call into
the kernel so it's a system call so
you're crossing that boundary and
there's always overhead associated with
that and then blocking you're blocked
until you know it can be sort of an
arbitrary amount of time right until
someone doesn't some thread does a V so
yeah it can't be slow right it just it
just depends you can't it's it's really
hard to bound the time that you're going
to be blocked now if you write the
program correctly eventually you'll be
unblocked you know eventually some
thread will execute a V but when we're
sort of assuming that the kernel does
some kind of when it implements its V it
does some kind of fair scheduling that
so a blocked a blocked P won't be in its
queue for forever right that the kernel
does some kind of something that's fair
so it guarantees that a P won't remain
blocked indefinitely
other questions okay so we can kind of
put all of this together and and use the
use our producer-consumer model to
implement a pre threaded concurrent echo
server now so far when we've when we've
used threads to in all our examples of
using threads and processes for servers
we created a new thread or process
whenever a new connection requests
arrived and then when it went and then
that that thread interacted with the
client and then whenever whenever that
interaction was finished it closed the
connection and exited and killed the the
thread or process now that's that's okay
but it's it's it's inefficient because
we're this creating and killing threads
introduces overhead so another way to do
this is to pre the treads or processes
ahead of time create a pool of threads
where each thread so we create a pool of
these worker threads where each of these
worker threads interacts with can
interact with a client okay so instead
of sort of creating processes and
threads on on-demand we create a what we
call a set of pre threaded or pre
threaded threads or pre forked processes
that do the work so the idea is that we
have this master thread in our server
that's waiting for connection requests
from clients by repeated calls to accept
and then when it when this thread
receives the connection request from the
client the accept the accept call the
accept function returns a connected file
descriptor ok associated with the
connection to the client and then it
inserts that descriptor into a into a
buffer ok now remember descriptors are
just small integers that index the
descriptor table right so they can be
passed around
from thread to thread because all the
threads are sharing the same the same
set that same descriptor table right
so the master thread puts the repeatedly
accepts connection requests and inserts
the corresponding connected file
descriptor into the buffer now each
worker thread waits for the so in this
case the items are descriptors so the
worker threads they're all waiting on
this for items to appear in this buffer
okay and when an item appears one of the
threads will remove that item and then
use that descriptor to interact with the
with the client over the connected file
descriptor associated with the
connection that exists between the
client and the server okay so now we
have we have these the concurrency comes
in the form of these multiple worker
threads interacting with with multiple
clients and then when a worker thread
finishes servicing a particular client
then it just goes and it checks for the
next file descriptor in the buffer okay
so this is much more efficient than our
previous model where for each new client
we had to create a thread or a process
and then destroy that thread or process
once we were finished
okay so we're sort of re amortize that
that we had to go through to create
these worker threads by leaving them
running and then replacing the
destruction or the killing of that
thread with replacing it with just a
simple as simple and very fast operation
of removing an item from the buffer okay
okay so let's let's see how we would we
would implement this and like like all
of these server examples it's
surprisingly simple right this is a
fully functioning a real server but we
can do it in one one page one page of
code so for this preet we're going to
use threads for our concurrent server
and we're going to use the s buff
package so we're going to create this
this shared buffer global variable
called s buff and we have listening
descriptor and connected descriptor and
we have the client length and client
adder that that will be used in the
accept call and we have the thread ID
that will be used in the when we create
that when we create this thread so now
that we start by we're going to in this
program we're going to pass in the port
number so the server is going to be
listening on some port so we passed that
port number in as the first argument so
we call open listened FD on our V of one
an open listened FD creates a listening
descriptor and returns it returns the
value of that descriptor and listen FD
and then we call s buffin it to to
initialize our shared buffer with with s
buff sized file descriptors and then we
create a collection of n threads worker
threads each of which will execute the
the thread routine which we've called
thread and no argument so once we create
these all of these threads then we go in
this infinite loop where we call except
on this listening descriptor so in that
except we'll block until a connection
request arrives and when it does the
accept returns with a connected file
descriptor that can be used to to
interact with the client
and once we get that connected file
descriptor then we just simply insert it
we insert that that connected file
descriptor into our shared buffer and
then wait for the connection request the
next connection request so our servers
very efficient right we're just doing an
accept and then a very fast insert into
the buffer okay and then we're going to
let the worker threads do all the work
associated with those with that with
with that that queue of descriptors now
the thread routine first detaches okay
so this is a case where we don't want to
run joinable because we're never going
to to join we're never going to wait for
these threads or have any any reason to
I kill them from the main thread so this
so now this this worker thread and in
this infinite loop each iteration it
removes an item from the buffer so it
blocks until there's an item that it can
that it can remove from the buffer and
it sets it to this local variable con FD
and then it calls a helper sort of this
this is like the the helper function
that implements the logic for this this
particular server and this is this in
this case it's an echo server so this
this echo count routine will interact
with the client echoing whatever the
client sends us until the client closes
the connection and then when it so
whenever the client is finished then
then we close the week we close the our
end of the connection and go back and
get the next item out of the buffer and
as you point out that echo count is just
a placeholder this could be anything
this could be the logic for a web server
for any any kind of web service or any
kind of service
now the the to initialize this echo
count function we need to we need to
initialize the mutex so we're so this
echo count function is going to have it
has it defines a global variable called
byte count so this in this echo server
we're going to keep track of the number
of bytes that we've received from all
the clients that we're interacting with
okay so there's a global variable called
byte count which is shared by all the
threads and we're going to update this
this byte count variable every time we
receive something every time we receive
data from from the client and we're
going to use mutex to protect the
accesses to byte count okay so we're
going to initially have to initialize we
have to call a function that initializes
that initializes this by first
initializing the mutex and then setting
byte count to zero and then within echo
count itself
there's some we've already seen Sud
we've already seen a way to initialize a
package you know if we have some kind of
package of library functions that are
going to be used by multiple threads
there's several ways to actually
initialize this package so one way is to
explicitly call have the the main thread
call this initialization function once
okay so we've seen that with like the S
buff package right the main thread has
to call the main thread calls S buffin
at once okay before any of the peer
threads execute any of the worker
threads executes but there's another way
we can do this too we can have that the
worker threads actually call the
initialization function and we can use
this technique provided by by P threads
where we define a static variable so
this is a static local variable but you
recall that this is actually treated
like a global variable so it every
thread has access to this variable okay
but but its scope is limited to to the
disco de cocao function so no other no
other function connect can access this
variable but each each thread that
executes this thread routine has access
to it and and in this context it's
treated like a global right so if one
thread updates the value every other
every thread sees that same value okay
so so we can use this this mechanism
from P threads but so we can create this
this this variable of type P thread once
T and initialize it to this special P
threads value which is sort of like the
P threads uninitialized value so this is
a value that P threads knows about that
indicates that that this this variable
wants hasn't been initialized
and then and then we call the pthread
once function passing at this this this
variable that we the address of this
variable created that we created and the
address of the function to call to
initialize whatever it is we want to
initialize in this case the the echo
count the the echo count variable and so
what this does every thread will call P
thread once but only one thread will
actually call the the initialization
function only the very first thread that
executes speith read once will we'll
call it the other threads this this P
thread wants call will be like a no op
yes question well that's the other
option so so the advantage of this is
that you can you I guess the advantage
is I I don't know that it's just another
way you can do it you I guess it avoids
it avoids having to do it in the master
thread that you can you can make your
you can make this package sort of
self-contained right that you're not
you're not really counting on the master
doing anything but yeah that's that's
the other way we could have done it so I
just wanted to show you this this this
other technique okay so once we once we
initialize once we once some thread
calls the NED echo count then we
initialize the reo package for all of
our accesses on this connected
descriptor and then we we repeatedly
read a line of text from the client okay
and then in a protected way we increment
bite count with the number of bytes that
we received from the client which is
returned by this Rio read line b
function and then we print a little
message just to sort of keep track so we
can see keep track of our running total
and then we release the mutex on this on
the byte count the global byte count
variable and then we echo that line back
to the client okay so any questions
about that
yes question so the line there's it okay
the question is the line that declares
the static variable once will it only be
executed the first time a thread
executes that statement no it's so the
answer is no every every thread will
define this variable and assign it this
to this this this P thread once value
okay what will only happen once is the
call to a net echo count okay so the
first thread that executes this P thread
once call will actually call an EDD echo
count every other thread every
subsequent thread will not call it it'll
be like a no op yeah uses the ones it's
just an opaque
cause the declaration line once it will
be selling the flag by resetting in
speech
yeah somehow it will but somehow the
pthread wants is keeping track that it's
it's executed okay so I I'm really not
sure how how its implemented okay so
somehow pthread wants yeah I guess every
you know this I mean this is just the C
declaration right so there's no the
pthreads has no control over
declarations right so every thread will
get it every thread will sort of update
this static variable and you're right if
the first thread
the second thread would overwrite this
value again but somehow pthread once can
keeps track of that okay in a in some
way that I I'm not sure about how that
works but this is this is the way you
get that behavior
can others there's some other issues
around synchronizing threads sort of
correctness issues that we have to be
aware of and so I hope your hope you're
sort of getting the sense that this
threaded programming is is kind of a
tricky business right and so one issue
that we always have to be aware of is is
is this idea called thread safety so in
general a thread routine can only should
only call functions that are that are
thread safe that have this property
called thread safety okay and a function
is thread safe if and only if that
function can be invoked by multiple
threads at the same time okay so if we
have a function f its thread safe if and
only if its execution can be interleaved
by multiple threads okay
and so we can identify a four different
classes of thread unsafe functions so
one classes is the functions that fail
to protect shared variables with mutexes
okay so we've already seen that with bad
count that was an example of a thread
unsafe that main routine was an example
of an unsafe thread function or no the
thread function was an example of an
unsafe thread function because it didn't
protect the act the update of the count
variable another class of functions that
that our thread unsafe is are those
functions that keep track of state
across multiple invocations so if
they're storing State in some global
global variable private or public global
variable the net that's thread unsafe
because multiple threads will be
accessing that State another way another
kind of thread unsafe function or
functions that return a pointer to a
static variable so there's there's
there's a number of functions in the
standard c library that were written
before threads or even on anybody's
radar and so so an example is the C time
function which takes as an argument a
time struck two binary time struct and
returns a pointer to a string date and
time string but the address in that
pointer is always the same right so the
this function is is defining some kind
of static variable and it's always
returned and then it's it's it it's
converting that the binary time struct
into it into a string that's always at
the same location and it's returning the
address of that string so every
invocation returns the exact same
address but with different content at
that address okay and this you know they
just they didn't realize that this was a
bad thing to do for threaded programs
because nobody was writing threaded
programs at that at the time
and then obviously any function that
calls and unthread unsafe function is
threat unsafe okay so let's look at
these these different classes of
functions okay so the class one
functions fail to protect shared
variables and so the fix as we've seen
is to use P and V to guarantee mutually
exclusive access and thereby protect the
accesses to the variable so we saw this
with that good count program and then
the the problem is it also as we saw
with good count is that the
synchronization up operations can be
slow so if they're in a tight inner loop
it can it can really slow your program
down okay the class 2 thread on safe
functions rely on some kind of
persistent state across invocations of
that function okay so the classic
example is the Lipsy rand function whose
in this the an implementation of which
is I took from the K in our book so this
this R and this is a pseudo
pseudo-random number generator a pseudo
random in the sense that if you give it
the same key it'll return the same
sequence of values okay so this is kind
of nice because it allows when you're
testing it allows repeatability so every
time you call it if you call it with the
same seed you can you're guaranteed
you'll get the same results and the way
this is implemented is that there's at
the seed if there's this there's a seed
variable called next which is used in
each iteration of the random number
generator and it's it's defined as a
global private so static makes it
private so it's not accessible to
programs that are calling the rand
function but it's it's used by the rand
function and so this this variable is
initialized to 1 there's a function
called s Rand which allows the user to
set the seed value so the
the default seed value is one but if the
user calls s ran they can pass in a seed
which will be then which will be which
is just would assign to this this next
variable and then each iteration of R
and does an operation on the seed so it
takes that the next value that's going
to be used is the is a property of the
previous value the function of the
previous value and then it returns a
pseudo-random number that's a function
of that next value okay so it's relying
on this each iteration each time you
call Rand you're relying on the this
next value that was computed by the
previous time that you called Rand
okay now this is perfectly fine and
there's no problem with this in a
non-threaded situation but what happens
if multiple threads now so suppose you
have multiple threads and and they're
each calling this rand function sort of
interleaving calls to two Rand okay the
the fact that that Rand is relying on
the this previous state if multiple
threads are calling Rand it's going to
break the pseudo-random property so each
thread that the the random numbers that
each thread gets back are not only a
function of the previous the seed from
the previous time that thread called the
function but also also a function of the
other threads that are calling it right
so so if a particular thread calls this
random number generator multiple times
it potentially won't see the same
sequence of pseudo-random numbers
because other threads will be jumping in
okay and
okay so it it's it's not it's not
incorrect and that the program will fail
but if the program is counting on the
pseudo random property then it creates a
problem okay so the the solution to this
is to rewrite Rand and require it to
require the caller to keep track of this
next variable okay so each caller will
keep its own local copy of next and it
will pass in a pointer to R and R and
we'll compute that value so now this
will be updating state in the calling
the calling thread but this is local
state on the on that thread stack okay
so every thread will have its own copy
of of next so we but we have to create a
new function and what we'll call it
underscore R the stands for reentrant
which is a property we'll look at in
just a second but it's more work for the
programmer because now the programmer
has to maintain this this sort of this
next value okay
okay another way that threads the
functions are unsafe is this this is are
these functions that always retain a
return a pointer to some global to the
same global variable or typically it's a
static variable but they always return
the same value each time the same
address okay so you can see this is
similar to that race that we encountered
before where we were passing the address
of a connected file descriptor to a
worker thread okay so now we're creating
a race so let's say one thread let's say
one thread calls this function so for
example C time takes this this time
struct as an argument okay which can
correspond to an arbitrary time it could
be the current time or just some
arbitrary time that the caller
constructed and it returns a pointer to
a char star so it just returns a pointer
to a string that represents the date and
the time its own ASCII ASCII string that
that represents the date and time but
it's always it's always returning a
pointer to the same the same location in
memory okay so you can see the problem
if thread a calls this C time function
with one with top one time struck it
gets back a pointer to the to the
character string corresponding to that
time struct but now let's say before
before thread a can use that read that
that string another thread calls C time
and that instance of C time will
overwrite that the copy of the time
string for that that thread a computed
so when thread a finally gets a chance
to access that time string its accessing
thread B's time string and not threat
ace time string okay and it just depends
if thread a can get to that and read
that variable before thread B over
writes it then everything's fine
and otherwise threat a's accessing the
wrong time string
okay so there's there's a couple of ways
to fix this like we could rewrite the
the function the c time function to take
as a de nother argument that passes in
the the location the address of the time
string so we could require that the
caller to allocate space for the time
string and passing the address to the c
time function okay but this has this
says this would require us to change all
the instances where we call c time but
we'd also have to change the the
implementation of c time in the live in
the Lipsy in the library right and so we
can't we don't have access to Lib C
source on our system right so that's
that's just not a feasible thing plus it
would break every other program that
called C time right so we just can't do
that
the another op a better option is to
create a new function of our own okay
called C time underscore TTS for thread
safe so we'll create our own sort of
wrapper function for it for the C time
and we'll use a technique called lock
and copy to to provide thread safe
access to 2c time so the way it works is
it will write this new function C time
underscore TS which just like c time
takes this a pointer to this time struct
but then it adds a second argument which
is a pointer to the threat of threads
private copy of the time string okay so
the caller allocates the space and
passes the pointer to this to that to
that string and then within c time we
have a local variable called shared the
shared pointer okay so this is going to
point to that that that shared global
data structure
that see time is is accessing and so
first we do the lock
that's the lock part of lock and copy by
acquiring a mutex and then we call see
time so only one thread at a time we'll
have this mutex so whatever thread so
once once we return from PE we know that
we're the only thread in this in this
this critical section so we call C time
the normal lip CC time function which
returns a pointer to this to the same
location and then we do the copy part we
copy that that string to the private
string that was passed in just into our
function once we've done the copy then
we can release the mutex and then we
return a pointer we return private P
back to the caller right ok so and we
don't we don't this is just more of a
convenience to the caller
because programs that are using C time
are expecting to get that pointer back
ok so by using lock and copy we have to
we have to make changes we have to write
this new function but it's fairly simple
and then we have to make changes every
place in our program where we call C
time we have to update those two calls
to C time underscore TS and create this
create this local string array ok yes
it has to be the variable cost
well typically these functions are
returning pointers to some data
structure and so they're they're sort of
updating the data structure and then
returning a pointer to it so it wouldn't
makes I don't know how I guess it could
return a struct and it would always
return now now
I can't think of any I can't think of
any reason why they would turn anything
but a pointer because they're they're
typically updating some some data
structure and then returning a pointer
to it
if they were returning if they were
returning scalars those scalars would
always be returned in EAX or RA X all
right so actually that would be okay
right it would just be it's the pointer
that causes a problem because it's it's
always returning that value in EAX but
it's always returning the same value in
EAX always pointing to the same the same
data structure okay good
okay now one-one potentially significant
disadvantage of lock and copy is that
this this copy might not always be as
simple as just doing like a stir copy if
if it's a complex diff if the function
that you're calling is computing some
complex data structure like a nested you
know a struct which contains structs and
pointers to arrays then this copy can
get can get quite complicated right it
it would require what we call a deep
copy so that can be that can be very
difficult to but in this case it's
simple we're just we're just doing a
we're just copying one string to another
okay and then finally the the fourth
class of thread unsafe functions are
functions that call unsafe functions
right so it's kind of obvious and then
the obvious fix is to not call thread
unsafe functions from within your
function and then you can make it thread
safe
now there's a very interesting an
important subclass of thread-safe
functions called reentrant functions so
a reentrant a function is reentrant if
it contains no accesses to shared to
shared variables okay so if all the if
every variable that it accesses is
contained on the is declared as a local
variable and stored on the stack for
that function okay that's called a
reentrant function and because there's
no accesses of any kind to shared
variables there's no there's no
synchronization required because every
function is is operating accessing its
own local copy of all the variables and
if multiple threads execute two
instances of a reentrant function
it's okay each thread has its own
separate stack so you don't need to
worry about any kind of synchronization
they can run independently so the reason
reentrant functions are so important is
because it's expensive to do
synchronization and so what you can
avoid it completely with these reentrant
function reentrant functions so they're
they're efficient so as that as the
diagram shows every reentrant function
is thread safe but not every thread safe
function is reentrant so we saw that
before right when we have a function
that accesses a shared variable we can
make it thread safe by protecting it
with a mutex okay but it's not reenter
n't because it's it's X it's accessing
shared variables okay
now on all the functions in the standard
c library which are enumerated in the
back of your k and r texture thread-safe
okay but not not necessarily reentrant
and most most syscalls are thread safe
with just a with a few exceptions that
I've listed here I don't I don't think I
don't think this is complete but these
are just some examples of some notable
ones and so for each each of these
thread unsafe functions Linux provides a
reentrant version which is denoted by
underscore R and then that reentrant
version has a different different set of
parameters typically the only exception
that I know about is I net n to a which
is an episode of an obsolete Network
protocol for converting sort of binary
Network addresses to human readable
ASCII addresses but this is this is ops
been obsoleted by by other calls so it's
I guess they just never never bothered
to create a reentrant version for it
because there's there's other options
alternatives to using that
okay another so another thing we have to
worry about is we've seen is races again
this is the real Bugaboo in in threaded
programs and it typically involves some
kind of unexpected sharing so in this
case I'm going to revisit this this this
incorrect threaded program that where we
introduce introduced a race by passing
when we create the thread we we pass the
argument to the thread which is like the
local thread ID we pass an address of a
variable that we have stored on the
stack and is Katun the eye that the the
loop loop iterator and so we've seen
that this causes this causes a race so
we incurred we we set initially I is 0
then we create a new thread which is
pure thread 0 and then this thread
dereferences the pointer to get its
local copy of the this sort of local
thread ID but now we've introduced the
race between the increment of I and the
dereferencing of the incrementing of I
and the main thread and the
dereferencing of I in the peer thread so
if this dereferencing happens before I
is incremented then we're good but if
this dereferencing happens after we
increment I so in other words at when I
equal 1 then we get the wrong value in
the peer thread for for my ID
so you might wonder I think there was a
question before about you know this
seems that the odds of this happening
seems so low why why are you even
worrying about it so we actually create
just to sort of test this out we wrote a
program to see if we could see if we
could actually see this race in practice
and that's one of the great things about
like 2:13 is that you we can just try
stuff out right so so we just tried it
out so we wrote it we wrote a simple
main thread that creates a hundred
different threads each with then we
passed the art as the argument we passed
the address of of this local variable I
okay and then in each peer thread we
detach the thread dereference and then
we have a function that saves the value
so we're we're storing we're storing
that value of I for future reference
okay so now if there's no race each of
the 100 threads would get a separate
distinct thread ID right so each each
value 0 through 99 if we made a
histogram of it there would be exactly
one instance of each of each value of I
okay but if there was a race there would
be for some values of Y there would be
multiple instances that were encountered
in multiple threads okay so you can see
if we go back here if if if we lose if
the peer thread loses the race and I
gets incremented before it can
dereference
now we've got peer thread zero actually
gets a an ID of one okay and then peer
thread one if there's no race it'll
it'll get the correct value of one so
now we've got two instances of one okay
so let's look so this is the case so
we've plotted the results for a case
where there's no race so along the
x-axis sorry this is too small the
x-axis gives us all the 100 values of I
0 through 99 and then the y-axis is the
count so this is a hit we're doing a
histogram of for these all the values 0
through 99 so in this case every value
has exactly one instance so no race
there was no race in in no races in
involved in all 99 are all 100 instances
if we run it on a single core laptop so
now each thread is sort of taking its
turn on a single core it happens a few
times right so there's a few times where
the one thread gets preempted and the
other thread begins to run before it can
so the peers when one thread gets
preempted before I can dereference the
variable so it gets the wrong the wrong
value but it's not very common it just
it happened one two three four five six
seven times but now if we run this
program on a on a multi-core server you
can see it happens a lot in fact it
happens most of the time so it almost
never we almost never get the correct
the correct value for for my ID
okay so this is just another example of
some of the create the things that can
just drive you crazy if you're not
careful when you when you program is and
threads with threads okay and as so as
we saw the the way to eliminate these
kind of erases is to avoid this the
sharing of state and in this case by
allocating for each thread allocating a
separate block in the in the heap that
will hold the that will hold the the
local ID for that thread and then
passing a pointer to that that unique
block of storage to the thread
okay so if that if all of that isn't
enough to worry about and by now you
should be losing sleep at the very
thought of writing a threaded program
another thing to worry about is deadlock
okay so here a program is deadlocked if
it's waiting for some condition to occur
that will never occur okay so let's say
a typical scenario right pee pee is the
potential the pee operation is a
potential problem because it blocks
right and it's waiting for that
semaphore that it's blocking on to
become nonzero well it's it's not too
hard to imagine scenarios where some
there's some combination of pees of pee
operations that sort of block each other
out okay and make it impossible for the
condition they're waiting on to occur so
for example let's say you've got two two
threads that need two two threads one
and two that need two different
resources a and B in order to proceed so
they have to acquire they have to do a
pee on the mutex that on this on the
mutex that that's associated with the
mutexes that are associated with these
two resources so let's say process one
acquires a so it does a pee on a x'
mutex that's one it's okay so it
succeeds at it so it acquires that
resource and then it gets preempted by
thread to which acquires B first instead
of acquiring a thread B for some reason
acquires B so now thread a holds the
lock on resource a and thread two holds
the lock on resource B and so now let's
say process thread two gets preempted so
now and thread one runs and so now it's
waiting it's trying to tries to acquire
the the lock on resource b-but threat to
our holds that lock and at the same time
thread to tries to acquire the lock on
resource a but process one is holding
that right so they're each so here's the
case where thread a is waiting for this
semaphore associated with B to become
non zero so it's blocked in this P
operation and at the same time thread
two is blocked in the P operation for
for for resource a neither of those
semaphores will ever be released so
thread one and two are deadlocked okay
and it it happened because just there
was this innocuous little bug in this
case where one the threads acquired
their resources in different orders
so here's an example of a program that
deadlocks and if you looked at this you
know the fact that it's wrong and buggy
doesn't jump out at you right so this is
this kind of stuff is very subtle so
here's here's a program we're going to
create two threads we've got an array so
and we have an array of meu Texas an
array of two mutexes so we create two
threads and we pass each thread it's a
local thread ID so of 0 & 1 and so here
we're avoiding the race we're just
casting this thread ID to be - a pointer
okay which is a little strange but it's
okay
and then we're waiting for those threads
to finish ok
each thread is going to acquire two
these two semaphores these two mutexes
but it's going to do it in a different
order
okay so it's going to do it as a
function it's going to take the ID so
it's going to sew thread zero will first
acquire a mutex 0 and then and then
acquire mutex 1-0 so then it will
acquire mutex 1 and thread 1 will first
acquire mutex one and then acquire mutex
0 ok so if we were to draw that diet and
then and then it will attempt to then it
will increment count so this is totally
bogus but it's just to illustrate the
problem so you can see thread 0 does a
peon semaphore 0 followed by a peon
semaphore 1 and thread 1 does a peon
semaphore 1 followed by a peon semaphore
0 and so we can see this that this is a
problem very clearly if we go back to
our progress graphs
so if you look at thread 0 it's doing a
peon semaphore 1 and of and it followed
a peon semaphore 1 followed by a V on
semaphore 1 and thread 1 is also is
doing a peon semaphore 1 followed by a V
on semaphore 1 so if you take if you
take the intersection of these two
regions you get the forbidden region for
semaphore 1 okay so this is the region
that enforces mutual exclusion so on
this on this the resource associated
with semaphore 1 and if you do the same
thing for semaphore 0 so here in thread
1 we're acquiring semaphore 0 here and
releasing it here and we're in thread 0
we're acquiring it here and releasing it
here so if you take the intersection of
those two you get this forbidden region
for s0
ok now the problem
his right is this region here this
so-called deadlock region because by the
rules of you know time can't go
backwards heart once the trajectory
enters into the this deadlock region
then it's doomed because there's no once
it enters this once it enters this
deadlock region there's nowhere for it
to go eventually no matter how it
progresses every trajectory will lead to
to this point here where it's boxed in
and can't and can no longer proceed
so so interestingly this this sort of
this this region back here on the on the
the sort of the tail end of the of these
two forbidden regions this represents
states that can never be reached so
these are on unreachable states which
may or may not be interesting and then
what makes this so nasty is that it's
non-deterministic right some programs
some trajectories if they get lucky
they'll skirt this deadlock region and
then the program will run fine right
there's okay so if it's trajectory may
be just by some you know just by some
arbitrary scheduling decision made by
the colonel the trajectory trajectory
gets passed the deadlock region in this
direction and then it'll eventually run
without any problem so it's just it's
only if the trajectory lands it within
the deadlock region then there were that
we're in trouble so so this is the
really nasty the really nasty part is
that you may run your program for a
million times and every trajectory every
one of those million trajectories skirts
the deadlock region okay but on the
million and first time that you run it
it it enters the deadlock region and
then deadlocks okay so it's it's it's
very it's a very tough problem to deal
with now fortunately you it's easy to
avoid if if threads that are acquiring
locks on on resources acquire all those
locks in the same order okay so in our
example if we rewrite this program so
that each thread thread 0 and thread 1
acquire their locks in the same order so
semaphore 0 first followed by semaphore
then if that happens and we you can see
it eliminates the debt the potential
deadlock region okay so now any
trajectory that we take will will be
fine because we've eliminated that that
that deadlock region and the the order
that we release the locks doesn't matter
because that that sort of affects the
the it affects this or unreachable
region you know the size and shape of
this unreachable reason region but it
there's never the order that we release
the locks can never introduce a deadlock
region
okay so that's it for today hope you all
have a very nice Thanksgiving holiday
and we'll see you on Tuesday