so today's the second lecture about
network programming we got started last
time and as you probably saw last time
there the AP is for this are really big
and hairy and messy and it takes just a
lot of time in my own personal
experience of rereading we looking at
code looking at examples rereading
documentation going back and forth over
that a dozen or so times before it all
really sinks in and it's one where it
really helps a lot to look at example
code and there's example code in the
book in that CSAP pc file that you've
seen versions of in various forms so i
can lecture for days and weeks but this
really would all settle in until you've
spent time studying yourself anyways I
want to repeat and go back over a little
bit of ground before but last time we
talked about the idea of translating
from a domain name which is something
like WWC mu edu to IP address which for
IP version 4 is a is a 32-bit address
it's usually written in dotted decimal
form and I showed you a program last
time called host info that you could
that will look actually at the code for
and I just wanted to show you today I
just did one very small tweak to that
program and I'll describe it today and
the interesting thing is it lets you
look at both ipv4 and ipv6 and it's one
of the interesting features the code in
the book and it's new to the third
edition is it uses a new API that lets
you pretty easily
write code that will work under either
of these two versions of the Internet
Protocol so for example with this
slightly modified program if I now look
up the IP address for Facebook you'll
see it comes back with two different
ones and the the first one is the
familiar dotted decimal form where each
recall that each of these digits it's a
decimal representation of of a single
byte so it's a number between 0 and 255
this is a ipv6 address which is I told
you is 128 bits long so that's to the
seventh takeaway 3 to the fifth 32 bytes
right and it's usually written in this
hex format with colons be after every
pair of bytes and I think the colon
colon just means that's a zero there
when the cute things Facebook did was
embed fac ii as a hex code inside of
their ipv6 address
and that's really different I get very
different results
running this at home and then I do here
and as I mentioned you'll get different
results running a DNS server depending
on where in the country are uh if you
repeat the same thing over and over
again you'll get different results and
that's because these very large
companies are providing servers that are
stationed all over the world and as a
way to sort of balance out the load of
the traffic they also have multiple
server addresses that then they kind of
rotate through to give you so that
different people will get served by
different machines so you see for
example Twitter our Google just gave me
two addresses in ipv4 and ipv6 address
Twitter gave me a for different ipv4
addresses so let's look then at the code
I'll go back through some of what we
talked about last time I quite honestly
I spent a fair amount of time looking at
it so I can really understand it better
because it's pretty it's not simple
stuff but as I mentioned that as we went
over last time this is sort of this
giant block diagram that shows all the
activity involved in setting up and
running both a server and a client and
just to repeat the idea is you need to
the server needs to fire up you can't
contact a server until that server
exists so it's the server is the thing
that has to exist first and all these
steps are what are required for a server
to begin on a machine and then to accept
a connection request from a client
similarly once the server is set then
the client can begin and it's like
placing a call to the server and it
makes a connection request and that's
accepted by the server and then what's
called a session begins meaning an
ability for these two machines to talk
back and for
worth over an internet connection and
they'll do it this example I'll show is
done by reading and writing as if they
were filed a file each end looks like
it's reading and writing a file and then
once the client is done with whatever it
it's trying to get it will disconnect
since we hang up its phone and then the
listening the server will detect this by
receiving an end of file when it
attempts to read from the client and
then it will close that connection but
and this I didn't have stated quite
properly last time this it's not going
to actually shut down at that point it's
just going to return back and accept a
new connection request and this is
what's known as an iterative server it
can only handle a single client at a
time later in the course we'll talk
about how to do a multi-threaded server
that can handle multiple connections at
one time so this is a pretty basic
version so the first step on either the
client or the server side is this very
hairy messy relatively new API called
get adder info and the idea of get adder
info is it's a sort of kitchen sink our
Swiss Army knife if you know all those
expressions of it has a zillion features
to that sort of subsume a lot of other
sort of individual protocols so for
example it's pretty much the same
whether it's ipv4 ipv6 it lets you sort
of go forward from and a domain name to
an IP address lets you go backward from
an IP address back to a domain name it
supports all of those things it will let
you look up what is the port number
associated with an HTTP server so it
will let you do all kinds of different
things and as a result it's a big and
messy API with a zillion
zillions features and parameters and and
so forth so you recall from last time
that the the the data structures we use
to refer to a connection whether it's an
ipv4 or an ipv6 connection is called a
sock outer and as I mentioned this is
sort of the C version of subtyping if
you know a language with a type
inheritance this is how it's done in C
it's done by casting and so in
particular the sort of generic socket
address all it needs to know is a two
byte field at the front that specifies
what kind of socket is this and then in
particular we'll be looking at what's
called a sock adder in which is an ipv4
version of of a socket and so what it
needs to know is a port number which is
a two byte integer and a I P address
which is a four byte address for ipv4
both of those are actually stored in
this structure as I mentioned in in
big-endian order even if you're running
it on a little endian machine and one of
the interesting features of that this
API this get adder info is it's largely
removed the need for you as a programmer
to worry about byte ordering and that's
a nice feature so in general for example
and get adder info if I want to pass an
ax port number I'll pass it as a
character string a string representation
of a decimal number in other words and
then the the code here within this API
will automatically turn that into a
16-bit integer and put it in the proper
byte order and same with how it takes
use of this 32 bit IP address and you
want to get it into dotted decimal form
it will do that for you without you
having to worry about byte order so it's
kind of a nice thing
so get editor info has a whole bunch of
arguments and some of them are
essentially outputs some of them are
inputs things you're passing into the
function and others are really more like
outputs how it gets information back to
you
so in particular the first one is just
the name of the host and that can be
either a domain name or a dotted decimal
name or one of those funky looking
things with the Cohens that you solve
for ipv6 the service is usually if
you're looking up so if we're using this
to look up that'll actually be a null
pointer and basically what typically
you'll have is one of those two will be
a string and the other will be a null
pointer and the reason for that is the
same function can be used either to look
up a service like what is the port
number associated with HTTP or it can be
what is the IP address of WWC mu edu the
hints is something that you're passing
in and it's basically as you fill in a
small amount of a fairly large body of
information about what specifically are
you looking for in this request are you
looking for an ipv6 information are you
looking for ipv4 and so forth and then
what it returns back that's why you pass
a star star is it will return back a
linked list that it's generated of
results and the reason for that as I
mentioned is that IP addresses are sort
of many to many mapping potentially
there as you saw it's possible for a
single domain name to have multiple IP
addresses it's possible for a single IP
address to have multiple domain names
and so this is how they handle that sort
of fact that they return a whole list of
results and associated with that once
that result gets used once you
done with it you're supposed to call a
function called free adder info that
will basically dispose of all the
elements of that linked list you don't
have to do it yourself with free and
then there's a another helper function
called GA r ster error that you use if
there's an error code to help you
interpret that error and it returns an
error code so as I mentioned it returns
up a link twist that result is a linked
list of these a get of adders Struck's
header info struck and the adder info
struct has iliyan fields some of which
you'll use and some which you won't this
is for example when you're passing in
hints hints is sort of that what you're
passing in the information you know some
conditions about what you're looking for
in this request and then what some of
these you pass in and some of it returns
and so some of these fields are ones
that then you can use when you're making
calls to other socket functions
functions in the socket library it'll
fill in instead of you having to worry
about what's the structure the format of
a sock adder in and how do I convert
into network order and stuff it will do
all that for you
so it's a little confusing to use though
because sometimes the stuff you're
providing is stuff you're giving it and
sometimes it's stuff that it's returning
back to you and then there's an inverse
function that so get editor info is
given a it's actually give me the
address information about some name and
get name info is I give you an address
and you give me back some documentation
about it including potentially a domain
name so there you pass in as a the first
argument is a sock adder struct remember
for this lecture and I think in the book
in a few places we've sort of created a
type def to alias so we don't have to
say struct sock adder all over the place
but that's what the SA is and it will
provide back information about that that
address so if you passing in a 32 bit IP
address you can get it to return either
a dotted decimal version of that or to
do the DNS lookup and have it come back
with the domain name for that
so this is that program that I just
demoed to you this one called host info
so all it's really going to do is use
these features to all on the command
line give a domain name you say and it
will just come back with a list of IP
addresses so and this is pretty much the
way you write code for this get adder
info API that you typically so hints is
the information I'm passing about what
it is I'm looking for here and so you
start typically by zeroing out that
entire field and then setting the
particular things you want
so in particular in this code that's it
that's in the slides and the one I demo
to you last time I'm only going to be
looking for ipv4 connections and so I
use the constant called AF I net which
is defined in the sockets interface and
also I'll say that I want a TCP
connection out what's called a socket
stream which if you recall is the sort
of protocol that 99% of the the IP
traffic in the world is carrying is on
TCP meaning it provides a somewhat
higher level abstraction of of what's
going on of sending packets back and
forth so that's as much hint as I'm
giving it here and now I'm I'm making a
call to get adder info and this argument
is the name which is I'm getting it
right off of the command line here so in
my demo it was always the commit up a
domain name I'm passing it null for the
service as I mentioned this call you
typically have one of the two are is
null but not both hints is what I'm
passing in is this is the kind of
information I want and list P is a will
now become a pointer to the results that
get returned by get adder info
so that's the calling all of its quarry
okay and now I want to go back so I got
one of those linked lists and that will
have a whole bunch of IP address of
potentially multiple IP addresses in it
maybe just one maybe none but some
number of them in a link twist and I
want to walk through that list and get
back the dotted decimal version of all
those names or the colon eyes of those
ipv6 addresses I don't know how you
refer to those by the way
I know relatively little about IB v6 I
have to confess so then there's a
function called get name info which
usually you use to take a socket address
IP address and go backward and get a
domain name but if I tell it by a flag
one of the the final argument to it is a
flag argument and say what I want back
from this is not a donut main name I
wanted in this numeric format either
dotted decimal or the Cohen's between
hex digits so by passing that to get
name info what it's going to return and
I'm passing in a buffer meaning of a
care star and some size of that buffer
and it's going to fill that in with the
string representation of it so you see
this is a way I'm going from the if you
look at this is the actual sock adder of
each of the wist elements I'm giving it
it's going from that sock adder which
embedded within it as you know is the
four byte IP address and what it's doing
is it's taking that flipping the bytes
well and converting it to the dotted
decimal form so this function can do a
lot of different things and I'm using it
for that particular feature here
question
if he is no then I will go very far hmm
yes because you know it's a
null-terminated whist so other questions
good questions but that's exactly the
code you saw running and all I did to
generalize it to include ipv6 addresses
was I commented out this one say I don't
I don't demand that it be a IP AFI net
is a shorthand for ipv4 so by commenting
that out it said okay I'll get whatever
TCP connections this domain will support
and that will include ipv6 addresses so
I thought it's pretty neat and you have
to be a pretty nerdy but I am pretty
nerdy to think this kind of thing is
neat but that you could write code and
in this way that whether you're doing
your different versions of the Internet
Protocol well it's all one common body
of code so we've seen demo of this okay
so now let's jump into that shows you
sort of a little bit of this get adder
info API now let's jump into the the
full-blown web server part and as I
mentioned in chronological order you
actually want to set up the server first
but it's easiest to understand the code
for the client because as you see it has
a couple fewer calls to make so let's go
for through the client and just imagine
that somewhere out there there's a
server that's waiting for us to connect
to
so this now doesn't perhaps when you
break it down maybe this picture looks a
little less daunting
we already saw get a tour info is the
way I'm going to get an IP address out
of whatever I'm where my server is
socket I mentioned this yesterday or
last time it's just a local call that's
used to allocate some data structures
for this particular connection and then
connect is like placing a call it's an
API it's actually sending over the
Internet to the server some information
saying hey I'd like to connect you and
then once the server risk that once that
connection is accepted then I can begin
my session so let's look at that
so first of all I have to go through all
this rigmarole with get adder info but
it will look pretty similar to what
you've seen before except I'm going to
give a little more information because I
want this to be I'm filling in a few
more details here because I want to
specify more features of this connection
so I'm saying that it's a TCP connection
that's a sock stream I'm saying that I'm
going to give it a port number in a
numeric form you could also say as I
mentioned of the certain ports have
standard names HTTP SSH and so forth and
you can actually pass in the string
representation of those but I'm using
this in a sort of idiosyncratic way here
and then this feature get adder config
is a parameter that's described in the
book and it they say it's a good idea to
use it and then I'm making a call to my
friend get adder info with these hints
and it's going to return back this
linked list of representing the the
results of this request so basically a
linked list of IP addresses
and now just like you saw before I'm
going to walk that list with a except
now what I'm going to try and do is for
each of those say well here's a number
let me give that a try and if that fails
here's another address let me give that
a try so I'm going to just sequentially
try all the different addresses you saw
for example for potential addresses for
Twitter I'll walk through all of those
and on each one I'm going to call for a
socket and the socket is the one that as
I said it allocates some data structures
I talked about this last time that's why
I'm rushing through is pretty fast but
you'll notice that the fields that
you're filling in are actually all been
generated for us by the get adder info
call so whereas the East have to
remember oh this is a number and it
should be a shortened network order and
yada da pretty much nowadays you can
just say here I'm just going to pass you
this information that this
was returned by a function call oh and
then as I mentioned also last time I
know I went through a pretty fast last
time socket actually returns back to you
a file descriptor and you recall a file
descriptor is just a small integer
starts with 0 1 & 2 and then it goes up
from there and so I'm going to interface
with this network code as if I'm talking
through files but it doesn't socket
doesn't actually do anything as far as
the internet goes there's nothing going
there's not even the you know serious
effort within the operating system
nothing goes over the network here so
the real work here is but it also
allocates some some local data
structures and then what I'll do is I'll
attempt to connect to the server and
again you'll see the various arguments I
have to pass to the connect command I
get provided for me out of this call I
made to get a tour info and that's
either going to work or it's not going
to work
similarly the socket call is either
going to work or not work be very
unusual for a call to socket to fail but
connect for example will fail if the
server's not available or doesn't like
you for some reason and so if that
succeeds I'm going to break out of this
loop I'm going to then free this data
structure and return the client the file
descriptor for the this particular
function its job is to open a connection
to a client and return a file descriptor
for it and this is just what happens if
you fall out of the loop not having made
any connections
ok so I know this is I'm marching this
fast and as I said I know from my own
personal experience I can attest this
stuff just takes time to understand
because there's so many different
features here ok but that's the idea is
we're going to now on this server side
which as I mentioned is that actually
what you do beforehand because you can't
really have a client connect to a server
that doesn't exist but it's just a
little bit trickier to understand what's
going on but you'll see it the first two
steps are the same I need a socket but
then remember what I want to do is
essentially set up a server that's
listening on a particular port for
clients to request on it and that's the
function of the bind and the listen
functions and then the accept is when
I'm saying ok the server is ready I'm
ready to accept requests and it will
fire that up in particular the accept
will just stop and hang up and wait
indefinitely until some connection
request comes in so if the server has no
customers if there are no clients it
will just be waiting potentially forever
with the call to accept ok everything
else goes through boom boom boom but
that one is where the actual waiting
occurs for client connections
some way I should mention the Kinect
will also hang up and wait until the
connection is formed but typically it's
built in with a time out so that it will
fail if it takes too long and there's
you can adjust the parameters on both of
these how long you wait for whether your
weight or not but I'm talking the
typical case so anyways that again what
will look a little those functions then
okay so this again we have to make a
call to get editor info and this time
it's not because I need any IP addresses
I already have an IP address I'm a local
server I don't actually need to know the
IP addresses of my of the clients I
usually won't know them but I need to
fill in all those nasty little data
structures and so that's what I'm going
to use get adder info here for here so
I'm going to say this time again I want
a TCP connection a sock stream I want it
to be a listening for any IP address
connection coming in so it's passive
meaning it's not actively reaching out
its
passively waiting for connection
requests I'll say that I'm going to tell
you a port number that I'm going to
actually use as my servers port number
and then I'm going to make a call and
this time you see that I'm not giving
any information about the host because I
am the host but I'm giving the
information of the port number that I'm
using for this server and the other
hints that I've just filled in and then
it will return a wispy yes
memset is the standard way that you set
all the bytes in in some number of bytes
to a fixed value it's the same as if
you've use B 0 before or B it was is the
way you often would zero out a bunch of
bytes and if you look at the web page
and I don't know why they say use memset
don't use b 0 anymore so cal equal to 0
it out but I'm not actually eleking
anything see the hints is a struct here
and remember is struct is just a bunch
of bytes and so if I make that
particular call to memset it will set
every byte in that structure to 0 and
this is sort of the official standard
way you're supposed to do that kind of
thing it's a good question so question
hey I passive is that it's a it's a
listening connection it's going to be a
listening connection and a I adder
config was some other argument and quite
honestly I don't remember but you saw I
gave it before with the get host name so
I don't remember it's it's a slot
somewhat obscure per parameter that's
not even a required parameter it's in
the book I'm sorry or you could Google
it right now
one interesting thing is I didn't say
that on this code on either side that
it's a Fi net I didn't force this to be
ipv4 code this will work for ipv4 or six
the exact same code
okay so again whispy comes back with a
list of stuff typically that list will
be of length one in fact I don't know
why it would be anything else but it has
the same general look to it so again I'm
going to make a call to socket to create
a file descriptor that I'm going to use
this will be the one that it's missed
the server listens on of your connection
requests and then there's another kind
of obscure thing you have to do of
setting some options on that socket that
will get it to free it up more quickly
if there's a failure if this is gone
this one I dunno and it's kind of
obscure and it's in the book so I won't
spend a lot of time talking about it
okay but now what here's the real work
is the bind call is the one that says I
want this file descriptor to be
associated with this information which
in particular specifies the port number
so that's where the binding occurs for
this machine
remember port numbers are a resource
that all the different applications on a
single machine are sort of sharing where
are competing for and so this is
requesting I want to use this particular
port number in doing this in setting up
a server and that may fail if the ports
already in use or if you're trying to
set up a service on a port that you're
not allowed to do like you're not
allowed to set up a service on port 80
unless you have root access
so and then again it passes in the
information that was filled in by the
call to get a tour info
so we're not quite done yet but we if
this succeeds then what we've done is we
bound a port number and a file
descriptor together and a socket
but it all that's done is that's again
just within the machine saying okay I
agree you you you particularly this
particular process gets to be listening
on a particular port but it's not
actually listening yet and I don't know
why they split it into two but they do
and now I actually have to explicitly
make a call to listen saying okay now I
really am ready to receive connection
requests and you can give as a parameter
of a number that says how many a request
connection requests are you allowed to
queue up before they start getting
refused and this is a performance
parameter that if you set it too low
then unless you have a really fast
server people will get failures in their
connection requests but if it's too big
then you can you're vulnerable to
certain types of sort of denial of
service attacks so again a little bit of
an obscure feature but the result of
this is now I'm returning out of this a
file descriptor that the server can use
to listen to pick up connection requests
okay so let's do a little example of how
we might actually do something and I'm
going to use as an example a rather
mundane application which is an echo
server an echo server is just one that
responds back whatever it just received
and the code for it saw in the book on
the slides we're studying
so let me set up this amazing
demonstration
so it's called the echo server I I
meaning iterative it can only do one
connection request at a time and I'm
going to set it up on my laptop here and
I'll connect to that
so you'll see that I told the server use
port 15 to 13 which is just a random
number I picked out as the port number
in general if you want to do your own
stuff you pick port numbers that are a
thousand or greater and they're limited
to be unsigned 16-bit n so 64 or 65
thousand something some maximum and as
long as and by the way if you're you
live in a corporate world your ports
will all be locked down and they will
not let you do this but in the CMU
environment has a pretty permissive
policy and actually I'm just doing this
on localhost but you're allowed to at
CMU open up ports like you want so
anyways I'm going to run this client and
you'll see that the server just said
I've received a connection from the
localhost not very exciting and I've
received it from port five five four
five seven so this is the part that got
assigned to the client in making the
connection the server is using port 15
to 13 and you recall we talked about
last time that a link is defined by the
host and port names on either end and
that the client side is usually assigned
what they call a ephemeral port it's
meaning it's just assigned a trip for
this particular session that I'm going
to run and now here's the amazing
feature of an echo server is that you
can type in stuff and it will come back
to you
because echoing so what's happening is
I'm sending those meaningful messages to
the server it's reading them and it's
just sending them right back again
and then the clients reading that and
printing it on the screen so that's it's
not it's sort of the minimum
functionality you could imagine but you
can see that the server is telling you
oh by the way I just received so many
bytes so many bytes so many bytes so you
can see that it's actually doing
something and then if I send it into
file which is just to control D the
client will exit and the server will
drop that connection but doesn't show
you anything and if I wanted to I could
start it again and you see this time it
signed a different ephemeral port to the
client but I can only do one at a time
if I tried to now do another connection
I will try and do it if I tried to do it
I wouldn't I
it would just hang up the the client
would hang up it would not be able to
get a connection because the server is
only able to handle one client at a time
okay so that's the what the application
does and now let's see how its
implemented
it's pretty simple the the nastiness was
those functions we've already seen so
here's the client side of it it calls
that function I went through called open
the client file descriptor where you
gave the name of the host and the name
of the port that you're the server's
operating on so I said here localhost 15
to 13 and I'm going to initialize a
buffer that will be used for
communication back and forth for this
network communication so now echoing
means I from a client perspective it
will just read in what I've typed so
using get s or F get s to read in what's
been typed on the standard input and as
long as that's not null meaning I don't
have a end of file then I will write it
to the client file descriptors so that's
how I actually send it over the network
as I do a write to that a socket that
that file descriptor represents and then
to get something back from the server
its response I'll do a read and riyo as
you call has embedded within it now what
file descriptor that read is using so
I'll say read from that particular file
descriptor fill the results back into
this buffer so I'm using buff both as a
sending buffer and a receiving buffer
and then just print that out onto the on
to the terminal and this is by the way
the new lines being included in this not
just the in all of this and that's how
it's working so that's all that happens
so the main point you see here is that
I'm using this a socket like a file to
both send and receive
the server code is just a shade more
nasty than that to support some of those
amazing features it has so in particular
there's a weird struct called a socket
or storage that is just again part of
this generic API that gives you a buffer
of some kind that's big enough to store
a name of a host is what I'm going to
use it for you and so I'm going to
accept a connection so except recall you
recall is the way it it says okay I'm
going to wait here until a client
contacts this server so that you make a
call to accept and it will just hang
until that contact occurs and then what
it will return from you is a new file
descriptor that we call a connection
file descriptor here which is different
from the listening file descriptor and
the reason is doesn't really show up in
this code where I'm doing iteratively
but you can imagine if I had a server
and I wanted to be able to maintain a
thousand connections at once there'll be
one of those file descriptors that I
pick up new requests on and then all the
other ones are the various other clients
that I'm communicating with right now oh
and then what accept fills in here into
this information it's a sock adder
struct is about information about the
client the IP address of the client
and I'll use this call called get name
info which is again at one of these
kitchen sink features that I'll pass in
this client address and it will come
back with the I the domain name of the
client and that's what you saw how it
printed out when the connection was
formed where that connection was coming
from so this all this business here is
used to support that feature of being
able to print out what's the host number
name and what port am I using and this
thing by the way client port is a client
host name and client port are both
buffers yes host name and port are both
buffers and I'm passing a pointer those
buffers and I'm passing their length max
line and then the call to get name info
is filling those in with a string
representations of the host name in the
port
and now it just makes a call to the echo
function which I'll show you momentarily
and then it closes that connection and
then this continues you see the while
one this is in a loop forever and you
actually have to control C on this
program to get it to quit okay so let me
just look one more so the func this now
is the echo function that the server
uses and it's pretty straightforward in
fact it looks kind of like what you just
saw except it flips around the reading
and the writing it will read some number
of bytes over the connection file
descriptor and if that's a nonzero
number then it will echo that back by
writing it if it's a zero that means
it's detected and into file and it will
just exit from that little loop but
remember echo is within a bigger loop of
accepting new connection requests okay
but again just see that it reads is way
of accepting information from the client
and then it writes to send information
back to the coin good so one interesting
feature is if you want to test some
programs you can use a program called
telnet which it used to be the
old-fashioned way you use before SSH
this is how you communicated with other
machines and it's absolutely completely
insecure so don't ever use it to
actually and most most places you can't
even make a connection to another
machine using telnet it's amazing how
simple life used to be but for example
if I tell net to myself on that port it
will begin a session and it will in fact
look a lot like an echo client because
because telnet just sends information to
the server and the server is designed to
echo it back and so it will print the
response and so if effectively telnet is
behaving like an echo client for me and
I'll demo that because it's useful I
mean this is a pretty trivial program
but there's actually times you can use
telnet if there's the server somewhere
out there and you want to give it a poke
and see what's going on as a tool you
can use telnet let's see you have to
escape with a control right bracket
quick okay so now let's move on to http
I try to get rid of all the animations
in this okay so that's sort of the
basics of the low-level socket
programming that you need to create
client-server applications so the best
example out there of a client-server
application is the world wide web and
you know the idea web servers and your
browser is a client so but all of that
sits on top of the protocols for that
sit on top of the other internet
protocols so we talked about TCP is sort
of sits on top of the lowest level the
packet protocol and then HTTP sits on
top of that and uses TCP connections to
send and receive data over the World
Wide Web and that's all according to a
protocol that was developed starting in
the early 90s but and that's what Tim
Berners Tim berners-lee did initially
and it's gone through a couple revisions
but the latest one is still dates back
to 1999 HTTP version
excuse me 1.1 so just as a some
terminology and you've sort of heard
this at various different ways is you
can one of the clever things about HTTP
is it lets you set set handles different
formats you can send a JPEG image you
can send a a text and so forth and those
are all encoded in a format called mime
which is actually just a way to take a
binary values and convert them into hex
formatted strings
oh and and then sort of a standard for
how you encode it at one end how you
decode it the other and so you get to
specify when you're sending stuff you
specify what what type of information it
is and then the other thing you've
probably experienced and now we're
talking a little bit ancient history and
I'll update it momentarily but
classically you either use static
content meaning a fixed web page that
was written in HTML format and was
designed to just give you information
that was the same every time you looked
at it or dynamic content where you will
change so for example a application a
server application that's giving you the
weather it's not the same page every
time and so it will format it in dynamic
content if you make a request nowadays
it's gotten a lot more complicated
because of JavaScript and all these
other sort of client-side programming
languages that actually execute code on
your client and communicates back and
forth to get results so I'm a little bit
dated here talking about this sort of
old-style way of working but in all
cases what actually comes across the
wires are some type of a file
and then you've heard the term URL
meaning Universal resource locator is a
combination of a couple things one is it
tells you where is that information in
terms of a domain name and potentially
with a port number and then also on that
particular host where where within the
host is that information to be found
and there's defaults like if you don't
give anything it defaults to index.html
for example but a URL in principle gives
you where to locate something on a
remote machine and now we've seen
examples of the tricks that DNS plays so
that even though you're giving a
hostname a domain name it could be any
of a number of different servers but the
the concept still the same
so when I make a request then when I
running my browser and I want to see a
webpage what it does is it sends an HTTP
request out to the server
to do something and to return back a
webpage and there's a couple of
different standard services the most
common the one that it's used ninety 90
some percent of the time is get get me a
page and there's other stuff too
and
and then it will respond back with
what's called the response line and
embedded within that response will be
the thing you're asking for but in front
of it all is a header that contains
other stuff that is of of some range of
interest of whether you really care or
not it can also come back with a
response that says there's an error code
as you know the infamous 404 error code
so let me give you a demo of this just
so we're talking a little abstract and
this is a little tricky to make it work
and I'll use auto telnet as a way to
probe a webserver
so I'll make a telnet connection to the
computer science departments a web
server and now I need to make a get
request this remember it all it is is
now I'm basically providing the exact
bytes that will be seen by the web
server so if I say get slash tilde
bryant test on HTML see if this really
works
hot worked
I'm always surprised when things
actually work ah
so anyways let's just look at what
happened so at the top is what I typed
in it's getting and this I'm giving some
the name of a particular web page that I
made up just for this purpose
a fairly simple web page and I'm telling
it I want the response in the HTTP 1.1
format and then I have to also give a
hostname explicitly and the reason for
this is a given machine can actually be
a serve multiple hosts like if you know
I want to pay for a hosting of some
domain name of say 2 godaddy.com but
it's serving hundreds or thousands of
different domain names and so it
actually used that host information to
figure out oh which particular web you
know customer am i supporting here ok
and now it came back with its response
and it said the code 200 means that was
accepted which it tells you ok and now
it comes back with this is the header
information that says here's the date
here the server here's some cookie
information it's a the overall content
is exactly 479 bytes and it's a text
HTML format and then it will return back
the raw HTML that this web page had
which is what I actually you know I type
that I did this by hand but you can
imagine other types of things and then
it just closes the connection so you can
see that this return both the header
information and the actual content
information as well and so that's the
general idea of what an HTTP transaction
looks like and the slides go through a
different version of it but it's the
same general idea
so the text has a really interesting
code that I highly recommend you read
and study called tiny which is the
world's smallest functioning webserver
and what it's really only a couple pages
of code it serves it says some very
basic handling of static and dynamic
content it's something you can sit down
and read and study 239 lines of code now
it lacks a lot of features it does very
bad job of handling errors it doesn't
have a lot of the functionality you'd
come to expect on a server so it's been
stripped down to the sort of Barriss
bones to demonstrate the the concepts
but it's pretty cool that it works and I
can say this because I didn't write it
so so the overall idea then is on the
cert it's a server so it's receiving
requests from clients from browsers
saying I want this web page or I want to
execute this particular dynamic program
to get dynamic content so it comes in
with a request get requests like you
just saw and it splits that it picks out
the what's called the URI the argument
to the get request a URI is a universal
resource indicator which is not a
complete potential URIs are a super set
of URLs URL has to include the hostname
and all the information to get from
anywhere to anywhere but a URI can just
be a portion of that information and
then it it will determine is this a
request for static or dynamic content
I'll show you both of them hopefully and
if it's a static content all it has to
do is retrieve a file on its own machine
send that back in that format that I
just showed you so let's take a look so
this is sort of the guts of the static
server
so what it's done is its received a
request this is you know a function a
helper function of of this code so I'm
kind of buried down in the middle but
what it's picked out is the server has
received a request for a particular file
name from the URI and it's also done a
look up through the OS call to figure
out how big is that file how many bytes
long is that file and it's also given
the file descriptor that is the connect
it the file descriptor for this
particular connection so all it's doing
here you'll notice is it's doing a bunch
of Spirit ups into a buffer and what
it's doing there is its formatting the
header information as a byte is just a
big long string including the returns in
it and one of the features which don't
ask me why the great wisdom of of Tim
Berners we did or whoever figured this
out but every line has to finish with
both a carriage return and a new line
instead of the usual Linux thing of just
new lines so that's what the backslash R
backslash n means but you'll see it's
going to respond back to with an okay
and some of this kind of information
that's not very exciting but the ones
that really matter are are the lengths
the in bytes that has to be given and
the type ones beginning this file type
oh there's another function oh I
remember why there's a another helper
function here that because this supports
not just text but also gif and JPEG
images so get file type is another
function somewhere else that's telling
which which a mime type is this
particular file and and so it's putting
that together and it's
and now write set out so it writes the
header information out to the client so
it's sending back to the client and then
it's going through a few gyrations here
to get the file open it up and then
there's a function called MF if you guys
covered them up yet know which is just a
tricky way to avoid having to actually
read the file into the machine
but basically be able to pass off a
pointer directly to or into the read it
through explicit read commands into yet
another buffer just avoids one step of
buffering so all it does is map then of
from the operating system where this
particular file is located and then
writes that so now it's sending it off
to the client and so this could be done
with a regular read in a but this is a
little bit more elegant way to handle it
and you'll notice by the way that the
content length here is the length of the
file the and not does not include the
the number of bytes in the header so the
header comes first
there's no length associated with it
that so sent back but now the only way
that the client knows exactly how many
bytes that response is going to be is by
picking out this number in the header
and reading that many bytes from it
we'll see that in a minute
but anyways this is the way a file gets
sent so now let's just real quickly look
at dynamic content so the idea of
dynamic content is it lets you pass in
parameters to a program that then gets
executed and the purpose that what that
program then has to do is compose a web
page and send that web page back
you so I'm going to demo this with a
feature built into here
so in particular you probably can't you
can barely see them I don't have a good
way to blow up the thing but the um you
can also see what kind of things I look
at but anyways if I just say local host
:
15 to 13 that means port number 15 to 13
on my local machine which is currently
running the tiny web server and the only
webpage available for it is this rather
stunning figure here but it shows that
it can handle both gif content and text
HTML but it also supports another
interesting feature which is a program
that can add two numbers called add com
so our idea for a startup company that
didn't quite make it so so in particular
that the idea of this is it's a CGI
program it's a dynamic content so that I
passing two numbers embedded within the
URL my request and it comes back with a
web page that is beautifully formatted
like this one so you can't see very well
maybe but if you look up there the teeny
tiny print at the top Yosi localhost
colon 15 213 that's the web server and
slash cgi - bin that's what this
particular server and what most servers
do for interpreting dynamic content and
then a program it's an executable file
called adder and then the argument
string that you embed in this kind of
curious way the question mark and then
use ampersands to separate out the
different fields so that's all pretty a
standard way of handling dynamic content
and as I said nowadays there's a lot
fancier ways of doing it but that's sort
of the basic way and you'll see it's
still getting
used today so imagine that this time
it's a get request but instead of the
adder function at some other Perl
program that is sitting on the server
somewhere called Eng and we won't worry
about what that program does we'll just
show you the idea behind it so in
particular there's a get request comes
in and it says cgi-bin
and then the next argument is
interpreted as the name of a file and
what will happen then is that the server
will spawn off a process
using our friends fork and exec which
you know so well now doing the shell web
so and that that program will execute of
will execute and it will its job then is
to generate a file in HTML format and
then the server will send the result
back to the client so there's a few
details we got to figure out to make
this work
one is how will I actually pass
arguments how will nvl know what's being
passed to it as arguments how npl get
whatever page HTML it creates back to
the server so that the server can send
it to the client those are all the sort
of details of the CGI specification CGI
stands for common gateway interface
so you just saw a demo of
edcom and so let's just look at how this
works so as I mentioned the way things
get passed is within the URL you include
the program name and then the question
mark is what is like the Terminator for
the program name and then all the other
arguments with ampersands between them
and you can't have any blanks in here so
they put % 20s and as you probably see
in various other those are called escape
codes when you can't use a particular
character how do you encode it in some
other way
so the first thing is how does the
server then pass the argument to the
program that gets executed well it's
really weird the way it does it is by
creating an environment variable for
your machine
that's called query string and so the
server defines that environment variable
and then the job on the CGI side of the
script is to then retrieve that
environment variable is a way of getting
the string you can already see hey wait
a minute what if you were running
multiple servers at once you can see
you've got a problem here but actually
no environments are specific to
particular processes so this will work
so it's creating for the application
program that we'll be able to sort of
retrieve from the operating system
essentially what arguments were passed
to the are being passed to it
and so this is what the code looks like
for the dynamic server again it's going
to write back
some information back to the the client
and let's look at this and now it's
going to set up this CGI a query string
environment variable and then use our
friends dupe and exec basically to
redirect the standard output to its
client oh I'm sorry
the file descriptor is the the clients
file descriptor so it will tell it's
going to go and we're enough work I'm
sorry so now we're in the child process
okay let me read all the code and within
the child process it's going to rename
the it's standard output so that it's
writing directly to the client and and
then call exec which as you know it's
the way you take this program which is
just given by a file name and fire it up
and get it going with that defined
environment value and then this is the
parent we'll just wait until the child
completes okay so now we're almost done
so the now this is what the actual
program the adder program does the one
that the CGI program the one that's been
forked off and exempt so it creates them
the HTML that you want to send back and
here it's pretty mundane the only actual
HTML and here are the peas meaning
paragraph markers so this is literally
generating HTTP HTML content and storing
them all in a string called content and
now it wants to send that content back
and you saw before that the server
already filled in the top-level stuff
but I have to tell what is the type and
how many bytes it is so I'll use
sterling to figure out how many bytes
I'm sending back and the content type
and then I will and I'm pretty effing
this which as you recall ivory mapped a
standard output now is talking directly
to the client and just to be sure it all
goes out I'll flush that out of there at
the end so what's happening here then is
that it's the job of the the CGI program
to write the HTML and to send it back to
the the client
so again let's just do a real quick demo
here got just enough time
Oh
so I've got the tiny web server running
down at the bottom and I'm using telnet
to reach it and so now I want to say
I have to take time
slash CGI - bin slash adder quest what
numbers do you want to add 17 and 13
so you don't get many shots at it so I
like to double check I'm doing
we worked always amazed so it shouldn't
surprise you what comes back because you
just saw the code that did it
but what you see then is that this first
three lines got generated by the the
server code that comes back with the ok
information about the server and then
the content length was generated by the
CGI program adder and the content type
and then this is the HTML that you saw
being generated so it's actually what
people say about this early world wide
web and it's gotten a lot more
complicated is the best thing Tim
berners-lee was to figure out how simple
it could be because other people were
working much more exotic ways to get
different agents to talk to each other
over the Internet and what berners-lee
figured out is we can just kind of
cobble together standard ideas of
sockets interface have some protocol
pretty straightforward protocol handle
different content type of set up these
dynamic things by forking off a process
every time which is extraordinarily
inefficient way to do it like to add two
numbers by forking off a whole process
and doing it is totally absurd but then
so is addcom but you know it's not it in
some ways it he took a bunch of ideas
that existed and figured out how to put
it together and I'll recognize that the
value people would obtain from that and
it took the internet from being
something that was certainly used by
nerdy people to talk to each other and
opened it up to all the things that we
know of today so it was a huge step
forward I give them full credit even if
from a technical point of view is
actually fairly straightforward ok so
that will do us for today