good afternoon everybody welcome good to
see you today we're going to continue
our study of exceptional control flow by
looking at some higher level mechanisms
known as Linux signals and see non-local
jumps now we're going to spend most of
our most of our time looking at signals
because they have a lot of subtleties
the semantics can be kind of confusing
so we're going to we're going to spend
most of our time there and I'll mention
the idea of non-local jumps but for
details on those you'll want to look in
your textbook and in the slides at the
Supplemental slides at the end of this
the slide deck now to motivate the
notion of signals I want to want to talk
a little bit about shell programs now as
we mentioned last time there's only one
way to create processes on a Linux
system and that's using the fork call in
fact the all of the processes on the
system actually form a hierarchy so that
the very first process created when you
boot the system up is the anit process
which has a process ID of one and then
all other processes on the system are
descendants of that of that init process
now the anit process when it starts up
it creates daemons which are
long-running programs that provide
services typically so for example of a
web server it other kinds of services
that you always want running on the
system and then eventually it creates
login so called login shells which
provide the command-line interface to
two users so when you log into a Linux
system what you eventually get to is
that is a login shell that's expecting
you to type commands now the login login
shells execute programs on your your
behalf so when we type something into
the shell
say we type the LS command we're asking
we're asking the shell to run the
executable program called LS and so what
the shell will do is it will create a
child and then it will execute LS within
that child process and it's possible
that that process may create other other
child processes so a shell is an
application program no different from
any other program that executes programs
on the behalf of users okay the default
shell for Linux is called bash but
there's there's other shells that that
were created on earlier with earlier
versions of UNIX SH was the original
shell called the bourne shell because it
was created by steven born and when
berkeley came out with their
distribution of unix they created a
shell called the CSH now the the
execution is in a shell is a sequence of
read and evaluate steps so first a shell
prints out a prompt and then it waits
for it waits for you to type something
in on the command line and hit return
okay and typically what you're what
you're typing in is a is a command which
is just the so the first thing you type
is a command and then you follow that
with optional arguments separated by
spaces okay so once you hit once you
type in a command and those optional
arguments and hit return the shell
checks for the end of file character
which is a control D to terminal and if
so it exits otherwise it evaluates that
command line and the evaluation consists
and then when it returns from the
evaluation it just does the same thing
over in it now the evaluation consists
of the following kinds of steps first it
parses the command line
and bite and and in the process so it
takes the command-line which in this
example is in buff and it produces an RV
array okay where arc v-0 is a command
and then our V one and two and so on are
the optional arguments and the
convention in a shell is that if the
command line is terminated by an
ampersand then you're asking the shell
to run that job to run that command in
the background meaning the shell won't
wait for that job to finish before it
goes through its next read stub if it if
the the line that you type doesn't have
an ampersand then you're asking the
shell to to run that job in the
foreground which means the shell will
wait so so first we parse this this
command line into an art V array and we
return whether or not it was terminated
by an ampersand D so BG for background
if art V zero is null then that means we
just hit a we just hit return right so
as an empty line so we'll just return
and just ignore those now a shell also
implements what are called built-in
commands so various things like jobs BG
f G are examples of built-in commands
which are just implemented in the shell
itself so if you type if the first thing
you type if the command you enter is a
built in then the shell will it will
check that it will check our v-0 for a
to see if it's a built-in command and if
it is it'll just execute it whatever
whatever it is you asked it to do okay
otherwise if it's not a built-in then
that means that that you're asking the
shell to run some program okay so in
that case the shell will fork a child
and then the child will execute that
program by calling exact ve passing as
the first argument the name of the
command and as the second and third
argument
RV and and the environment respectively
now exactly if you recall from last time
never returns unless there's an error so
it checks so we check it the return
value for x ik ve and if it returns less
than zero fact the only time it will
return if it does return it will always
return minus one but we're just being
careful here so we check that for a an
error and in in print and error message
if we find an error and then exit so
once the once the once the parent gets
control again then it waits for that
foreground job to terminate okay so if
it's not a background job then it waits
for it to terminate by calling wake ped
and waiting for that child that
foreground job to terminate and then and
reaping it otherwise if it's a
background job it just prints say a
message and goes on so this is really
interesting right that there's really
the only difference between a foreground
job and a background job is just that
the shell does a weight pit on that job
or not right so there otherwise there's
really there's really no difference now
what's the prob there's a problem with
our example show and that the problem is
that we're we're doing the right thing
for the foreground job we always have to
reap these children so they they so that
they're their state can be released but
we're not we're not doing anything to
reap any background jobs right when if
the background job so if not BG we're
just printing a message and then we're
returning and then we're continuing with
this read evaluate step and never never
going back and and taking care of that
of that background job so this is a
problem because that the background job
will eventually become if we have enough
of those jobs we create a memory leak
that could crash the system right so
this is an error
so what are we going to do about this
well it turns out that exceptional
control flow will help us solve this
problem and what happens is that the
kernel will notify the shell when when a
any of its children terminate okay and
then the shell can can then react to
that and issue a wait pit okay and this
this notification mechanism that the the
kernel uses is something called a signal
so a signal is a small message that the
kernel delivers to a process to notify
it that there's been some event in the
system now so this is very similar to
the exceptions that we studied the last
time right except it's it's it's all
implemented in software now kernel
signals are always sent from the kernel
but sometimes they're sent at the
request of another process right
sometimes the the kernel will notice
that there's some event other times
another process will ask the kernel to
send a message to some other process now
that we say that it's a small message
because the only information that's
contained in a signal is its it's a
unique integer ID and the fact that it
was it was it was delivered okay so
that's so there's nothing else in a
signal except except that it arrived and
that it has some some some unique ID now
examples of these are the sig int so
signals have this I this unique ID and
then they also have a name so the sig
antis is what the when you type control
C at on the command line the kernel
sends a signal to every any processes in
the foreground and the default action of
receiving a SIGINT is to terminate right
so this is how if you're running a
foreground job you hit control C
you get the prompt back because it kills
that job sig kill number nine can be
used to kill terminate any program so
these two have sig ant and sig kill have
the same effect on the programs me that
they kill the program the the unique
aspect of sig kill is that there's no
way to ignore it or override it okay so
this is like the failsafe as we'll see
there are there are ways to to catch and
ignore other signals like sig int sig
SEC v is the our favorite segment
segmentation violation so if you if you
access a region of memory that's
protected or or not legal then your
program will the kernel will send your
that process a sig seg v okay signal and
that the default the default effective
that is to terminate the program sig
alarm is a way within your program you
can arrange for a signal to be sent to
yourself so you can say inside your
program send me a sig alarm signal in
three seconds something like that so
this is a way to do things like you can
set up timers you can set up timeouts
like if you want to X if you want to set
a timeout value and you're doing some
some some work and you want to guard
against that that work taking
exceptionally long time you can you can
you can use sig alarm to set a timeout
and then a very important one is as
we'll see that would be very important
for our shell is the sig child signal
which the colonel sends to a parent
every time one of its children
terminates or stops okay so this as
we'll see now we'll see this is how
we're going this is how our shell that
is going to actually reap it's it's all
of its children right is by taking
advantage of the sig child signal but
before I can show you that we need to go
through a number of concepts
around signals okay like I said the the
semantics of signals it's probably one
of the thorniest aspects of Linux it was
it was developed very early in the the
lifespan of Linux when and it maybe
wasn't as clean as it could be right so
in order to get a handle on signals
we're going to be very careful about
defining terms and very careful about
the way we talk about them so we say
that the kernel sends or delivers a
signal to some destination process and
it does this by setting some state in
the context of the destination process
now nothing happens except that some
bits get changed in the destination
process context okay there's no there's
no impact of immediate impact of sending
a signal now a kernel sends a signal
either because it detected some event in
the in the system like that like a child
process is terminated for example or
another process has asked the kernel to
send to deliver a process on a signal on
its behalf and there's a number of ways
to do that one of them is with the kill
system call it's kind of an unfortunate
tournament I mean the so kill is a
general way to send signals and the the
impact is not as is sometimes not to
kill the program right but for some
reason they chose to to call it kill
now the destination process receives a
signal when it's forced by the kernel to
act in some way to react in some way to
the delivery of a signal okay so these
are two very different things sending a
signal set state in the context of the
destination process receiving a signal
is what happens when the destination
process is is finally forced by the
kernel to act in some way to react in
some way
now some possible ways to react are to
just ignore the signal okay to terminate
the process or to catch the signal by
executing a user level function called a
signal handler so in this case when we
when we catch signals it's very similar
to the the and executes a signal handle
it's very similar to executing a an
exception handler in response to some
kind of event in the system now the
difference is that exception handlers
are in the kernel signal handlers are
actually just in your C code okay there
and they execute in your in your process
so the so the way to think about if if
we catch a signal by executing a signal
handler we have our process executing
instructions and then the signal is
received by that process so the kernel
passes control to a signal handler which
is also just in the code that's
executing in the current process it's
just a function in our in our C code the
signal handler runs and when it returns
it eventually returns back to the next
instruction and then then we continue
okay so it's it's it's just like kind of
like an interrupt right we just
temporarily pause what we're doing in
the in our code to execute this this
handler before just continuing on
okay now we say that a signal is pending
if it's been sent by the colonel but not
you have received okay so if at any
given point in time there can only be
one pending signal of any particular
type okay so this has very important
consequences for using signals because
you can't cue signals up right at any
point in time there's there can only be
one pending sig child signal for example
or sig sig in signal and if a subsequent
sig child signals say is sent it just
over writes well you can think of it as
it has no impact
it's just discarded right if there's
already a pending signal so they don't
they don't queue up in any meaningful
way now our process can block the
receipt of certain signals okay now it
can't stop signals from being delivered
but it can stop it can stop the process
from having to react to the route to
that signal when it's received okay so
block signals can be delivered but they
won't be received until the signals
unblocked
and pending signals are received at most
once now the colonel keeps track of
these pending and blocked signals in bit
vectors that will call pending and
blocked and pending represents the set
of pending signals right where each bit
in the pending bit vector corresponds to
some particular signal okay so this is
why they can't be queued right because
there's only one bit for any signal Kay
there's only one bit in the bit vector
and if we and when we deliver a signal
we're just setting will set that bit the
colonel will set that bit we deliver
another signal of the same type it'll
just set that bit again which has no has
no effect
now the colonel sets that the bit in
pending when the signals delivered and
it clears it when the signals received
and the colonel also provides mechanism
for users to block signals with this
blocked bit vector so the block bit
vector is the same size as the pending
bit vector turns out it's just a 32 bit
int okay and it can be set and cleared
the bits and that can be set and cleared
using the sig proc mask system call okay
now that the blocked in the linux
literature the blocked bit vector is
also called the signal mask
okay now we want to look in a little
more detail about sending and receiving
signals so let's start first with
sending signals first we need to
understand the idea of a process group
so every process belongs to exactly one
process group and those so here I'm
showing a shell that's in process it has
a process ID of 10 and a process group
ID of 10 the shell created a foreground
job which has a process ID of 20 and a
process group ID of 20 and then all of
the children that this foreground job
created have the same process group ID
of 20 so these these process groups can
be set by a system call set called the
set process group ID and you can and you
can fetch that process group using the
get process group system call so you can
see in this example what what this shell
is done is it created a foreground child
so it created this child and it it
changed the process group ID to be equal
to the process ID of the child and then
when this child created other child
children they just inherited the same
process group ID okay
now this this notion of a process group
is useful because it allows you to send
signals to groups of processes at the
same time and you can do that with a
program called kill which is typically
in /bin directory
and that the kill program you can use
the kill program to send an arbitrary
signal to either an individual process
or all the processes in one process
group so let's look at an example this
program this Forks program creates two
children and with each of which has a
process group of 24 8 1 7 and of course
they have different process they have
different process IDs and so if we if we
do a PS we see these two we see these
two processes running and these just go
into loop so they'll just they'll just
run continuously okay now we can we can
use kill to to kill an individual
process for example so if we call it the
first argument indicates what signal you
want to send so in this case it's its
signal 9 which is the cig kill signal so
kill minus 9 is is a very typical
usually if you want to kill processes
you just kill minus 9 and actually one
of my favorite Auto lab nuke names for
213 was the nickname was kill - 9 15 - 1
3 so but then then the second argument
is the if it's is the the process ID so
this is asking this is asking the kernel
to kill process ID - for a 1 8 by
sending it a cig kill signal now if the
if the process ID is is preceded by a
dash then it sends a signal to every
process in process group - then it
treats this argument as a process
group and it sends a signal to every
process in that process group so in this
case it will send a signal to both of
these both of these children processes
and then afterwards we if we do a PS we
see that those processes are gone okay
that it really did work that way now
another way to send signals is by typing
either control C or control Z at the to
the command line control C causes the
kernel to send a signal to every job in
the the foreground process group and
control Z causes it to send a signal to
every job in the in the foreground
process group the default action for
SIGINT is to terminate the process the
default action for the sig tea stop is
to suspend the process stop it until it
receives a sig cont a signal
so you can see an example of this here
we have a program that creates a parent
and a child running in the foreground so
the parents running in the foreground
now when we type control Z to the
command line the shell notifies us that
it's suspended that process and if we do
a PS we can see the parent and the child
indeed are suspended so the PS indicates
that it's suspended or stopped using RT
now next we type in the built in the
shell built in which is F G and F G
restores those those suspended jobs to
the foreground so after typing F G now
we're running this our program again in
the foreground and then we can kill it
by typing ctrl C which which elicits a
SIGINT whose default action is to
terminate and then when we do a PS we
see that indeed that's that they're gone
now the third way that we can send
signals is by using the kill system call
so here's an example of how that works
so in this in this example we're
creating end children now each of which
goes into an infinite loop and we're
recording this the process ID of each
child that we create and then in it we
go in another loop we go through and we
we kill each of those child processes
with by using the kill function passing
it the process ID and the signal that we
want sent to that process okay and then
we do our due diligence and reap each
one of those children that we've
terminated
now this isn't strictly necessary
because we're going to exit as soon as
this 412 function returns we're going to
exit the code so but we're just being
you know careful here and maybe a little
pedantic but
okay now now let's look at how we
process receive signals
now suppose process a is running along
executing its user code and then there's
a control passes into the kernel because
of some exception
now that exception can be either a timer
going off they've been interrupts or it
can be a trap user calls a system call
okay but it's always caused that the
trap into the or the transferring
control into the kernel is always caused
by some exception so at this point the
kernel calls its scheduler function and
it decides to to do a context switch
from process a to process B and it gets
processed be all set up and right before
it returns from that exception and right
before it's ready to pass control back
to back to process the user code and
process B it checks for any signals that
any pending signals okay and it does
this by computing a bit vector PNB so
pending non blocked which is the logical
and of the pending bit vector and the
inverse of the blocked bit vector okay
so PN B is a list of all the pending
signals that aren't blocked okay so
these are all the pending signals that
should be received if now if pn b is all
zeros then there's no pending signals so
it just returns it passes control back
it passes control back to process b
which can continue executing however if
if P and B is nonzero then it chooses
the smallest nonzero bit in PN B and it
forces process P to receive that signal
the corresponding signal
the receipt of the signal triggers some
action in in the process and then we
repeat that for all the nonzero signals
K that are nonzero bits that are set in
PN B and finally when we've gone all
through all the non zero bits then we
pass control to the next instruction in
in the in in process P so the receipt of
a signal always triggers some action
which is either the process terminates
the process stops until it's restarted
by a sick can't signal the process
ignores the signal ok so that's there's
always some predefined default action
but we can modify that that default
action by using a function system call
called signal ok so we can now signals a
little that's another sort of misleading
kind of term just like kill right
because when we when we send a signal to
a process we don't always want to kill
it and signal doesn't actually signal
anything it just it just modifies the
default action associated with some
signal okay so if the signal function
takes out a signal number and and then
specifies a change in the default action
for that signal and those default
actions can be either to ignore the
signal ok ignore signals of type signal
revert to the default behavior for that
signal or we can we can give it or it
can be the address of a user level
signal handler which is a function that
we've declared in our C program ok it's
there's nothing special about the
function it has a certain prototype that
has it takes a single argument which is
the signal number so when that function
gets called in in response to receiving
a signal that argument will be set to
the signal number so calling signal with
a and specifying a signal handler is
called installing a handler and then
executing the handlers referred to as
catching or executing they were handling
the signal and and this this handler
then is just like an exception handler
when it when it returns it will be when
it's executed it will interrupt the
whatever is currently executing in the
process when it returns it will return
back to that point and continue
executing okay so here's a simple
example of of installing a handler so
here in Maine where we're going to
install a sig int handler which is
called sig int underscore handler which
is defined up here and the prototype for
this function is returns nothing and it
takes a single integer argument which is
the signal number and returns nothing
okay and after we install that handler
then we're going to execute the pause
this call which just waits for a signal
handler to execute ok so pause
terminates the current or suspends the
current process until a signal is
received and a handler executes in that
process and then pause then pause
returns so we're going to wait until the
SIGINT happens so sig entry call is when
we type ctrl C so when you're doing your
bombs did did you panic at some point
and try to hit ctrl C to get out of it
okay so that snarky message you got that
was we did that by installing a signal
hello SIGINT handler in in in your bomb
okay so when when you type control C
that elicits a a SIGINT when that SIGINT
is received we printed this message and
then eventually let you exit
now signaler signals are another
examples of concurrency now we've seen
concurrency earlier in the form of
processes right concurrent flows
overlapping in time okay logical flows
overlapping in time by definition are
concurrent now with with processes the
because they have separate address
spaces those concurrent flows never
interfere with each other right so in
some sense processes are very easy to
deal with and we don't really have to
worry
one process doesn't have to worry about
being interfered with by another process
in fact you have to go to great lengths
to share like to share things between
processes you have to use specific
system calls in order to say share
memory between two processes now signals
are another form of concurrency this is
the second time in this class that that
you've experienced concurrency and so a
signal is just a concurrent flow it's
just a logical flow a sit so a handler
is just another logical flow that runs
concurrently with your program right so
we're let's say we're executing a while
loop in process a okay that while loop
is is executing and in process a
receives the signal which causes a
transfer of control to this handler this
handler executes so this is a concurrent
flow that overlaps in time with the
while loop in process a eventually this
handler returns and we return for the
back tip to back to process a now one of
the reasons signals are so tricky is
because of this this overlapping
concurrent flow this
this concurrency because the signal
handler runs in the same process as the
main program so it shares all the global
variables of that program okay so you're
that signal handler is a function that
you've declared and it has access to all
all the state all the global state in
the program okay and the existence of
the shared global state can create real
problems
and we'll get into more details about
some of those problems so another way to
look at these signal handlers disking as
concurrent flows is using this this
context switch diagram so suppose we're
executing in process a and now at some
point a signal is delivered to process a
now nothing happens right just just the
pending bit gets set in process a at
this point now at some point there's a
transfer of control into the kernel and
the kernel decides to do a context
switch from A to B and now B gets to run
for a while there's another transfer of
control to the kernel and the kernel
decides to schedule process a and now
right before it returns control to
process a it notices that the the
pending bit for this signal is set so it
causes process a to receive that signal
so that executes the handler code when
the handler returns it returns for brief
briefly to the kernel which then
transfers control back to the the next
instruction that the process was going
to execute now handlers are also tricky
because they can be interrupted by other
handlers so suppose we have our main
program that catches a signal S which
causes a transfer of control to handle
or s and then we'll handle RS did you
have a question
okay well handle RS is is is executing
the the program catches a signal T which
causes a transfer of control to the
handler first for T and when then when
at handler returns it returns to the
point to the to the to the instruction
and handle or else that was where it was
interrupted and then handle or us
continues its execution and eventually a
return
back to the the point in the main
program where it was interrupted now
signals that the colonel always blocks
pending signals of the type currently
being handled right so a handler for a
signal of type T can't be interrupted by
the receipt of another signal of that
same type okay can be as I showed in the
previous slide it can be interrupted by
a signal of another type but not by a
signal of the same type so that's sort
of an implicit form of of blocking but
there's the kernel also provides a
system call that allows you to
explicitly block and unblock signals in
the form of the sig proc mask function
and then there's associated so this
allows you to block and unblock a set of
signals and then there some support
functions that allow you to create those
sets so just think of these as bit
vectors and these functions will set in
set and reset the bits and those those
bit vectors so let's see how we can use
sig proc masks to temporarily block and
unblock a signal so this is going to
this is going to turn out to be very
important for you when you working on
your shells that which is your next your
next lab assignment okay
so what we do we'll use cig empty set to
create an empty mask so this is a mask
with all zeros okay with with no
elements in the set and then we're going
to add a single element to this set
which is sig int and now we temp we have
some code that we don't want to be
interrupted by the seed of sig end okay
so we want to temporarily block the
receipt of sig n signals and we do it by
calling sig proc mask with the command
say I want to block I want to block the
signals that are spent that that are in
the set specified by mask and I'll
assign the so this will become my new
mask so this this becomes the new
blocked bit vector okay or the not the
this the new signal mask and it makes a
copy of the old one and stores it at at
the address specified in the third
argument so at this point after we
returned from sig proc mask sig n
signals are blocked and they won't be
received and then we so we can execute
this code knowing that we won't be
interrupted by receipt of a sig int and
then we can restore the previous block
set by using the cig set mask in stopper
ation and passing in the previous mask
that we that we saved up here when we
when we initially blocks again
okay so signals and signal handling is a
really tricky business and there's sort
of three things that make them so tricky
and kind of nasty really one is that you
have to be very careful to write
handlers that are safe
okay so there's you can write signal
handlers that are unsafe in the sense
that they'll create a deadlock in your
program okay or you can or you can write
signal handlers that will that will
corrupt a global data structure that's
being modified by the main program so I
mean imagine imagine your main
programming is updating some some data
structure like a linked list and right
in the middle of updating that data
structure when it's when it's no longer
consistent the program gets interrupted
by the receipt of a signal and if that
signal handler is updating that same
data structure reading that structure or
modifying it then it's going to
encounter it in an inconsistent state
and and and you're in trouble okay so
this the fact that it's the fact that
it's it's it's it's easy to write signal
handlers that are that are unsafe is is
is one aspect of that makes them tough
to deal with another aspect is they have
this funny semantics that signals aren't
cued and so if you're not if you're not
really careful about this it's very easy
to use the receipt of signals to count
events and you can't do that
if signals were cued you could use you
could use the receipt of a signal to
count events in the system but you can't
do it because their signals aren't cued
and then a third a third aspect of
signals which makes them tough is that
they're not even they're not even
portable across different versions of
Linux okay so if you use
solaris or some form of bsd it's not
necessarily the single handling
semantics aren't necessarily the same as
they are in Linux
okay so we'll we'll look at all three of
these in a little more detail and first
we'll start with writing safe handlers
so let me give you some guidelines for
how to write safe handlers and this is
just a collection of fun this is just a
collection of sort of collected wisdom
from from various sources but it covers
a lot of aspects of signal handlers so
the first guideline is to keep your
handlers as simple as possible for
example the simplest possible handle I
can think of just sets a global variable
and then it returns okay and in fact
cert the CMU cert provides guidelines
for sort of compliant programs and this
is the only signal handler that they
allow this is the only compliant signal
handler one that just sets a global
variable and then returns okay
guideline number one call only functions
in your handlers that are that have this
property of async signals safety okay
and we'll look at this in a second but I
want to point out that printf s printf
Malak exit functions that are very
common and commonly used are not safe
okay
guideline number two is to always save
and restore error no on entry and exit
so you know error no is a global global
variable that's set when there's
whenever there's an error in a
system-level function so you need to
save and you need to save and restore it
on entry and exit so that it doesn't get
overwritten if you're interrupted by
another handler
[Music]
okay if you're accessing any shared data
structures inside a signal handler that
are also accessed by your main routine
then you need to temporarily block
signals while you access that data
structure both in the main routine and
your signal handler right and the reason
for this is what I described earlier if
your main routine is updating that
global data structure and then it gets
interrupted and the signal handler is
reading that data structure it's going
to find it in an inconsistent state and
bad things will happen okay you want to
be sure to declare your any global
variables that are shared between signal
handlers and the main routine as
volatile okay the volatile attribute
will prevent the compiler from putting
that that value in a register so if you
declare a global variable as volatile it
will always be reads and writes will
always go to and from memory okay so
this is very important right you might
if you don't declare these global
variables at volatile and the compiler
chooses to put to put one of those in a
in a register then you may miss that
variable being updated so suppose
suppose your signal handlers is setting
a global variable and now suppose your
main routine is spinning waiting for
that global variable to get set well if
it's in a register the write to that
variable will just update the register
right and so your main routine is in
danger of just of spinning forever not
not seeing the change right okay so
always use volatility so that they're
not stored in registers and then if you
have fun if you have a special kind of
global called a flag which by definition
is a variable it's only read or written
not incremented or updated it's just
read or written if you have if you have
a variable with that property then you
can declare it with this SIG atomic tea
tribute and if you do that then the
system guarantees that reads and writes
to that variable will be atomic so you
don't have to in other words you don't
have to protect accesses to the shared
two accesses or references to those
global variables okay and so by this by
atomic which means that the the read or
write of that flag will always happen in
one uninterruptible step okay one
uninterruptible load or store particular
now in practice on most systems this SIG
atomic T is an int kids so you can you
can read or write an int with one one
instruction okay so it's it's atomic but
if you want to be portable you declare
it with sig atomic T and then it'll
it'll work on none it will work on all
systems okay we mentioned this property
of a sync signal safety now a function
is is safe to be used inside of a signal
handler if it's either reentrant okay or
if it can't be interrupted by signals
and will a reentrant function as we'll
see when we study threads is a function
where all of its all of the data that it
accesses is on its own stack okay so no
global variables no pointers to global
variables everything's stored on the
stack locally okay so that means you can
be it's called reentrant because you can
write have multiple instances of that
function and they all have their own
separate copies of all of the variables
that they're they're using now the POSIX
standard guarantees 117 different
functions to be a sync signal saved
these include underscore exit right wait
wait kids sleep kill but unfortunately
there's some very popular functions that
aren't on this list printf s printf
things that you really want to use and
in fact Wright is the only output
function that's a sync signal safe
so this is kind of a problem because
especially when you know you something
you'd often like your signal handlers to
output information but you can't if you
want to really be pedantic and careful
you can't use printf in fact it's
possible to write a program and I'll try
to I'll try to it's possible to write a
program that does a tight loop of
printouts in the main routine and then a
steady stream of interrupts which
execute a handler which also does a
printf okay now
the printf call has to acquire what's
called a lock on the terminal okay each
printf inside that that library function
it acquires a lock which means only one
instance of printf can write to the
terminal at a point in time if another
if another function tries to acquire
that lock it has to wait until whatever
function owns the lock releases it okay
so a lock prevents a lock is a way for
to get mutually exclusive access to two
shared resources so if we have a tight
loop in our main routine with executing
printf imagine what happens if one of
those printouts acquires a lock on the
terminal and then gets interrupted not
by the receipt of a signal now within
the signal handler it calls another
printf and that printf tries to acquire
that lock and it blocks forever because
nothing's going to release that lock
because the the main routine was
interrupted by the handler so you have
what's called a classical a classical
condition called deadlock which is we
have a process waiting for an event that
will never occur in this case the the
printf and the signal handler is waiting
for a lock to be released that will
never be released
so it's interesting you can try this
it's it's it's not too hard to to create
this deadlock situation so to deal with
this I really didn't want to tell you
guys that you couldn't have any output
in your programs and writes a very
difficult thing to deal with so so I
created a small little library called
the safe i/o library consists of three
routines and they're available to you in
the CSAP PC file which is distributed on
the website and it consists of three
reentrant routines sio put us
prince/princess string put L prints
along and SiO error prints a message and
then exits okay so you can safely use
take my word for it you can safely use
this in your in your signal handlers so
if we were going to rewrite our SIGINT
handler from the from the binary bomb we
could rewrite it like this and now we
have every function is is a sync signal
safe all right now signals are also
tucked because of this this funky non
cueing semantics of and so it's really
easy to make mistakes when you have an
implicit assumption that the that the
receipt of a signal it can be used to
count the occurrence of an event so
let's look at this let's look at this
example program we install a sick child
handler okay and this is actually this
this sort of close the loop member we
talked about our example shell
we're wondering how are we going to reap
those those background children well we
do it by installing a sick child handle
like we're doing in this example so this
here we have a program that installs
this sick child handler
and then it creates n different child
processes where each child sleeps for a
little bit and exits and then it spins
until the C count variable becomes zero
that the parent I'm sorry the parent
spins until the C count variable becomes
zero now in the in our child handler we
we have a global that's that's
initialized to zero
see count and then we wait we're going
to wait so this child when the child
handler gets called that means it's
called because we received a sick child
signal okay so in our in our handler
we're going to reap that child by
calling weight and we're going to Dec
and then will decrement C count okay so
once all of the children if then have
been reaped C count will be zero and
then the parent can exit this this while
loop okay now in this particular example
N was 5 but will you run this code we
only the handle or only gets called
twice okay so the the message handler
Reap child only gets executed twice
right which means the handler was only
called twice we created five children we
terminated five children but we only
reaped - okay so that the problem is
that when we the problem is that we
assumed that the receipt that the that
the execution of the child handled our
correspondent to the single receipt of a
single sick child signal okay when when
in reality these signals aren't cued
right we had in reality multiple sick
child signals were delivered to that
child which kept overriding that
at bid in the pending bit vector and the
delivery of those signals didn't didn't
have didn't cause any reaction in the
process until that process was was just
about ready to be rescheduled and only
then was where was a signal received
but even though like say three signals
were delivered only one was received
okay so you can't use events in this
case we're using event we're using
signals to count events which in this
case is the termination of a child okay
so the receipt of a signal in this case
it only indicates that at least one
child terminated right not not one child
terminated all we can infer from the
receipt of that signal is that at least
one child has terminated okay so to fix
that when we receive a sick child we
have to put we have to put the weight
that's reaping on our children we have
to put that in this in a loop so we have
to assume that the receipt of a sick
child if we get a sick child there could
be multiple terminated children that we
have to that we have to reap and so we
put we put that in this loop and we
execute this loop until there's no more
terminated children in which case wait
will will will exit with an error code
of minus one and a error know of a child
so this isn't really an error it's just
it just means there's no more terminated
children so we check as long as if our
error knows naughty child then we have
an error otherwise we terminated
normally as we expect it now if we run
this code now we we see that we reap all
five children as as we should
okay so let's the litany of problems
with signals first it's easy to write
handlers that aren't safe second it's
easy to get the semantics wrong third
they're often not even portable across
different versions of Unix so there's
some older systems I don't know if any
there's some earlier versions of Unix
that after you catch a signal it
restores the default action so you have
to reinstall the handler every time well
every time a handler gets called you
have to re-install that handler by
calling signal inside the handler itself
we don't have to do that for for Linux
systems on on some systems when you have
so-called slow sis calls for example
read you know if you do a read system
call the kernel doesn't wait around for
that data to arrive it's it you know it
sends a request to the disk controller
and that schedules another process right
so in a way that the read call is sort
of and then only when the data arrives
and the interrupt comes in announcing
that the data arrives does that read
call finish and then restore and return
so you can think of read is actually
kind of broken up into two parts right
then and so that functions like read
these kind of functions are called slow
sis calls and on some systems if the
process receives a signal before a slow
system calls has finished the kernel
will will just abort that system call
and return from that system call with an
error okay so from users point of view
you're doing a read call and it returns
with this this e enter signal this e
enter error you did nothing wrong you
just happen to have the bad luck of
being interrupted by some signal and so
in your user code you have to check for
that and if if a slow system call like
read is
interrupted by signal you have to redo
it so you have to put which is really a
pain right because you have to put these
these read calls in a loop and keep keep
looping until it succeeds and finally
some systems don't block signals of the
type being handled right so that the
solution for this is a replacement for
signal so the problem is with the signal
syscall and the solution is a newer
syscall called sig action which provides
a mechanism a replacement for signal
that provides a mechanism for portable
and predictable signal handling and so
what I've done what I've done is created
a rapper called
uppercase signal that takes the same
arguments as that the signal call but
inside it calls the sig action function
to get portable signal handling and so
it's it's not really important to go
into detail about this the point is in
your code you always want to call
uppercase signal using the rapper that
provided in si si PP dot C and then if
you do that then you'll always block
signals of the typing handle the system
will automatically restart slow syscalls
that have been interrupted by by signals
okay so fortunately there's an easy fix
for this now let's let's finish up with
them there's some interesting I
mentioned that signals are difficult
because of these the fact that they're
they're concurrent flows so I want to
look at some sort of subtle issues that
you can run into because of this
concurrency and and I want to talk about
how to identify those errors and how to
fix them
so here's a program that this is like a
simple shell program that maintains a
jobs list right so every time it creates
a new child it adds it to the jobs list
and every time that child terminates it
removes it from the jobs list okay so so
our simple show just in a loop it just
creates a child and then executes the
program within that child and then in
the parent it correctly blocks all of
the signals temporarily while it adds
the job to the job queue and then it
unblocks
and then it unblocks those signals okay
so this is correct and that it's it's
protecting access to this the shared job
queue because that that that job that
job queue is also manipulated by the
sick child handler so when when a child
terminates and the parent receives the
sick
this handler runs and this handler goes
through and it reaps all of the children
potentially terminated children and then
for each one it deletes that
that job from the job queue all right so
here's a classic case we have two
concurrent flows our main routine and
our our signal handler they're each
accessing a shared data structure in
this case the the job queue okay and
they're there correctly blocking signals
while they update this this job queue
but this program has a really subtle and
nasty bug in it can you see what it is
what's the sequence of events that would
cause this program to to fail yes
exactly that's exactly it so is it
possible that the the child process
could terminate before the parent has a
chance to add that job to the queue and
the answer is yes right we you cannot
make any assumptions about the execution
ordering of the child in the process or
about how long they run right so it's
it's it's very possible that the child
can connect after after the four control
returns to the child instead of the
parent and then the child terminates
before the parent ever has a chance to
to add that job to the job queue so now
what's happened is that the the child is
deleting a deleting a job that hasn't
been added to the job queue right and
now when the parent finally gets around
to running it adds that job to the job
queue and that job will never be deleted
right so this is the kind of subtle
nasty horrible kind of bug that you run
into when you're dealing with
concurrency trying to keep track of all
of these interleaving of events can just
make your head explode all right now and
it happens and Sigma it happens with any
kind of concurrency where you have
concurrent flows accessing shared
resources and signal handlers are no
different now we'll look at principled
ways where we can deal with this kind of
sharing when we study threads later on
but I just want to point this out to him
scare you a little bit all right so
here's how we would fix that what we
have to do is somehow avoid the avoid
the the avoid the possibility of the
child handle or executing before the
parent can add the corresponding job to
the job queue now we can't control
whether the child executes first or the
parent execute first and we can't
control how long the child runs but we
can control when the the sig child
handler runs because we can block
signals
okay so what we'll do we'll modify our
program - we'll use cig proc mask to
block cig tiled signals before we create
the child okay so at this point after
this invocation of cig proc sig child
signals are blocked okay then we create
the child and before we do our exit ve
since we don't know that child may may
need to reap its children right we don't
know if it we by default children
inherit the the blocked a bit vector of
their parents okay so when this child
runs F after it returns from fork at
this point right after the fork sig
child is blocked in the child as well
right so if if we didn't do anything if
and the child created children and tried
to reap you know reap them with a sick
child handle that sick child handler
wouldn't run right so that would be a
problem so in the child before we
execute that the program itself we
unblock sick child and this was an
example that I was alluding to last time
of how it's useful sometimes to separate
creating processes with executing
programs right then so this allows us to
get our our signal mask set up the way
we want it before we run our program in
the child so now even if the child
terminates early the sick child handler
won't run until after we've added the
job to the to the job queue because we
don't unblock sick child until after the
until after we call a job okay
okay now there's another so this this
sort of scenario be very relevant to you
when you do your shell lab okay so you
want to be careful not to not to make
that mistake another another thing that
you you're going to need to do in your
shell lab now you remember in our simple
our simple shell example we did the
weight inside the main routine so we
waited for foreground jobs using weight
but now in a real shell we're going to
have our sick child handler do all the
all the weights call all the weights and
it week so we can't put the weight has
to go in the sig child handler can't go
in the main routine okay so if it so
high if we can't put a weight in the
main routine how are we going to how are
we going to detect that our foreground
job is finished okay so somehow so what
we could do we could define in the sig
child handler when we read the
foreground job right we've created a
foreground job when we read that
foreground job we could set this global
flag we could declare the process this
process ID a variable PID as a as a
global flag and then just assign the
process ID of the of the of the
foreground job okay so in this this is
an example of a handler it just all it
does it sets a flag and then exits
and then in our main routine okay we
want to we want to block sig tile just
by just like before okay to avoid that
that race condition between the parent
and the child and then we create the
child and then and then in the and then
the parent we set PID to zero okay then
we unblock sig child and then we wait
for the sick child handler to run and
set PID to non zero okay okay everybody
see that I mean this so this is correct
right but it's extremely wasteful right
we're spinning we're using valuable
processor cycles in this in this tight
spin loop just executing over and over
and over and over and over and over for
who knows how long okay so that's not a
good that's not a good solution alright
so let's look at a couple other things
we might might consider and that have
been considered by generations of 213
students so one thing you might think
well I'll just instead of just putting a
semicolon here I'll pause and then I'll
wait for the sick child handler to run
and then I'll go back up and I'll check
I'll check PID again now you have to put
this in a loop it still has to be in a
loop because we have other signal
handlers in our program we have a SIGINT
handler so it might be if we do the
pause here and this again comes in and
say get Sigyn handler runs that would
cause us to exit the pause function and
go back up so we have to keep checking
PID because we're not sure we have to
keep checking for the specific signal
handler sick child handler to run
instead of other handlers that might run
but this is actually wrong because it
has a race can you see what the race is
what's wrong with this there's a good
chance that this thing will block
forever yes
yeah that's so the the problem the
problem with this is like so if the
signal if the signal is received after
PID is checked but before the pause
executes okay which is possible right
it's unlikely but it's possible if that
if that signal is arrives here then the
handler will set PID to non zero and
then we'll execute the pause and the
pause will be blocked forever waiting
for a signal that will never arrive
right because the sync child signal
already already came very subtle right
so this code looks okay it looks benign
but it's wrong and and and your program
would just hang forever so we say well
okay that's no good
we could replace the pause with asleep
so we could say let's let's check PID
and then sleep for some predetermined
amount of time in this case one second
and then go back up and check PID again
so this while this is correct it's way
too slow right we're asking the system
to wait for a second which is an
eternity and there's there's forms of
sleep nanosecond where you can wait
instead of units of seconds you can wait
in units of nanoseconds but that what
value do you use right if it's it that
so that's if you choose a value that's
too large then you have this problem the
slowness problem if you choose a sleep
time that's too small then you have the
other problem that it's inefficient so
the solution is to use six suspend which
is the last last thing we're going to
look at today so six suspend is a
function that takes a signal mask and
it's equivalent to an uninterruptible
version of these three statements so we
block the signals that are specified in
the signal mask and then it's atomic in
the sense that
after that this this these two
statements can't be interrupted they're
always executed together okay so we
blocked these signals and then we
execute the pause okay so there's no
chance of a signal interrupting this
program in between the sig proc mask and
the pause okay and then and then when a
signal does come in and the execution of
the handle or causes pause to exit then
we set the mask back to what it was
before okay so the proper way then to
wait for a signal is to use sig suspend
in the following way so here's our
here's our program again we before we
create the child's we block sig child
then we create the child and now we're
going to wait for the sick child to be
received now sick child is still blocked
okay so there's no danger of the sick
child handler running okay so we set
that global variable to zero and then
while it's while it's non zero we
repeatedly call sick suspend and sick
suspend is using the previous mask that
was set up here so sick suspend is using
the mask where sick child is unblocked
okay when we when we entered this first
cig proc mask sick child was unblocked
so this allows inside the cig suspend
sick child is unblocked okay so it
allows for the the handler now to be
received or to be executed okay so in it
and it does it safely because of the uh
the atomic nature of those those first
two instructions
so once the so it's possible that the
the implicit pause inside of sick child
could be interrupted by say another
signal like SIGINT okay in which case
we'd loop back up we notice that PID was
still zero
and we go back into six suspend with
with sig child unblocked okay so that
makes sense to everybody and now so this
is exactly the behavior we want where
we're not wasting resources but we've
eliminated the race okay so that's it
for today if you're interested non
non-local jumps are this weird thing and
see that allows a function to return to
some other function that didn't call it
okay but it's described in your textbook
and also in some additional slides here
if you if you're interested