all right good afternoon everybody
welcome good to see you all welcome also
to our our viewers on video so last week
we looked at this this virtual memory
mechanism and how it provides so many
different useful functionalities to the
system along with this sort of
abstraction of having this large
contiguous array of bytes now once we're
given that that large array of bytes now
we have to manage it and we have to we
have to have some mechanism to to manage
and use that that resource okay so
that's the topic of our our lectures
this week is a storage allocation and
how storage allocators work and how you
use them to manage the matter the
virtual memory in your system so the the
basic idea of a dynamic memory allocator
is that applications use it to to
manipulate virtual memory to create to
to allocate and free chunks of virtual
memory that you need in your program and
it's this this memory is maintained in
it in an area of virtual memory called
the heap okay and although all all
languages have some ask some mechanism
for we're acquiring and manipulating
this this this dynamic memory so in NC
it's a phone it's the malloc package
languages like Java have the new the new
method now the allocator the allocator
maintains the heap as a contiguous
collection of blocks where and it blocks
can be allocated or free ok allocated
meaning that they're they're being used
by some program application free meaning
that there
available to be for use by an
application and there's there's two
types of allocators the kind of
allocator that you find in c such as the
malloc package it's up to the
application to both explicitly allocate
the the memory and explicitly free it
when when the when the application is
finished with it okay so the system
won't won't free up any memory that you
allocate unless you do it explicitly by
calling the by calling the free function
but there's other languages that that
support implicit allocators and in these
in these implicit allocators the
programmer al explicitly allocates
memory but then the system takes care of
freeing the memory okay so it's that the
burden of freeing the memory is shifted
from the application program to the to
the system and it it frees this memory
implicitly sort of behind the scenes
using a process called garbage
collection okay so languages like Java
ml Lisp um they all they all do implicit
implicit they all support in close at
allocators now today we're going to just
we're going to discuss explicit memory
alligators on Thursday we'll get into
implicit alligators and how they work
now the alligator and C is provided it
by the standard c library in a set of
function called malloc package the the
malloc function is used to to allocate
memory and it takes as input a size
argument which is in bytes okay and then
it returns a pointer to a to a memory
block that contains at least size bytes
and that block is the line T on x86
systems to eight bytes on x86 64 systems
to 16 bytes if size is 0 it returns null
and then it returns minus 1 like like
most typical
system calls the programmer frees memory
by calling the free function it takes as
an argument a pointer that was returned
from some prior invocation of malloc and
it returns nothing and it frees that
I've given this pointer that was
returned by the prior indication of
malloc it frees the block at that
address and then returns that block to
the pool of available memory now there's
some there's some other functions so
sialic is a version of malloc that gives
you an initialized block of memory
that's initialized to 0
and realloc you can you can malloc a
block and then call realloc to change
the size of that previously allocated
block and then there's a function called
S break which is used internally by
allocators to grow and shrink the heap
so when an allocator needs more memory
it calls S break to to get that
additional virtual memory and then that
that's added to the heap that the
portion that grows the heap and then it
adds it to the memory that the the
allocator is is manipulating
so here's an example of how we would use
Malik and it's in a simple program we
have a pointer to an int P and we call
malloc and we we want to allocate an
array of N in so this is that this is
sort of the standard way you call it we
want n int and so we we call it with n
times the size event because remember
the argument is in bytes malloc returns
a pointer it returns that generic
pointer void star pointer so we cast it
to a pointer to an int to keep keep the
compiler happy and then assign it to to
P we check for a we check for a null
return value so I should I should point
out the it returns 0 on error so we
check we recheck recheck for this no the
snow pointer which is 0 in print an
error if it's no now once we've got that
pointer now P we can treat it just like
an array so we can so inside the loop if
we want to initialize it we loop across
the elements of the array
initializing each one to some value now
when we're finished when we're finished
with this chunk of memory that we've
allocated then we free it by calling
free with the pointer P
okay now the so we're going to look
today at how functions like malloc and
free are implemented so we're going to
make a few simplifying assumptions so
I'm going to memory it is byte address
we know that but for the purposes of
this lecture we're going to assume that
it's it's word address okay so we're
just going to look at word size units
and I'm going to assume that words are 4
bytes so they basically the size of an
int so this isn't actually this this
isn't true I need to fix that so
basically we're going to we're going to
think of words as four byte quantity
sort of integer size quantities and then
our blocks or contiguous chunks of those
words that can be either allocated or
free so here we have a portion of the
heap which consists of a four word
allocated block followed by a two word
free block followed by another for word
allocated block followed by a three word
free blocking and we'll indicate these
free blocks white by white and will
indicate allocated blocks with some some
shade of of color so let's look now how
a sequence of of allocations and freeze
would work and now notice I'm calling
malloc with the size of in words not
bytes just to keep just to keep things
keep these pictures simpler
so in this first we call malloc and
allocate of a forward block then we can
that and that gives us a pointer P 1
then we call malloc again to get a
five-word block so it just takes it one
of the free words and allocates it we
call malloc again to get a six word
block and then we free the block that's
pointed at by P to this purple block
okay so now we that frees up that block
and then we do another allocation for a
two word block and so the the allocator
looks to see if it can find a free block
that has enough enough room and it finds
that it finds this free block here that
has five free words and then it
allocates the the requested block inside
of that that free block now allocators
work under a lot of a lot of different
constraints okay so it's hard to write
an allocator because of all these
constraints applications can choose any
combination of allocated and free blocks
so you can't predict what what an
application is going to request and and
the application is required to free a
block by when it frees a block to pass a
pointer that was returned from a
previous invocation of malloc okay so
the the application has a few
constraints but but really the only one
that it has is that the fact that the
when it frees something it has to be a
pointer from a previous invocation of
malloc
now the malloc operates or allocators
like malloc operate under a lot of
different constraints they can't control
the size or the number of the allocated
blocks because they have no control over
the what the application is doing if an
application calls Malik Malik has to
respond right away it might you might be
able to do a better more efficient
version by batching up requests and then
responding to all those requests at once
which the allocator can't do it when it
gets called it has to process the
request and then return right away it
has to of course it has to allocate
blocks from free memory so it can't
in general I can't touch any allocated
block right once it allocates a block
that block belongs to the application
and the the malloc package can't touch
it now this this has a number of
implications so this means that the
allocator can't it can't move blocks
around like it can't compress blocks
like an alligator might want to take
allocated blocks and smoosh them all
together to create larger free blocks
hey but it can't do that okay so once
you know in a language like C once once
an alligator gives a block to a an
application it can't touch it okay now
blocks like blocked because blocks are
holding data structures like strux
or you know scalar scalar objects it has
to be aligned to the size of the largest
object that that can occur okay so for
64-bit systems that's 16 byte alignment
for 32-bit systems it's 8 byte alignment
now alligators are really interesting
objects because they they combine a
trade-off of both so running time sort
of speed and space so it's kind of a
space and performance trade-off you're
trying to optimize both you want it to
run as quickly as possible but you want
to you wanted to use the virtual memory
in the heap as efficiently as possible
okay so let's and we define these these
sort of speed and and efficiency memory
efficiency metrics we have we have two
metrics that we use one is called
throughput so given some sequence of
malloc and free requests are 0 through R
and minus 1 so just some where R is
either a malloc or free our goal is to
maximize throughput and the peak memory
utilization and what makes malloc such a
fascinating and interesting study is
that these often conflict like it's very
easy to make a really fast malloc that
that has terrible memory utilization so
throughput is just the number of
recomputed requests per unit time so if
we have 5,000 malloc calls and 5,000
free calls in 10 seconds then our
throughput is a thousand operations per
second so it's just measuring sort of
how efficiently are our malloc can can
process these requests from an
application
now peak memory utilization is a measure
sort of how how much useful space so how
much it measured how efficiently the
allocator uses the heat sort of how much
is wasted on sort of overheads in the
data structures that the allocator has
to uses to in its implementation so
we'll define a payload when when malloc
returns a block what when it I'm sorry
what an application makes a call to
malloc it's requesting a certain size
block and that that block is called the
payload so if we call malloc with an
argument of 10 bytes we're requesting a
block that has a payload of it that's at
least size 10 okay and the 10 bytes that
we request that are called the payload
everything else in that block is is
overhead okay so after after we've run a
sequence of requests the aggregate
payload is the sum of all the the
payloads in the currently allocated
blocks okay so in a perfect allocator
the the aggregate payload would would
would equal the amount of memory the
total size of all the allocated blocks
right because there'd be no overhead
would just be we just be pure every
block would be pure payload
now we're going to assume that the heap
is is monotonically non-decreasing so it
always gets bigger okay so are this is a
simplifying assumption it's not it's not
true in a real Malak package but we'll
just assume that the allocator never
decreases the size of the heap it only
increases the size of the heap okay so
the peak given those given those notions
of aggregate payload and heap size the
peak memory utilization after k plus 1
requests is the sum of all the is the
sum of all the payloads divided by the
total size of the heap so the in the
best case each each block in the heap
consists of pure payload so the
utilization would be 1 that's the best
we can do but in practice each block the
allocator is going to place have data
structures and padding inside of each
block that that that keep it from
getting a perfect utilization now one
one obvious thing is that since blocks
have to be aligned to some you know if
they're 16-byte aligned then blocks have
to start on 16 byte boundaries and they
have to be at least 16 bytes so if you
were to request a payload of 2 bytes
you'd have a lot of wasted bytes right
that would sort of decrease the
utilization so this is some of this some
of this overhead is unavoidable but your
job as a someone who writes them
implements malloc is to try to keep that
as small as possible
so poor memory utilization is this
example that we just talked about is an
example of what we call fragmentation
and there's there's two types of
fragmentation internal fragmentation
occurs if the payload is smaller than
the block size so it's just what we're
talking about and this can be caused by
either padding in the block or some kind
of data structure in the block that the
allocator needs sometimes to it you
might make a policy decision that if at
if application requests a small block
you might return a larger block just to
keep so the blocks don't get sort of
splintered up into little chunks you
might want to keep blocks at some
minimum size
now internal fragmentation you know
given a series of requests we can we can
just stop and freeze the heap and it's
very easy to sort of compute the amount
of internal fragmentation we can at any
point in time we can just look at all
the previous requests that we we've made
and and look at the size of the payload
for each one of those requests and so we
can so we can determine the level you
know get at a point in time we can
determine the level of internal
fragmentation just by looking at the
previous request so there's another form
of fragmentation called external
fragmentation which is a little more
difficult to to deal with so external
fragmentation occurs when there's enough
memory in the heap but there's there's
no single free block that can satisfy a
particular request ok so external
fragmentation occurs when the
application makes a request for a block
but nowhere in the heap is there a free
block a free block that's large enough
to satisfy that request
so an example of this like suppose
here's the previous example we looked at
now where we have after a series of
malloc and free calls we have two free
blocks in the heap one containing five
words and the other containing two words
so the total the total number of free
words in our heap is seven seven words
and now we get a request for six words
hey we have enough free blocks we have
enough free words in the heap but we
can't satisfy that request and it's it's
because of it's because of this
phenomenon called external fragmentation
for example if we'd have if we'd have
somehow allocated
Oh
yeah I don't know in this case I don't
think we could have avoided the external
fragmentation but nonetheless there's
enough memory here we just just the way
that our blocks are configured in the
heap we can't satisfy the request so in
this in this in this case that the
allocator has to go and get more more
virtual memory would have to go and it
would have to get more virtual memory
and extend the heap out this way and to
get a large enough free block so you
know assessing and sort of understanding
external fragmentation is difficult
because unlike internal fragmentation
which depended on the previous requests
external fragmentation depends on future
requests so if we look back at this
point we say is is our is our heap
externally fragmented well we it depends
right we can't say it turns out it is
because the next request is is for a
block of size six but if all of the
future blocks or future requests were
for bullet
we're for blocks of you know say small
blocks then we be able to satisfy those
than and we wouldn't we wouldn't suffer
from external fragmentation
okay now when we build an alligator all
kinds of issues come up and that I've
glossed over with my simple examples
right you know how do we know if we call
free how does free know how much memory
to free up right we don't call free with
a block size we call it with a pointer
so how does free know how big that block
is how do we keep track of all the free
blocks when we have you know when we're
satisfying an allocation request we're
going to fight we're going to look for a
free block that is larger than the the
requested size on that that case what do
we do with the extra space in the block
we do we just keep it in the block you
know and and suffer some internal
fragmentation do we split that block
into a smaller block there's a lot of
free blocks in the in the heap how do we
when we make an out when the allocator
gets a allocation request how does it
pick from all among all of those
different free blocks make as many
choices and then once when free tries to
insert a free block we're in the heap
you know where does it insert it okay
when it's when it's freed and how do we
reinsert a free block what does that
mean okay so today we're going to look
at at all of these issues starting with
knowing how much to free so how big our
block sizes so the typical the standard
method is to keep sort of a word sized
quantity at the beginning of each block
that gives the size of that block in in
some units I'm showing them here in word
size units okay so that if if the
application Malick's a payload of size
wants to wants to now like a payload of
size four then the allocator needs to
find a block
of size five so consisting of four
payload words at least four payload
words and then a header block
a header word at the beginning that that
indicates the size the total size of
that block and then it returns a pointer
p0 in this case to the beginning of the
payload
okay so now we know how big each block
is that's pretty simple and how we keep
track of the free blocks and this is
where it gets interesting the simplest
method is to use that we call an
implicit list an implicit list of free
blocks and the idea here is to just put
a header in the front of every block in
the heap whether allocated or free okay
and then we can use that starting at the
beginning of the heap we can use that
size to walk the heat okay so here's a
block of size five so we can we can jump
we know that the next block starts at an
offset of five with the second block we
know the then the next block starts at
an offset of four and so on okay so we
call it an implicit free list because
there's there's no real list of free
blocks but we can trick an traverse that
all of the free blocks in the heap by
traversing all of the blocks in the heat
and then just ignoring the the allocated
blocks okay so
now another thing we could do is we
could actually use some of the some of
the words in the block to create a
linked list of some kind either us
singly or doubly linked lists and in
this case we it's an explicit list of
the free blocks and we can just walk
that list so we here we visit the first
free block and then there's a pointer to
the next free block and so on so this
you can see this might be a little more
efficient because if we want to traverse
the free list in this case it's a it's
going to be ordered the number of blocks
in the list okay it's going to be linear
in the total number of blocks in the
heap which might be quite large there
could be lots of allocated blocks in
this case with an explicit list any
traversal just just be linear in the
size of the free list question
yeah that's the question is done we need
a free bit and we do and I'll we have
that's the next question
now another method a more sophisticated
method instead of having one free list
we can have multiple free lists where
each free list contains blocks of a
certain size or certain range of sizes
or we can get really fancy and use some
kind of some kind of a balance tree to
sort the blocks to use the tree to sort
them by size order now today we're going
to look at the implicit list the
simplest kind of free list and this will
identify a lot of basic concepts that
are used in the more sophisticated free
list question okay the question is what
do you what do we mean by different free
lists for different size classes so what
what I mean is that you identify a range
of sizes and you associate that range
with with each of these individual free
lists okay so one free list might hold
blocks of size 0 to 8 and another free
list might hold blocks of size 9 to 16
and the other another free list may be
17 to 32 you know some and so you're
guaranteed you now know when you're
traversing a certain list you know the
range of sizes of the blocks in that
list the the reason you might want to do
that by the way is that imagine you had
an infinite number of of these lists one
for each possible size then every time
you allocated a block you'd get a block
of exactly the size you needed so
there'd be a minimum amount of
fragmentation if you had an infinite
number of these of these size classes
now if we of course we can't have an
infinite number but the more of these
size classes we have the closer we get
to that ideal
all right so let's look at how we would
build imprint implicit free lists so as
you correctly point it out for each each
block we need we need both size and the
allocation status question
why can't we map every size class
if I'm fine
yeah that's so why can't we have an
infinite number of size classes
I suppose you know that'd be an
interesting strategy to to think about
so you can't have an infinite number of
size classes but you could create a new
size class for every new size that you
get and that that might work but it just
depends on the the range of these size
classes and the frequency and one
problem you might have is that you you
would get maybe if you only get it
depends on the distribution of your
sizes that you get if you're getting an
equal number if your distribution of
sizes is is fairly uniform that would
probably work pretty well if you're
getting if you have requests if if you
have a lot of requests for different
size classes you'd have a lot of sort of
wasted free lists I think right good so
it's a good question it depends on it
depends on your workload and there and
that is for that and that is a really
useful strategy for so you if you have
really popular size classes in your
request then you could just make you
know special case special case free
lists to handle those requests and then
and then let the other free list sort of
handle a wider range and imagine if you
had a free list where all the blocks
were the same it could be a lot more
efficient right because you won't make
you only need like a bit vector 1 1 bit
for each potential block to tell you
whether it's allocated or free so it
could be very efficient you wouldn't you
wouldn't need to walk any any lists or
anything
that's a good question and that's the
kind of thing you'll be thinking about
when you do your Mallik lab it's one of
the there's a huge design space in
implementing malloc function and we just
we just explored a one tiny part of it
just now
so with this implicit list we're going
to need both the size of the block and
then its allocation status whether it's
allocated or free now we could do this
in two words right but that would be
wasteful
so the standard trick is to take
advantage of the fact that blocks have
to be aligned okay so this is actually
it's kind of a pain in the neck to
always have to align these blocks but we
can take advantage of it in this case
and the reason is is that if a block is
aligned to some say 8 by 8 or 16 byte
boundary then the lower order bits are
always going to be 0 so if it's aligned
to an 8 byte boundary the lower order 3
the 3 low order bits will always be 0
right 8 is 1 0 0 0 16 1 with 4 zeros 24
1 1 0 0 0 right so there any any 8 byte
any 8 byte aligned block has to be size
8 and it has to start on address that's
a multiple of 8 all right so those the
the size will always the size of that
block will always have 0 the 3 3 or 4 a
low-order bits set to 0 so we can take
it we can take advantage of that and
we'll just make will just have 1 I will
just have one header word and we'll use
the lower order bit to store the
allocation status okay and we can do
that because we know it's always zero so
when we so we use that low order bit to
store the allocation status and then the
remaining bits correspond to the size
and then whenever we want to extract the
size we just mask out this allocation
status and always set it to zero because
we know that it's zero
so let's look in detail what given this
given this form of implicit list how we
might set things up so in this case
we're going to assume for bite words
okay in sized words and we're going to
align on eight byte boundaries okay so
remember the payload of our blocks
always has to start on an eight eight
byte boundary so the way we do that is
we create this unused word at the
beginning of the heap that's aligned on
this eight byte boundary and then the
the first block and the heap starts at
an offset of four from that from the
beginning of the heap so we have the
header which is is not aligned and then
we have the payload which follows in
this case it's a payload of one one word
and that starts on this that begins on
this this eight word boundary and then
the next block and and here we're
indicating a free block consisting of
eight bytes and then that's followed by
an allocated block the one here of
sixteen bytes or four forwards
and now the payload is only two words so
we have to pad right all of our blocks
because we're assuming that they're
aligned on eight byte boundary all of
our blocks have to be a multiple of size
multiple of eight okay so here's the
case of internal fragmentation where we
have this extra this extra block in
order to maintain the alignment
requirement so that that ensures that
the next block payload starts at a an
eight byte aligned boundary and so on
and so we can walk this heap by just
following these headers masking out the
allocation bits and then we have this
special epilogue block which is a zero
it's a block of with a zero sized
payload
it's an allocated block of size zero and
this is a this is a trick this is a
trick you should use to so this and
we'll see when we look at coalescing why
this is why this helps but this this
allocated block at the very end
eliminates some sort of special cases
when we when we start to coalesce free
blocks we'll talk about that in just a
just a moment but you can finish your
like this this this this allocated block
of size zero is also helpful in
terminating when you're walking this
list you can you can check for a size
allocated block of size zero to
terminate your search
okay so given this kind of structure
then how do we find a free block okay
there's a there's a number of different
ways the first the first way which is
called first fit up first fit is to
search the free list from the beginning
and just look for the first block we can
find that satisfies the request so we're
allocating we're asking for a block of
size 10 we start at the beginning of the
heap and we walked a list we walk the
heap looking for a free block that's at
least size 10 and we needs to be
actually it needs to be 10 plus the size
of our header 2 so once so that's a
simple idea now some people have
proposed an alternative called next fit
so the idea here is that instead of
starting over each time from the
beginning of the heap to find a block
that fits we just pick up where we left
off the last time okay so we look we
scan the heap and we find a block that's
that's big enough to satisfy the request
and then we remember where that where we
left off and the next time the request
comes in we pick up the search starting
where we left off now this seems like
would be a good idea but but studies
peer achill studies that people have
done have shown that this actually
results in worse fragmentation so you
know you can you can consider it but it
it generally it's generally probably not
the best thing to do now another
alternative is to find that the Block in
the heap if a free block in the heap
that's the best fit so look at so in
general look at all the blocks in the
heap and find the block that fits the
best ok so if we ask for 10 bytes try to
scan the heap for the block that has the
closest to 10 bytes in it okay so that's
called best fit and best fit you can see
it might be more it
sounds like it would be a lot more
expensive right because you'd have to
look instead of just looking until you
find a fit you'd have to scan all the
free blocks and then pick the best one
okay but it has a nice property that it
improves memory utilization okay so if
this isn't this is a classic example the
space time trade-off so it's slower but
it improves it improves our use of the
efficiency of the way we use memory
and there's now we mentioned we
mentioned an alternative way to organize
the free list using multiple free lists
for different size classes now going
back to that example again if we had an
infinite number of size classes one for
each size that would implement best fit
with a constant time search we don't
we'd know exactly which free list to get
the block from the problem of course is
how much memory such a organization
would use but the interesting thing
about using multiple free lists is that
the more the more of these free lists
you have the closer you get to it to a
true best fit okay so you can approach
best fit and then at some point you
begin to get diminishing returns so so
that's another sort of design decision
is how many of these multiple free lists
do you need and what what's sort of what
what should be the size ranges
associated with them
okay another question now once we found
a block so the application is made a
call to malloc the malloc package is
look in the free list that somehow using
some some policy it's identified a block
that in which the requested block a free
block in which the requested block will
fit okay so now what does it do it has
to the malloc package has to allocate it
has to sort of take that but so there's
a question how does it it could allocate
the whole block and return that back to
the programmer or it could it could
choose to split out a portion just only
the portion of block that's needed and
then create a smaller free block okay so
for example if if we if our if our
application is has requested a block of
size 4 or I'm sorry it if the malloc
package is determined that that it in
order to satisfy the application request
it needs a block of size 4 okay
including the header then it would look
and it would try to find a free block of
at least size forward so let's say it
chooses this block for some reason maybe
because it was a next fit picked up here
so this free block is actually six
contains six words so the allocator has
to decide whether just to keep this
block of size six and just return that
back to the to the application or
whether to split that block into two
blocks into an allocated block of size
four which it then returns to the
application followed by a free block of
of size two
okay now another question is how to free
a block so the application is requested
the elec is called free and it's asked
the allocator to free up a particular
block so this is pretty simple
so if we want to free up this block you
just clear the allocated flag so if we
want to free up the block we just
created you just clear you just set the
allocated bit to zero and you're done
it's really simple but the problem now
is this this creates external
fragmentation so here now if if we just
free that block of size for what used to
be a block of size six now consists of
two contiguous smaller blocks one of
size four and one of size two and so now
if that's followed by a request for five
blocks now we're stuck right so this but
we've got plenty of memory and it's even
worse in this case that memory is all
contiguous just because but just because
we just oh we just cleared the free
block we didn't we didn't really notice
that it was contiguous and so we ended
up in with the situation where we have
these two contiguous free blocks
so this this suggests that when we do
when we free up blocks that we somehow
need to coalesce any neighboring blocks
to keep blocks as big as possible right
so we cannot one of the invariance of
any decent allocator is that they're
never there never contiguous free blocks
like this it's always a free block
followed by an allocated block okay so
the idea is that if we free a particular
so here we have this allocated block and
if we free that block and we somehow
have to check and see if there's any
adjacent free blocks either following
either neck either next in memory or
previous in memory and if there are we
need to as part of the freeing process
we need to coalesce those two blocks
into a into a larger block the largest
possible block possible now it's pretty
easy if we're if we're asked to free
this block this green block it's pretty
easy to check the the next block because
you just we have the size we have this
header so we know that the next block
starts at an offset of four so we just
we just we just check we know and we
know that the header for that block is
at your offset of four so we just check
the allocated status of that next block
using the using the size using the size
field in our header but what about the
previous block what about this block how
do we check that
well given given all that we've talked
about now the only thing the only way we
could do it would be to start at the
beginning of the heap and now walk the
free list until we get to this current
block remembering the previous block so
each time we each time we traverse we
remember the previous block okay so that
but that would be very inefficient right
that would be that what that would make
free linear in the size of the heat
because we'd have to in order to check
the previous block we'd have to walk
starting at the very beginning
and walk the entire heap so the solution
for that is was proposed by a famous
computer scientist Don Knuth in 1973
it's very clever it very simple like all
really good ideas it seems obvious that
when you see it but it turns out to be
very clever and a very very useful
technique and the idea is just to
replicate for each block replicate the
header block at the end of the block
okay so each block now contains a header
and a footer identical header and footer
and then this creates sort of an
implicit backwards backwards link that
we can use so now given given some block
that we want to given some block that we
want to free we know that the the size
of that block will just be one one word
previous in memory so so we can just and
it's always a fixed fixed offset of one
word so given you know given a pointer
to the header of this block we can look
one word back to see the size and the
allocated allocation status of the
previous block okay so and so that
allows us to do that in constant time
and so this footer is sometimes called
the boundary tag and Knuth call that a
boundary tag but we'll just and we can
call it a footer to be sort of parallel
with with with the notion of a header
but the the key thing is that it's just
identical has the identical size and
allocation status
and also given yes question so the
question is if we want to have a
boundary tag when we allocate a block do
we need to set aside space for it and
the answer is yes most of the time I'll
show you a one I'll show you one
optimization in a bit okay so given
given this idea of a over the boundary
tag and and and given that we have some
allocated block that we want to free
this yellow block yes question
I
yeah we so they quit yeah so just to
summarize the question you need to when
you allocate when you're looking for
blocks that fit you have to include the
the size of the header and the boundary
tag it would you then you'd have and
then you have to insert padding to get a
size a total block size that's a
multiple of that set of multiple that
satisfies your alignment requirement
sorry yeah I mean it can yeah if you
have it the question is wouldn't I use a
lot of memory and it can if again it
depends on the requests the request
pattern if if the application is
requesting lots of small payloads then
it's going to it's going to waste a lot
of memory if it's requesting big
payloads not so bad
okay so given that we have some block
that we want to free there's four cases
that we need to consider when when
coalescing the case where the the next
block is allocated and the previous
block is free is allocated a case where
the next block is free and the previous
block is allocated a case where the the
previous block is free and the next
block is allocated in the case where
both the previous and next block are
free okay so in case one where we have
our allocated block that we want to free
surrounded by two allocated blocks we
don't do anything right because we only
call us free memory so so in this case
we just set keep the size of the header
and footer stays the same and we just
set the allocation status to to shift
free
now if the if the next block is is free
and the previous block is allocated what
we do is we we check the boundary tag of
the the previous block and we see that
it's allocated so there's nothing to do
there we use the size to check the
allocation status of the next block we
use n to jump to the header of the next
block we see that it's allocations
status is free so these two blocks need
to be coalesced so we do that by just
adding adding the two sizes together to
create this larger coalesce block and
setting its allocation status to zero
now in the case where the previous block
is is free again we we check the
boundary tech footer when we see that
it's we see it it's free so in this case
we create we have to update the size of
the the old the header of the old
previous block to create this now new
larger coalesce block can we and we
update the header and the boundary check
footer accordingly and then in the case
where where both the previous and the
next block are free we create a single
block a single block that's the sum of
all three of those sizes
okay so is that is that clear to
everybody
now as you pointed out correctly pointed
out that boundary tags can create
additional internal fragmentation
because they're they're not part of
payload so by definition they're their
overhead and so you might you might ask
yourself are there any cases where you
don't need a boundary tag
so which which blocks need which blocks
need a boundary tag
could you get away with does an
allocated block need one
yeah you're if you're not going to if
you're not if you don't need to coalesce
and you don't need to that footer and
what kind of blocks don't you call us
allocated blocks so what
so maybe we can maybe maybe we don't
need those at those boundary tech
footers on allocated blocks right just
on free blocks but then how are we going
to determine that the previous block is
allocated or free if an allocated block
doesn't have a boundary tag footer yes
sorry well yeah you would give it one
when you free it but somehow when we're
doing coalescing we need to check
somehow that that previous block whether
it's allocated or free okay but how does
it know it's whether it's a boundary tag
or not not sure no that's okay that's it
okay yes bingo you got it so remember
this remember remember because of our
alignment we've got we've got multiple
at least three bits in three or four
bits that are always zero
we're only using one of them so why not
use another one to contain the
allocation status of the previous block
okay so very good that was
it's so the idea so here's the block
that we want to free and here's its
header and we pass the P to it and we
wonder if we want to free it and we've
got we've got one bit we know that if we
have a eight byte alignment we know that
these are all implicitly zero so we're
using this is a allocated block that we
want to free so it has an allocation
status of 1 and let's use this let's use
one of these spare bits to indicate the
allocation status of the previous block
okay so far if the previous block is is
allocated and this would be a 1 and when
we're checking to see whether we need to
coalesce we just check that we just
check that that that's 2nd allocated bit
the allocated bit of the previous block
and if it's 1 we don't need to know what
its size is okay we don't need to know
where that block is because we're not
going to coalesce it okay so in that we
don't need so here we don't need a
boundary tag for an allocated block but
now if that if that block is free it'll
have a boundary tag so we'll check if
that block is free then the the
allocation status will be will indicate
free and then we know we need to we need
to coalesce and we're going to need
we're going to need a boundary tag
because we need to know where that block
starts we need to know its size so that
we can go back and and update this size
to include the you know the total
coalesce size of those two blocks
so is that that clear yes oh I just uh
it's just the allocated bit so zero
means not allocated one means allocated
oh why are those bits that are why are
the bits always zero why okay so blocks
have to be aligned to eight byte
boundaries okay
oil payloads have to be aligned to eight
byte boundaries okay that means that
that blocks have to be the size of
blocks has to be a multiple of eight
because it's the same thing as when we
were doing padding alignment instructs
the next each block has to be a size has
to be a multiple of eight so that the
the block that follows that in memory is
aligned properly okay so you're
guaranteed because of the alignment
requirement you're guaranteed that of
eight or sixteen you're guaranteed that
the size of the blocks are always
multiples of either 8 or 16 okay and so
that and that so that because that size
is always a multiple of eight or sixteen
you're guaranteed that either three or
four
four bits are all zeros
okay
[Music]
any other questions
okay let me summarize then some key
policies when when implementing an
allocator and I mentioned that there's
the design spaces for these things is
really large and really interesting
there's a lot of things that you a lot
of decisions that you have to make about
various policies so the first is the
placement policy where when we when
we're trying to find when we're trying
to place a free block I mean and out
when we're trying to place an allocated
block somewhere in a free block
somewhere in the list
what what what policy do we use first
fit next fit or best fit and generally
these things they trade-off throughput
for fragmentation all right so the the
faster faster versions like
if you're willing to if you're willing
to deal with with lower throughput like
in the case of best fit then you can get
better memory utilization now there are
interesting there are interesting ways
to improve the performance of best fit
you might you might consider something
like good fit which is sort of a mix of
first fit and best fit so maybe maybe
you only search the first you know a
portion of the heap and then identify
the best fit you know maybe instead of
searching the entire heap you just
search some some portion of the heap and
then cut off the search and then within
that region that you search do you pick
the best block so that's something that
called good fit so that that kind of
approximates best fit or you can use
these multiple free lists to approximate
best fit and that's and then and there
you the real advantage of using multiple
free lists is that it not only improves
memory utilization but it improves
performance too because the individual
lists that you're looking for you know
that they contain blocks that are close
to what you're asking for and since
you're dividing all the free blocks up
amongst multiple amongst multiple free
lists those free lists will be shorter
okay so your searches will take less
time and your your probability of
finding a block that fits goes up
because you're segregating these
different size classes
now there's a we also have to decide on
some splitting policy so when we find
when we find a free block that's big
enough what do we do with the leftover
the leftover part of that block you know
once we placed our allocated block into
that into that free block what do we do
with the leftovers do we just leave the
leftover part in the block itself and
return that back to the application
you know avoiding so that sort of
keeping keeping larger blocks or do we
go ahead and split it like like I showed
before and splitting we go ahead and
splitting that block and creating the
creating the original free block
allocating a portion of it and then
creating a smaller free block so that's
you know that's a policy we may you may
want to you may want to for small
requests for small payloads you may up
to a certain size you may not want to
split so you may not you may decide not
to split blocks smaller you may not you
may decide not to create free blocks
that are smaller than some threshold and
only splitting for 4 requests for larger
blocks and then there's the there's a
coalescing policy now we've seen freeing
is pretty quick now it's constant time
because of the boundary tag footers but
you may you may want to you may want to
try to just speed that up even more by
by deferring the coalescing so you could
you can do coalescing it every time the
free is called like like we just looked
at or you could defer coalescing to some
later time you know maybe when you're
scanning the free list when you're
scanning the free list looking set try
trying to find trying to place an
allocated block in response to a malloc
call maybe as you scan that free list
you could go ahead and do the coalescing
at that time right so
I'm not saying which one is better it's
hard to it's really hard to argue for
deferred colas and giving the constant
time performance of a boundary tag-based
coalescing but it but it is an option
okay so here's the summary then of
implicit lists this is the simplest well
it's a very simple kind of allocator i
it's it's the cost to allocate is linear
in the in the size of the heap worst
case that the cost of free is constant
time even with coalescing memory usage
will be will depend on the placement
policy first fit next fit or best fit um
it's not used in practice because of the
linear time the linear time cost of
allocation okay but it it can be used in
sort of special-purpose allocators where
you have a small number of size classes
maybe or you have a very you know that
you have a very small or a fairly small
free list but the ideas of splitting and
coalescing that we looked at or general
to all allocators okay so the idea of a
boundary tag boundary tag-based
coalescing is is u is used regardless of
the structure of your free list so
implicit lists are useful to study
because they introduce some important
concepts but generally they're not
they're not they're not that useful
so next next class we'll look at some
more sophisticated organizations of free
less the explicit list and multiple free
lists in particular alright so we'll see
you then good luck on your shell lab due
tonight and we'll see you on Thursday