welcome good to see you today we're
going to begin a transitioning from how
our programs interact with hardware to
how they interact with software in
particular system software and we're
going to start that investigation by by
studying and learning about a process
called linking which is how the system
builds builds your programs ok so we're
going to study the the process of
linking and then I'm going to show you a
really cool technique called library
inter positioning which it which allows
you to use linking to actually intercept
on function calls in in libraries like
the standard c library so it's a very
very powerful and interesting technique
and it's all enabled by by linking so
let's start with a simple program this
program consists of two modules a main
dot C and some dot C some dot C takes as
an array as an argument and a length N
and then it sums up the elements of that
array and returns the sum back to the
caller main dot C calls the sum function
using and passes it a two element array
of intz and then returns that and then
returns the value received from some
yeah we that that's kind of an odd thing
to do to return your your exit status
like that but we just did it so that the
compiler wouldn't optimize away all of
our code I know let's look at what
happens if when we want to compile those
those two modules for each of main dot C
and some dot C the GCC calls a series of
translators on that on those modules on
those dot C files first calls the C
preprocessor CPP
then it calls the the compiler the
actual compiler which is cc1 the
compiler generates assembly which is
then translated by the assembler AS and
resulting in a dot o file called main
dot o similar things happens first for
some dot C so after after the after
these three translators work on the code
we have two object files two dot o files
the linker takes those those dot o files
and put some links them together sort of
smashes them together to form a single
executable called
that we can then run then we can then
load and run on the system so the main
dot C and some dots they are called
source files these dot o files are our
object files that we are separately
compiled but and we call them
relocatable object files because they
can be combined together to form the
fully linked executable object file so
why do we do it like this you know why
why do we allow this so-called separate
compilation you know why don't we just
have like one big you know one big file
that with all of our code in it well
there's a couple reasons the first is is
modularity so by by allowing you to
break your code into smaller pieces you
can put related functions into separate
source files you can define libraries of
functions so it's just it's just good
technique and it allows you to kind of
break your code up into nice to nice
modular pieces the other reason is
efficiency so if if we if we've broken
up our program into multiple chunks if
we change and if we if
we only need to change one of the chunks
we don't have to recompile the all the
other all the other modules right we can
just recompile the one module that we
changed and then link them all together
again right so it's it's efficient in
time it's also efficient in space
because you can take all of say all of
the functions in the standard c library
you could put them all together but then
the only functions that you actually get
compiled and linked into your program
are the ones that you actually call ok
so you can you can save space you don't
you know normally you use only a small
subset of the standard C functions and
so you there's no there's no point in
linking all of those functions into your
code if you don't need them
alright so what do linkers do well
there's two main there's two main tasks
that a linker performs the first is
called simple resolution so programs
define and reference symbols okay that
what the linker refers to as symbols and
these are global variables and functions
okay in the names and those those
objects they're referred to as a symbol
so here we're declaring we're defining a
symbol called swap here we're referring
when we call swap we're referring to
that symbol okay that's a reference to
the symbol and here we're defining a
pointer to an int called
XP so we're defining XP and we're
initializing it to the address of X so
we're referring that's a reference to X
okay so the symbol definitions are
stored in the object file by the
assembler in a symbol table which is an
array of structs where each truck
contains information about the symbol
like the name of the symbol its size and
where it's located
now what we mean by symbol resolution is
that during the linker plinking process
the linker associates each symbol
reference with exactly one symbol
definition okay so it's possible in
multiple you know why is this an issue
well it's possible like in multiple
modules you may declare a global
variable with the same name the linker
has to decide which one of those
definitions to use for all subsequent
references
now once once the linker is associated a
unique object with each a unique symbol
definition with each reference then it
does the second step which is relocation
and during relocation it merges all of
the modules together into a single into
a single executable object module that
can be directly loaded and executed on
the system so when it when it when it
does this merging it has to it has to
figure out where each each symbol each
function and each variable is going to
be stored okay and this is called
relocation because initially functions
are just stored at some offset in their
in their object module right because
that the linker doesn't know where those
functions are actually going to be
eventually a loaded into memory so
before before relocation the address of
a function in the object module is just
its offset in the in the module and
similarly for data during the relocation
step the the linker decides on where
each symbol is going to be ultimately
located in memory one at X when the
program executes and it binds that that
those absolute memory locations to the
to the symbol and then and then it goes
and looks at all the references to those
symbols and it updates those references
so that they
now they point to the correct address
okay so figure out where stuff is going
to go for each definition figure out
where it's going to go and for each
reference then update that reference so
it now points to the right spot so let's
look at what what these how these steps
work in more detail before that we need
to we need to define a few things so
there's there's three kinds of object
modules that I've alluded to there's the
dot o file which is a relocatable object
module this is the output of the
assembler okay and it's it's not it's a
binary file but it's it's not in any
form that can be directly loaded into
memory it needs to be manipulated by the
linker before it can be actually used
there's the executable object file which
is generated by the linker these are
called a dot out files sometimes
historically the very first Linux
systems the executable this sort of the
default name that they the developers of
UNIX used the default name for their
executables was a dot out so that's just
sort of a historical reason that it's
it's it's called a dot out and then
there's another type of object file
called a shared object file or dot iso
file which is a sort of modern a modern
technique for creating shared libraries
and we'll look at those we'll look at
those later today
now object modules come in a standard
format called elf format and it's it's a
unified format for dot o files for
executables and for dot iso files they
all use the same format the same general
format so this while these these elf
binaries are their binaries they're very
structured ok and they're broken up into
sections the at the beginning is the is
a header that defines things like the
size of the word
the byte ordering whether it's a dot o n
a dot out or a dot s o so it just
provides some sort of general
information about this about this binary
and then there's what's a so called
segment header table which is it only
it's only defined for the executable
object files and it indicates where all
the different segments of the code are
going to go in in memory so where does
your stack go where do your shared
libraries go
where does your that you're initialized
and uninitialized data where does your
code go right so all these all these
various sections are defined in the
segment header table and then there's
the code itself which is is called the
dot text section for sort of arcane
historical reasons so dot text is always
code and then that's followed by
read-only data such as the jump tables
in switch statements so text and read
only the dot text and dot ro data have
the property that they're they're both
read-only you don't write to them then
that's followed by the data section
which is contains space for all of your
initialized global variables and then
there's a section called BSS which
contain which defines the uninitialized
global variables now this doesn't
actually take up any space because
they're uninitialized droids ok but
there there are entries in the symbol
table for them and in it at when this
program gets loaded these variables are
going to need they're actually going to
have to have space allocated for them
BSS is another one of those sort of
arcane names that cope goes all the way
back to the 60s for there was an idea of
instruction called the block started by
symbol I think a better way to remember
what it means is better safe space ok so
you can if you have a separate section
for the uninitialized variable since
uninitialized you don't have to you know
they don't have to consume any room in
the in the dot o file ok there's also a
section for the symbol table this
contained like I said it's an array of
structs for procedures global variables
and anything defined with the static
attribute and each one of these each one
of these symbols gets an entry in the
symbol table and then there's two two
sections called them that contain
relocation info so this is the notes
when that when the linker went and
identified all the references to symbols
it put a little note to say I'm going to
have to remember to fix this the
reference to this symbol up when I when
I actually create the the executable so
a relocation entry is just like a note
that the linker or that it's a note that
the assembler makes to the linker to say
hey you're going to have to fix up this
this reference because I don't know I
don't know where this symbol is actually
going to be stored in memory when it's
when it's loaded okay and then there's a
debug section that contains information
that relates line numbers to in the
source code to line numbers in the
machine code okay and so this is called
debug and this is what you get when you
compile with dash G and then there's a
header table that that tells you where
all these different sections start now
to a linker there's there's three
different kinds of symbols global
symbols are defined in some module m and
they can and they can be used by other
modules right so I mean did you notice
when we if we have a program that
consists of multiple modules and we
compile each one of those modules into a
dot o file will be calling functions
that
aren't defined that are defined by other
modules right okay so those but there's
no error though that the compiler
doesn't doesn't throw an error because
it's assuming that those are defined in
other modules and it assumes the linker
will be able to find them in and
determine the address so anything that's
defined with that any global either
either global variable or function name
that's defined without the static
attribute is a is a global symbol okay
now and then external symbols are kind
of the flip side of that external
symbols are symbols that are referenced
by some module but defined in some other
module okay so in our in our in our
little running example when when main
dot C called the function some it was
referencing an external symbol okay and
then there's there's local symbols and
these are symbols that are defined and
referenced within a module okay and
those you create that this is not this
is different from local variables
okay the linker you know local see
variables are managed by the compiler on
the stack linker has no idea about local
local see variables okay in this context
when we talk about a local symbol what
we're talking about is is either is a
global a global variable or function
declared with the static attribute whose
that can only be referenced from within
that module so we say that the scope the
scope of the a function or global
variable defined with the static
attribute is limited to the module that
it was defined in okay so this is in C
this is how we do abstraction and this
is how we can create sort of private
functions that and pup private functions
that can't be called from from outside
that module okay so for instance if we
want to make a library
and see of functions we want to make a
collection of functions that other
programs can then call it link into
their program and call the functions
that we want to make visible to to other
programs are defined without the static
attribute and the functions that we want
to have private and just be internal we
declare what the static attribute okay
and that way we get abstraction and we
get hiding information hiding and we're
only exposing data and functions that
that we want that we want to expose all
right so let's look in detail how the
symbol resolution step works we recall
our example our example program so here
we're referencing a global called array
that's defined within main dot see here
when we here we're defining main a
global called main here we're
referencing a global called sum that's
defined in some dot c and val is a local
c variable on the stack and linker knows
nothing about that
okay now an or doesn't know anything
about IRS which are also local variables
now let's just let's make sure that we
understand the difference between local
static c variables versus local non
static c variables so here we're
defining a local static variable called
int within this function f now because
it's local its scope is limited to this
function so this variable X can only be
referenced within function f and
similarly for
this definition of X and function G can
only be referenced by by function G now
what's but because it's declared with
the static attribute it's not stored on
the stack it's actually stored in in the
in dot data just like a global would be
so it's it's like a global in the sense
that it's actually stored in dot data
rather than the stack but it's like a
local see variable in the sense that its
scope is limited just to the function
that it's defined in okay so what what
the compiler will do it'll allocate
space for each definition of X so this
and it'll give it some name to
disambiguate it so maybe it will call
this one X dot one and maybe this one X
dot two so these symbols are allocated
in dot data because because they're
initialized and they get symbol table
entries just like just like any other
symbol
okay so I said that during symbol
resolution the linker associates each
reference each symbol reference to
exactly one unique symbol definition now
how does it do that if there's multiple
symbol definitions across all the
modules so to understand this well will
will will define symbols as being either
strong or weak so strong symbols are
either procedures or function function
names or initialize global variables
weak symbols or uninitialized global
variables
okay so int foo here is a strong symbol
because it's initialized we're
initializing it p1 is strong by
definition foo is is weak in p2 see this
this definition of foo is weak because
it's uninitialized and the definition of
p2 is strong okay so that the rules that
the the linker uses are the following
multiple strong symbols not allowed so
that's an error okay so that means that
if we if across multiple modules we
declare a function with the same name
the linker will throw an error that's
not allowed given a strong symbol and
multiple weak symbols if the linker will
always choose the the strong symbol now
remember if we initialize a global
variable and we if we declare a an
initialized global variable across
multiple modules that's an error because
those are strong symbols okay by rule
one but if we have one strong symbol and
multiple weak symbols all with the same
name then the compiler will choose the
strong symbol okay and it will associate
all references to that symbol will go to
that strong symbol and if there's
multiple weak symbols then it just picks
an arbitrary one and this this is we'll
see can be problematic
now you can override
with this GCC flag called no common and
if you if you declare your function with
this no common argument then multiple
weak symbols will throw an error in a
linker all right so why do we care about
all this stuff well it turns out if
you're not aware of this stuff you can
you can run into some really serious
problems that are just perplexing and
confounding right so linker linker
errors are like the worst kind they're
the hardest kind of debug because people
aren't usually aware of what's going on
inside their linkers and usually it's
only like the very best programmers that
really understand you know how these
linkers work and what kind of errors
they can throw and how to debug them so
let me show you some examples of of
these these kind of errors all right so
we have a program we've word we have two
modules so each of these rectangles
corresponds to a module and we're
defining p1 in each module so that's too
strong symbols that's an error okay
now here we've we're defining p1 and p2
so we're okay but now we've got two week
symbols both are integers variables
called X so and if these modules are
referencing X the linker will just pick
it will just pick one of these to serve
as the definition but is is this really
what you want now in this case it
doesn't really hurt anything because X
is declared in both modules as an int
all right so it'll just be it'll just be
some integer sized variable that and
it'll be it'll be somewhere and but it
doesn't really matter which which one
the linker chooses but we start to get
into trouble if if we declare these weak
symbols with different types so here
we've declared an int X in one module
and a double X in another module so if
we write to X if the linker just
arbitrarily chooses this this symbol
definition to use now this is a symbol
that of length 8 of size 8 if we
anywhere in this program if we if the
linker chooses that then anywhere in the
program those references to those
references to X will be to this double
word this double word even even in this
module if we reference X it'll be an
8-byte right so it will overwrite Y with
the
hi order excuse me oh no it's completely
it's just committal just pick one
arbitrarily and you don't know I mean it
alright here's now this is here's a
problem we've defined a strong symbol X
because we've initializes so the linker
will always will associate all
references to X to this integer sized
this integer sized symbol so if we write
oh yeah right so so rights to X here
this will be a double in this module but
it will overwrite Y in this module so
that's really nasty
and here we were defining a strong
symbol X so references to X in the
second module will always get it will
refer to this initialized variable which
might not so it might not be what you
want right you may you may be assuming
that it's uninitialized in your code
okay and then you get the the ultimate
nightmare scenario is suppose you know
because we're following a standard ABI
we can compile our code with multiple
compilers and this actually happens in
some oh yes questions oh yeah actually
you're right it will it will still take
preference and and you'll be writing a
for by quantity which is is what you
want so that slides not quite right so
oh yeah what is the point of doing the
static versus non static if it's always
being referenced just locally in
constantly
what is the point of declaring it's time
is it it stores it in like no no no it's
if you reference up if you reference a a
variable that's you mean so a variable
is defined in your module and then you
with the static right oh they're both
they're both local so you do this if you
want to value two to retain from if you
want if you want that variable to retain
value from invocation to invocation so
suppose you it's usually a bad idea as
we'll see when we study threads because
it makes your code non thread safe but
like early like random number generators
would it would compute a pseudo-random
number and then it would store it in a
static variable and then use that as the
the starting value for the next the next
time you call that function so whenever
you want values to to persist across
function invocation to reduce static yes
something
really crash
well wait a minute let me let me get
this straight rights to X and P 2 will
actually correspond to the memory look
that it will actually go to the memory
location I'm sorry I I need to amend
that
so rights to X in P 2 will be 8 bytes
because the compiler you know the
compiler knows that it's a double but
it'll go to a memory location that's I
that's only 4 bytes because X because
the linker chose the strong symbol okay
so so the rights to X and P 2 will
actually overwrite Y ok
I'm sorry yes question
that's just usually the way it happens
you know no no no global variables go in
in data they don't go on the stack but
usually if you define local variables in
a function it will put them it will
allocate them one after the other on
them on the stack okay all right so all
this discussion about these these weird
strong weak symbol rules that the linker
have it's another reason to avoid global
variables if you can now if if you if
you need to declare a global see if you
can declare it static because that'll
limited scope to the the module that
it's declared in so that's a good idea
if you can do it and if you define a
global variable initialize it so that
you'll you'll you'll find you'll
discover if you have multiple initialize
global symbols with the same name in
your code and then if you want to it's
always good practice if you're
referencing an external variable to tell
the compiler about it by using the X
turn attribute all right
so now at this point the linker has
associated every symbol reference with
some simple definition now it has to
take all those object relocatable object
files and smush them together and create
like one one big executable so suppose
with our example a little running
example each main dot o and some dot o
contain a code and initialize data some
dough doesn't have any initialize data
it just has code and then there's their
system code that actually runs before
and after your program so when when your
program run it actually starts executing
a startup code from from lib see that
that sort of initializes things and then
the last thing that it does is it calls
main and passes it arcs RC and RV okay
and then when you're when your program
exits well that's a cyst call but if
your program if your main function
routine does a return then it returns
back to that startup code which then
doesn't exit okay so so this is just and
so this this consists of of text and
data as well and so when we when the
linker relocates these these object
files it takes all of the the code the
text sections from each of the modules
and puts them together contiguously init
in the dot text section for the
executable object file ok so it just
puts them together in some order that it
determines and it creates a combined dot
text section in the executable that
contains all of the system code and the
all of the all of the code defined in
the modules and then it does the same
thing with the data takes all the all
the dot data sections from the various
object files and puts them together in
in one combined data section
in the executable and it also emerges
the symbol tables and in the debug
information as well now when it just the
act the act of sort of relocating these
these object files requires the linker
to figure out where it's going to
actually store these these these
different these different symbols when
the system gets when this program gets
loaded so it it has to pick an address
for main that that function will start
at some absolute address it's going to
have it's going to do the same for swap
so for all the all the data arrays right
and but the problem is is that when this
code is is is compiled the compiler
doesn't know what addresses the linker
is going to pick so the so the compiler
creates these these reminders to the
linker called relocation entries which
which are then stored in the relocation
sections of the the object file and
these these relocation entries are
instructions to the linker that's
something that there's a reference to a
symbol that's going to have to be
patched up when the the code is actually
relocated and merged into the executable
so let's look at a couple of these a
couple of examples so in our in our main
dot c module there was a reference to
this to this global symbol called array
okay and then there was also a reference
to this this this global symbol sum
which is the function so the the
compiler creates two relocation entries
the first one for the reference to the
array a so here we're moving remember
EDI is the first argument so remember
our sum function takes the address of
the of array of the input array as its
it's argument so this move we're moving
the address of the array into EDI for
the first argument but the compiler
doesn't know what that address is going
to be right so it just it just it just
it just moves in it an immediate value
of 0 into EDI temporarily right so you
can see this is all zeros the bf is the
move instruction and then there's allsey
rows in for now and then it places this
relocation entry in the in the
relocation section of Maemo and it it
says it says to the linker at addre at
offset
a so these let me remind you these are
our main zero module only contains one
one function so that function starts
that offsets zero in the in the code
section of the module in the dot text
section of the module if there were
other functions in this module they
would they would follow immediately
after ok and it so you can see what what
the compiler is it's just all it's just
generating offsets of these instructions
from the beginning of the dot text
section and it it includes this
relocation entry which says to the
linker hey when you're relocating main 0
add offset a in this dot text section
you've got a reference a 32 a reference
to an array in the form of a 32-bit
address ok so that so eventually the
linker is going to have to patch up
these so this is address 9 this is
address a it's going to have to patch up
the four bytes starting at address a
with the absolute address of the symbol
array
and then similarly the reference to the
reference to this the reference to this
function some the compiler has no idea
where some actually will end up it
doesn't even know what module it's in or
even if it's even if it is defined in a
module so in this case it just it does a
call with all zeros and then it adds
this relocation entry that says to the
linker at offset F you've got a four
byte pc-relative reference to a function
to assemble called sum and then it this
is sort of a arcane detail that but and
it includes there's an option to include
a bias in the in the offset and since
we're using since calls are since calls
are always resolved using pc-relative
addressing the value that's going to be
placed here at these four bytes that
offset F is going to be an offset from
the current or I p value or program or
counter value and since the program
counter always points to the nest get
next instruction it includes this which
is four bytes away it includes this this
offset of minus four so if it sits I I
talked about it in detail in the book if
you really want to know how this works
but just the point here is that there's
enough information for the linker to
actually fill in the right address so
now if we look at the relocated text
section so if we if we compile this code
into an executable and then we use
object on to to disassemble it then what
you see is this this reference here
where we move the address of the address
of a into EDI those four bytes which
were original
zéro have now been updated with the the
actual address of array in in memory at
runtime okay so the linkers decided that
the array is going to go at address zero
x six zero one zero one eight and then
it's it's actually patched that the four
bytes in the cup in the in the move
instruction with that absolute address
and the call to sum is is it's also been
updated but this one's interesting right
that so the the address it's been
updated with the PC relative address of
five okay so when this program runs this
call instruction what it will do when it
when it determines when it computes the
absolute address of of the function some
it will take
it will take the the current value of
the program counter which is the next
instruction so four zero zero four III
and it will add to it whatever whatever
value is in this immediate field okay
which is a two scomp you interpret it as
a two's complement integer so it can go
it can be relative you can go - or or +
in this case it's saying that the
function that you want to call is that
is is at four zero zero four III plus 5
which is 4 0 0 4 e 8 which is the
address of some okay and so the linker
the linker does that the compiler has
all the smarts the compiler computed the
relocation entry the linker is just
blindly going through each of those
relocation entries and just doing what
it's told okay but the net result is
that now all of these these references
have been patched up with with valid
absolute addresses
now once the linkers created a an object
file that object file can be loaded the
code and data and that object file can
be loaded directly into memory with with
no further modification ok so the if you
look at all of the read-only sections in
the executable so there's this init
section which we're not to worry about
that that all the code is in the dot
text and things like jump tables are in
our Oh data all of this data can be
loaded directly into memory as is okay
so these bytes can just be copied
directly into into memory and that that
forms the so called a read-only code
segment the the data in the dot data and
BSS X sections can also be copied
directly into into memory and in the
case of the variables and data they'll
be initialized to a value that's stored
in the symbol table so we're drawing our
our memory here this is the this is the
the memory address space that every
Linux program sees and we're drawing
addresses starting from 0 and going up
increasing as we grow up and every
program is loaded at this the same
address 0 X 4 0 0 0 0 0 and so the the
code comes directly from the object file
the data comes directly from the object
file and then that's followed by a
runtime heap which is created and
managed by malloc so when you need
dynamic dynamically need to allocate
memory like
using malloc that memory comes out of
this heap which starts immediately
following the the data segment and grows
upwards the stack is at the very top of
the the visible memory that's available
to application programs the memory above
that is is restricted to the kernel okay
so if you try to access those memory
locations you'll get a seg fault and
then the stack as we know grows down so
this is managed and created a run time
and then there's this region somewhere
in this huge gap between the stack and
the heap there's a region for shared
libraries so the dot Esso files all get
loaded into this this memory mapped
region for shared libraries now that the
top of the heap is indicated by this
global variable maintained by the kernel
called break BRK and the the top of the
stack as we know is is maintained by the
general purpose register RSP now there's
a little bit of a this is a little bit
of a simplification if you actually look
at the addresses returned by malloc
there's actually a there's actually two
heaps there's a heap up here and in the
high memory that grows down that's used
for large objects very large you know if
you mount like a whole bunch of space
and then the heap that grows up is is
reserved for smaller smaller objects so
I'm not really sure why they do this I
think it allows them to have separate
allocation algorithms for large objects
and small objects
okay so one of the one of the real
advantages of linking is that allows us
to create libraries of things so it's
always something we want to do as
programmers we always we always want to
create abstractions and then present
those abstractions to to users right and
we do that by creating libraries
defining an API yes I think it just is
no no it actually that's a good question
I the things I've done it just grows
until it runs out of memory right there
so I don't think actually that's a
really good question I mean I've I've
done those experiments and it it
eventually reaches some limit yeah I
don't I don't know it's a very large
number but I so you know as programmers
we always want to abstract define api's
implement package up those api's and
make them available to to other
programmers so how can we actually do
that how can we make commonly used
functions available to other programmers
well one thing given what we've learned
so far you could just take all the
functions and put them all in a single
big C file right and then programmers
would just link that C file into their
into their programs if they want to use
them right another option would be to
take that might get kind of unwieldy if
it's a big library right lipsi has
hundreds and hundreds of functions so
another option would might be to just
take each function put it in a separate
file and then compile them all together
and compile and link them all together
so this is more space and time efficient
than then our first option but it seems
like it would be burdensome on the
programmer because the program would
have to know where all the all these
functions were and put them in make
files it'd just be a lot of you know
this you could end up with a
ridiculously large command line to GCC
so that the one solution to this problem
is that the first solution that the
developers of Unix
came up with us something called a
static library so the the idea where the
static library is that you create this
archive called a dot a file which is
it's just a collection of dot o files
where each dot o file contains a
function ok so you take all the
functions in your library you use option
two to create a bunch of dot o files and
then you use a program called an archive
or AR to take those dot o files put them
together in a all together in a big file
called an archive out with a with a
table of contents at the beginning that
tells you the offset of each one of the
dot o files ok so an archive is just
this concatenated collection of dot o
files and then and then you link you
pass that archive to the to the linker
and it only takes the dot o files that
are actually referenced and links them
into the code right so it's a more
efficient way you can have a huge
archive but like Lib C but if you only
call printf the only dot o file you get
is printf 0 okay so the way this works
is as before we take
now we take all the functions we want to
put in our library we run them through
our translators to get dot o files we
pass those to the archiver to get a the
archive so in this case Lib CA and which
has this code for printf that we might
want to use right and so we can we can
we can recreate that archive anytime we
want so if one of these functions
changes like say printf changes you just
re archive the dot recompile printf and
then re archive all of the dot o files
so in Lib C it's it's about 1500 object
files and it's archived things like
printf scanf simple integer math and
there's also a math library which has
you know several hundred common
functions for things like floating point
math sine cosine tangent etc these
libraries the convention is that a
library always is prefixed with Lib with
Li B and then and then sort of new some
indication of what it what it does
so now let's see how linking with these
static libraries would work so I've
created a little example here I've
created a library called Lib vector a
and it consists of functions that
manipulate vectors and this is a real
simple library it just adds there's a
function to add two vectors x and y
together and and return the result in Z
and then another similar function that
will do pairwise multiplication of two
vectors so X I times y I equals Z I and
now I compile these two programs and
pack I want to package them into an
archive called lib vector a and then in
my in my main program I'm going to call
one of those functions advic to add
these two vectors x and y together
so now what happens when we compile this
this program we've already we've
constructed the archive lib dr. a from
add vector and multi and we pass that
archive to the linker along with our
main 2.0 relocatable object file and we
also pass it lib CA which has the
definition of which contains printf 0
and anything else that printf 0 my call
so these three the linker detects the
reference to advic the function add vac
and so it just pulls advocaat o out and
and ignores the rest
similarly for printf 0 and then it
compiles all those main main to 0
Advocaat o and printf dot o all together
into this fully linked executable called
prog to see for compiled time so we're
doing this we're doing this link we're
doing this this linking at compile time
when we call a GCC now what the linker
does when it's when it's using static
libraries it scans all the dot o files
and dot a files in order on the command
line so you're just typing GCC and then
a list of dot o files and davay files in
some order so so during the scan it
keeps a list of the current unresolved
references right so if let's say let's
say it looks at main dot o first and
there's a reference to printf that's an
unresolved reference because print is
not not defined in main dot o so that
goes in a list of undefined references
and at some point or another as as each
new dot o file or dot a file is
encountered the linker tries to resolve
its list of Unruh
of references with the symbols that are
defined in that dot o file or a file and
then if there's any entries in the list
at the end of the scan then there's an
error okay so that the key here is that
the linker will try to resolve these
references from left to right on the
command line and so this is another sort
of important thing for you to know as
programmers because the order that you
that you put your files on the command
line actually makes a difference okay so
you can get sort of weird baffling
linker errors if you if you use the
wrong order so for instance suppose
we've got a function an object module
called Lib test that calls a function
that's defined in in Lib mine a okay so
these - else - big L period that that
says to look for to look for a library
files in the current directory that's
what the dot look there first and then
look in the normal places that you look
and the the - lowercase L that's a it's
like an abbreviation we could replace
this with just the fully spelled out lib
mind ed okay but you'll see this this
lowercase L used a lot so so Lib test
calls a function that's declared in in
Lib mind a so the linker looks at it
looks at the unresolved symbols in
libtech zero and it detects that there's
this unresolved function let's say it's
called foo I know it's it's called Lib
fun so and it puts it on the list and
then it goes on to the next command line
entry and that's live mine dot a and in
there it finds it finds this symbol of
lip fun and it it resolves the reference
to that - Lib phone - the actual address
the relocated address
now if we switch the order and we put
lib mind on a first followed by lib toss
zero well there's there's no unresolved
references in this library right it's
just the collection of function
definitions so it there's no unresolved
references so the linker looks at that
that's all good and then it looks at lib
toss zero and now there's an unresolved
reference to two lib fun but we're out
of we're at the end of the command line
so that's a linker error so you get this
you get this really cryptic error
message and if you didn't know about
this ordering rule you wouldn't have any
idea how to debug it okay so the static
libraries are kind of the old fashioned
solution that the modern solution is to
use dynamic libraries or shared shared
libraries so the reason the reason
there's this sort of newer form of
libraries that static libraries have
some some disadvantages so every if you
compile with static libraries then every
every function that uses printf which or
every program that uses printf has to
have a copy of printf okay but almost
every every program uses printf right so
there's a shared shared libraries allow
provide a mechanism where there can just
be one wherever there's just one
instance of a shared library member like
like printf and every program running on
the system will share that one copy
so that's the that's sort of the big big
disadvantage is this potential
duplication so shared libraries are
different in the sense that they contain
code and data that are linked and loaded
into the program not when it's not when
it's compiled and linked and into a
executable object file but actually when
the program is loaded into the system so
linking of references to shared library
objects is deferred until the program is
actually loaded into into memory until
the executable object file is actually
loaded into memory and this can either
and it can even happen it can happen
when the program is actually loaded into
memory but it can also happen at runtime
anytime at runtime so you can be you can
be running a program and that program
can arbitrarily decide to load a
function that's declared in a shared
library okay and I'll show you that it's
really cool now these things are often
called they're called shared libraries
they're called dynamic link libraries
like in Windows they're called DLLs dot
iso files they're all referenced the
same thing
okay so that this like I said you can
the the dynamic linking can occur when
the program's loaded or after it's
loaded and actually running and there's
this sort of big deal that shared
library routines can be shared by
multiple processes and we'll look at
this this will make sense when we look
at virtual memories so don't don't worry
about that now but but here's how the
process works
so we've first we have to create instead
of creating an archive we create a
shared library so our live vector
routines instead of creating an archive
a file we create a shared a dot SOF file
using the using the shared argument to
GCC so we take our two input functions a
Drac and molbeck and share it says to
create and we're telling GCC to create a
shared library and place it in live
vector D so okay and so and there's also
that the the C the C developers have
created a punctured library called Lib C
so that contains printf and on it and
other standard library functions so we
take our program main - this is the same
program that calls advic and we compile
it into main to zero and we pass main to
zero and these dot iso files - the
linker now the linker doesn't at this
point it doesn't actually copy let's say
we're using advic or printf it doesn't
actually copy those functions or do
anything with them in the executable it
just makes a note in the symbol table
that those functions will need to be the
references to those functions will need
to be resolved when the program is
loaded okay so it it puts in a
relocation entry that says fix this up
when you load the program so it's
partially linked but
it's not fully linked you can't take
that you can't take a program
you can't take a executable file that
was dynamically linked and loaded
directly what you what you do is the
loader which is the X X ee system call
and we'll learn more about that but just
this is just a cyst call that loads
loads executables into memory and runs
them the loader takes the executable and
then it takes the the shared iso files
that this this program needs k it also
made when the linker also made a note of
which dos o files it needs so the loader
calls the dynamic linker which takes
those dos o files and then actually
resolves all the references to any on
any unresolved reference okay so the the
address of advic the ad vac and printf
functions isn't determined until the
program is loaded and by that and it
isn't determined by the dynamic linker
until the program is loaded so that the
dynamic linker does it goes through a
similar process that the static linker
did sort of fixing up references to add
back at references to to printf and then
at that point the binary the binary is
in it is in a form that can be executed
directly so question
yes what if you look the part where did
like where is that like if you include
violence and use anger and greed zero
actually
if okay the question is what happens if
you include a file so includes are
handled by the C preprocessor so they're
gone they're long gone by the time the
by the time the linker gets around to it
okay so the C preprocessor just takes
sharp sign define sharp sign include and
and interprets those and outputs another
C program so if you if you include a
file the C preprocessor just takes that
file and just expands it and the output
C program contains an expanded version
of all the files that you include it
okay
now what's really cool is that you can
also do this dynamic linking at runtime
so what I showed you before we're doing
it at load time but you can also
arbitrarily decide to to load link and
call a function from a shared from a
from any function defined in a dot iso
file and the way you do it is there's a
there's an interface called the dl open
that's in Lib C that allows you to do
this and so let's say we want to this is
this is our main program and just like
before we want to call advic okay but
advic now is defined in it in a dot iso
file the exact same dot SL file that we
generated before when we compile so
we'll call this DLL dot C when we
compile this program DLL dot C we have
no we have no idea that it's going to
call a function from from Lib dr. D so
we just compile it as though a
standalone C C program within this
program though we declare a pointer a
function pointer called advic and we
give the prototype for this function
it's pointers city so it's a two input
arrays the output array on the size and
then first we dynamically load the
shared library that contains the
function we want so we call DL open and
we say load up this this dot SL file
into memory so that I can call a
function but don't resolve you know
don't worry don't worry about the
resolving the references to it functions
until I actually tell you - that's the
lazy part and so what what this deal
open returns a handle that that then you
use in subsequent calls okay so if we
don't if the handle is null there was
some kind of error like maybe maybe this
data so file does
exist so once we've opened that dot Esso
file then we use DL SIM with the handle
so this and then we we give it as we
pass as a string the name of the
function that we want to invoke and we
get what we get back from DL sim as a
pointer to that function and then we can
we can use that function just like any
other function so we can use that
function pointer and we call it just as
though it were a statically defined
function so you can see this is real
very powerful technique
okay so looks let's finish the the last
little bits of the class I want to show
you it to try to convince you that
linking is is actually interesting which
is kind of a hard sell sometime yes
question yes no it's that's how you know
you just it's it's declared as a
function pointer and you then you just
you just you just use the name of the
function you don't have to dereference
it or you just you call it you call the
function by just using that that that
function pointer name okay just like I
did
if you dereference it I just get back a
pointer value you get back the address
of that function all right so it's kind
of a hard sell to that to convince you
that linking is is interesting but I'm
going to try ok so there's there's this
powerful technique called
inner library inter positioning and the
goal is to intercept function calls from
from libraries and do something
intercept them for for some reason right
so what we typically want to do is
intercept a function call maybe record
some to some statistics or do some error
checking and then call the real function
as intended right so so the idea is
we're going to create wrappers and when
the program when a program calls a
function what we're going to do is we're
going to execute its wrapper instead
okay and we're going to do it without
changing any of the source
now there's a lot of reasons there's a
lot of applications for this that the
neatest one that that I know is that
these Facebook engineers so we're trying
to deal with this year-long bug in the
Facebook iPhone app and nobody could
figure out what was going on and they
figured it out using library inter
positioning they figured out that there
was something in the network stack
writing to the wrong location they
figured it out by intercepting all the
calls from their Facebook app that did
rights so things like write write to the
EP right so they just they intercepted
all those calls and then they were able
to when they looked at the arguments and
how those functions were being called
they determine the air you can also use
it for monitoring and profiling like so
if you want to know like how many times
different functions get called you can
you can do you can interpose we use it
for for generating address traces so
you're malloc when you do your malloc
lab later in the semester you're going
to be evaluating your malloc using a
traces that we generated from real
programs using this inter positioning
technique right so we we enter post on
all the malloc and free calls in like
Netscape and then we just recorded what
addresses and and sizes Malik was was
returning and what what blocks free was
freeing up and we just created a trace
of those and and then so let me show you
how you would do this so the idea let's
say we have this main program and the
idea is to trace all the malloc and free
calls so there's one malloc call and
there's one free call and we want to
know what these addresses are and we
want to know what these sizes are so we
can do this at either compile time link
time or run time to do it at compile
time we first write wrapper functions
called my malloc and my free where my
malloc call
most the real malloc function and then
it prints out the the size that it was
called and the the address that malloc
returned okay so this when we run our
program it will it will print out these
all these addresses and it does the same
thing for free and then here's the trick
in malloc dot H we we define malloc to
be my malloc okay and free to be my free
and then we give the prototype for it so
the compiler doesn't get confused and
then we can PI might we compile my
malloc C into a dot o file and then we
call week then we complete we call our
program which is is our main program int
dot C for inner positioning and we call
that and here's the trick we call it
with the - cap I argument and we say
look for any include files in the
current directory okay so this was
similar to that el - cap el argument but
because we tell GCC to look in the
current directory first so this is sort
of where the inner positioning happens
this because when it does that it's
going to it's going to find a it's going
to find a library called malloc H
I mean o dot H file called malloc dot H
and so all the calls to malloc will be
translated by the C preprocessor to my
malloc so when we run this it prints out
the the trip malloc and free trace now
we can also do this at link time so we
can tell C in order to do this we had to
get access to the we had to compile the
program we didn't have to change it but
we had to compile it we can use link
time at our positioning if to avoid that
that that compilation so the way this
works we define our wrapper functions
with this special name underscore
underscore wrap malloc
and this calls the real malloc function
and then prints out the information and
then at link time then we do the inter
positioning by calling the linker with
this special
- WL argument and so what this does the
the - WL flag to GCC says hey take what
follows the argument that follows
replace all the commas with spaces and
then invoke the linker with this
argument okay so what we're doing is
passing a linker arguments to the linker
and this - - wrap argument to the linker
it tells the linker to resolve all
references to Malik as underscore
underscore wrap Malik and all references
to underscore real Malik - should be
resolved as Malik okay so anywhere in
the program what we call Malik it'll be
resolved to underscore underscore wrap
Malik and it will invoke our wrapper and
then the wrapper calls real Malik which
which by because of this flag resolves
to the the actual Malik routine now here
you can also in the really the really
amazing thing is you can also do this
inter positioning it load timer and run
time when the program is loaded so you
don't even need access to the dot o
files all you need is access to the
executable right and for every program
we have access to the executable so
think about that we can take any program
and we can interpose on its library
calls at runtime so the way we do this
is we write the wrapper function now
uses the DL sim call that we saw before
and we call it with this special
function the special argument called
next and we silver and what this is
saying is get the address of the real
Malik okay so and we're going to we're
going to trick the linker into looking
first to our our implementation of
malloc
but here we want the real one so we're
telling it to get to look in the next
place its next place that it would
normally look and and and fetch the the
address of Malik so the result is a
pointer a function pointer called Malik
P and then we can just call that
function to get to call the Lipsy Malik
and then print out the the data okay we
do the same thing for free st. we use DL
sim in exactly the same way for free and
then the inter positioning now happens
when the program is loaded so notice we
built this our main program now in tar
for run time inter positioning we built
it I'm sorry we created our dot SL file
my Malachi so using the shared argument
and then and then we we compiled int int
dot C into this executable called int R
but notice there's no mention of my
malloc dot s o anywhere and now the
inner positioning happens when we
actually run the program and we do it we
we affect the the inner positioning by
setting an environment variable called
LD preload to my Malachi so and so what
this is a environment variable that
tells the dynamic linker to look first
in the the value it looked first in the
the value of LD preload is a list of
locations look first in those locations
when to resolve references and only only
later look in the normal system places
so we're saying to look in my malloc dot
s o4 unresolved references first and
then and then we're invoking so this is
in bash this is how you initialize an
environment variable so we're
initializing it to my malloc do so and
then we're loading and running the
program and so the LD so all the
references to malloc get turned into the
references to the wrapper function
the malloc function that we defined in
in our program okay so that's uh so
that's it so that that inter positioning
is a really cool technique and it's only
it's only possible because of linkers so
alright so good
we'll see you on on Thursday and good
luck with your cash labs