all right well good afternoon everybody
good to see you welcome welcome to all
those students watching on video as well
before we start we were talking about
joinable and detached threads and you
asked the question about why you would
ever want to have threads running in non
detached mode you know why you'd ever
run in want to have him running joinable
and I didn't give you a very good answer
so I want to try to to answer that for
you better turns out there's an
important class of sort of parallel
programming there's a there's an
important parallel programming model
called fork and join where program
consists of a series of phases in each
phase in each phase you have a worker or
a master sorry and it creates a bunch of
worker threads and then each of those
worker threads solve some part of the
problem for that phase like so maybe you
take your data structure and you break
it up into chunks and then each thread
updates the its own chunk of that data
structure but for whatever reason the
the master then has to wait for the
worker threads to finish before it can
go on to the next phase so it it does
adjourn so this is called the fork and
then it waits for all the threads to
finish by doing a join okay so this is
called this is called the fork and this
is called the join and only when all of
the threads have finished can it go and
do the next do the next phase
okay so this this model is really
important in things like scientific
computing where you might you're
simulating some domain you're simulating
nature so you represent that as some
domain like maybe you're simulating how
heat flows over a plate you know metal
plate and so you might might have these
workers you might partition the domain
amongst a set of those workers and then
each one of these phases is a time step
and then so once once all the workers
have finished a time step then they can
advance to the next time step and so
sorry I don't know why I didn't think of
it that's a that's an important reason
why you'd want this okay so we saw we've
seen the threaded threaded programs are
are nice because you they you can share
all the global variables but this the
sharing can can have unintended
consequences so somehow we need a
mechanism where we can control how the
flows of each individual thread are
interleaved so that bad things don't
happen when we share data structures
okay so this this process of controlling
the the interleaving is called
synchronization so we're going to look
at techniques that you can use to write
correct threaded programs by properly
synchronizing them now first though we
need to have a clear idea so sharing is
the issue right if we have threads that
aren't sharing any resources then
there's no problem right that we saw
this when we looked at it processes
there's no shared data structures with
processes so we process these just run
independently we don't really care how
they're interleaved note no worries okay
but as soon as they introduce sharing
then then we have to be careful okay so
to understand how to synchronize threads
we first need to have a clear idea of of
what we mean by sharing in in threaded C
programs so the the answer is not as
simple
as global variables are shared and stack
variables are not shared okay so with
instead what we X is shared if and only
if multiple threads reference some
instance so that that variable X all
right so if only one thread is accessing
a particular variable then it's it's not
shared okay so in order to know exactly
what we mean by shared we need to answer
three questions okay first what is the
memory model for threads okay
second how are instances of variables
mapped to memory and then and then third
how many threads might be referencing
those the instances of those variables
okay so we'll look at each of those now
in turn each of those three questions
okay so first is that the memory model
the conceptual model is a little bit
different from the the operational model
the way it really works
okay so conceptually we have multiple
threads that run in the context of a
single process okay and some of that
context is shared and some of its not
shared so each thread has its own
separate thread ID stack stack pointer
program counter condition codes
general-purpose registers and then they
all share the remaining process context
which is data structures that the kernel
maintains for the threads the virtual
data structures to support the virtual
memory system open files install signal
handlers and so forth so that's the
conceptual model and if that were that
if that were really enforced it would be
nice it would make things simpler for us
but unfortunately in real life this
model is not strictly enforced
now although register values are really
separate right the kernel maintains
separate context for the all the
registers so that that part is good but
since the threads share the the address
space a thread can access the the memory
the stack one thread can access the
stack of an another thread okay so
although conceptually these stacks are
separate and distinct and in private
they're really not and so this can
create some problems so here's an
example of that we'll come back to later
of how this one thread can access the
stack of another thread so here we're
defining a global variable called
pointer which is a char star star and
then in the main routine on were
declaring a local variable called
messages which contains it's a two
element array which contains a couple
strings which these will be printed out
by by the threads that we're going to
create and then we assign the global
pointer to the vet to the address of the
array messages okay so now pointer
points to messages and then we create in
a loop we create two threads each of
which executes this routine called
thread and and we're passing an argument
so the P threads will assign a thread ID
but in this case we're going to assign
our own local thread ID by passing this
loop index okay so this is an example we
talked about this last time it's it's
kind of it's this is perfectly okay
there's no race but it's it's a little
weird because we're going to take this
index I and cast it to a generic pointer
okay
and then after we create these threads
then we'll exit the main thread now each
the thread routine dereferences its
argument to get the local the local
thread ID and then it it declares a
static variable count that we're going
to use to count how many times this
thread routine is called inside of a
thread and then it just prints a simple
message from identifying that giving the
local thread ID and then the message
indexed by my ID so pointer points to
messages so thread zero will print hello
from foo and thread 1 will print hello
from bar and then and then we increment
the pre increment the counter variable
okay so although it doesn't you wouldn't
you would it looks like we're accessing
this global variable pointer but since
that was assigned to be the address of
the local variable on the main the main
thread stack we've got this these peer
threads accessing local variables on the
main thread stack okay so that I just
this is not it you never want to do this
as a very bad practice but I it's a kind
of thing that can happen sometimes by
accident you know if you forget that
pointer actually was assigned to you
know some-some stack address okay so
that so the second question that is how
do we map variable instances to memory
now we looked at this when we when we
studied linking but let's let's just
review this quickly again to make sure
that it's clear to you so global
variables are variables that are
referenced outside of a function and
virtual memory the linker when it does
symbol resolution make sure that there's
exactly one instance of every global
variable in virtual memory
now local variables are declared on the
stack inside of a function without the
static attribute and so in this case
each the stack for each thread will
contain one instance of that local
variable
now if variables are declared inside of
a function with the static attribute
then the scope of that variable is
limited to that function meaning no
other function can access it but that
static variable is stored along with all
the other local variables so there's any
static variable declared inside of a
function has exactly one instance in in
memory and if you were to have say
multiple functions that declared the
same a static variable with the same
name the compiler would would
disambiguate those somehow it would it
would append some kind of unique it
would somehow make that name unique okay
okay so what recall how all these
different types of variable instances
are mapped into memory
okay pointer is a global variable so
there's one instance of pointer in the
address space and it's stored in the in
the data segment
I I and messages are examples of local
variables to Maine so there's one
instance of these stored on the stack of
Maine stack and we'll denote those with
this notation we'll say variable I I dot
M means variable I is stored on main
stack and messages is stored on the
stack of Maine okay now my ID is a local
variable declared defined in this thread
routine and so there's actually since
there's two of these threads there's
there's now there are in memory there's
there's two instances of my ID one one
for each stack okay associated with the
stack associated with each thread so my
ID p0 is stored on P R thread 0 stack
and my ID dot p1 is stored on P R thread
1 stack ok and now this counter variable
the static counter variable has just
exactly one instance in in virtual
memory and it sits in the data segment
along with the other global variables
like like pointer okay now so the
question is which of these variables are
shared and which are not okay so we can
remember what we said is it's shared if
if more than one thread is accessing an
instance of that variable okay so let's
let's just list all the different
variables and then let's look at each of
these threads and see if it's referenced
by that thread okay so what about what
about pointer right there's just
it's referenced by the main thread right
and what about Pierre threads zero
yeah it's referenced by peer thread zero
right here right here and similarly for
pthread and one okay so so pointer is
referenced by all three threads
now what about count counts not
referenced by the main thread but it is
referenced by the two peer threads now
what about I in main that's referenced
by main of course but not by but not by
either of the two threads now we're
about messages the messages array okay
so that's that's accessed by my main and
indirectly through pointer it's
referenced by each of these two peer
threads now what about my ID defined in
in peer thread zero okay so that's
referenced that's a local variable so
it's only referenced by peer thread zero
right it's not referenced by either the
other threads and similarly for for my
ID and in peer threat one
okay so given given that definition then
which of these variables is shared so
it's it's really straightforward with
yeah okay so the question is discount
count as a share variable and answer is
yes because because it's declared static
it's there's one instance of it in in in
virtual memory and each of the threads
references that instance okay so it's
it's shared it's really like a global
variable it's just a scope is limited to
the the it stored the same way a global
variable is but its scope is limited to
the function that it's defined in okay
so to determine if each one of these is
whether which which of these variables
are shared in which one's not we just we
just look go across and for any any
variable with its shared by more than
more than one thread then it's shared so
pointer shared so pointer is shared
count is not shared
oh no no count is shared because it's
it's referenced by peer thread zero and
peer thread one i's not shared because
it's only referenced by by main so
messages is access referenced by all
three threads so it's shared but my ID
is is not shared because it's only
referenced by exactly one thread okay so
so pointer count and messages are the
shared variables in this program and the
others are run share yes would like the
second process and over so she declared
my ideas static with the second process
of overridden it yeah that would be a
race okay so that would we just depend
on which which thread executed first so
you would really wouldn't want to do
that
okay so so we have a very clear notion
now of what we mean by sharing
so these being able to share variables
like this in this ways is very handy but
you can run into some really nasty
problems that are very surprising so let
me show you an example this is a program
called bad count so obviously there's
something wrong with this I'm giving you
a little clue but what we want to do is
we want to create we want to create a
bunch of threads or a number of threads
and each of those threads will increment
a global variable called count some
number of times the same number of times
okay so so we pass in the number of
iterations as the first argument and
here's our well here's our global
globally shared variable and you
remember what volatile means everybody
remember what that means so what is
volatile what is volatile tell the
compiler yes
it actually you you're on in the right
direction actually tells it tells the
compiler never to put that variable in a
register okay so it always it will
always read that value from memory or
store it to memory and you do that
because of exactly the kind of
possibility that you mentioned so so in
this in this case we have we create two
threads but with two distinct calls to
two pthread create each of these threads
will will run the the thread routine
called thread and it will pass and as an
argument the address of the number of
iterations that it should that it should
iterate now you remember when we were
looking when we were passing connected
file descriptors if if we pass an
address that was a race okay but in this
case there's no race this is fine it's
fine just to pass the address of number
of iterations so why is it okay in this
case but it wasn't okay when we were
passing the connected file descriptor
that we got from acceptant to our thread
routine
yes exactly because the thread doesn't
modify the value and that the problem we
had before was that our main thread was
modifying that connected descriptor on
on the next call to accept but here it's
just a read-only variable so we're okay
but you see the how tricky the reasoning
can get right there's you can't do
pattern matching to determine whether
you've got races or not races right so
you can't just say well it's always bad
to pass the address of some variable to
a to a thread routine okay because it's
not it just depends on the context okay
so in this case we're passing the number
of iterations and to each thread and
then we're waiting for each of those
threads to finish so this is an example
of why you need why you might want to
have a non detached thread because you
can't we want when we check when we
check the value of count we have to make
sure that every thread is finished
before we check whether we got the right
value or not okay so we wait for each
thread to finish and now since we've
created two threads each of which is
incrementing count Editors time we
expect count to be equal to two times
and ITER's and if it's not we print my
favorite error message otherwise we with
with the value of count otherwise we
print okay also with the value of count
okay so now what's going on in the
thread routine very simple it
dereferences the the the argument that
was passed in and stores it in the local
copy of entities and then it loop
senators time in can increments count
each time so and then returns so this is
very innocuous what could go wrong and
since this is threading since this is
concurrent concurrent programming
especially since it's threaded
programming what there's the odd lots of
subtle things can go wrong so it turns
out this program has a really serious
bug
okay because when we run it when we run
it on a Linux box sometimes if we call
it with an argument of ten thousand
sometimes we get the correct answer two
times ten thousand or twenty thousand
but then the next time we run it we get
some weird number 13050 one completely
wrong and so what what the heck is going
on here okay so to understand that we
have to look at the assembly language
for this counter loop so that we want to
we we need to look at the the December
language for this counter loop in the
thread routine so we'll break it up into
three chunks that the the first chunk is
sort of getting ready for the loop we'll
call that the head and we'll denote
we'll denote it as H of I for thread I
and then we'll we'll we'll isolate on
these three instructions that are
directly related to incrementing count
okay so you see the first instruction
moves it loads the global of the value
and global variable count into register
RDX so will denote that as L of I next
it increments RDX and we'll denote that
U of I for update so it updates RDX and
then it stores the value the updated
value of RDX into count
okay so into the location associated
with the loke the global variable count
and and then the rest of the the rest of
this loop is getting ready for the to do
the next iteration it's not directly
related to incrementing count so we'll
just sort of group this all together and
refer to it as T of I for tail okay
now let's look at let's look at how this
how these two threads might be might be
executed and remember in general we
can't assume that there's any specific
interleaving so any interleaving of
these two threads is possible no matter
how remote it might seem so let's look
at one example let's say we're executing
on a single core so we're only going to
do one instruction at a time and in this
column will show which thread is
executing
so either thread 1 or thread 2 and then
we'll to know which instruction in that
thread is executing either H lus or T
and then this column shows the value of
RDX for thread number 1 and this column
shows the value of RDX for thread number
2 right and since that the kernel keeps
separate copies of all the
general-purpose registers the for each
each thread these can be different okay
and then this last column shows the
value of count in memory so let's start
executing so initially count is equal to
0 and thread one gets the kernel
schedules thread thread 1 so it executes
say CH 1 that has no impact on on count
then thread 1 loads the value of count
into its copy of RDX updates it so now
our DX is equal to 1 and then stores
that value in RDX
back to count so now count is equal to 1
now at this point the kernel decides to
schedule thread to sew thread two begins
executing and when it begins executing
value of count is 1 so it executes H of
I then it loads count into the art into
thread 2's copy of RDX so now our DX
equals 1
updates it now it's equal to 2 and then
stores that value back to count the
kernel then decides oh and then and then
it finishes executing the tail
instruction and let's say we're just
doing one iteration of this and then at
this point the kernel decides to
schedule thread one since thread two is
finished so thread 1 1 executes the
remaining statement that it has to
execute and at this point both threads
have finished and count is equal to 2
which is the value we would expect ok so
this so this is ok and notice how so
this is actually this is an inner
leaving that works ok we get the correct
value and notice how I did it grouped
the 3 instructions that are actually
involved in updating count together and
it will call that we'll call those 3
instructions a critical section and I've
color-coded them so you can easily keep
track of them alright let's look now
let's look at another another
interleaving which is feasible right but
in this case it results in the wrong
value ok so here we start with thread 1
again it loads it's the value of count
into its copy of RDX updates it but then
before it can store it the kernel
decides to schedule thread - so thread 2
begins X executing it loads count into
its copy of RDX - and notice count is
still 0 right it's it's 1 in the value
of in thread one in the RDX the copy of
RDX and thread 1 but it hasn't been
updated in memory so when when when
thread 2 loads its value of count now
it's copy and RDX is 0 now at this point
the kernel reschedules thread 1 to
execute so thread 1 does it
store of its copy of RDX into count and
then finishes executing it the tale
instruction the colonel reschedules
thread - which picks up where it left
off it updates its copy of of count
so now RDX goes from 0 to 1 and then it
stores that value into count so all
we've done is we've overwritten count
out a value 1 and we've overwritten it
with a value of 1 so when we finish
execution of these two threads count has
the wrong value okay in the that then
the general like the general thing to
notice is you see how these critical
sections have been interleaved right in
this in this case this is the first the
critical section for thread 1 executed
before the the critical section for
thread 2 okay but in this case the two
critical sections interleaved okay
so let's see another example of that so
here you can see that these are
interleaved so probably suggest there
might be a problem yes so I'm sick scuse
me
well no okay so the question is would
would I or count count if we okay it is
defined as volatile it didn't I yeah so
that that's why I mean there's actually
and the compiler could have compiled
this code in different ways right there
is actually an increment instruction
that you will increment a variable in
memory so you could have done the
compiler could have generated this this
3 instruction sequence is one
instruction and then we wouldn't have
this problem but the problem is that
it's it's it's loading into register
then incrementing and then saving so
that the problem comes about because we
can this this thread can be interrupted
before it finishes this three-step
sequence this load modify store sequence
yes
it would wait yeah so it that's right
yeah I guess I wasn't clear it it
prevents it from being stored
permanently in a register right so it it
if it's it may have to be loaded into a
register but then it'll be written back
okay whereas the the compiler would have
the option like we've seen it with local
variables right the compiler just it
never allocates stack space it just
keeps that local variable in a register
all the time okay so this prevent the
volatile attribute prevents the compiler
from doing that okay so let's look at
another example
so here thread one starts it loads it
loads count into RDX then thread two
starts and it loads a count which is
still 0 into RDX 2 updates it and then
stores it so now count equal to 1 when
thread 1 resumes it updates its value of
count and RDX and stores that back to
count and so again we have we have the
same problem okay so the the problem
here is that we're interleaving these
these critical sections and you can
understand why this is bad with a nice
or graphical technique called a progress
graph
so in a progress graph if we have 4n
threads it's an N dimensional Cartesian
grid that characterizes the execution
state space of a concurrent threaded
program so in this case each here we
have two threads so it's a it's a it's a
it's a 2d coordinate system so each each
axis represents the progress the
execution progress of some threads so
the x axis here is thread 1 and the y
axis corresponds to thread 2 and then
each one of these edges corresponds to
the execution of an instruction ok so we
start out in an initial state and then
the first thing we execute is h1 so
that's represented by this this arc here
so this this position this point right
here represents the state where we've
executed H we finished executing h1 in
thread 1 but we haven't yet executed any
instructions in thread 2 ok so in
general each one of these points
represents sort of the current progress
of the program or the execution State so
for example this this state right here
represents the state where thread 1 has
completed a completed l1 and thread 2 is
completed s2
and now the execution of a program is
modeled as a transition from one state
to the other and there's some so from
from this and there's there's
constraints on how on how these these
states can advance so from this state l1
s to Y obviously time can't go backwards
right so we can't we can't go backwards
like in this direction to the left and
we can't go down okay so we can only go
to the right and up and since we're
assuming that each instruction executes
there's only one instruction executing
at a time we can't go diagonally that
would be two instructions all right so
from l1 s to the next execution state is
either here if thread one execute or
here if thread of thread to execute okay
so you can put all these together to
form a trajectory which characterizes
one execution of the program right and
any feasible set of transitions from one
state to the next
corresponds to a feasible trajectory so
so for example h 1 l 1 u 1 h 2 l 2 s 1 T
1 u 2 whoops
u 2 s 2 and T 2 that's a feasible that's
a feasible trajectory and it's one
possible it represents one possible
execution or so one set of interleavings
for this program
now these L these three these three
instructions l U and s that operate on
that manipulate count form what we call
a critical section with respect to count
and the idea is that instructions inside
these critical sections this with
receivership with respect to the same
global variable shouldn't be interleaved
so we can capture this geometrically by
taking the intersection of these
critical sections to form what we call
an unsafe region so in this an unsafe
region is is is the points within an
unsafe region are those those points in
an execution where the critical sections
are being or interleaved okay so for
this particular example there's four
points within the unsafe region and if a
trajectory ever touches one of those
points then we've interleaved critical
section and we're going to get the wrong
answer okay so the idea is to try to
stay out of these unsafe regions and if
we do we say that that trajectory is
safe so here's an example of a
trajectory that's safe now this is okay
right this point right here is not in
the unsafe region because we haven't
executed we only executed h1 here
remember a point corresponds to and it's
the instruction that we've completed
that instruction so then so here we're
skirting the unsafe region but it's
still okay so this is a safe trajectory
we'll get the right answer for this one
however this trajectory is unsafe
because it it enters the unsafe region
at this point here and even though it
quickly exited the there's an
interleaving there that creates a
potential for a correct answer
okay so the question is how do we
guarantee a safe trajectory and this is
the this is what we call synchronization
so somehow we want to we want to sort of
configure the kernel
so that'll never schedule an unsafe
trajectory so how do we do that
so somehow we we have to synchronize the
execution of those threads and another
way to think of this is that we we we
need to guarantee mutually exclusive
access to the critical sections all
right so once once the kernel begins
once the thread starts executing the
first instruction is critical section we
don't want it to be interrupted by
another thread that has a similar
critical section okay we don't want it
to be interrupted we don't want one one
critical section with respect to a
certain global variable to be
interrupted by another thread that has
all right that's currently within that
same critical section okay sorry
yes question seems unlikely for me that
it okay so the question is how likely is
it that you get a correct trajectory and
it happens right you can run it
sometimes you do it just depends usually
it's wrong sometimes it's right and it
just depends it just depends on how the
kernel scheduled it and you can't assume
any particular scheduling right so if
you say if you want to if you want to
claim that you would never get the right
answer then you're assuming that the
kernel is always going to schedule the
unsafe trajectory but you can't assume
that in fact it doesn't sometimes you
just get lucky
and it turns out you have to you have to
call this function with a pretty big
number in order to trip it up if so the
it makes sense right if usually what
what what the kernel does is that I we
can only schedule
we can only reschedule a thread you know
swap it out and schedule another thread
in when there's some exception okay so
that that passes control back to the
kernel so these exceptions are in two
forms either calling system making
system calls so that'll that'll trap
into the kernel so that's a form of
exception or the timer interrupts goes
off which transfers control back to the
back to the kernel so the timer the
timer is going off on intervals of like
milliseconds right so if we're just
doing one iteration it in each thread
when a thread gets executed the chances
are very low that the timer is going to
go off while that thread is executing
you know it's its little loop but as we
and we're not making any system calls
right so there's there's nothing that
will there's nothing we're not we're not
passing control back into the kernel
ourselves so the only way the kernel is
going to get access is if the timer
interrupts goes off so if we're doing a
very small number of iterations the the
probability that you know say here's the
timer interval it's going off at
intervals like this here this the the
probability we'd have to that's thread
would have to been scheduled right
before a timer interrupts will go off or
to interrupt that one or two iterations
so it turns out we have to schedule we
have to call this function with a lot of
within ITER's being fairly large so that
the the probability of the timer
interrupts going off during that during
that during that loop but gets
increasingly large that makes sense
so the classic solution from this comes
from the early 1960s one of the most
famous computer scientists is a Dutchman
named as edgeguard Edsger Dijkstra and
he came up with the the classical first
solution to this problem which is what
we're going to look at okay and it's
it's it's still the first it's it's
fundamental and very general purpose and
there's there's been many iterations and
variations on this idea but semaphores
were the first and classic solution
which we'll look at
okay so a semaphore is that is a non-
global integer that's used as a
synchronization variable by two to
kernel functions called P and V our two
system calls called P and V these P and
V are correspond to the Dutch words but
we just you just we just call them P and
V right you just have to learn what what
they do so each of these takes as an
argument a semaphore and the P operation
has the following semantics if if s is
non zero then decrement it by 1 and
return immediately and this test if it
that it's non zero and the decrement
occur atomically okay so so they'll
never be interrupted
however if s is zero then suspend this
thread until s becomes non zero and that
thread then is restarted by a V
operation okay so if if P if the
semaphore is zero P just blocks it just
gets suspended until it gets restarted
by a V operation and then after it
restarts the P operation now can
decrement s by one and return control to
the caller
okay the V operation just increments s
by one and this increment unlike that
count plus plus that we looked at just
looked at this that increment occurs
atomically okay so it can never be
interrupted and then after it increments
s it checks to see if there's any any
threads that are blocked in a pea
operation so you can think of the kernel
just keeps a queue of threads that are
blocked in a pea operation and the V
operation after it increments s it
checks that queue for any any threads
that were blocked because when they did
the pea operation the semaphore was zero
and then it restarts exactly one of
those threads in some indeterminate
order okay in some order that you can't
you can't assume it just picks one using
some some selection algorithm and it and
then it it it unblocks the suspended the
suspended process okay which then
completes its pea operation by
decrementing yes
okay this seems like really simple but
it can be kind of hard to get your head
around the first time you see it so are
there any questions about P and V
okay so that the key idea that these
definitions of P and V is that it
imposes an invariant on the semaphores
called the semaphore invariant which is
s which is that for a semaphore s being
operated on by P and V operations S is
always greater than or equal to zero
okay and that doesn't seem very exciting
but it turns out this is a very useful
property that will allow us to enforce
mutual mutual exclusion on these
critical sections so the P and V
operations are are provided by P threads
in the form of three functions there's a
Semin it functions which initializes the
semaphore to some value
okay so semaphore is can be initialized
to any any value greater than or equal
to zero some weight is the P operation
and some post is the V operation okay
and because I'm old-school I provide
wrapper functions for those in the in
your si si PP dot H file called P and V
okay it's also more compact to
okay so recall our recall our buggy
program called bad count dot C which was
giving us the wrong answers for count so
how do we use semaphores to fix this
program so the basic idea is to create a
semaphore which is initialized to 1 and
so by definition we'll call any
semaphore which is initialized to 1
that's used for to provide mutual
exclusion we'll call that a mutex okay
and this goes back to the early Dijkstra
papers so we'll associate a unique mutex
initialize to 1 for each shared variable
in our program ok so in this case count
we have count so we have one shared
variable that we're concerned about so
we'll we'll create one new text that
will call mutex and then you surround
the critical section with respect to
count with a p/e you call P then you
execute the critical section and then
you call V
now there's some there's some
terminology we'll use when we talk about
semaphores so a binary semaphore is is
the semaphore whose value is always 0 1
and then a mutex is this sort is a
binary semaphore that's being used to
for mutual exclusion the P operation is
called locking the mutex will refer to a
V is sometimes unlocking or releasing
the mutex and if a process is holding
the mutex then that means it's been
locked but not not not released so
mutexes and binary semaphore s are
always initialized to 1
accounting semaphore and the mutex is
used for mutual excuse exclusion but you
can also use semaphores to count sort of
events in the system and often times for
those accounting semaphores have sort of
non non values that are greater than 1
okay so for mutual exclusion we'll to
fix our program we create a new program
called good count dot c and here we
initialize a mutex or we create a mutex
and initialize it to 1 and then we
surround the the critical section which
is the 3 assembly language instructions
embodied that implement this count plus
plus instruction we surround it with a P
followed by it by a V and if we do that
we always get the right answer
but you know P&V our system calls so
there's overhead associated with these
so they're not free in fact they're
orders of magnitude this program runs
two orders of magnitude slower than the
incorrect buggy version all right so so
why do these mutexes work so here we've
got a progress graph now where we've
we've decorated our program with P and V
operations so we put the P before the
critical section we execute the critical
section and then we call V and now if
you were to look you remember P and V P
increments the sum of P decrement the
semaphore V increments of samba4
so if you were just to look at the value
of that semaphore for every point in the
execution state space you'd get these
you'd get these values so here we
initialize the semaphore at the origin
we initialized it to 1 so the the value
of of our semaphore at the origin is 1
and let's say we just move along so
we're just executing thread 1 so after H
1 the semaphore is 1 we do the P the
semaphore is 1 so P just decrement sit
and it proceeds so now the semaphore
value becomes 0 and it remains zero
until we execute the V and when we
finished executing the V the semaphore
now is is 1 again okay so if we go
through a similar reasoning if we look
at the trajectory to get to any point in
this state space so let's say let's say
this point right here so to get there we
could we could execute thread 1 up to
this point finish the L 1 and then
execute h 2 and then do the at this
point the semaphore is 0
and then P decrements the semaphore so
now it's minus one but that's that's
impossible
that can't happen because P plus
remember if if the semaphore is 0 P
blocks it doesn't decrement it okay so
the semantics of the P operation
prohibits this this this transition it
prohibits this transition to the state
where the semaphore is zero to a state
where it would be minus one and so it
creates it creates what we call a
forbidden region so these these points
in the state space where the the
semaphore would have a value of minus 1
are are infeasible that can never be
reached by the definition of of P and V
ok so this this forms a forbidden region
around the unsafe region and in doing so
provides mutually exclusive access to
the to the critical sections in each
thread okay so if so this this is the
fundamental reason why P's and Vees can
be used to provide mutually exclusive
access
so many questions on this I explained it
so clearly that there's no questions
all right good well you get to go you
get to get to leave early then work on
your Mallik lab so all right so we'll
see you Monday we're going to look at
sort of some advanced topics this was
like her first introduction to
synchronization on Tuesday we'll look at
more advanced topics in synchronization
in ways ways that you can use semaphores
for to provide other other more
interests other interesting kinds of
synchronization for your programs okay