good afternoon everyone so today we're
going to transition into a topic that to
me is sort of the reward for having
slugged through all the low-level stuff
you've done up to this point to be able
to really understand and become adept at
programming network software not there's
a lot to networking that we're not going
to cover but at least to have some
familiarity with it so I know that a lot
of you are sort of in the midst of
trying to figure out how to make Melek
run and make it run fast and so this
this uh topic is really more pointing
toward the future but it's very relevant
to the final web you'll do for the
course and so we're starting to to get
ready for that
so like I said this course is not really
a full course in networking there's many
other courses at the university that are
and so what we're going to try and do is
give you just a little flavor of it and
particularly as everything in the course
of programmers perspective so how you as
a software developer would make use of
the c-level api's that are relevant to
network programming and why isn't this
working
okay so the idea behind most networking
systems is what's called the
client-server model and the idea is that
there's a service out there that you
want access to and you as a customer or
a client are making a request to that
server so an example would be when you
order something on Amazon Amazon has a
bunch of servers and you go to your web
browser and canta it contacts the Amazon
a web server and you make transactions
you request something you provide
information and it gives you back pretty
pictures of things you might want to buy
it acknowledges your credit card
transactions those are all very classic
client-server types of interactions you
as the client Amazon is the server
another interesting example is a
telephone so if you think about it a
telephone is both a client and a server
in that when I'm making a placing a call
to somebody else I'm the client and that
person's phone is the server right it's
sitting there waiting for calls to come
in and when that call comes in it makes
a connection we talk over the phone and
then I hang up either side hangs up so
there's a lot of instances out there of
of some variation of client and server
and it's a much richer idea in that you
can often switch back and forth the
roles of those two parties but it's a
pretty universal and a ubiquitous way of
thinking about how to set up a network
system so in general then the idea is
that there's a system working the client
is making some requests to the server
the server does something locally to
deal with it it receive it gets
information that retrieves from its
database the things you might want to
buy and then it sends back information
say a nicely formatted a web page with
all
kinds of shopping suggestions and then
the client decides what to do next so
from a hardware perspective the
interface to a between the network and
your computer is called the NIC or
network interface card even though it's
not always on a card and we really won't
talk about hardware at all but what's
most interesting from it is that it
looks to your computer like an i/o
device and in fact the UNIX of API for
dealing with networks makes it look like
a file so in particular just as a disc
sits off of a bus and you write data to
a disk or you read it from a disk
similarly the network sits off of a
similar bus and when you want to send a
message you actually do it by writing to
a sort of virtual file that's called the
network and if you want when you're
receiving data you do it by reading and
so just as several weeks ago I gave the
lecture on Io
it turns out that it's extremely
relevant to network programming and
that's the basic model that that was
created by the early developers of the
sort of standard UNIX and now that's
carried over not just to UNIX but it's
the same model for Windows and other
operating systems so and now let's just
talk a little about what computer
networking means the idea of a network
is it's a collection of systems that are
referred to as hosts that are able to
communicate with each other over some
kind of communication fabric let's call
it communications system and they're
sort of partitioned into mostly referred
to as lands or local area networks that
you establish within a small region and
then a wide area network which would be
over
or something the size of a city or
perhaps more and over a enterprise such
as CMU it's a very complex set of for
example there's wireless base stations
that right in this room that you're
interacting with when you're using a
wireless system or your your phone and
then there's a whole networking
infrastructure within the university the
then goes to some commercial providers
AT&T in particular that give it access
to the the commercial Internet and then
there's another set of network
connections hosted by the supercomputing
Center that give you access to what's
called Internet 2 which is the resource
that's used for communicating among
universities so underneath you know when
you're doing your networking stuff
there's this amazingly complex
combination of things going on the idea
of an internet is supposed is refers to
the idea the general idea of a network
of networks taking for example the local
area network that this base station
provides and connecting it up to other
networks on campus and across the world
and when we refer to the capital I
internet that refers to the one instance
the the most significant instance of an
Internet
so lowercase I means the sort of general
idea of creating a network of networks
uppercase I is the specific example that
we all know and use all the time
that's organized by a certain set of
principles that uses a particular set of
protocols and so forth and of course we
tend to just talk the internet and most
people know that what that really
implies is the sort of existing network
structure that there is and that's good
enough for the purpose of this course
we're not going to talk much about other
possible designs one might have for a
network so most of the low level
networking is supported by something
called Ethernet and the term Ethernet
actually has evolved tremendously over
time
so that it's almost more like a brand
name that it is in specific technology
and the version you're familiar with the
wired version of it you have a wire to
some sort of a box like that you plug
the your ethernet jacks into and
historically those were called hubs and
the idea of a hub was it was just a
repeater that whatever came into it from
one computer it would broadcast to all
the connected machines and so you only
want to do this for maybe a a dozen or
so machines that it's like a party-line
they're all hearing what everybody else
is saying and in fact the original first
version the ethernet did that by
everyone interacting over a single cable
carrying essentially radio signals and
similarly when you're in this room using
a wireless internet a wireless internet
is sort of like a hub and that all the
packets that you're sending all across
the room they're all sort of making use
of the same radio frequencies the same
communication channel and there's a
protocol for how they detect when two
messages get set at the same time and
therefore interfere with each other so
that can only sort of scale up to maybe
at most a hundred different hosts
communicating because they're all
sharing a single communication channel
now in the wired world what's evolved is
usually when you buy a box or you get
one from your cable company with all
those ports in it it's actually called a
router or sometimes a switch in that it
it doesn't broadcast to everyone it it
selectively tries to guess is this
particular message bound for this
particular host and only send to that
one and as you know you can take these
and wire up I think about up to six
levels deep in and hops and basically
create a network
of wired connections and they'll all get
from one to the other somehow and then
after that it gets more complicated you
can add more sophisticated types of
switching on top of it
but so the general idea of even an
Ethernet is actually a fairly complex
thing but it's some sort of conceptual
level we can just think of it as a bunch
of hosts that can talk directly to one
another and then an internet then refers
to the idea of taking those local area
networks and connecting them together
via routers and routers obey a
particular protocol based on the address
that you're trying to send data to and
and so what you end up with conceptually
is a whole bunch of hosts spread
potentially all across the world and
then some magical system of routers that
will get a message from one place to the
other based on a mode of addressing
where there's some known address of the
hosts that you're trying to send to and
it will hop through multiple routers to
get from one place to the other and
that's true whether it's on campus
or whether it's hopping all the way
around the world
and so again there's this huge body of
information and knowledge about how that
routing works and how its reliable and
all that but we're going to just assume
that somebody else has figured that out
and our job as programmers is just to be
able to communicate from one host to
another
and so how could you design a system
where all these diverse systems made by
computers made by different
manufacturers operating under different
countries with different
telecommunications bodies governing
bodies and so forth how can they all
work with each other and the requirement
is you have to have a protocol you have
to have some common set of conventions
for what messages look like how they get
sent what happens if one of them doesn't
make it how do you recover from that and
so forth and so what does a protocol
include well it has to include some way
of naming things so that if I want to
send to some host I have some way of
designating who that host is and then
there's the routing system has to have
some reliable way of getting my data to
that named host and that's the delivery
mechanism and that's usually done and
one of the things that we now accept as
as universal but it really wasn't when
it first came out was idea of you take
all your data and you divide it into
packets and packets are typically about
a thousand to two thousand bytes and so
if you have a longer message it chops it
up into individual packets and sends it
across and all the communication occurs
at the packet level that's different
than the historic phone system I was a
connection based system meaning that if
I was calling somebody there is a
dedicated wire set of wires maintained
by the phone company that would be
reserved and locked down for our own use
during the entire duration of that phone
call
so to get them from one host say a to B
what happens is we want to send a packet
and that packet will contain some amount
of data and the idea of a packet
communication then is you put little
headers on that contain certain routing
information the equivalent of what you'd
see on the front of an envelope of a
letter perhaps and so and at different
points in the way they'll have different
numbers of headers and different
protocols or formats for what those
headers look like so in particular
within I want to send a message and I'll
I'll do that and then the software that
runs on my machine that handles this
will put a header in front of that that
describes the internet routing and then
it will tack a header in front of that
that talks about the local area network
routing that gets used and that's what's
referred to as the a P hat H the packet
header for the Internet Protocol and f
h1 the frame header for this particular
message being sent within this local
network and then the network interface
card or the adapter here is then
responsible for putting that out over
this local communication of capability
and then that gets received at the other
end by the network adapter at the
receivers direction it will put up its
own frame header on it to pass it in and
that then gets tripped off so that all
hosts be set sees is the the data that
gets sent but this idea of putting
headers in front and at times sort of
what they call encapsulation that I'll
take this big packet and I'll just tack
some more information on top to the
front of it
header information and I'll send through
the rest of it just as a set of bytes
so the internet that we know and love
the capital I internet then has a
particular set of protocols that are
you've probably heard the terms one is
called the IP the Internet Protocol
which is the one that defines ideas
about how do you get how do you name
hosts on the Internet and how do you
send packets and they're referred to
sometimes is datagrams meaning that a
packet is just a single entity that gets
sent from point A to point B and the
underlying IP doesn't guarantee delivery
so it's based on what they call best
effort communication meaning that at
each step along the way
if for example things are good then it
will just send this packet along if
there's too much congestion there's been
a you know somebody's turned on their
microwave oven and it's set up some
radiofrequency interface interference
then at the IP level it just drops that
packet and says whoops I screwed up
sorry it doesn't even say sorry it just
does it silently
and then you can as a programmer make
use of that very global level so
normally as a programmer you don't
really want to program at that level
because you'll send packets and they
will get there but you can if you want
to and it's called UDP a protocol it's
just a small software layer over IP and
there's some applications that you'll
see for example in the computer game
world where you want to send information
really fast and if some information gets
dropped it's not a big deal that people
actually program at that level we won't
really talk about that the more common
protocol that gets used and carries 99%
of Internet traffic is what's called TCP
or transmission control protocol and
that provides a reliable the equivalent
of telephone connection that I can
reliably send data from point A to point
B as many bytes as I like it's a
guaranteed
every it's sometimes fast and sometimes
not but it's there and it's built on top
of the IPO of this datagram meaning that
it has to take whatever you're sending
and slice it up into these single
packets if one of them doesn't get sent
it will resend it until it gets there
they have to deal with the fact that
packets can travel different paths and
one can get ahead of the other in
transmission and so it has to reorder
them in the correct sequence and so
there's a lot of stuff under it but
we'll just assume that it kind of works
and so you can just rely think about it
is I have a stream connection I can send
from A to B and B can send a stream of
data back to me and we're all happy and
so that's the version that looks like
file IO I just keep writing to a file
and it's sending packets over the
network to the other end and then the
other side can be sending stuff to me
and I'm just reading it and I'm just
reading bytes of data not worrying about
how that got broken up into individual
packets and so that's referred to as the
sockets interface and you'll hear the
term socket programming and that's
exactly what we're talking about
and so from a sort of software system
than software hardware system then the
client and the server are both
implemented as application programs at
the respective endpoints on their hosts
and they make use of of software and
libraries that run at some combination
of the user level and at the kernel
level and therefore I have access to
direct resources and so I is a program
or an application programmer then make
use of this software API that lets me do
socket programming and it's based on
gives directly supports tcp/ip
so first of all we're going to talk most
of the time about what's called ipv4 a
version 4 which is the one that's been
running for since the 1980s I think
early 1980s and is this the standard and
we'll talk very only mentioned very
briefly the idea of what's called ipv6
which is sort of a next-generation
version so the idea of a ipv4 and this
is now we're talking about IP and and
this is true of TCP as well is that an
address is actually just 32 bits but
it's usually expressed in what they call
dotted decimal form and you've seen
these addresses before that it's four
decimal numbers and they can only range
between 0 and 255 because each one of
them is a single bytes worth of
information so we're used to writing
things in hex now in this course but
we're going to write it as each byte is
written as a decimal digit and they're
actually passed and stored in what's
called network byte order which is big
endian byte order and so we have to
worry about the whole big endian vs.
Goodell Indian thing when we're doing
network programming and you can actually
learn a lot there's a whole levels of
how the different bytes mean but for
example any IP address it starts with
128 dot 2 is at CMU I think and then and
so essentially CMU owns that part of the
IP address space which if you think
about that's approximately 2 to the 64th
2 to the
no not to the 64th - to the sixteenth
different IP addresses available for use
by campus alma and as i mentioned
there's a newer version called ipv6 that
gives you a 128-bit addresses you can
imagine actually that if you think about
how many nodes are there in the Internet
if a four byte address is only to the 32
so that's four billion and I don't know
about you but I have a lot of different
things that use IP I have a phone I have
two laptops I have a couple desktops so
if all if every one of us used multiple
IP addresses then actually the world
would be out of them right there's seven
billion people in the world not all of
whom have access to the Internet but a
large fraction of them do and so there's
a whole kind of crazy way of dealing
with the the multitude of possible IP
addresses so the obvious thing would be
well let's just allocate a lot more
addresses and jump let's just skip 64
bits and go right to 128 and that's the
idea behind ipv6 but quite honestly this
has been one of those technologies
that's been out there for over 15 years
and still has a very low level of
adoption so it's it's still a future
technology people have basically figured
out all these crazy schemes to make use
of of just stick within the four byte
limit um
okay so let's start talking the program
the sort of programmer perspective on
this and this is one area where you'll
wish you weren't programming in C but
you are so there's a lot of really
crufty stuff and it was all developed
most of the software protocols were
conceived before C even was what it is
today
so like the Kernighan and Ritchie book
you have is called the second edition
and it's based on what was called ANSI C
or ISO C but these all date before that
they date back to the original Kernighan
and Ritchie so for example void star did
not exist in that era and so you use
care star as a generic pointer and so
there's just a lot of stuff in this
programming interface where you go wow
that is really crufty and that that
truth is yes you're right so in
particular there's a lot of different
structures that are defined and one of
them is called an in adder which means
internet address and it's just defined
to be a 32-bit unsigned number and in
general as I mentioned there the so
called network byte order whoever
designed the original protocols was a
fan of big endian addressing and so
that's what it is even though actually
most of the machines that are out there
in this world are little endian and so
there's a set of standard library
functions that you use to convert
between network order and host order and
the idea of it is now if I run my
software on a little Indian or a big
endian machine these functions will do
the right thing so if I just use these
standard libraries then I don't have to
worry about porting it every time I
change the word ordering of a machine
one of the things you'll notice here is
there is no function to convert 64-bit
data between a network order and host
order so I don't know what people do
when I do it I just write my own saw my
own
to do it or I don't because I know my
other end is a little endian machine
so anyways these are already some
functions you'll start seeing for that
look like network conversion software
[Music]
and as I mentioned the addresses are
written in a dotted decimal form and
it's also big endian so if I were to
write in hex 128 is of course 8 0 so
that's the most significant byte of the
IP address and then there is a set of
functions API calls you can use to
convert between this dotted decimal
format and the actual just a 32-bit
unsigned int and actually it used to be
there is you might see some older
presentations where they use different
names for this but the most recent
version API calls this the the
presentation version the dotted decimal
they referred to it as a presentation
then you can look up the and it's in the
book to what the the calls to these look
like but you probably don't or very
seldom when you're thinking about I want
to go to Google you don't think about
what its IP address is you just go to
WGAL calm and for everything you do you
refer to it by this I it would have
referred called Internet domain names
which is a hierarchical naming system
whereas you know there's dot e-d-u is
for educational institutions dot-com is
for commercial net is general networking
of many countries have their own suffix
so you know dot de is for Germany and so
forth and so those are called the first
level domain names and then there's a
hierarchical naming structure under that
and up
there's actually an interesting question
of okay how do I then map from those
hierarchical names those domain names
into this dotted decimal or the 32 bit
IP address and the job of that is by a
very large distributed system called the
DNS the domain name system where the
only sort of centrally managed part of
it is at the top level so for each of
these first level domain names there's
there's a collection a very large
collection of machines that keep track
of all the all the IP addresses that map
to one of those first level domain names
and then for example CMU maintains its
own naming Authority so anything that
says something dot CMU edu there's local
DNS servers within CMU that are picking
apart ok where should you know if I say
CS CMU edu what would be the the IP
address for that well and it's actually
pretty interesting how this is managed
because it's all it's totally
decentralized there's a whole set of
protocols that govern how naming is done
but conceptually we can think of it as
just this big database that gives me a
mapping where I can give a domain name
and it will get back to me a one or more
IP addresses I can give an IP address
and it will come back with one or more
domain names
oh and so there's actually an
application you can run on most machines
called nslookup and there's another one
called dig that you can use to find
basically probe the DNS and find in
either direction you can look at the
given a domain name you can find its IP
address given an IP address you can find
its domain name and we also I'll show
you some code that just as an example of
how you do the programming I'll just
show that momentarily called hostname so
just some examples
you know if I look up some address like
the the website for the computer science
school computer science using nslookup
it comes back can people see this okay
doing it bigger it's okay so this is
what NSF looks like and this stuff here
just tells you you know who where was
the actual directory entry in the which
DNS server actually gave this
information back and it says that WCS
CMU is actually a synonym for a weirder
one called w web - l-bfgs CMU dot edu
and its IP address is 128 - like you'd
expect
- 1713 and of course that works not just
at CMU but I can you know go ask about
what Stanford is up to and it will come
back and its IP addresses of something
170 1.64 and that's been managed by that
and you'll see again it's I asked for
WCS stanford.edu it said well the real
name of that is CS dot stanford.edu and
this actually is a point that the the
mapping between domain names and
internet addresses is not one-to-one you
can have multiple domain names that
refer to the same Internet address but
you can also have multiple internet
addresses
excuse me
that's weird
so like twitter.com when I ask for it it
comes back with four different addresses
and if I do the exact same thing again
mmm Kim but yeah you see it came back
with the same no not even the same
addresses it came back for example here
the one that ends with dot six that
wasn't in that first was so it came back
with a slightly different set of
addresses and a somewhat different order
and the idea of that is that actually
has multiple servers so when I send to
twitter.com or Google or any of these
major servers there's not just one place
in the internet that's handling
everybody's Google traffic through
thousands of places spread around the
world
and the way they get you there is by
playing tricks with the DNS that Google
is constantly sending updates to the it
maintains its own DNS servers so it's
constantly changing them and it will
actually give you different addresses
depending on where in the world you're
located as well to try and provide a
server that's sort of reasonably close
to you geographically so there's all
just all kinds of tricks that happen
through DNS that is part of the way they
can sort of manage this huge set of
addresses
and then there's some other domain names
that don't have any IP address that
they're somewhere in the hierarchy that
hierarchical naming system but they're
not actually referring to a particular
host so it's a Multi multi mapping in
the the API city reflects it
so this is just going what I told you
they sometimes one-to-one sometimes many
domain names refer to the same address
sometimes of one name maps to multiple
addresses that change over time and then
there's some where it's a valid name but
it doesn't have an IP address it doesn't
have a host associated with a question
for example let's say I create my own
servers how does that generate it oh how
do I get how do you get your own IP
address well all you have to beg borrow
or you have to either borrow or buy them
so for example at CMU there is some
number of what they call statically
allocated IP addresses where it's just
fixed assigned to that machine and you
can register form and request them
through computing services but most you
don't have that most you get one that's
I signed dynamically so there's a pool
of addresses that you basically they
call them leasing that you are assigned
with for a while and then but it could
possibly be reassigned to someone else
and that's part of the way it can manage
you know somewhat limited set of IP
addresses
so the idea of like I said that the main
a way we'll think about it is in terms
of what's called TCP and it says
connection oriented protocol where I
establish a connection from one one host
establishes a connection to another host
and they they can communicate to each
other sending arbitrarily long streams
of bytes to each other and so the
connection is then two hosts that can
talk to each other and each of those
endpoints is referred to as a socket and
so I can and a socket is both an IP
address and what's called a port number
so there's a 16 by 16 bit number for
every connection that's referred to as
its port and the reason for that is just
because I'm talking to a particular
machine that that machine can support
different services it can provide SSH
connections it can provide FTP
connections it can host a mail server it
can host a web server so a particular
machine might have a multitude of
different services and so those are
differentiated from each other with what
are called port numbers and similarly
Isaac client might have connections to
dozens of hosts going at any given time
I'm cruising the web I'm you know doing
all that different stuff and that's all
differentiated the client end that
there's different ports associated with
your different programs that are running
and so a port then is a 16-bit integer
that identifies which particular
endpoint is being communicated with it
either the client side of the server
side and typically at the client side
these are assigned dynamically and the
referred to as ephemeral ports meaning
they only are assigned for the limited
duration that you have a connection with
that that you're maintaining that
connection and then
there has to be some way if I'm going to
contact and I want to know the DNS will
tell me what the IP address is of say
google.com but I have to know that
am i communicating with its web service
which is port 80 or HTTP secure socket
is a different report number so which
service I'm asking for and there's a
standard list what are called well-known
ports that are that I can contact at the
server end to get the particular service
I'm looking for and those are assigned
there's a big waste of port assignments
and so the again that's part of the sort
of a whole set of internet standards is
the the identifiers for the different
ports what services those are and how
those particular protocols work
so when I have a connection then as I
mentioned I'll think of it as a
connection then is as a link between two
machines based on some known port
typically at the server end and a
dynamically assigned or ephemeral port
assigned at the client in and I can
refer to then that connection then is
identified by the combination of the
hosts at the two ends and the ports that
they're using
and in general then it's the job of the
colonel to differentiate the different
connections that are coming into a
machine and figure out which software
which process to wake up when a data you
know when some data arrives from another
machine in which actual program running
on that machine will make use of that
data and that's done by associating for
each of the ports a particular process
executing program that's going to handle
those particular requests and it's
totally possible for a client to be
interacting with a single server over
different ports but those are considered
to be different connections and and so
they don't really interfere with each
other
so that's what I mentioned is this is
what we refer to as sockets programming
or the sockets interface it was
developed sort of as the internet was
evolving in the late 70s and early 80s
so socket then as I said is certain
logically one end one of the two ends of
a connection and from an application
point of view you'll see it as a file
descriptor just the low-level file stuff
that you've already seen that you can do
reading and writing from um and and so
that that's the sort of mental model
that is provided by the socket interface
but it's a very different you know the
actual implementation of network when
you write to a socket it's firing up all
kinds of network stuff whereas you write
to a disk it's operating a disk
controller so at the hardware level and
even at the lower levels of software
they're very different beasts but you as
an application programmer see some
commonality there
okay so let's jump right into the API
and again this is a place where you
you'll wish you were programming in a
language that had a type hierarchy but
you aren't you're programming in C so
there's a type there's a zillion
Struck's that you kind of have to get
familiar with but one's called a sock
adder and basically it's just a 16 bytes
worth of stuff where the the only thing
that's special here is that the leading
two bytes a designate what type of
socket this is and particularly be
different whether it's a TCP socket an
ipv6 socket a UDP socket and all those
will have different numbers a different
constant in there that tells you which
type of socket it is and then the high
level the sockets in a lot of the
programs don't need to know you know
which type of connection this is they
can just deal with they basically call
other software to deal with that
so that's why it's referred to as being
families specific and then the socket
stuff isn't even necessarily referred to
the internet the capital I internet and
so there's a more specific one called a
socket or underscore in that is used for
ipv4 sockets
well not ipv6 and so in particular it
fills in fields one is called the port
which as I mentioned is 16 bits and then
the IP address the four byte IP address
both of which are in even if you're
running the software on a x86 machine
these should be in big endian order up
and you'll see that this is what I mean
that this is sort of a C's version of
subtyping if you know something like C++
or Java or you know a language with type
inheritance that you can think of it as
a sock adder in a sort of a subclass of
a sock adder right it has more
information it's compatible with but has
more information than a socket and then
there's another type of for ipv6 has a
different kind of struck that they fill
in for its information and then they
they Pat it out with eight bytes of
zeros just because this particular
protocol doesn't require the full 16
bytes okay so this is sort of what it
looks like to operate a full-blown
client-server system from a programmers
perspective and we're going to for the
rest of today and all of Thursday go
through all these steps and you as a
programmer are actually going to have to
understand each of these steps what they
do what they mean and how to use them
the good news is there's some pretty
standard patterns here and so you can
often grab some existing code say out of
the book to use that will make this not
as painful as it might look so but the
overall idea of this this picture then
is sorry kick it used to fit my remote
doesn't work on the the right hand side
refers to the steps that the server has
to go through and the left hand side is
what the client does so the upper right
is what it takes to set up a server that
is then a program that's running there
ready to receive connections from a
client and perform various services and
so obviously before the client can do
anything the server has to exist so that
has to be the first step in setting
things up and then we have to we'll fire
up a cert a client that will make use of
this service and then there'll be what's
referred to as a session meaning a kind
of back and forth communication between
the client and server doing whatever
they're going to do this is not specific
to any particular application and like I
said it will involve you'll see Rio
underscore remember those who are
reliable i/o functions we talked about
as part of the UNIX i/o so it's a way to
read and write in a room and and handle
some of the quirks of low-level i/o but
basically this is sending and receiving
messages over the Internet
and then once that's done typically then
the client will close its connection
sort of equivalent of hanging up its
phone and say ok I'm done and then
sometime later or maybe never depending
on what kind of web you know service
this is if the the server wants to shut
down it has its own a collection of
calls that it makes to stop that service
so anyways just to kind of give you the
landscape of what this picture means
so we're going to sort of jump into the
middle this the top level up and we'll
focus actually which will we focus on
well we'll talk to some level in
parallel because there's a lot of
commonality as you can see between what
goes on with the server and what goes on
with the client yeah and so actually the
top level call this one called get adder
info is the way that it sort of initiate
things and actually does the the lookup
to map from a domain name to a IP
address so we'll cover that later
so the first step in on either side then
and creating a connection is a call to a
function called socket and the reason I
wanted to Blackboard was to help you
keep track of this
so the first call is a doesn't do much
oh and that's why the the function call
is socket but the it only happens within
the application it doesn't make a use of
any part of the operating system doesn't
send anything over the network and the
idea is to basically say hey I want to
create a socket and it's given three
arguments the first two which is AF
underscore I net all these upper case on
names are constants that are built in or
included in the various uh dot H files
that you include in writing this code
and AF underscore I nut just means it's
a I P V four so 32-bit addresses and
then the second parameter is says you
want a sock stream and that refers to a
TCP connection it's referred to as a
stream connection because like I said
you get to send as many bytes as you
like a stream of bytes to in either
direction and then
zero protocol well I guess it must not
be very interesting because I set it to
zero so we don't need to do anything in
this particular case there are man pages
on this by the way which if you just
tried to learn all sockets programming
by reading men pages you'd go crazy but
once you kind of have the idea of it the
man pages are pretty useful and then the
next part you'll see we're looking only
now on the server side is called bind
and
what bind does then is that specific
then to a server and now this is a make
this interfaces to the kernel it says I
want to
designate which IP address and let me
just so I'm going to cheat a little bit
by making sure I don't say anything
that's not true
yeah I'm right sorry I just want to make
sure bind actually tells you oh excuse
me you'll see that a socket the call to
socket returns an int but it's what it's
returning is a file descriptor remember
we said that if you refer to a file a
low-level file just by an integer ID
typically a small integer value there's
some standard ones for standard in
standard out standard error and then
beyond that they're just assigned
incrementally so socket will return a
number that you then refer used to refer
to this as a file so bind then you've
pass in that the name of your socket
file descriptor and you provide a
whether is a socket adder ends
ah and si I'm using the the notation si
as a shortcut for sock adder struct sock
header and then you have to also say
what the length of the address is so in
the case of ipv4 that would be four but
you don't usually use that number
directly there's a we'll talk about it
but that top-level call called gedit or
adder info as a relatively new API that
was created and is in this addition to
the book but not in previous ones is
that become the now the standard way
that you get all the parameters that
you're supposed to pass into all these
different calls and the idea of it then
is it's a pretty small adjustment to
then write code that's good for either
ipv4 or ipv6 so you don't normally give
the actual number from that you get it
from another place and passage it
so binding then is it's a kernel call
that designates which particular service
this program is going to be hosting but
which will be the server for and that's
given by its port number
and then the next step is to to listen
and that's just a call that says
ah that will now convert this socket to
a listening socket which you need as a
server so it's a way of telling the
kernel that this will be it will be a
server SAR so obviously bind and listen
are related ideas but you have to do
both steps and in that particular order
to create a listening socket or one for
a server and then the final part of that
to operate us is to say except
and
oh that means okay now we've established
this now I'm actually ready to receive
phone calls is essentially what it says
is this is the final step to say okay
this one's ready to accept connection
requests it has a similar set of
arguments to sock it is sock it but
slight difference and now the
interesting thing is acceptable return
yet another file descriptor I'll so the
first file descriptor is the sort of
generic accept and base basically except
we'll just hang there and wait until
some client makes a connection and when
it does then it will set up a new socket
and a new with a new file descriptor
that then the server communicates to the
client via that one and I'll talk about
why it's a different file descriptor in
just a second okay over on the client
side goes through similar steps of
socket but it doesn't have to bind or
listen or accept because this is a
client and instead what it does is it it
makes a call to connect
so let me finish this off so these are
all on this the server side and on the
client side it will make a call to
connect and that's its job of that is
from a client side is to set up a
connection to server
and so
it's arguments it's a little easier to
understand how kynect works so in
particular the call to socket that was
made beforehand returns a file
descriptor and what this says is I want
to on that particular using that
particular socket connect to this gives
a combination of an address and a port
number and it has to give this address
length which I said like I said as
before it's usually that number is
filled in using the return value of of
get adder info but that's sort of the
equivalent of poisoning the Coleman and
it returns just a code which is whether
the connection was successful or not
so let me just talk about these
different ports and what it all means
when you setup a connection so when the
the server went through bind and listen
it created a listening port from that
which is the one that it's listening for
connection requests on and then the
client when it called socket it was
given a particular file descriptor for
that that socket and it sends out a
connection request that goes out over
the network and lands at the server and
then the kernel hands that off to the
the the program that's running on that
particular port and hands it off to the
that call will be handled by the accept
call to accept by the server and then as
I mentioned except actually returns a
new file descriptor which the server
will then use as its connection point to
this particular client and the theory of
that is you want to be able to in
general as a server be handling multiple
clients at the same
time but if I'm communicating with with
Google or Amazon you should be able to
do so at the same time so you want a
possibility of from a single host to be
able to serve multiple clients and
that's why they're all assigned
different file descriptors at the server
end for that particular connection so
you can think of it as the listening
file descriptor is just listening for
incoming requests for connections but
once it sets up a session and
communicates back and forth those are
going through different ports on the
server side of things or different file
descriptors I'm sorry same port
different file descriptors from the
software that's running on the server
okay and then during the actual
communication then as I mentioned it
uses reads and writes as a way to send
and receive messages and that goes on
for as long as you know and according to
whatever lo-ove particular protocol is
being supported by this application and
then in the end then when the client the
client is done it causes a request and
what that looks like from the server end
is it tries to read from a file and it
receives an end of file a signal instead
and that tells the server okay this
particular connection is is gone and so
now it will close that particular one as
this picture shows here potentially the
server could loop back around and accept
a connection from another program and in
fact this can be done this is what we
call a serial or a knitter aware it can
only manage one connection request at a
time and when we get later in the course
and we stock talk about multi-threading
we'll be able to set it up so this thing
can start accepting requests for another
connection even while it's handling one
particular client but anyways what it
will look like is the server will read
the attempt to read that we'll get an
end of file it will close that
particular connection and it will go
back and it will accept a new connection
from a new client
okay I'm going to jump ahead and
actually start talking about some slides
from that we're if you look online
they're actually from a Thursday's
lecture because there's a lot of ground
to cover in that lecture and I'd like to
get a little head start so I mentioned
this up this function called get a door
info which is sort of the modern way in
C at least to find information about
that deals with all the funkiness of
host names host addresses all the
conventions about ports and some of
these various structures and things like
that and the advantage of doing it this
way instead of the old way is first of
all now it sort of unifies ipv4 and ipv6
have very similar looking interfaces and
it's fairly easy to write code that can
handle either and the other was there is
problems with these old ones that they
were designed in an era before
multi-threading and so they have various
statically allocated buffers which gave
a lot of bad conditions that you had to
watch out for in writing code and we're
prone to errors of various sorts and so
this new new format it's actually harder
to use in many levels because it can't
hide away as many details as it used to
but it has the advantage it works better
in a multi-threaded environment the
other thing that makes it hard is it's
trying to be sort of the kitchen sink of
of protocol managers and that makes it a
little bit nasty and messy and so we're
only going to sort of focus in on the
parts that we really need to make use of
for this course
so in particular there's this function
called get adder info where the
information you're passing is a host
which can be either a it's a string as
it shows most these are care stars are
actual real strings not fake strings oh
it used to be back in the old days you
use care stars of generic pointer
because there weren't void stars but
these are actual strings so you give the
name like the the domain name of a host
or you can give the dotted decimal name
but written as you know sequence of
characters one to eight dot so forth a
service for example that this is ipv4 T
TCP service some other information that
that's associated with this particular
connection they refer to as hints
because again this is trying to be a
very generic looking call and then you
pass it in a pointer and it will fill in
and return back a pointer to a data
structure which is essentially the way
it's returning results back to you and
then associated with that is a call
called free adder info that will then
deallocate this space that's used by
this data structure from the result and
then there's one called get adder info
string error which lets you interpret
the various error codes that get created
by this routine of the value that it
returns so let's just look a little
about this and so the result that's
returned by get a door info is a link
twist oh that is null terminated just
like most wink lists are where it gives
some combination of the name of this
particular some naming information for
the the first top-level one is the what
I showed you the canonical name for this
particular
IP address and then it gives some
address information which is you know an
ipv4 them that will encode the IP
address and as a next pointer to change
this link voice together and so this is
actually one interesting thing about
this is it sort of takes care of that
many too many mapping potentially of of
names so if I give for example
google.com it will return a link twist
of all however many or you saw with
Twitter it was returning about four
different addresses so this will return
actually five missed entries the first
will be the canonical name and then it
will give each of the four IP addresses
that's relevant at this particular time
and then you as a programmer then sort
of walk this list you step down this
list and typically try to use each
address one after the other and if you
fail on one then you try the next and
try the next until you hit the end of
the list and then you say whoops
can't do it and that goes whether you're
writing a client or a server so that
adder info let's look back at what that
is
oh so a door info then is what gets
returned is a list of a door info
strokes and so the adder info struck
contains various fields which talks
about what type of data is here what
type of socket is it what its canonical
name is how long are its addresses you
saw that it's an argument to some of the
calls a pointer to a sock adder struct
that's the way that is encoded for IPV
what we've already seen sock adders is a
sort of low-level data structure that
gets used and then an X pointer to chain
the link twist together and so you'll
see some of these are the arguments that
then you will use to pass into the other
functions like bind and with Simmons and
connect
and then there's another version called
get name info which you use when you've
got an IP address and you want to find
what is its domain name and because you
remember that mapping is also
potentially a one-to-many there can be
multiple domain names associated with it
and so it has a similar general thing
we'll just look right now it get added
info so just as an example of how you'd
write code to make use of this and
essentially just as a way of probing the
DNS server is I want to set up an
argument a call to get adder info where
the string I'm going to pass the name is
whatever I type in at the to this
application to main and it just for
hints just passes a a bunch of zeros and
lists P again these are this will just
be a pointers that I haven't actually
oh okay so you'll notice hints is
actually a struct itself whereas list P
and star P are just lists P and P are
just pointers to structs they don't have
any allocated data so the hints I'm just
going to fill in that struct with all
zeros because I don't really need to
provide any hints I am telling it that I
want a an ipv6 TCP connection here and
then so what it will do is it will
return back
what returns an error code but it will
fill in returned to me a pointer to a
this link twist data structure I showed
before
and now I can step through that list
using standard linked list code and make
calls to the get name info function
which will return back domain names
and then when it's all done I have to
free up that whisk that got returned
otherwise all great memory stuff so just
as a demo
what I'm on
Oh host info sorry ah so you can think
of it this is like a not very fancy
implementation of nslookup so the kind
of stuff we already saw before but let's
all it's returning are the different
addresses and one of the things that I
found curious is it returns them in the
same order all the time instead of
within a slow cup it kept changing it
and I think that has to do with caching
no that changed I know it's kind of
interesting if it's it you might want to
play with this code it's kind of you can
see what's going on in different places
and so you can see though that it's it's
basically getting the same kind of
information that you would from nslookup
it's really just creating the DNS server
to do this but that's the start of what
some of this code looks like and
one of the things you by the way when
you're writing your own code you often
make use of what's called localhost and
that always just refers to the machine
that you're running on it always has
this particular IP address so that
address just refers to the machine and
as a programmer you do all your testing
on one machine you just set up both the
client and the server on the same
machine and play with it so localhost is
a very useful way of doing code
development and if this shows you can
request host info for others thanksgivin
and you can also by the way
always give a dotted decimal address
and I'm just making it up here what and
it's not very interesting because it
returns back the same address it's more
interesting to run nslookup on that
so that just gives you a sense and as
you've seen this code is pretty messy
stuff to work with there's a lot of
struck so you have to initialize you
don't initialize you pass pointers and
so the code always looks a bit crufty
but that sort of the the interfaces it
exists and you'll just have to get
somewhat comfortable with it so that
will do us for today then thanks