well hello everyone interesting how far
fewer seats are filled than at the
beginning of the course so that of
course we're in the final stretch of
this course you're working on the last
lab and the material that we're covering
both this lecture and next lecture are
not on the exam and you don't need them
for your web so at some level you could
just tune out and skip it all and if
your only purpose in taking this course
is to pass it or to get some grade in it
and that's it well go ahead to now but
on the other hand the material we're
talking about is very relevant to where
computers are today and where they're
going in the future
and so if you think about the longer
term and whatever your investment is in
the computer industry and computer
technology is then I think you'll find
these very worthwhile but so think of
this more as the icing on the cake
you've learned the hard stuff you've
you've done the grinding part and now
you get to think beyond the sort of
narrow confines of the course material
and and think bigger but that's really
the way you should be viewing this
lecture in the last lecture which will
be on Thursday so today what we're going
to talk about is parallelism and the
issue is that that Wow
that PowerPoint is a product made by a
certain company in Seattle that it's not
always reliable
but the issue is as you know nowadays
when you buy a computer you don't get
just one CPU on the processor chip you
have at least two on a typical laptop
even my phone has two cores in it and as
well as for graphic processing units and
a typical the the next generation of
iPad will be a six core processor so
these have become not just the the sort
of specialized domain of of high-end
machines but actually there all the time
and actually we'll talk some next time
why is it that instead of having one
fast computer you get to a medium size
medium performance processors on a chip
or more and that that's actually a
really interesting technology issue that
I'll talk about next time but it's the
way it is so you can think of it when
you write a program ah and it runs as a
single thread then you're basically not
making use of the computing resources
that you have available to you so the
natural thing is well could we make our
programs run faster by doing multiple
threads so you've already learned or
you're in the process of applying a
multi-threaded programming as a way to
deal with a concurrency of external
events there's multiple clients who want
to make use of a server and instead of
serving one and then another and then
another if you can handle them all it's
sort of a an external use of concurrency
but what we'll talk about today is more
in internal use can I make use of
multiple threads running on multiple
cores to make a program run a single
program run faster and the message
behind that is yes but and what I mean
is it is truly possible and
people spend a lot of time making
programs run faster by using multiple
threads but it's harder than you'd think
it should be and it's fraught with as
you probably already experienced
programming bugs but also it's just
really darn hard to get the kind of
performance out of a multi-core
processor that you should would think
it'd be available so we'll talk about
some of that and then we'll finish it up
a little bit understanding of how how
when you writing concurrent programs you
want to think about the state of memory
and how that's a challenge for
multi-core processors or in fact any
concurrent concurrent system so there's
actually two sources of concurrency on a
modern processor multiple cores which is
you have actually a multiple CPUs on a
single chip but there's also something
called hyper-threading which is in my
experience less useful but let me go
through this so this is what a typical
modern processor looks like processor
chip is that there's actually on a
single chip there's multiple independent
CPUs and each of them has some part of
the cache hierarchy which is private to
that particular core and then there is
another part of the cache hierarchy
that's shared across cores and then they
all have a common interface to main
memory so if these cores are running and
this is what happens a lot is they're
running programs that are completely
independent have nothing to do with each
other
then they more or less just exist and
run and they're happy as can be they are
caching parts of their own state and you
know sometimes this cache will get
polluted by the junk from other programs
in terms of performance but it will
matter with functionality the trick when
you're trying to do multi-core
programming as a parallel computing
thing somehow getting all these cores
working on parts of different parts of a
single problem in a way that makes it so
that you get the performance out of it
they don't spend all their time
basically arguing with each other about
who has access to what and also they're
not stepping over each other and messing
up each other's state so hyper threading
is a little bit more into the deep works
of how a processor operates you'll
recall from the lecture on a performance
or what's chapter 5 of the book that a
modern microprocessor looks absolutely
nothing like the model that you get by
looking at assembly code instructions
the model of assembly code is you
execute one instruction then you execute
the next one then you execute the next
one
modern prostitutes don't do that at all
they haven't done it for well they
haven't done it that way for 30 years
and since 1995 so since 20 years they do
it in this totally different way which
is sometimes referred to as out of order
processing and so just real quickly but
the basic idea is on the processor chip
there's multiple functional units that
are capable of doing different types of
operation there's ones for integer
arithmetic these ones for floating-point
arithmetic and so forth and then there's
separate blocks that interface to the
memory actually to the cache memories
and they're both loading meaning reading
from the memory and storing writing out
to memory but these units are sort of
operate independently and what happens
is there's a block of logic which is
actually enormous with huge block of
logic in an x86 processor that reads the
instructions out of the instruction
stream rips them apart into little
pieces keeps track of data dependencies
and control dependencies and then
schedules all the various operations in
your program on these different
functional units so we talked some about
that of in the context of how can you
write up
program that will sort of maximize how
much is going on down here by writing
your code in a particular ways so all
this is an introduction to say this is
how you have to understand what hyper
threading is so in a single execution
mode there's basically one instruction
decoder and it has its own set of state
here its own program counter its own
queue of operations that it's already
decoded and haven't completed yet
it has its own set of registers they're
actually not registers like you'd expect
they're they're highly virtualized
registers but all this state is there to
help to service the execution of one
thread of execution with hyper threading
basically what you do is the idea that
is to say 90% of all programs don't
really make use of all these functional
units especially if you're blocking on a
load because there's a miss in a cache
then all these arithmetic units are
sitting there without anything useful
work to do
oh and so why don't we just double up or
quadruple upper K times up the state
associated with the decoding and control
parts of the program so that you can
have multiple threads running and
sharing these functional units among
each other so they're operating really
independently their states are not
intertwined but they're sort of making
more use of the available hardware for
performing functions and so that's
called hyper threading that's an Intel
term you also sometimes hear call SMT
simultaneous multi-threading and in my
experience and we'll see here the
numbers it doesn't really make that big
a difference but it turns out to be in
the sort of large picture things a
relatively inexpensive feature for them
to throw on to processors and so they do
and so nowadays at least with an x86
processor usually have to weigh
hyper-threading in them so given that if
you look at our shark machines which are
a little bit old there's sort of 2010
era machine but they were high-end
machines in their day and so they still
actually are more powerful than what
you'd buy as say a desktop and way more
powerful than as a laptop that you'd get
today so they're actually pretty decent
machines and actually we'll talk next
time about why computers aren't a lot
faster than they were five years ago
that's actually an interesting
technology thing so that they their
server class machines so they have
multiple cores and they have eight of
them which is a lot you can buy ten core
machines x86 machines on a single chip
but I don't think you can get more yet
so these were fairly advanced machine of
their day and they also have two-way
hyper threading so in theory you should
be able to get sixteen independent
threads running sort of 16 Way
parallelism potentially out of a program
if you can keep everything working and
keep bad things from happening
so let's give a really trivial
application one that should be very
simple to make run in parallel that says
imaginary we want to sum up the numbers
between 0 and n minus 1 which is by the
way a really stupid thing to do because
there's a very simple closed-form
formula for it which is good in the
sense it will let us check our work but
it's a completely stupid application but
it just shows you this idea and so what
we're just going to do is is block off
if we have n way parallelism we're just
going to split our range of numbers n
ways and just have a single threads sum
up one n of the numbers and then they'll
collectively sum together the result in
some way or another so this is about as
easy a parallel program as you could
imagine so let's do a 1 version which is
said well gee I understand how to use
threads P threads and I know about these
things called semaphores or mutual
exclusion so what I'll do is just all
I'll have one place in memory where I'm
collecting the sum over all n values and
for a thread to be able to add to that
if it will lock it it will get a mutual
exclusive access to it increment it and
then unlock it and we'll just let all
the threads go helter-skelter
locking and unlocking this so the code
for that's pretty easy to write it it's
a here's the the code of course all
threaded code looks a lot messier than
you think it should but in the end it's
a fairly straightforward code so in
particular this is the thread routine is
passing through this weird Varg pea
structure that you do with with threads
the way you pass arguments to a thread
routine but basically it's figuring out
where is the start and end range of the
numbers then adding for all i between
the start
before the end I'll lock that acquire a
semaphore lock I'll increment this
global sum and then I'll release the
lock okay so pretty much the style of
code that you've been working with and
what you find is actually this is really
a bad idea so running as a single thread
it takes 51 seconds to do that it would
be by the way if you didn't lock and
unlock because it's only one thread
you'd blow this away it would take just
a couple seconds so and then you see as
you add more threads it actually gets
worse and especially if you jump from
one to two you increase by a factor nine
how much time it takes and it always
starts to get better as you get up into
eight threads and then it gets worse
again so the reason is that locking and
unlocking is a very time-consuming task
and basically you can think of is that
you if you have that map of the
multi-core processors with all their
private caches in one shared cache these
threads are basically fighting with each
other for control for that one memory
address that they that they're
incrementing and it has to grab the
control away from one core to your the
core that's accessing it do the lock
unlock and then it gets grabbed back for
it so it's a miserable performance for
cache huge overhead for the semaphore
activities and just really a bad thing
all around and so lesson one is
semaphores or mutexes are very expensive
and if you're trying to do low level
parallelism you don't want fine-grained
locking at that level otherwise you're
just completely sunk and so that's not
the way to do it I won't go into it but
there's quite a bit of literature about
what they call lock free synchronization
which is a way to avoid semaphores but
get the effect and they wouldn't work in
this context either those just if you've
ever heard that term those are generally
designed for examples where you expect
relatively little contention between the
threads and so you try and be optimistic
and then roll back if something bad
happens this is a case where nope all
those threads are going to be pounding
that one memory location and they're
really fighting for it and so there is
no good solution to that problem the
other thing I'll point out is this jump
here shows you that hyper threading
isn't really helping us here going from
the fact that we slowed down from 8 to
16 means we can't really make use of 16
threads in this application 8 threads
are better than 4 but obviously all
that's kind of a waste of time because
this is just really a bad idea all
around so let's do something different
let's have each of them accumulate their
own sum for their own sub range and
we'll give up so we'll have an array of
accumulators where the each thread is
incrementing only a one element of this
array so they're not fighting with each
other directly for it but they are
fighting for if you think about it for
the same cache line because an array is
typically stored and so it's not totally
nice ah but this it gives you a pointer
to this idea if if we could sort of move
into a private state the stuff that
we're making the most direct access to
then we'll get better performance so
this is the thread routine and that the
point is that there's some global array
called pesum but it's only incrementing
the the part of it that sort of assigned
to this particular thread and here you
do see a performance improvement right
so one thread takes 5 seconds remember
before it was 58 so that shows you just
the advantage of the cost of semaphores
right there is a factor of 10 and you
see you are actually getting an
improvement all across the line
including up to 16 threads you're still
getting an improvement it would flatten
out
should have just shown the number 432
but it would flatten out at this point
but it actually is getting some
advantage out of hyper-threading as well
so that's good it's not an amazing speed
up so you can think of what they call
the speed up is the performance of it
running on a single core versus the
performance on n cores and in the ideal
case it goes n times faster and we're
not quite hitting that well but here's
you've already learned that it's
generally bad to be accumulating into a
memory and so why not do the thing we
learned before which is you accumulate
in a register and you only update the
memory when you're done with that so
let's just do that and I'll call that
the local version I'll just increment a
sum which is a local variable and only
when I'm done then I'll store it in the
global array okay so it's functionally
equivalent to the one we just showed
we're just moving instead of
accumulating in a global array we're
accumulating in a register and here you
see a pretty big performance improvement
so blue is what we showed with the the
global array red or orange is what's
this local variable and so you see it's
actually interesting we're getting a
performance improvement as well although
it bottoms out at eight and it actually
gets worse when you go to sixteen and
this is showing that hyper-threading
isn't really helping here because
basically the the single thread is just
accumulating as fast as it can and
adding to a register and so it's making
pretty good use of what functional units
it uses and putting multiple threads
sharing it isn't really helping at least
not on the shark machines this actually
might be different on different machines
and actually if you recall from the
performance optimization we found that
if you're just doing a bunch of
additions
you can make use as associativity and
get more accumulation in parallel so you
could actually speed up this program
just the single threaded version of this
program pretty well but anyways it shows
it okay this is starting to look like
your your a your single threaded
performance is pretty good and B you're
getting some useful speed-up out of
parallelism but as I said this is like
the easiest example in the world to
parallelize so if you can't do it here
then then life is pretty hopeless as far
as multi-threading so let's talk about
as I mentioned this idea of speed-up so
speed-up is just defined to be the time
for a single-threaded program divided by
the time for for P threads running or
actually will use it P cores instead of
P threads question yes generally the
scheduler has some kind of go balancing
built into it and it will tend to
especially in a case like this where the
threads are sort of grabbing and running
making they will generally get spread
across the the cores so that's a pretty
the Linux scheduler is pretty good at
that when you have more threads than
there are cores then then it basically
starts scheduling them in some cyclic
order and you you won't you'll at best
you will not get any advantage and in a
worst case you actually start slowing
down from having more threads than are
there good question so there's really
two versions of speed-up one is if I
take my multi-threaded routine and run
it with one thread and then I met do it
with P threads or cores I can get a
speed-up but actually the truer thing is
if I take the best-known sequential
algorithm for performing this task with
the best implementation of that
and then I compare it against my
parallel one and so that's referred to
as absolute speed-up which is the the
best measures you know you give both
sides the opportunity to do the best
implementation that they can and then
you compare it and then what's referred
to as the efficiency is how close to the
speed-up get to the ideal speed-up which
is if I'm running on P cores
I should be P times faster and you'll
see that we're you know the question of
hyper-threading versus not we're sort of
here we're saying no you don't we're not
trying to gain from hyper-threading you
can play this game various ways and you
can argue back and forth whether
hyper-threading should count so for P is
P the total number of possible threads
or the total number of cores it's really
a something to argue back and forth
about so the point is the efficiency
though is is measured as how much do we
do relative to ideal and so this is what
you get for this code the local version
of P some you'll see that our efficiency
numbers are somewhere in the hi somebody
range which is good but not great it's
pretty good actually if you can get 75
percent efficiency you're doing better
than most but again that's because this
should have been the world's easiest
program to parallelize so and the best
speed-up we're getting is a factor of
six out of eight course so again that's
pretty good but this really should be
something you can do well so that just
gives you a flavor of what parallel
computing can be so now it's sort of
back off and talk some general
principles just like the speed-up
there's a fella named Jean nom Dahl who
coincidentally just died a few weeks ago
he might have seen it in the news he was
one of the original pioneers at IBM in
their mainframe computers then then at
some point he in the 60s
he started his own company called um dal
computers and they were like they were
the the cool company in mainframe
computers if that could ever be
considered cool right and he built a
competitor's to IBM that absolutely
drove them crazy because they had a
virtual monopoly they actually were
subject to antitrust suit
so um Dahl was a sort of the the rebel
who broke away from the mother company
and started a competitor and he made
this very simple observation that's
called Alma's dolls law which is
basically junior high level algebra to
think of this but it's actually a fairly
perceptive point about what's the
possible benefit of speeding up
something and this is discussed in the
book you know this isn't just for
computers it's any process that you want
to speed up and it's a very simple
observation which is suppose there's
some fraction of a system that I can
make go faster and I'll call that
fraction P P is some number between zero
and one point zero right 100% zero
percent and let's suppose we take that
part that we're going to make run faster
and improve its performance by a factor
okay then we can just very simply talk
about what will be the benefit of that
performance so we'll call it T sub K and
what it says is the fraction P of the
time will be reduced by K but the
fraction that you can't change a one
minus P will remain at its old time and
that's um dolls law that's it that's the
whole thing and one interesting measure
is what if K were infinity what if we
had unbounded resources to speed things
up and what the observation is the best
feed up you'll get is a 1 minus P and so
just think it this way if you have 10%
of it that you can't change the other
90% you make infinitely fast
then your performance improvement will
be a factor of 10 that's really all it's
saying right pretty straightforward idea
so this has sort of direct implications
in so the example is suppose that we can
improve the performance of some system
of 90% of it and we can speed up by
factor 9 and that number is chosen to
make the numbers work out then we'll get
it best at 2x performance improvement
basically what it says is the part of
the system that you can't speed up will
become your bottleneck and that's just
the way it is so the implications for
this repair while programming are fairly
obvious that if we can take our
application and chop off some fraction
of it and make it run K times faster by
running it on K cores then the part of
it that's still running sequentially
will come to will limit the ultimate
performance we can get so that's not
really an issue for this summation
problem because it really does divide
into as many independent tasks as as you
have numbers and as you can see you can
make them run but many other
applications do some part of it that I
can't really make know parallel so just
as an example and just for the sake of
this class you know an example of a
little bit more involved a problem in
parallel programming and multi-threading
let's think about sorting a bunch of
numbers so we have n numbers and we want
to sort them and we have some number of
threads that we can do this with is
there way we can speed this up and you
think about it's not that clear how you
do it there's actually a vast literature
in parallel sorting and those you've
taken or won't take the class 210 will
be exposed to a lot of this but I'm just
going to do a very simple version which
is quicksort so quicksort is for example
the the C library program Q sort
quicksort it was invented in the early
1960s or 1950s by a guy named Tony Hoare
who also founded a lot of the
fundamental logic of program so he's
like an amazing person still alive today
lives in Cambridge England but if you
ever have a chance to go to a talk by
him do so he's amazing person anyways
the idea quicksort is very simple and
this is sort of the basic sorting
algorithm you grab some element from the
array that you're trying to sort that's
called the pivot and then you split the
data so that you look at the elements
that are either greater or less than the
pivot and potentially also equal let's
just assume all the elements are unique
here so you just split it into two piles
one is the lesson once a greater now you
creatively you recursively you sort
those two piles by the same method and
when it's all done you end up with
everything sorted one nice thing about
it is it can be done in place meaning if
you have an array of data you can do
this all just by swapping elements
around and not have to use any extra
space which you would for example with
merge sort so this is a fairly simple
algorithm and just to visualize it then
you have some block of data X array and
you want to sort it so you pick an
element called the pivot and there's
various strategies for doing that and
now you just subdivide X into three
parts L the left hand R the right hand
meaning less and greater than P and then
you place P in the middle and then you
recursively when you're doing this for
in a sequential code you'll pick one of
these two usually leftmost or rightmost
whatever doesn't really matter and
you'll recursively you apply the same
method to to the left side and
ultimately after enough recursions you
get to the point where L has been sorted
and that's shown in this kind of a
swishy color thing and call that L
and same with you'll do the same thing
now with the right hand side and when
you're done this is usually done in
place so you just the L part works on
one array part of the array and the are
part on another and when you're done
they're in sorted order the very simple
sort and generally has very good
performance so this is what the code for
it looks like which is usually you have
is a special case if there's only one or
two elements and then you do this
partitioning so this routine of
splitting it between the left and the
right hand part is handled by a function
called partition and then if there's
more than one element in the left side
you sort that and if there's more than
one element in the right hand side you
sort that and then when all these
recursions are done then the array is
sorted so pretty typical code and we
won't go in the trickiest part writing
the code is how do you make this
partitioning go fast but I won't go into
that just imagine it happens so this
algorithm actually has a natural version
of parallelism which is in my sequential
version I was sorting both first the
left and then the left of the left and
the left of the left of the left and
kind of working my way until I got that
whole array sorted and then I was coming
back and I was working on the right and
then the left part of the right and the
left to the left to the right and blah
blah blah
and doing these recursions because the
way the codes written right I am doing
the full sort of the left-hand part and
only after that is sorted then I'm doing
the complete sort of the right-hand part
so the point is it's it's an algorithm
where I'm working just on one part of
the array of the time but there's a very
natural recursion of parallelism here
that says okay I've got two parts they
each need to be sorted
let me just fire off two threads and let
them do
with that and that's the so it's what
you call divide and conquer parallelism
it's a very natural kind of parallelism
it shows up in this code so basically
I'll do the same thing as before all at
the top level will be a purely
sequential process of partitioning and
but then assuming a partition comes up
with some non-trivial split then I will
recursively begin fork off to threads
each of which will be responsible for
the other and so we'll sort of look like
I'm working on the two parts in parallel
and eventually both sides will end up
now this picture isn't really quite true
and that it looked makes it look like
they're all kind of synchronized
together and I'm doing a you know kaboom
down like this in a strict way but in
fact they're not it's very asynchronous
the left part is one thread the right is
another they just go at their own pace
and at the end I'm just going to wait
for it all to complete but there's no
strict temporal ordering on how that all
occurs
so the way I'll write this in the code
is available on the course website I'm
only going to show you a glimpse of it
it's a non-trivial amount of code it
takes to do it but basically what I'm
going to do is have a bunch of a pool of
threads that are ready to work and
that's a pretty typical way you write
threaded code because actually the the
initiation of a thread is a non-trivial
amount of computation so usually what
you do is you say I've got this many
cores I'm going to create a set of that
many threads and they will each work by
sharing a task queue
so some agent that is a forking off work
for the different threads to do they
will do the work assigned to them when
that's complete they'll come back and
say ok I'm ready for something new and
it will give them something new so I've
there's a little bit of code a very
rudimentary code there of creating this
task model and task scheduling so the
basic rule will be any given task any
given thread then at any given time has
been assigned sub sub range of this
array to be a sorting and it will be
specified by the base meaning the
starting point of this particular range
and then the number of elements that
it's a told it's sort and one other
thing I'll do is once I get down to this
array being small enough I'll just sort
it sequentially and and we'll see how
big that block is or not is actually
performance parameter that you can use
for tuning the program so the point is
that you don't want to take this down
too far because the the sort of overhead
of threads is enough that when you get
to fine-grained you're actually going to
start losing performance
so assume that it's bigger than that
I've been given some block there what
I'll do then is I'll run the partition
step this thread will run it a partition
step just using the exact function I
showed you or didn't show you and then
as long as and then I will us create and
add to the task queue two new tasks a
one de for the left part and one for the
right part and then the scheduler that
will assign two threads to handle those
two parts and so that code will that's
exactly how the code is going to work
it's going to keep reusing the same
threads over and over again to but at
any given time they'll be given a range
of places what typically will happen is
they'll run their partitioning step and
then say okay I've done my job now
assigned to new to new threads to do
this and that's the general scheme of it
or they'll say this is a small enough
block I'm just going to sort the darn
thing okay so that's really all the code
does it's online if you're interested in
this kind of stuff it's um I think it's
pretty well written code because I wrote
it so this is sort of that the somewhat
simplified version of the code say
initialize my task queue scheduling
system create global variables of
describing the beginning and end of this
array to be sorted create a new task
queue and then this is the main function
the TQ sort helper is given some range
of of addresses and a pointer to the
task queue that's used to manage these
tasks and then uh
when it's all day we'll just wait till
all the tasks have completed this is at
the top level
this isn't part of any recursion this is
the top level code and then it will free
up the data structures and then this is
the the part of it that actually does
the real work it will say so now the TQ
sort helper is the part that's a
scientists to sort some particulars
poises from the the starting address the
base and some number of elements and so
this is what each task will do and it
says okay if this is a small enough
block of elements I'm just going to call
my serial quicksort to do it otherwise
I'm going to
oh it's a little bit Messier this okay
now otherwise it's going to spawn a task
to do the sorting let's see I was a
little mixed up this is a high level so
the actual splitting occurs in this
thing which is where it so this is the
actual thread routine and what it's
saying is run the partition here and
then call this TQ sort helper which you
just saw on the left and the right parts
of it so just to review then the actual
spawning of a task is done by this
helper routine but then that what it
calls is the the thread routine is what
does the work here and what it will do
is it will do the partitioning within
that thread and then it will just throw
back and add to the task queue two calls
to this helper but as that kind of so
between these two routines you can see
it's doing this idea of a divide and
conquer parallelism so this is a
performance running on the shark
machines and this is a fairly
straightforward I'm just taking some
number of random value two to the
thirty-seventh
that can't be right
finish this is numbers not to the
thirty-seventh right you agree with me
to the 37th is 128 billion roughly so
this number is not right I'll have to
check it out
and now what this x axis so the y axis
just denotes how long does it take to
complete by the way one thing if you're
used to measuring performance based on
CPU time that's not useful when you're
talking a parallel computing you really
want to talk a elapsed time the time
that you'd get from looking at a clock
and measuring it and dealing with
whatever inefficiency occurs there so
these are actually the elapsed run time
of the entire program and you'll see
that it varies according to this thing
called the serial fraction the serial
fraction is just at what point do I
slide between a serial quicksort or keep
dividing so how big does the array need
to be as a fraction expressed as a
fraction of the original array before I
I will go into recursion if I were
actually to write this a real
application I wouldn't do it based on a
fraction I'd do it based on a block size
to say anything smaller than a thousand
elements or some number like that but
this code just happens to be expressed
this way but the thing to notice that's
interesting is you'll see here if the
fraction is 1
it basically says I won't split this at
all I'm just going to call a sequential
quicksort so this is a purely sequential
version of it and what it shows is if I
once I start - I'll be willing to sort
of split this up and do parallelism I
start making run faster and faster and
faster I'll and then I get into this
trough and now if I start going finer
and finer grain then I'm running into
the problem where the thread overhead is
more than the advantage I'm getting by
doing the parallelism and I'm faster to
run that block bigger sort just use
a sequential algorithm rather than
parallel but the good news here is this
is a pretty long trough here so it means
is if you're trying to tune this program
it's not that hard you're not going to
pay a huge penalty if you don't know a
parameter exactly so as long as this is
a huge range right 30 from a 32 to 4096
it's a factor of of a lot to the fifth
and 2 to the 12th is 2 to the 7th fact
128 see how I do my arithmetic and
powers at 2 anyways it's roughly at you
know
128 so several orders of magnitude
decimal orders of magnitude over which
you get pretty comparable performance so
that means from a performance tuning
point of view it's not that hard to do
and you also see we're getting a pretty
decent speed up on our eight core to a
hyper-threaded machine we're getting up
basically out 7x performance and
hyper-threading really isn't helping us
at all is part of the lesson here but if
you just think of it as eight cores then
that's pretty good
so there is an obvious place here where
there's a Nam Dolls law issue going on
if you think at that first top-level
split the first call to partition is
being done over the entire Ray by a
serial sequential process right that so
at the very least that is not going
parallel at all there's going exactly
one thread is doing the initial
partition and then that splits into two
so at most you have two threads worth of
parallelism and then the next level down
at most four and so you really don't you
have to get several levels of recursion
down before you're really running on all
the course that you have available so
you'd think that that's limiting your
speed up and it does and that's part of
the reason why our best performance is a
factor of seven and not a factor of
eight or more so there's quite a bit of
work as I mentioned on how to speed up
performance including how to make
quicksort go faster so there's a vast
body of literature on parallel sort
so one thing I tried was to say okay
well let's try and do this partitioning
step they least the top couple levels
let's try and do a parallel version of
that and so the idea is you pick one
pivot element but now you fire in this
example for threads and each of those
four threads runs a partition step on on
one-fourth of the range and it don't
generate their own versions of left and
right and then you globally figure out
how many are in each of these sub ranges
and then you tell each thread okay now
you copy your part of it over to the
relevant section of the array but the
good news so there's some amount of
synchronization that goes on there but
you can imagine that this partitioning
step once when you're running it is
completely independent of across the
different threads so it's getting a
almost ideal speed-up so I implemented
this and tried and I couldn't make it
run faster than the original code and I
think the the problem with this was the
copying the cost of copying data here
was even though it's being done by
multiple threads and getting pretty good
performance out of the memory system
because you're doing sequential you know
all the cache issues are pretty good
here but that's just enough extra work
that has to be done for this parallel
code that doesn't have to be done the
sequential code is totally in place
meaning not using any additional storage
not copying and so that's just enough of
a penalty on the parallel part that it
didn't really improve performance at all
so that code is shown as part of the
code on the course website but like I
said I I banged on it quite a bit and
trying to tune it and squeak it in
various ways and could never make it so
I got better overall performance out of
this program
and so that's again a lesson and that's
one of the unfortunate lessons is you
can spend a lot of time trying to make a
program run faster and get absolutely
nowhere and it's frustrating because you
put in a lot of work and you know it's a
pretty cool idea and you'd love to
publish a paper about it or tell your
friends about it and it just goes
nowhere and it just sits there and
there's nothing unfortunately there's
not an accumulated repository of the bad
ideas of computer science don't waste
your time trying this that people can
talk about so this is just a lesson to
learn so anyways that was my experience
with that again other people have spent
a lot more time this is one of the most
common applications that people try to
do parallel programming for so some of
the lessons from this is you need a good
strategy for how you're going to get
parallelism out of your application and
I showed you two basic versions one is
partitioned into K parts they're more or
less completely independent of each
other or something like a divide and
conquer strategy where you can keep
splitting it but the two splits that you
create out of that can go concurrently
these other different types of
parallelism - in general you want to
make the inner loops you can't have any
synchronization primitives in there it
will just run too slow um dolls law as I
mentioned is always sort of lurking in
the background of if you can always feed
up a part of your program then the other
part will become the bottleneck but the
other thing is like I said you can do it
you've got the tools you've learned with
with P threads and your knowledge of
programming and your understanding of
cache memories and things like that
you've got the tools you need to be an
effective programmer of this kind of
thing but you have to and there's
nothing that beats sort of trial and
error and testing and tuning
experimenting if there's some parameters
that need to be set then you want to run
experiments
will sweep through the parameters to try
and figure out what the setting should
be so that's sort of a little bit about
parallel programming let me just finish
this lecture with a little bit of sort
of classic issues about concurrency that
that are critical when you're dealing
with these systems based on what you
call a shared memory model of
computation so multi-core is an example
of conceptually multi-threaded
computation remember you're you're
working within a single virtual address
space and you have private stacks but
the more global the heap memory is
completely shared across threads and so
that's what you call the shared memory
programming model and that's what we've
really been looking at this course so
there's a certain interesting question
about called memory consistency models
and here I'll illustrate it with a very
simple example imagine we have two
global variables a and B and we have two
different threads and so the first
thread is going to write meaning assign
a value to a and it's going to read
meaning print the value of B and the
other thread is going to do the opposite
it's going to write assigned a value to
B and print the value of a and so now
the question is what are the possible
outputs for this program and so there's
a model that sort of the accepted
standard called sequential consistency
which means that these events can occur
well that these that within a single
thread things have to occur in the
sequential order of that thread but
across threads whether write a a write B
occurs first is completely arbitrary and
similarly whether writing of B occurs
between these two actions or before is
all too arbitrary so what what it means
is you can take two different threads
and you can interleave there
their events in anyway but you should be
able to pull out of that interleaving
the sequential order of either of both
of the two threads so when you do that
you end up you can enumerate in the
example like this all the possibilities
you can say well look it first is either
going to be right a or right B
let's pick right a so now the next event
will be either a read of B or write of B
and then if I if I do write a write read
B then I've completed this thread and so
now the only possibility is to write to
B and read a and so forth you work out
all the possible things you get six
different event orderings and then what
will be printed is well first of all
whether you print beer before a would
depend on the relative ordering of those
two threads so that's shown I'm showing
the B value in blue and the red value in
in red the I'm sorry the a value in red
and you'll get these different
possibilities these are all the six
possible outputs of this program but
you'll see that there are two two other
outputs one could imagine that won't
arise one is to print 101 in other words
to have them both print the original
values of these two variables and that's
impossible because I have to have done
at least one right before I can reach
either of these two print statements
right so it's not possible for these to
still be in their original values of
when I hit these print statements now
and whichever order I hit these two so
those two are impossible so that's the
idea of sequential consistency that
there's some very large number but of
possible outputs of a program but in any
case they can't violate the ordering
implied by the individual threads so
you'd say okay that seems like pretty
obvious thing but actually if you think
from a hardware perspective it's not
that trivial to make that happen so let
me just throw a show you a scenario of
multi-core Hardware that would violate
sequential consistency assume that each
of our threads has its own private cache
and so if I execute this statement what
I'll do is I will grab a copy of a from
the main memory and bring it into my
cache and I will assign this new value
to it and similarly a thread to will
grab a copy of its of B and and update
that and now if I do my two print
statements if thread two picks up the
value from the memory not knowing that
thread one as a modified copy of that
value then it would naturally print one
and similarly if if thread one picked up
a copy of B from main memory it would
print 100 so we'd see exactly this
unallowable execution and the reason is
because each of these threads have their
own private copies of these variables
and they're not properly synchronized
but you could see in a hardware scenario
it would be easy to build this hardware
and make that mistake so how does it
work in a in a multi-core processor well
they have a trick they call it Snoopy
caches and it's a little bit like the
readers writers of synchronization that
you're working on for your proxies that
you want to make it so that if
everyone's just reading some shared
value they should be able to get copies
into their own caches to optimize the
performance of it but if one of them
wants to write to it
it needs to get an exclusive copy of it
and lock out any other thread from
accessing that either to read it or to
write it from long enough to make the
update and so they have a protocol where
they tag actually and these tags are at
the level of cache lines typically so
the tagged cache line in main memory
with its state and the typical state
would be invalid it's shared oryx its
exclusive so shared means that there can
be a copies of it but they can only be
read-only copies and exclusive meaning
that it's exclusively available to a
single thread so this is built into them
the hardware of a multi-core processor
so what will happen that is in order to
do a write to a thread one will acquire
an exclusive copy of this element and
that actually tagging happens down here
at the main memory and in the cache both
oh and similarly if if thread two wants
a to write to B it must get an exclusive
copy of that and then when the read
occurs what happens is actually this
cache miss will send out a signal on a
bus a shared communication medium saying
I want to read a and instead of the main
memory responding to it actually it will
that result will be supplied by the
other cache and it will convert the
state of this element to being a shared
element locally but you'll see that the
main memory element isn't updated yet it
goes through the whole right-back
protocol you've already seen and
sometimes it will update that there's
different implementations but this is
why it's called a Snoopy cache is that
it basically thread two is
is peeking into or getting it access to
information that's available in thread
ones cache and so now thread two will
correctly get a copy of a that's in this
shared state and the same goes would be
it will snoop over and thread two will
one will get a readable copy these are
now all marked as shared State and so if
if either of them want to write they'd
have to now basically get exclusive
access to it and that would have to then
disable the copy and the other in the
other location so you can imagine this
protocol being non-trivial actually to
get right and to implement and it gets
way more complicated than this with all
the variations on it so but it's become
the norm in in multi-core hardware
design but it's actually part of the
factor that limits the core count on a
processor because just the hardware
involved in keeping the consistency
across the caches is non-trivial it has
to work very fast we're talking at the
cash rate access speeds so there's not a
lot of time involved in there so
actually implementing this stuff making
it run making it scale across say eight
cores 10 cores 16 cores is not a not a
trivial thing but that that goes on in
the background and so you can for most
systems nowadays you can assume that
there's some memory consistency model
that you can program to that's supported
by the hardware of the system and that
this serial serializability that's
referred to as sort of the the easiest
to understand there's others at a little
bit more nuanced well guess that fell
off the bottom here and doesn't seem
right
that's it okay so just to wrap that up
then it gives you a flavor of and you
can see that getting programs to run
fast through multi-threading is not not
easy you often have to rewrite your
application you have to think about the
algorithm you have to worry about
debugging it as you've already
discovered at both the the shell web and
the proxy lab that concurrency where you
can't predict the order of events makes
it much more difficult to debug code so
all these factors come in and you have
to have some understanding of the
underlying mechanisms that are used and
what their performance implications are
so in particular let me just observe
here that if I'm like doing
synchronization across threads like you
saw that original one where they are
fighting over this global variable P
'some whatever it was called you can
imagine these the caches in this battle
with each other to try and get exclusive
access to this single memory of value
and because each one is running as fast
as it possibly can but each one requires
getting exclusive copy writing to it and
releasing it so that locking mechanism
is flying back and forth between these
caches and it's really not very fast so
that's the kind of thing is why and also
you know as an application programmer
you're making calls semaphore call
bounces you up into the OS kernel which
is a cost involved so this thing has all
the bad all the things that make
programs not run the way you really like
them to so that's one of the challenges
in parallel programming is how do you
actually make use of the parallelism
that's there without getting bogged down
by the cost of the various
mechanisms of control oh so anyways this
is part of what you have to appreciate
and understand as a programmer is how
these things work at a level deep enough
that you'll have some sense of what
makes programs run faster or slower
where the mistakes could want so that's
just a little little flavor of a much
bigger topic so that's it for today