so today we're going to continue our study of virtual memory
by looking at
more detail at how how address
translation works and then and and then
we'll learn about how virtual memory
works on real systems on Linux and x86
64 systems and that the payoff for that
is that you'll really be able to now
understand how fork and exec really work
and how how vital the virtual memory
system is due to these sort of the
entire working of the system so let's
look at some specific examples of how we
do address translation and here's that
reference slide so let's suppose we have
this simple memory system with fourteen
bit virtual addresses twelve bit
physical addresses page size of 64 bytes
so in our we have so we need six VPO
bits offset bits and then the remaining
bits are the virtual page number and
similarly for our physical addresses we
need we need six offset bits and the
remaining bits form the physical page
number okay now our that the TLB in this
in this system has 16 entries and it's
4-way set associative so remember that
the TLB caches page table entries okay
and those page table entries are
uniquely identified by the virtual page
number so we only need to use the VPN to
to access entries in the in the TLB we
have 16 entries 4-way set associative so
there's a total of four sets and so we
use the low order the two low order bits
and the VPN as the index and then the
remaining bits just like any other cache
or the tag bits
okay and then this we've initialized
this with some some various values now
notice that the actual contents of the
the TLB are in this read in this region
here right so the the set this is just
to help identify what set there there is
no entry called set with a value of zero
right we just will just
we're just identifying that as it and
say yeah just--we're just explicitly
listening the index and so each of our
entries in the TLB consists of this tag
and if that if the TLB entry is valid a
physical page number okay now we also
need a page table so we'll have we'll
assume that we have this page table with
them we're just showing the first 16
entries and the each page table entry
consists of a physical page number and a
valid did if valid bit is on then then
that indicates that the page is in
memory and and the PPM field gives the
physical page number okay and again
there's there's no actual this VPN
column doesn't actually exist in the
page table okay and now we have a simple
simple direct Mac direct mapped cache
it's addressed with physical addresses
like and it contains 16 sets each with
one line and we'll assume a four byte
block size so we have so we have a four
byte block size so we need to offset
bits for the cache 16 sets we means we
need for cache index bits and then the
remaining bits are for the tags now just
it's just an accident in the way that I
define this the system that
the cash tags are exactly the same as
the physical page number so this this
this is just the coincidence and it
doesn't isn't necessarily that way okay
now with the magic of av audio-visual
systems
switch good
okay so let's we're going to look at
this a couple examples using this this
little system okay now so let's suppose
the CPU executes is an instruction that
generates an effective address it's a
virtual address of 0 X 0 3 d 4 and then
it passes that to the MMU
which is needs to figure out the the
corresponding physical address and then
it needs to fetch the data from cache or
memory ok so let's the first thing we do
is we just write out the bits for this
virtual address okay and then we
identify the different fields ok so we
have the offset virtual page offset bits
and then the remaining bits or the
virtual page number okay the offset in
this case is 2 4 0 X 2 for the VPN is F
and then we have that the two TLB I bits
which are 1 1 so 3 and then we have the
tag bits which are also equal to 3 so
the first thing that the MMU does given
this address is it checks the TLB on
hoping that the page table entry that it
needs is cached in the in the TLB so it
goes extracts the index bits 3 and that
that gives us so now that that says that
if if this page table entry is in the
TLB it's going to be in set 3 ok so so
we go to set 3 and now we're looking for
an entry in set 3 with a with a tag of 3
okay so we go across this one there's 4
entries in this here's a
entry with the tag of seven so that's
not ed and plus the valid bit zero
oh here's a here's an entry with a tag
of three and a in a valid bit of one so
we're luck we lucked out the page table
entries in the TLB and so the the TLB
returns the value the the physical page
number which is zero D back to the MMU
which can now construct the the physical
address so it constructs that physical
address PA by copying directly copying
the VPO bits to the PP o-- bits okay
right as we discuss the last time that
the virtual page offs that's always
identical to the physical page offset
because the block sizes in the virtual
address space and the physical address
space are the same size okay so here so
we get the low order PPO bits and then
the physical page number which came
which comes from the p te that's cached
in the TLB is zero XD and so that forms
the PP n bits of the physical address so
they cut these these now constitute our
our physical address so now the next
step once we have the physical address
is to look to send that to the cache and
ask the cache to return the value at
that address and in this case we're just
doing one byte accesses okay so we're
asking the cache to return the byte
that's in this at this physical address
okay so the the cache of course it first
checks to see if that if the the byte
that's requested is contained in some
block in the cache okay so we so it it
takes in it extracts the cache index
bits which is 0 0 1 0 1 so 5 and so if
this if this byte that's being requested
is in the cache it's going to be in set
5 so we go to set 5 and then we're
looking for a tag of 0 XD and lo and
behold here's
we have a matching tag and about
matching valid bit so the good the line
that we're that we request that is is in
the cash and the word that the word that
we requested is at offset - okay so we
go to so this is offset one
this is offset - oh no I'm sorry
let's see what oh I'm sorry it's it I
was getting confused the into these are
the index bits so the offset is actually
zero here's the this is the this is our
physical address okay and the and the
the value of that offset is zero so
we're asking for the in the fifth set
we're asking for the the byte at offset
zero and that's 0 X 3 6 6 so we have a
hit the cache returns that byte back to
the MMU which which passes it back to
the processor which stores it in a
register most likely ok so let's look at
another example and I've recorded these
here for you if you want to go back in
and look at them let's look at another
example this would so this time the CPU
sends a virtual address of 0 X 0 0 to 0
to the MMU ok and so if we if we write
out the bits for for that virtual
address we get we get we get this result
and then we mark off the virtual page
offset the virtual page number and the
TLB index low-order bits of the virtual
page number and the and then the tag for
the the TLB T so as step 1 same as
before check with the TLB let's see if
that page table entries in the TLB T in
the in the in the TLB so we're asking in
this case
this set if this if this page table
entries in the in the TLB it will be in
edit it will be in set 0 and it will
have a tag of 0 so we look we look in
set 0 for a tag of 0 now this doesn't
match oh three here's oh nine that
doesn't match
zero zero matches but the valid bits 0
so this isn't a valid entry it's just a
coincidence that this tag was was 0 so
this is a TLB miss ok so that's a bummer
because now we have to go off the chip
and make an expensive memory access to
read that page table entry from the the
page table so now we have to so now we
have to check with the the page table
[Music]
and we're looking for virtual page
virtual page zero so we check the entry
at virtual page zero to see if that page
if that page is in memory and if so if
it has a valid and if it is in memory
because the valid bits one so this so we
have a valid physical page number so the
memory returns the page table entry or
the the PPN back to the the back to the
MMU which is a it's a 0 X 0 X 2 8 and
now the mm you can use that that
physical page number to construct the
the physical address so as before we
copy the virtual page offset directly
into the physical page offset and then
our PP n is is to 8 so we have 1 0 its
to 1 0 0 0 8 so now concatenated that
those form the the physical address and
now the MMU has a physical address that
it can hand off to the cache and request
that the cache return that value at that
at that physical address so now the the
cache gets that physical address and it
it extracts the cache index bits which
in this case are 8 okay 0 X 8 so if this
the block if the word that we're looking
for is contained in the cache I'm sorry
if the byte that we're looking for is
contained in the cache it'll be in set 8
ok so we go so the cache goes to set 8
and it looks for a matching tag which in
this case is it turns out that it's 28
just like the PPN just by coincidence
so in in set eight we have a tag of we
have an entry the block has a tag of
twenty four so there's a Miss okay so
this is a cache miss and now the cache
has two requests
past that physical address to the memory
to fetch that byte
yes how do ya the question is how do you
know how do you determine the size of
the virtual page offset and yes it's
based on the page size it was 64 bytes
so 64 bytes so that that's why we have
six 6vp oh and PPO bits
okay so is that clear to everybody that
that's a kind of thing that sometimes
turns up on exams you know just
yes any relationship between the length
on physical page number and the cashback
that one okay so the question is is
there any relationship between the
length of the physical page number and
the cash tag this was just a complete
coincidence
okay it just it just happened it was
just a coincidence they normally they
don't necessarily have to line up like
that any other questions yes yes um so
for instance if I'd had more sets in my
cache then I need more bits and they'd
spill over right if if my it was just a
coincidence because I had six PPO bits
and just a block size of four and four
sets so if I if my cache had more sets
the cache index would spill over and
then the cache tag wouldn't match up
with the physical page number okay so
it's a similar question before were like
in this case that's that's right it's
similar to the question before and it
just happened to be a coincidence maybe
I should have chosen a different example
but they're completely independent
everybody else good okay
okay so now I want to I want to talk to
you about how how this stuff all works
in a real system in this case it's a
core i7 system from Intel thin x86 64
it's a family of high-end desktop
systems x86 64 if you are similar to the
the shark machines that you use to do
your labs so here's the here's the way
the memory system looks and none in the
core i7 the processor package is the
chip okay so that's like a single and
then and then there's four cores in this
package each core is a separate as a
separate CPU and canary executes
instructions separately okay so each
call each each of these cores has a
register file and then a some hardware
that fetches instructions it has two l1
caches there's a data cache called the D
cache which is used to fetch data and
which holds data fetched from memory and
then there's an instruction cache called
an AI cache which holds instructions
fetched from the code the code region so
data this the d cache has data only the
AI cache has instructions only there
each 32 K bytes 8 way set associative so
they're very small but they have fairly
high associativity and then the next
level in the hierarchy is a an l2 so
called unified cache because they can
hold both instructions and data okay
it's a little bit bigger 256 K bytes and
also eight-way associative and so both
of these caches are on the on the core
itself ok
and then outside and enters an l3 cache
which is shared by all cores which is 8
megabytes and 16 Way associative okay so
the access is because the l1 cache is
closest to the processor this is this is
fast this is like four cycles to access
l1 l2 is bigger and a little further
away so it the it's about 10 10 cycles
to access this and l3 is off the core
right so it has to go over a connection
some connection off the off the chip
into this into this cache and so the the
access time for this l3 cache is like 50
30 to 50 cycles now the the MMU has it
also has a hierarchy of tlbs
and i was talking with a student after
class the last lecture night I
mistakenly said that the the system
didn't have a hierarchy of tlbs
but it does there's a a small l1 data
TLB and a and a separate instruction TLB
so the this has 16 64 total entries and
it's 4-way set associative so how many
sets are there then in this how many
sets in the l1 data TLB
sixteen right good and then the an inch
the instruction TLB has more entries
interestingly so it's it's an
interesting decision I guess the I guess
the thinking I don't I don't really know
I'm just trying to conjecturing that the
reason they would make the instruction
TLB bigger is that the the penalty for
missing on instructions would be much
larger
but yeah I'm not sure it's an
interesting decision and then there's a
there's a unified TLB below that which
is a larger larger still so the I think
if you're wondering I mean it's
interesting to think like why do they
have these like like these second-level
caches why didn't they just make these
out the l1 cache is bigger right
and in the case of the in the case of
the D cache and the I cache over here
I'll show you in it just a little bit if
you hang on there's a really interesting
reason why they can't make these things
bigger or much bigger right there
there's a so there's there's a there's a
property of the they're sort of they're
constrained in the in the size of the
offset and index bits in these these
caches and it's interesting I'll show
you in a second for that for the TLB I
mean one reason that comes to mind for
why they didn't why they have the second
level is that if they decided just to
make the l1 data D TLB and ITL B's
bigger you know take the take the
transistors that they used for this l2
and and just give them to the the level
one TLB s it you're kind of by
partitioning those by partitioning those
those that storage ahead of time you're
kind of locking yourself in so if if you
didn't have this level two TLB and and
you just increase say you gave half and
so it made L 1 and L the data TLB an
instruction TLB twice as big then you're
sort of locking yourself in right if if
if you run you might run out of you
still might run out of instructions and
and have capacity misses in that in that
l1 cache I'm saying similarly for data
right so you're not sure you may in a
particular program there mate
there may be a lot more data page table
entries than instruction page table
entries in or vice versa so by by
creating the second level of a cache
you're kind of hedging your bets right
so you may the Miss penalty when you
have this l2 cache the Miss penalty in
l1 isn't nearly as big as it would be if
because if you didn't okay so that that
that's sort of the thinking that goes on
now there's a there's a memory
controller which count which fetches
data from memory and then there's links
to other cores into the i/o bridge now
m2n so it's really interesting so it's
interesting to see how this all fits
together end to end so let's let's let's
look at it so the CPU generates a
virtual address in Intel systems the
virtual addresses are 48 bits we have 4
K sized blocks so 12 offset bits and
then 36 VPN bits so first we look in the
in the cache I mean in the TLB and
there's as we said before there's 16 TLB
sets this is the l1 I'm showing the l1
data TLB so we break it up into 4 TLB I
index bits and 32 tag bits so we do a
lookup on the in the TLB to see if we
can find that the Pte that contains that
the corresponding physical page number
for this virtual address if we have a
hit then the MMU can just construct the
physical address directly by copying as
we saw before copying the gpo to the PPO
and then using the PPM that was returned
from the TLB how's that for an out
acronym so
if there's a TLB miss then the system
has to fetch the the corresponding PT PP
n from the page table using that multi
way lookup we looked multi level lookup
we looked at before out and I'll show
you how this works in a little more
detail coming up but the end result is
that a page table entry is located and
the PP n is extracted from that and
concatenated with the PP o to form the
physical address then the MMU passes
that physical address to the cache the
l1 data cache has 64 sets so we need six
cache index bits now here's what I was
alluding to before notice that the
number of cache index and cache offset
bits is exactly identical to the VPO in
the virtual address okay so the the
cache offset and index bits in the
physical address are identical to the
the DPO the offset bits in the virtual
address ok and this is not a coincidence
ok unlike that other example I showed
you this is not a coincidence and this
is sort this is at the root this is at
the root of why the l1 cache is so small
is that the way the way Intel implements
their cache lookups which we'll see in a
second depends on the cache index and
cache offset bits and the physical
address being identical to the offset
bits and the virtual address anyway so
then we do our cache we do our cache
look up using the the cache doesn't look
up using the using this physical address
takes the index bits to identify asset
uses the tag to see if there's a match
if there is then we have a hit which
returns the resulting word back to the
CPU otherwise there's a miss
so then the cash has to request the data
from l2 l3 and main memory
eventually worst case that that data
comes from main memory so I guess worst
case it comes from disk right if you
have page miss page hope so eventually
though the data the data comes back and
is returned back to the CPU
now that the page table entries on in
Intel systems have the following
structure you can see that the the level
the level one page which levels the
level 1 through 3 pages remember that
that page table entry points to the
address of the next level page table ok
so it contains the level 1 the level 1
PT e contains the base address the
physical address of the level 2 table
and so on there's a there's a bit this
is the valid bit they call it the P VP
for present so this identifies whether
that the page is in memory or not if
it's not then it's then there's a the
location of it of that page table on
disk there's bits that control whether
the that page table can be read as it is
read-only or it can be written this
corresponds to all reachable pages so
you know you can so all reachable pages
so all all of the portion of the address
space that's covered by this particular
page table entry there's also a bit that
indicates whether users can can access
that or if they need to be running in
kernel mode so this this is how the
kernel protects its code and data from
from user programs there's a there's a
bit here to indicate whether we should
be using write back or write
through for this for these page tables
and all the systems I know of use use
right back just because of the Miss
penalty the enormous miss penalty forget
what CD does there's a there's a
reference bit which is set when the MMU
reads or writes reads or writes that pit
the the page table at this points to and
there's and then there's a there's a bit
that indicates whether that the page
size is either four K bytes or four
megabytes okay and then there's this
there's this new disabled it's the XD
bit which which disables allows you to
disable or enable execution from all the
pages reachable from that page table
entry so this is how the stack modern
systems protect the stack from code
injection attacks ok the last level page
table entry points to a four it points
to not another page table but actually a
page in memory ok and so the same we
have the same bits here the same 40 bits
that that give the physical address of
that page in memory and then we have the
indication of whether that page is is
present in memory or not and the rewrite
and X and permission execute permission
bits right through a write back there's
a reference there's this reference bit
and then there's a dirty bit which the
MMU sets when it writes to that page ok
so this is how this is how the OS knows
that it needs to when it selects this if
it selects this page as a victim it it
looks at the dirty bit to see if it
needs to write that page back did you
have a question
have the protection that are being
provided by the new sarcastic versus Jax
oh excuse me net you can't execute any
instructions you can't load any
instructions from that page okay
the this user or supervisor mode it
determines whether you can access that
page so if it's set to supervisor mode
only the kernel can can access that page
anything on that page if it's set to you
then anybody user code and kernel code
can access that page any other questions
okay so then the the way it does address
translation then is the physical for
this process so the kernel for each
process maintains the you know set of
page tables of course and then it in it
maintains the address of the first 11
one table in a register called CR 3 ok
and this is a physical address points to
the base of the level 1 page table the
the VPN is broken up into 36 divided by
4 equals 9 bits that give offsets into
each page table entry absolutely
okay so so there's two to the ninth
potential page table entries in each in
each pay in each of these different page
tables so the this VPN one is used the
high order nine bits are used to compute
an offset into the into that table and
you can see each each level one PT II
covers a swath of memory that's 512
gigabytes in size so you can see for
most most programs that exist today
you only need one level one page table
entry that to be initialized that would
cover you know the vast majority of your
programs the the next nine bits it so
the page table entry in the level 1 the
page table points to the it gives the
physical address of the level 2 page
table and then the VPN bits in the the
virtual address are used to compute an
offset into that table and so on it just
cascades and then finally the last the
low-order bits of the nine bits of the
VPN are used to form an offset into the
level 4 page table which in which each
each PT e points to an actual page it
gives a physical page number so then
that that physical page number then is
extracted and concatenated with the VPO
which we copied down to form a physical
address
okay so that everybody good okay now
there's this there's this cool trick
which I was alluding to earlier that
limits the size of l1 cache now to this
point we've been we've been using a
model where that the MMU takes the verge
does address translation and creates a
complete virtual address a physical
address and then it sends that physical
address to the cache okay but in reality
intel does this cute trick to speed up
l1 cache accesses so what in reality
what happens so we're given a virtual
address okay and in this virtual address
the index and offs the physical the
index and offset bits in the physical
address are identical exactly correspond
to the PPO in the physical address which
is exactly identical to the DPO and the
virtual address so that means is that
when the the MMU is given a virtual
address it can send the VPO off to the
l1 cache even though it's of even though
l1 is is phys is it is physically
addressed we can send the the VPO in the
virtual address to the l1 cache because
of this because of this phenomenon that
the the PPO is identical to the VPO so
even before the MMU is doing any address
translation it can send this these these
VPO bits to the cache and then the the
cache can get busy extracting the index
the cache index bits looking up you know
looking up all of the the lines in that
in that set and then have everything
ready for the tag check which can only
occur after the address translation
happens so it can only occur once
there's a physical address with a
from which we can extract the the cash
tag so this so there's a little bit of
parallelism now in the l1 cache accesses
so we can be the mmm you can be doing
address translation while the the l1
cache gets going on it's it's lookup
okay so now let's look at how Linux
implements virtual virtual memory and in
doing so will now get a clearer
understanding of how fork and exec and
loading really work okay so we've seen
this pictures of picture like this
several times before this is the virtual
address space of the Linux process
because we have because of the way the
virtual memory system works every
process has a very similar-looking
address space that program text the code
is always loaded at the same 0 X 400,000
address and that's followed by
initialized data which comes from the
dot data section of the the executable
binary and then there's a BSS section
which contains uninitialized data that
was that was defined in the binary and
then the heap then the heap grows up
from from the initialized data there
it's pointed to by a global variable
called in a global variable in this
process context called break so the
kernel keeps track of where the top of
the heap is for this this process
there's a memory mapped region for
shared libraries and then at the top of
the users the user level user
user-accessible memory there's this user
stack which grows down and which is
pointed to by RSP and then the that the
kernel code and data live up in the
upper portion of the address space now
this picture isn't completely accurate
there's actually like a big gap between
the top of the stack and the beginning
of the
the colonel code and data I'm the reason
for that is that the Intel Architecture
says that that so there's 48 virtual
address bits right so if so that's it's
the high-order bit of that 48 bit
address is 0 then all the all the
remaining bits have to be 0 all of the
all of the height the remaining 6 the
remainder of the 64 high order bits need
to be 0 so it's kind of like sign
extension right and if that if that high
order bit and the 48 bit address is 1
then you extend the the 1 all the way up
to the remaining high order bits okay so
those are the only feasible bits so what
that does is it creates a that the
Colonel's living the Colonel's living in
in a portion of the virtual address
space where that the 12 the 12 high
order bits are all ones okay so that
creates so you can think of it this is
the colonel lives in the very top of the
64 64-bit address space okay
another way to think of it in Colonel
addresses always start with one the most
significant bit is 1 and user addresses
always have a most significant bit of
zero key that's just the detail doesn't
doesn't really affect things but with
him what is important is that this this
is the process virtual address space of
a process right and so the kernel exists
in the virtual address space of each
process in it so there's there's kernel
code and data and then it also Maps it
has a region of its virtual address
space that map's
each element of this of this region with
an address in physical memory ok so that
this this mapping this region is is
corresponds to the amount of DRAM on the
chip and so it's a mechanism that the
kernel uses to get access to physical
addresses ok and this is important
because remember the kernel there you
can never you can't turn off address
translation right it's always happening
ok even even when the kernel runs the
address translation is happening the
kernel is generating virtual addresses
so this this this this this region this
is map to a region of physical memory so
that if if the kernel accesses bytes 0
of this of this block it will it will
actually be the the the the address that
the corresponding physical address will
be 0 and if it accesses a byte at an
offset of 1 in this region the physical
address the corresponding physical
address from the address translation
process will be 1 ok so basically by
reading and writing into this region the
kernel is reading and writing into
physical memory and this so there's
portions of the kernel that are
identical for every process right the
codes the same it's not in but then
there's there's process specific data
structures that that the kernel
maintains for each process that
the context for that process so we refer
to these refer to all these with all
these data structures as the the context
and these of course have to be these
would be different for each process now
Linux or organizes this this virtual
address region as a collection of what
it calls areas an area is like a segment
think of it as just a chunk of a
contiguous chunk of related memory items
so the there's a there's an area for
code there's an area for data shared
libraries have areas there's an area for
the stack and it
it contains there's a structure for each
process called the task task struct and
this contains a pointer to the MM struct
which has a bunch of stuff in it but the
it contains the the address of the level
one page table okay so that's part of
the context when this process runs when
this process is scheduled the kernel
will take this entry this PGD entry and
he'll copy it into cr3
okay so that's how it switches just by
changing the cr3 register the kernel
changes the address space so that's how
and once once that once that cr3 value
is changed then the process no longer
has access to the previous processes
page tables right so and then there's a
and then there's a pointer to a list of
these these so-called area structs the
area struct identifies the start at the
beginning and end of the region any
protections like is this read-only
region for example so the code the code
section would be set as read-only or is
it read right and enter some other some
other flags
we'll see which we'll see later
in particular when we when we look at
sharing and mapping for our purposes
these these flag bits tell us whether
the page is shared with other processes
or whether it's private to this this
process so normally the default is that
pages are all private but you have the
option if you do if you do a fair amount
of work you can get processes to to
share to share memory okay so let's look
at what happens when we have a page
fault so let's say so there's you know
the processor issues and instruction the
address translation process determines
that the corresponding page isn't
contained in memory so it triggers a
page fault and so the fault handler
there's several up there are several
things that might have happened one
maybe we were reading memory it faulted
because that that memory that area
doesn't even exist
we haven't even created the kernel
hasn't even created allocated that that
page in virtual memory yet okay so
that's an error
so that's accessing a non-existing page
elicits a seg fault so the kernel
figures that out because it runs down
this list of various trucks and it it
doesn't find this address anywhere
within the ranges of those areas so
that's that's a seg fault caused by
accessing a non-existing page another
possibility is that the instruction is
attempting to write into a read-only
section segment of the virtual address
space
well they this that there's nothing in
the page table the MMU typically would
check the the permission bits in the in
the page table entry and throw an
exception if the write is trying to to
write to a read-only page but in this
case that there was no page table entry
right at the trick that's why I
triggered a page fault
so the MMU doesn't know that this is an
illegal right
the colonel can check the protection for
this area and if if in the kit in the
case of text that will be set to read
only so that triggers a protection
exception which actually Linux reports
as a segfault and then then the other
option is that maybe we're trying to
read data from a valid from a valid area
so then the kernel faults that the
requested page in and and returns the
requested data back to the back to the
CPU
okay the last thing I want to look at
today is is it yes
okay s-sorry
yeah so all of the segments are
contained in the executable file okay
there's a at the at the beginning of the
elf binary there's a list of all the all
the different segments okay so when it
went it when eggs act loads the binary
creates it creates areas for each of
those each of those segments good yes so
like you so easily it is still first
checks like you just have you it gets
but it's just like once it this is after
the page fault yes the MMU doesn't know
about these okay so yeah the question is
exactly how are these areas structs use
and they're used they're used in this in
this content in this example anyway
they're used during the page faults okay
and also just as a an aside I've shown
these actually are implemented as list
but in the real system they use some
kind of tree red black tree or something
like that
okay so I want to talk about the last
thing we're going to look at today is
this is this this interesting idea
called mapping and it will help us
understand a lot about what's going on
in the system when it executes fork and
exec so VM areas are initialized by
associating them with disk objects okay
and so this this process in a using a
process known as memory mapping right so
the every every area and thus every page
within that area is associated with some
portion of a file and it's that and
that's the initial contents of the pages
in that area come from that file okay so
the the an area can be backed by what we
call or get its initial values from
either a regular file on disk so this we
saw this so in the case of pages that
are containing code that that area that
has a code is mapped to a portion of the
executable binary okay and then the
initial values of that area come from
that executable binary file okay so
that's how that's how we get that's how
we get data copied back and forth from
or from executables into into memory the
file can also be an anonymous file
meaning it's a file it's an it's some
anonymous file that consists of all
zeros it's an anonymous file of
arbitrary size that consists of all
zeros and so of course it doesn't exist
this is just a trick so this allows us
to create pages that are initialized to
all zeros okay and then so the if a page
is associated with the anonymous file
then the first fault will Alec
a physical page of all zeroes so this is
called the demand zero page okay so it's
brought in on demand and it's
initialized to zero
once now once an anonymous once a file
wants a page that's backed by an
anonymous file is written to or dirtied
then it's like any other page okay and
then dirty pages are copied back and
forth between memory and a special swap
flow now you remember in normally
processes don't share anything with each
other okay but it's possible using this
idea of mapping for processes to be
mapped to the same objects so suppose
that we have we have two processes with
their own separate virtual address
spaces and the pages in these two
processes are being mapped to portions
of physical memory so let's say there's
a an area a segment in process one
that's been mapped to this to this
object so to this portion of a file okay
now process 2 can also map to that same
that same object and notice even at a
completely different virtual at virtual
address so there's no there's no
relationship between the region of this
virtual address space that's mapped to
the shared object in process 1 and the
region of the virtual address space in
process 2 that's mapped to the same
object and the kernel because these
these objects have unique names right
their files the kernel can can check the
other processes to see if any other
processes are mapping to that object and
if so map this region of the virtual
address space to those same physical
pages ok so now we have a situation
where each process is accessing some
chunk of its virtual address space and
those accesses are actually being done
on the same region of physical memory so
this might be useful you might imagine
um you know say these processes are
servers you know say you've worked a
bunch of copies of Apache you might want
to have some kind of shared cache maybe
a shared memory cache between those all
those different copies so this this
would be in this case your cache would
be a file a file on disk and then as you
as you access regions of that file those
pages get copied into physical memory so
that would allow you to have a shared
cache in in the in the memory across all
those all those processes now sometimes
there's another objects can also be
private meaning they shouldn't be shared
ok across processes
and there's a special an especially
interesting kind of private object
called the private copy-on-write object
so the the idea here and you'll see when
this will become very important when we
look and see how fork actually works the
idea is that we have an object that's it
we have two two processes that are
mapping to the same object but instead
of instead of this being a shared object
it's what we call this this private
copy-on-write object and just like
before these two regions of the virtual
address space map into the same region
of physical memory but they're tagged
using the and this is where those flag
bits come in there they're the pages in
this area are flagged as private
copy-on-write okay now what that means
is normally if this was a shared object
let's say this was a shared object and
processed to wrote did a right into this
region of the virtual address space if
this was a shared object that right
would also be reflected on the disk on
the file on disk but if it's if it's if
it's flying this instead of being shared
if that if that area this area is marked
as flagged as private copy-on-write then
if if process to does a write to a page
in that area then instead of it
reflecting that change in physical
memory and on the the shared object it
makes a copy of that of that page a
separate copy of that page and maps it
to some unused portion of the physical
address space okay so that's why that's
why we have the name copy on right so if
we but if we read if we read values from
this area nothing happens it just it
will just read from the this portion of
the physical address space okay it's
only when we do a write to some page in
an area that's flagged as private
copy-on-write
it's only when we do that right that the
system first makes a copy of that page
and then does the right okay now why on
earth would why on earth would anybody
want to do this actually this this
notion of copy-on-write is is another
one of these kind of fundamental
important system concepts that's used a
lot whenever you want to share things
efficiently yes right
then you don't know love which one two
and three ready to thank you can you get
some tissue if you didn't do this if you
well although the rights all go through
yeah the memory system okay this is a
really really good question and it's
it's beyond our scope but the memory
system takes care of those and it
provides some guarantees so it the
memory system you're right it's
receiving from multiple cores it's
receiving multiple multiple instructions
multiple addresses and the memory system
itself takes care of sort of providing
some ordering on those and it provides
it provides some sort of non-trivial
guarantees on what you can assume the
ordering is but that's a that's a pretty
a pretty complicated topic that we'll
get into
it's called the consid it's called the
consistency model right so every every
processor provides some kind of
consistency model any other questions
okay so why is this copy-on-write
technique useful and interesting well it
turns out I mean if you if you think
about fork it seems like it would be
terribly expensive right you have if you
want to fork a process you know the
naive way to do it would just be to copy
you'd have you have to somehow get us
exact copy of the address space but a
separate a separate copy of the address
space that's identical so if you
approach this naively you'd have to make
copies of all the page tables all of the
other data structures and you'd also
have to copy all the memory right so if
you're you know if you're forking a
process that's created a huge number of
virtual pages and it's address space
those would all have to be copied to and
mapped to different portions of the
physical address of the memory okay so
you'd have it would be very expensive
right potentially almost unbounded
depending on how much memory you are
using right so unfortunately this this
copy-on-write
technique provides an efficient solution
and so the idea when we do fork when we
when we when a process executes fork the
kernel has to create exact copies of all
those internal data structures they mmm
struck the area structs and the page
tables there's no way to get around that
okay but those aren't those aren't
really huge of they're not as
potentially huge as the the actual data
that the program is is accessing and
then and then it Flags each page in both
processes as read-only
okay even though they're not no matter
where they are any process any page in
that process it flags is read only and
then it Flags each VM area struct in
both processes as private copy-on-write
so on return now each process has the
identical address space because it they
have it has identical page tables okay
we've made copies of the page tables and
all of the other all of the other
structures and if as those processes
just read then they're sharing the same
physical pages right it's only when a
process does it right that the the
system will create a new page will
create a new page using this
copy-on-write mechanism so it's only
when a process rights to a page will it
tries to do a write the page is flagged
as read-only okay in the PT II that
triggers a fault the kernel looks at
that looks up the access that looks up
the flags for that for that particular
page sees that it's private
copy-on-write and so it makes a copy of
the the target page and maps it to a new
region of the physical address space and
then does the allows that and then and
then when the right executes again and
then it restarts when that fault handler
returns it restarts that instruction and
now the right is writing to the copy
okay so what what this does a very
clever technique it defers the the
copying till as long as till as late as
possible and it only does copying when
it's absolutely needed okay so in some
sense it's the most it provides you with
the most efficient way to a most space
efficient way to represent those two
those two different virtual address
spaces and so what's interesting is that
regions of the virtual address space
that that are read from never get copied
so so they it's perfectly fine for those
two processes to share to share that
data on physical memory because it's
never written to write so okay so that's
why that's why Fork isn't so bad right
good now xx ve now that we know about
sharing and now that we know about this
this mapping notion the exec the e
function loads and runs a new program in
the current process okay
and so what it does is it frees all the
all the area structs for the current
process right so xx not creating a new
process it's running a new program in a
new virtual address space within the
current process ok so it it so it frees
all the Arias trucks and page tables for
the current process ok and then it
creates new area structs and page tables
for the new areas and the programs so
the program and initialize data those
areas are backed by the file in this
case the executable binary and their
program is backed by the portion of the
executable that contains code and the
data segment is is backed by the portion
of the executable file that contains
initialize data so these two together
are private what we call their private
ok these this object it shouldn't isn't
being shared with with any anything else
and it's file backed because these this
area is backed by portions of a file the
the uninitialized data which was
specified in the BSS section of the of
the binary that's defined as a private
demand 0 area ok
so this so these these pages will all be
remembered by definition BSS is
uninitialized okay and so the system
initializes these to zero so any pages
then any pages in the heap are also
private demands zero now the memory
mapped region for shared libraries
remember every every process share is
the same copy of Lib C and in memory so
this is a region of the virtual address
space that's shared okay because it's
shared by multiple processes and it's
backed by files of and the de file in
this case is the deso file the shared
object file and the code for this region
is backed by text the the portion of the
this object file that contains code and
data is initialized data is backed by a
portion of this file that that contains
data now there's I haven't shown it here
but there's other there's other portions
of this of this region that need to be a
private copy-on-write because different
Lib C functions if a Lib C function has
static variables or can contain state
like a random number generator typical
random number generator retains state
across each invocation okay so that
state would be different for each
process so there needs to be a sort of
private copy-on-write
area for for any data that's that's
being written to
and I suppose I suppose the system would
just with just if you if you made this
entire region now you'd have to have it
you'd have to have second portions of
this that would be private copy-on-write
and then the stack is private demand
zero okay so so what what exact does is
it just sets it creates new areas that
are backed backed by a different by the
object file that you want to execute and
it creates areas for BSS and stack that
are backed by anonymous files and it
creates a this memory-mapped region
that's that's a shared object which
corresponds to Lib C and then it sets
the program counter or IP to the entry
point in text and then once as this
program runs now notice we haven't
loaded anything right all we've done is
set mappings we just we just created
data structures in the kernel and we've
we've created mappings between portions
of the address space and these objects
but nothing's actually been copied into
memory yet okay well this is all we've
just created we've modified data
structures in the kernel now but once
the once the loader sets our IP to the
entry point the first instruction in in
this text segment then Linux will Fault
in all the code and data that's needed
on demand so loading loading hab is
deferred until the loading of a page of
code or data is deferred until that code
or data page is actually referenced and
accessed so it's very this is very
clever and very interesting I think how
how it's like yet another example of how
useful and how tightly integrated
virtual memory is with the operation of
the system right you wouldn't have to do
this you could just as part of the
loading process you could just copy
those
take those object files you could just
have a loop that would read these object
files and just copy them into copy them
into memory and create page table
entries for of as as you did it but even
that would be efficient that would be
inefficient too right what if you had a
very large array that you'd initialized
to some nonzero value that would require
you to copy that that entire array in at
load time even though you may be only
accessing a small portion of that of
that data structure now the kernel
provides a function called M map that
allows you to do your memory mapping
just like the kernel does okay and so
it's basically a way it's a system
called it that allows you to request the
kernel to map a region of virtual memory
on your on its behalf and so this this M
map function takes a a virtual pointer
which is some pointer into the virtual
address space and it Maps tries to map
length bytes starting at this address it
tries to map that portion of the virtual
address space to the object to an offset
to some objects specified by this file
descriptor okay so remember we when you
open a file you get back a file
descriptor so it's mapping this region
of the virtual address space starting at
start for length bytes to a region of
the that the file denoted by this
integer file descriptor so it's it's
mapping length bytes in that file
starting at offset offset now and then
there's the user can specify different
flags what kind of protection they want
for this this whether its private or
whether it's read or whether it can be
it's read-only or read/write and they
can also specify
by the typeof of object if you map and
anonymous if you use this flag and M map
then you get a demand 0 page okay that's
the anonymous file in which case you
don't need to specify this this file
descriptor and you can map that object
as being private or shared okay like we
talked about before
now the kernel will will it will return
an pointer to the start of this mapped
area not necessarily this this start
address is like a hint to the kernel so
if it can it will will try to map that
area but if that portion of the virtual
address space is already contained in
some already existing area then it'll it
will pick an unused portion of the
virtual address space to to map okay so
what what we're doing really is we're
we're taking an offset into some file
specified by that FD argument and length
number of bytes and we're associating
that or mapping that into us the same
sized region of the virtual address
space okay so now if we do if we read
now again nothing gets copied okay it's
just a mapping so that if we were to
read a portion of let's say we mapped an
unused portion of the virtual address
space and then at using M map and then
after M map we just started scanning
through this this portion of the virtual
address space you know say it's an array
we then we've M napped a big array as we
read as we read each non-existing page
will be swapped in automatically kate
will trigger page fault and it will be
swapped in and the value that it has
will be will be determined by the the
contents of this portion of the file
okay and then so one here's an example
of how you can use em map to do and this
is kind of an interesting example we're
copying a file from standard into
standard out without ever transferring
data to user space so the normal sort of
into naive way to do this would be to
read from a file read from standard in
and then write to standard out so to
syscalls one read and one write we can
actually do this using using one 1m map
and then a single right okay so what we
do is we open a file our v1 is is
standard in or we I'm sorry we open a
file that was passed in on the command
line we get its size and then we call em
and then we call this M map copy
function to say copy copy that the copy
of the bytes the size bytes from this
file to standard out so this n map copy
function does M map using that file
descriptor sets that is read only
private sets the size and length means
everything or at the off at an offset of
zero and then we do one writes this call
to standard out passing at the pointer
to the buffer that we want to copy and
of size bytes so as this as we so as we
so this will read this will read bytes
1f the right the right call will read
bytes in buff P one after the other and
as that happens they'll be faulted in
and then it will write them I will write
them to the descriptor indicated by a on
the one which is standard out okay so
that's that's it for today hope you guys
have a good weekend and see you next
week